<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title xml:lang="en">Preface to The White Lotus of the Good Dharma</title>
                <author role="preface" ref="contributors.xml#person-248">Dzongsar Jamyang Khyentse Rinpoche</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.09 <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-051-001P"/> 
             </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Preface composed for the digital edition of Toh 113 The White Lotus of the Good Dharma.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-10-18T15:52:37.544Z" user="celso">18/10/2019 15:52:37</note>
           </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front/>
        <body>
            <div type="preface">
                    <head type="preface" tid="2427">Preface</head>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="2513">by Dzongsar Jamyang Khyentse Rinpoche</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3163"/>
                    <p tid="2401">If we try to imagine 2,500 years ago, atop a small mountain in the
                        ancient kingdom of Magadha, in the heat of the subcontinental sun, an
                        audience—that included 1,200 bhikṣus, 2,000 bhikṣus-in-training, and 6,000
                        bhikṣunīs—gathering around Buddha Śākyamuni, we might have some difficulty.
                        It is difficult to imagine historical places to which we have never been. It
                        is also difficult to imagine such a large group of people fitting
                        comfortably on a small mountain. And even more difficult to imagine it if
                        one has been recently to the actual place, in the Indian state of Bihar,
                        where all of this supposedly took place.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3164"/>
                    <p tid="2402">But if we do not at least try to use our minds to imagine these
                        things—if we remain limited by our concepts of reality and relative
                        plausibility—then it will be difficult to receive the blessings, to
                        understand the teachings, and to really practice the instructions contained
                        within a sūtra as historically celebrated as <title xml:lang="en">The White
                            Lotus of the Good Dharma</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3165"/>
                    <p tid="2403">Popularly known as the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus Sūtra</title>,
                        this is one of the most revered Mahāyāna sūtras in the history of Buddhism.
                        Devotion to it as being superior to all other sūtras has, in China, Korea, and
                        Japan, created traditions based solely upon this sūtra. The Japanese chant
                        <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Ja-Ltn">Namu myōhō renge kyō</foreign>
                        (南無妙法蓮華經 “Homage to the White Lotus of the Good Dharma Sūtra”) has become
                        the primary practice of tens of thousands of so-called Buddhists around the
                        world. The mere existence of this sūtra must have brought millions of people
                        into the Dharma and done much to ensure devotion to Buddhism and patronage of
                        it over millennia.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3166"/>
                    <p tid="2404">We should rejoice in this. But we should also be mindful that
                        rigid attachment to the letter—rather than the spirit—of this sūtra has led
                        to some misunderstanding and discord amongst Buddhists. And that is not
                        a good thing. For example, the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus Sūtra</title> has been
                        wrongly invoked to justify gender bias, material grasping, and even
                        self-immolation and militant proselytizing. So it is most important to read
                        and study this profound sūtra with a proper understanding of its underlying
                        meaning and spirit.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3167"/>
                    <p tid="2405">In the evolution of humankind, we have constantly strengthened our
                        capacity to think and communicate in ways that not only convey information,
                        but also create imagined worlds. It was this ability to forge common myths,
                        imagined orders, and hierarchies that enabled us humans to cooperate in
                        larger numbers than ever before, leading us to evolve from being
                        hunter-gatherers to settling in small agrarian communities, and then in towns and
                        cities. Over the centuries, we have come to believe more and more in the
                        imagined realities of corporations, nations, and hierarchies.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3168"/>
                    <p tid="2406">We Buddhists are not immune to these belief systems. For example,
                        Mahāyāna and Vajrayāna Buddhists have evolved their own entrenched
                        hierarchies that often look down on the Śrāvakayāna. Even the often-used
                        term “Hīnayāna” can be used by Mahāyānists in a derogatory and chauvinist
                        way to look down on the śrāvakas. This is really very important to note here
                        because the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus Sūtra</title> has been misused time
                        and time again by such chauvinists to justify and entrench their feeling of
                        superiority.</p>
                    
                    <p tid="2407">But here in the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus Sūtra</title>, the
                        Buddha actually says:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3169"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="2408">
                        <l>“I teach many dharmas in the world</l>
                        <l>So that here and there I bring liberation from attachment.</l>
                        <l>I give the teaching of the three yānas,</l>
                            <l>Which is my supreme skill in methods.” (<ptr target="#UT22084-051-001-389"/>)</l>
                    </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3170"/>
                    <p tid="2409">If one is a supreme being, if one has mastered the dexterity of
                        skillful means to address the variety of people in the world, one is able to
                        skillfully teach different methods or “yānas” to suit the characteristics
                        and affinities of people who are naturally inclined to different
                        proclivities. The Buddha continues, saying:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3171"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="2410">
                        <l>“Apart from the skillful methods of supreme beings </l>
                        <l>Who give the teaching of separate yānas,</l>
                        <l>There is only one yāna; there is no second,</l>
                        <l>And there is never in the world a third.” (<ptr target="#UT22084-051-001-490"/>)</l>
                    </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3172"/>
                    <p tid="2411">This, to me, suggests that, apart from the supreme beings who have
                        the capacity to differentiate yānas without categorizing them into
                        hierarchies, for each of us more lowly beings there is only the yāna we are
                        taught and that we should be practicing. This emphasizes the importance of
                        the role of the teacher who gives us the practices suited to our own situation.
                        It is merely our own egos and minds that search for reference points, make
                        judgments, and habitually create these hierarchies. So, it may help to
                        remember that no matter what we understand in this sūtra, the Buddha
                        says:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3173"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="2412">
                        <l>“A lord of the world appears in the world</l>
                        <l>In order to teach the wisdom of buddhahood.</l>
                        <l>That is his one activity, there is no second:</l>
                        <l>The buddhas do not guide beings with a lesser yāna.” (<ptr target="#UT22084-051-001-491"/>)</l>
                    </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3174"/>
                    <p tid="2413">We must always remember that a tathāgata “appears in this world
                        for that one deed and one action, for that one great deed and great action,
                        and with that intention.” A tathāgatha does not discriminate between beings,
                        nor judge the yānas that are taught to them or by them. Remember, the Buddha
                        is also known as the Tathāgata, and also has many more names, including
                        Arhat, the Tibetan of which literally translates as a “foe-destroyer.” But
                        in his case, foes were not people. They were his emotions and his habit of
                        clinging to his ego, which he overcame. Throughout his previous one thousand
                        lifetimes as a bodhisattva, the only things the Tathāgata ever destroyed
                        were his emotions and his ego; he never once harmed a single being.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3175"/>
                    <p tid="2414">And so, when we talk about the motivation of tathāgatas to appear
                        in this world, we must remember that, like the Buddha, they have as their
                        only intention and motivation the enlightenment of others. As a buddha, the
                        Tathāgata possesses “supreme skill in methods” and teaches according to “the
                        various aspirations, natures, and thoughts of beings.” In a way, we can say
                        that the Dharma teachings one receives are like bespoke suiting: a tall,
                        lanky man and a round, jolly one could be wearing the same suit, made of the
                        same cloth, and the same thread, but with the skill of an experienced
                        tailor, they are fitted—bespoke—for the individual. From afar, passers-by
                        would say these two men are wearing the same suit, because the end result is
                        that both are wrapped in the same cloth and both look good in it, but the
                        methods used, the size of the patterns, and the particular cut might have
                        been very different. Similarly, the ways in which the Dharma is taught are
                        meant to be similarly bespoke. The Buddha says:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3176"/>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="2415">“I teach the Dharma by using a variety of teachings on
                        accomplishment, and various teachings on causes, reasons, parables,
                        supports, and skillful methods.” (<ptr target="#UT22084-051-001-448"/>)</p>
                    </q>
                    
                    <p tid="2416">The idea is that whatever method—or whichever yāna—is taught to a
                        particular being, that method is the one that will most efficiently awaken
                        that being. In that sense, this idea of a hierarchy is no longer as real as
                        we think.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3177"/>
                    <p tid="2417">It is really this idea of skillful means that is so important in
                        this sūtra, and that can help us to appreciate all yānas. The Tibetan 
                        for skillful methods is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign> (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>). The 
                        word <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign> brings with it the connotation of
                        a “trick”—or even a “catalyst,” because skillful methods speed things up without affecting the elements
                        involved.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3178"/>
                    <p tid="2418">Ideally, a skilled spiritual master will change the skillful
                        method or “trick” they use to suit the capacity of the person they are
                        dealing with. Does lemon have the same effect on wine that it has on cow’s
                        milk? No. Even if liters and liters of lemon juice were added to wine, it
                        would not separate into curds and whey. Similarly, a skillful method that
                        works extremely well for one person might be useless for someone else. This
                        is why the path is so meticulous and complex, and also why it is so
                        intriguing. When the right trick is applied to the right person, the right
                        result is achieved. The Mahāyāna really excels when it comes to these kinds
                        of methods.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3179"/>
                    <p tid="2419">Thanks to this wisdom, Buddhism has never been limited to one
                        geographic region or race. Nor has it become a survival kit for just one
                        nationality. More than twenty-five centuries have passed since the Buddha
                        taught this sūtra. In that time, the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus
                            Sūtra</title> has inspired millions of beings to seek liberation for the
                        sake of all beings. When a teaching has been around for a while, it is
                        important to consult and examine its source texts. For Muslims, that source
                        is the Koran; for Christians, it is the Bible; and for Jews, it is the
                        Torah. The source of all the Buddha’s teachings is the sūtras, because it is
                        the sūtras that faithfully record the Buddha’s own words. As the sūtras are
                        the Buddhadharma’s bottom line, it is crucial for all Buddhists to read,
                        learn, and explore them with an open heart and to understand them
                        accurately.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3180"/>
                    <p tid="2420">When a farmer plants and then harvests rice, he ends up with both rice
                        and hay. Most farmers dedicate their efforts to the cultivation of the rice;
                        but sometimes, when wisdom falters, farmers become distracted by the hay.
                        So, on a practical level, we must first develop the intention and the
                        motivation of desperately wanting all sentient beings to awaken. We are not
                        on this path for a good life, or for a better car than our neighbors, or to
                        create more hierarchies and prejudices than exist already in our mundane
                        worlds. We must always remind ourselves of our intention: we must look for
                        the rice, and not be distracted by the hay.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-051-001P-3181"/>
                    <p tid="2421">That is why it is so
                        important for Buddhists to examine the root texts, the source material, in a
                        language they can understand. Translation of the sūtras is crucial in making
                        the words of the Buddha understood, and therefore crucial to preserving the future of the
                        Buddhadharma. And so I greatly welcome the new publication of this profound
                        and influential sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The White Lotus of the Good
                            Dharma</title>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>