<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Kangyur</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བཀའ་འགྱུར།</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">84000 Structural Outline v 2,0, based on Degé phar phud</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC11494"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="1">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="LOBBY"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-26T18:25:21.324Z" user="celso">26/02/2019 18:25:21</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The collected scriptures: the Tibetan translations of the Indian texts that are considered to be the words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about" tid="13">The Kangyur</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="14">The Kangyur and its divisions</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The Kangyur is the principal collection of the Buddhist scriptures in Tibetan. It contains some 900 works in over 100 volumes, all translations into
                        Tibetan of the Indian texts considered to record the words of the Buddha (while its sister
                        collection, the Tengyur, contains translations of the treatises composed by the great Indian
                        Buddhist masters and scholars).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">Most Kangyurs (see below) are divided into sections or divisions containing scriptures of different kinds. Their order may differ,
                        but broadly comprise Vinaya (Discipline), Sūtra (Discourses), and Tantra, sometimes with an
                        additional collection of Dhāraṇī (Incantations). The Sūtra section often comprises several
                        separate divisions, which have here been grouped together for clarity under one heading,
                        Discourses, but can be seen as subdivisions within it.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The order of the sections and texts here follows that of the Degé Kangyur, and the individual texts have been
                        numbered according to the widely used Tōhoku catalogue, which also follows the order of the
                        Degé Kangyur and Tengyur (Ui, H. et al. eds. 
                        <title xml:lang="en">A Complete Catalogue of the Tibetan
                            Buddhist Canons</title>. 1934: Sendai, Japan. Tōhoku Imperial University.)</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="15">History</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The word Kangyur (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ ’gyur</foreign>) literally means “the Word” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’</foreign>) “translated”
                        (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gyur</foreign>). Translation of the scriptures brought to Tibet began in earnest
                        in the late 8th or early 9th centuries during the reign of King Trisong Detsen, and
                        continued under his successors Senalek and Ralpachen. Translation in this initial imperial
                        period was a highly organized, state-sponsored project, carried out by learned Indian
                        masters (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paṇḍita</foreign>) working with trained Tibetan translators
                        (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lotsāwa</foreign>) under the supervision of a chief editor (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhu
                            chen</foreign>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">This prolific “early propagation” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snga dar</foreign>) period saw the translation of a large majority of the sūtra works now found
                        in the Kangyur, and the tantras of the early propagation that are now collected in the
                        Nyingma Gyubum (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnying ma’i rgyud ’bum</title>). It was brought to an end by the
                        9th century persecutions of King Langdarma, but a second wave of translation activity
                        accompanied the period of the “later propagation” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi dar</foreign>) starting in
                        the 10th century, and texts brought from India (particularly tantras) continued to be
                        translated for several hundred years.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">Early descriptive inventories such as the early 9th century Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan kar ma</title>) and Pangthangma
                        (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang thang ma</title>, probably a decade or two later) record the titles and
                        other details of the translated texts held in particular libraries, and systematized them
                        into categories. Different collections of sūtras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo mangs</title>), tantras
                        (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud ’bum</title>) and other categories of texts existed in many monasteries,
                        but the Kangyur itself, as a deliberately compiled and edited collection, only gradually
                        took form and was never formally closed to the addition of newly translated texts. Even
                        today, there is no single, authoritative version of the Kangyur. It is perhaps more accurate
                        to speak of “Kangyurs,” for the extant versions, while broadly similar in their content,
                        differ considerably in their detail and in the ordering and classification of the
                        texts.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">Some scholars hold that most Kangyurs can be traced back to work done in the early 14th century at the Kadampa monastery of Narthang (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar
                        thang</foreign>) near Shigatsé, where Chomden Rigpai Raltri (<foreign type="person" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan rig pa’i ral
                            gri</foreign>) and his disciple Üpa Losal Sangye Bum (<foreign type="person" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbus pa blo gsal sangs rgyas
                                ’bum</foreign>) collected and copied the best available copies of texts from many monastery
                        libraries in the region. It may have been on the basis of this collection that two distinct
                        (though later intertwined) lineages or traditions of Kangyurs evolved. One of these started
                        with an edited version of the Kangyur produced at the monastery of Tshal Gungthang in
                        1347-1351, and is known as the Tshalpa (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshal pa</foreign>) Kangyur tradition. The
                        other tradition is called the Thempangma (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">them spangs ma</foreign>), from a
                        manuscript so named that was produced at Gyantsé (<foreign type="place" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal rtse</foreign>) in 1431
                        from sources in the locality; it may have had its roots in another edited and rearranged
                        version developed by the great scholar Butön Rinchen Drup (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bu ston rin chen
                            grub</foreign>, 1290-1364) and his followers at the monastery of Zhalu (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zha
                                lu</foreign>) in the mid 14th century and later at Gyantsé, too, although there is direct
                        evidence only of Butön’s work on the Tengyur. Butön had earlier (in 1322 or 1323) compiled a
                        list of translated texts (both Buddha-word and treatises) arranged according to a taxonomy
                        of his own devising, and his choice of texts and classification scheme had some influence on
                        many Kangyurs of both traditions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">New Kangyurs were compiled, edited, and copied or printed through the centuries in different places all over the Tibetan cultural
                        area, often as a meritorious action sponsored by a local ruler as well as an opportunity for
                        editorial re-arrangement and improvement. The way the two main traditions of Kangyurs
                        influenced each other in these versions was complex and involved not only the versions and
                        variants of the texts they contain but also—independently—their classification and the
                        structure of their divisions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">However, with several caveats, it can be said that the manuscript Kangyurs known (usually from their present location) as the Ulan
                        Bator (1671), London (c.1712), Stok Palace (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang</foreign>, 1729), and
                        Tokyo (1858-1878), are closest to the Thempangma tradition, while the Tshalpa tradition is
                        reflected in the xylograph Kangyurs of Yongle (made in Beijing in 1410, the first printed
                        Kangyur) and its “Peking” successor printings the Wanli (1605), Kangxi (several between 1684
                        and 1720), and Qianlong (1737); the Lithang (1609-1614) and Coné (1721-1731), also
                        xylographs; and the Berlin manuscript (1680).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">Almost all of these Kangyurs contained at least some elements of the other tradition, and several of the
                        Kangyurs most used today are conflations to an even greater degree (in various differing
                        ways) of the two traditions. These include the Narthang (1730-1732), Degé (1733), Urga
                        (1908-1910), and Lhasa (or <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhol</foreign>, 1934) xylographs.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC11494-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">Outlying, local Kangyurs have come to light in recent decades (e.g. the Phuktrak,
                        Newark Batang, and Tapho manuscripts) whose contents may reflect earlier stages of the
                        independent circulation of collections of translated texts.</p>
                </div> 
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>