<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sher phyin/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitā</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="5">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:23:18 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The collection of discourses on the Perfection of Wisdom (Toh 8-30).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">The Perfection of Wisdom</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The Tibetan Buddhist tradition classifies the discourses (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūtra</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo</foreign>) delivered by Śākyamuni Buddha
                        in terms of the three turnings of the doctrinal wheel, promulgated at different places and times in the
                        course of his life. Among them, the sūtras of the first turning expound the four truths, those of the
                        second turning explain emptiness and the essenceless nature of all phenomena, while those of the third
                        turning elaborate further distinctions between the three essenceless natures. The sūtras of the Perfection
                        of Wisdom (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</title>) are firmly placed by their own assertion
                        within the second turning, promulgated at Vulture Peak near Rājagṛha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">It is in these sūtras that the role of the compassionate bodhisattva with a mind set upon enlightenment
                        achieves pre-eminence over the śrāvakas and pratyekabuddhas of lesser attainment. The central message
                        subtly integrates relative truth and ultimate truth, reiterating that great bodhisattva beings should
                        strive to attain manifestly perfect buddhahood in order to eliminate the sufferings of all sentient beings
                        rather than merely terminate cyclic existence for their own sake, even though, from an ultimate
                        perspective, there are no phenomena, no sentient beings and no attainment of manifestly perfect
                        buddhahood.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The relentless deconstruction of all conceptual elaborations with respect to phenomena, meditative
                        experiences, and even the causal and fruitional attributes characteristic of the bodhisattva path, which
                        is explicitly emphasized throughout these sūtras, may have been controversial, but it has given rise to
                        both Madhyamaka dialectics and to the non-analytical meditative pursuits of the Chan (Zen) tradition. In
                        Tibet, on the other hand, these sūtras are generally approached through study of <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Ornament of Clear Realization</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhisamayālaṃkāra</title>, Toh 3786, a
                        treatise said to have been dictated to Asaṅga by Maitreya) and its extensive commentaries, which
                        constitute the Parchin (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phar phyin</title>) literature—one of the principal
                        subjects of the monastic college curriculum. These treatises elaborate on the eightfold structural
                        progression of the bodhisattvas’ goals, paths and fruit which are implied, though understated in all but
                        the recast manuscript of the <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra in Twenty-five Thousand Lines</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Traditional Tibetan accounts hold that, following their promulgation by Śākyamuni, the sūtras were
                        concealed in non-human abodes—the longest <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra in One Billion Lines</title> among
                        the gandharvas, the <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra in Ten Million Lines</title> among the devas, and the
                            <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra in One Hundred Thousand Lines</title> among the nāgas—the last of these
                        being retrieved and revealed by Nāgārjuna from the ocean depths and initially propagated in South
                        India.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The extant texts forming this cycle of sūtras are replete with abbreviations, modulations and other
                        mnemonic features, indicative of an early oral transmission—even today they are read aloud as an act of
                        merit in monastic halls and public gatherings. At the same time, the medium length and longer sūtras
                        explicitly extoll the merits of committing the sūtras to writing, in the form of books, as an offering for
                        the benefit of posterity.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">In Tibetan translation, the sūtras of the Perfection of Wisdom are contained in twenty-three volumes of the
                        Degé and Narthang Kangyurs—comprising approximately one fifth of the entire collection. This division of
                        the Kangyur precedes all the other sūtras in the Buddhāvataṃsaka (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phal
                            chen</title>), Ratnakūṭa (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon brtsegs</title>) and General Sūtra (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>) divisions of the Kangyur, reflecting the high prestige of the
                        Perfection of Wisdom within Mahāyāna Buddhism as a whole.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">They include twenty-three distinct texts, foremost among them being the “six mothers” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yum drug</title>) and the “eleven children” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bu bcu
                            gcig</title>). The six mothers are the “longer” and “medium” length sūtras, which are said to be
                        distinguished by their structural presentation of all eight aspects of the bodhisattvas’ path, as
                        elucidated in <title xml:lang="en">The Ornament of Clear Realization</title>. The shorter texts, being
                        terser, do not fully elaborate this structure. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The six mothers are outlined as follows:</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="10">1. The <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in One Hundred Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śatasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>, Toh 8) comprises twelve volumes,
                                twenty-five fascicles and seventy-two chapters.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="11">2. The <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in Twenty-five Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcaviṃśatisāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>, Toh 9) comprises three volumes,
                                seventy-eight fascicles, and seventy-six chapters.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="12">3. The <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in Eighteen Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭādaśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>, Toh 10) comprises two and a half
                                volumes, sixty fascicles, and eighty-seven chapters.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="13">4. The <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in Ten Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>, Toh 11) comprises one and a half
                                volumes, thirty-four fascicles, and thirty-three chapters.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">5. The <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in Eight Thousand Lines</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭasāhasrikāprajñāpāramitā</title>, Toh 12) comprises one volume,
                                twenty-four fascicles, and thirty-two chapters.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">6. The <title xml:lang="en">Verse Summation of the Perfection of Wisdom</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitāratnaguṇasañcayagāthā</title>, Toh 13) comprises nineteen
                                folios.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-9"/>
                    <p tid="16">In most Kangyurs the long sūtras, 1-5 (Toh 8-12) each occupy their own primary section of the collection,
                        but here they have all been placed under a single heading for the genre.</p>
                    <p tid="17">Of the shorter sūtras, all contained in a final “miscellaneous Prajñāpāramitā” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sher phyin sna tshogs</title>) volume of the section, the best known are the <title xml:lang="en">Diamond Cutter</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajracchedikā</title>, Toh 16, in three hundred
                        lines), commonly known as the <title xml:lang="en">Diamond Sūtra</title>, and the <title xml:lang="en">Essence of the Perfection of Wisdom</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitāhṛdaya</title>,
                        Toh 21), justifiably famous as the <title xml:lang="en">Heart Sūtra</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-10"/>
                    <p tid="18">Others include increasingly condensed versions: a version in 2,500 lines known as <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Suvikrāntavikrāmin</title> (Toh 14), versions in 700 lines (Toh 24), 500 lines (Toh 15),
                        50 lines (Toh 18), <title xml:lang="en">In a Few Syllables</title> (Toh 22), and even <title xml:lang="en">In One Syllable</title> (Toh 23). The version in 150 lines (Toh 17) is strongly tantric in style and
                        content, and indeed several of the sūtras are duplicated in the Tantra section of the Kangyur.</p>
                    <p tid="19">In addition to these Tibetan translations, there are extant Sanskrit manuscripts from Gilgit and Nepal,
                        complete in some cases, partial in others, and Chinese translations representing all of the longer and
                        medium length versions of the sūtra, with the exception of <title xml:lang="en">The Transcendent
                            Perfection of Wisdom in Ten Thousand Lines</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14665-11"/>
                    <p tid="20">A bibliographic appraisal of all texts within this division can be found in Conze, Edward, <title xml:lang="en">The Prajñāpāramitā Literature</title> (2nd edition), 1978: Tokyo, The Reiyukai.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>