<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phal chen/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Ornaments of the Buddhas</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14666"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="6">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-09T18:52:07.913Z" user="john">09/03/2019 18:52:07</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Presented as a single, long sūtra, although many of its 45 chapters are independent works (Toh 44).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about" tid="21">The Sūtra of the Ornaments of the Buddhas</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14666-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This very long work in 45 chapters fills no less than four volumes of the Degé Kangyur. In its current
                        form, it is presented as a single extensive sūtra (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaipulyasūtra</title>), but it
                        probably evolved as an encyclopedic coalescence of shorter works, many of which circulated independently
                        and are still seen as texts in their own right. The whole work is classified by Tibetan editors as
                        belonging to the Buddha’s third turning of the wheel of Dharma.</p>
                    <p tid="3">The early 9th century Tibetan translation is of similar size and content to the late 7th century Chinese
                        translation by Śikṣānanda, both being larger than the earlier Chinese translation by Buddhabhadra (early
                        5th century). Chinese translations of individual works that were later incorporated into the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka were made even earlier (late 2nd to early 4th century), and may provide evidence of the
                        gradual evolution of the Buddhāvataṃsaka from its component parts. No version in any Indic language has
                        survived, and Indian treatises only quote some of its component texts rather than the whole work by the
                        name Buddhāvataṃsaka.</p>
                    <p tid="4">Tibetan historical tradition, however, as recounted by Tāranātha and mentioned briefly in the Degé Kangyur
                        catalogue, tells us that in India the collection not only existed but was originally a great deal larger,
                        with one hundred chapters (according to the Kangyur catalogue) or one thousand (Tāranātha), but is now
                        incomplete because an arson attack on the library at Nālandā reduced it to only thirty-eight surviving
                        chapters. The date of this event, said to have been responsible for the decimation of many other
                        scriptures, too (including much of the Ratnakūṭa), is placed some time before the lives of Asaṅga and
                        Vasubandhu, along with accounts of other calamitous episodes during a period of political turbulence and
                        unstable patronage for Buddhist institutions in India.</p>
                    <p tid="5">The Buddhāvataṃsaka was studied far more extensively in China than in Tibet, generating an extensive corpus
                        of commentarial literature, and a whole school of Chinese Buddhism, the Huayan, is based on it. Although
                        held in great esteem in Tibet, it was very little studied as a whole, and only a few of the later chapters
                        were widely known and quoted. It was translated into Tibetan in its entirety by Jinamitra, Surendrabodhi,
                        and Yeshé Dé, almost certainly from a Sanskrit original. The Tibetan translation contains two chapters, 11
                        and 32, not found in any of the Chinese translations.</p>
                    <p tid="6">According to Chinese tradition with its several versions, the whole work is divided into 34 or 39 chapters,
                        grouped into eight or nine “assemblies” according to the places and occasions where the teachings they
                        relate took place.</p>
                    <p tid="7">The way the text is divided into chapters is different in the Tibetan version. Several of the Kangyur
                        catalogues mention the first 29 chapters as constituting the Buddhāvataṃsaka proper, and add various
                        alternative titles for the work such as <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas smag chad</title> (the
                        buddhas’ absence of darkness), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smad chad</title> or <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rmad
                            gcad</title> (universal containment, the latter being the form used in the first line of each
                        fascicle), as well as <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snyan gyi gong rgyan</title> (ornaments for the ears) and
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">padma’i rgyan</title> (lotus ornaments). Following both of the surviving
                        early text inventories, the Pangthangma and Denkarma, they then name a selection of the later chapters,
                        leaving ambiguous their status as texts independent of the Buddhāvataṃsaka itself or part of it. The text
                        itself gives its component parts none of the trappings of independent texts, such as Sanskrit titles or
                        the usual opening phrases. However, as some of the later chapters are known to have circulated
                        independently in India as well as in China and Tibet, it is reasonable to speak of the Buddhāvataṃsaka as
                        a “family” of texts even if little is known of how and why they came to be grouped together in this
                        way.</p>
                    <p tid="8">There are nevertheless some shared features. Most of the narrative elements of the texts (with the exception of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title>) take place in the few weeks following the Buddha’s awakening. As tradition holds that he did not teach during this time but remained silently in meditation, the teachings set out in the texts are given by Mañjuśrī, Samantabhadra, and other bodhisattvas. Another common feature is the view that all buddhas and bodhisattvas, wherever they may manifest, are emanations of the Buddha Vairocana. </p>
                    <p tid="8">Some of the chapters with known independent status are as follows:</p>
                    <p tid="9">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gocarapariśuddha</title> (chapter 16) may be the same work as a sūtra with
                        this name cited in several Indian treatises. It is listed as a separate text of the Buddhāvataṃsaka in the
                        Mahāvyutpatti, and a work in the Tengyur (Toh 3965) summarizes its contents.</p>
                    <p tid="10">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajradhvajapariṇāma</title> (chapter 30) is listed as a separate text of the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka in the Denkarma catalogue and is probably the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajradhvajasūtra</title> mentioned by Śāntideva in the Bodhicaryāvatāra (VII.46). It contains its own
                        set of ten chapters.</p>
                    <p tid="11">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśabhūmika</title> (chapter 31) is known to have circulated as an independent
                        work in India, and has survived as a complete Sanskrit manuscript in Nepal. It is found in Kangyurs of the
                        Thempangma tradition and independent Kangyurs as a separate sūtra, as well as a chapter of the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka, the two Tibetan translations in such cases being different ones. It figures in its own
                        right in the Mahāvyutpatti.</p>
                    <p tid="12">A Sanskrit text of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anantabuddhakṣetraguṇodbhāvana</title> (chapter 37) has
                        recently been discovered, with a colophon in Sanskrit describing the sūtra as from the Buddhāvataṃsaka; it
                        also exists as two independent Tibetan translations, Toh 104 and Toh 268.</p>
                    <p tid="13">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhadharmācintyanirdeśa</title> (chapter 39) is also found in the General
                        Sūtra section of the Kangyur with the same title as an independent work (Toh 187) that appears to be a
                        close but not identical translation of the same original.</p>
                    <p tid="14">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samantabhadracāryanirdeśa</title> (chapter 42) is listed as a separate text of
                        the Buddhāvataṃsaka in the Denkarma catalogue.</p>
                    <p tid="15">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatotpattisambhavanirdeśa</title> (chapter 43) is also listed as a
                        separate text of the Buddhāvataṃsaka in the Phangtangma and Denkarma catalogues and figures in its own
                        right in the Mahāvyutpatti. It is quoted in several Indian treatises.</p>
                    <p tid="16">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lottaraparivarta</title> (chapter 44) is listed as a separate text of the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka in the Phangtangma and Denkarma catalogues, and figures in its own right in the
                        Mahāvyutpatti.</p>
                    <p tid="17">Approximately the last third of the Buddāvataṃsaka is taken up by the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūha</title> (chapter 45), one of the best known texts of the family. It is also listed as a
                        separate text in the Denkarma catalogue, figures in its own right in the Mahāvyutpatti, and is quoted in
                        numerous Indian treatises. It has also survived as a complete Sanskrit manuscript in Nepal. Its story
                        narrating the youth Sudhana's spiritual quest and meetings with fifty-two teachers is depicted in detail
                        in the stone carvings of Borobudur in central Java.</p>
                    <p tid="18">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadracaryāpraṇidhāna</title>, the dedication “Prayer of Good Action” recited
                        widely in the Tibetan Buddhist tradition, forms the conclusion of chapter 45. It is also found on its own
                        in the Dhāraṇī section (Toh 1095).</p>
                    <p tid="19">Other works that may be considered members of the Buddhāvataṃsaka “family,” but are found elsewhere in most
                        Kangyurs, include the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnolkā</title> (Toh 145 and 847), passages of which are
                        found in chapters 17 and 20, and which is listed as belonging to the Buddhāvataṃsaka in the Phangtangma
                        catalogue and in the Mahāvyutpatti; the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgataguṇajñānācintyaviṣayāvatāranirdeśa</title> (Toh 185); the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhadharmācintyanirdeśa</title> (Toh 187), which is an independent version of chapter 39, has the
                        same title, and is close but not identical; and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śraddhābalādhānāvatāramudrā</title> (Toh 201).</p>
                    <p tid="20">For further details, see: <lb/>Skilling, Peter, and Saerji, “The Circulation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title> in India” in <title xml:lang="en">ARIRIAB</title>, vol. 16, 193-216 (March
                        2013). <lb/>Nattier, Jan, “The Proto-History of the Buddhāvataṃsaka: the Pusa benye jing and the Dousha jing,”
                        in <title>ARIRIAB</title> vol. 7, 323-360 (March 2005). <lb/>Hamar, Imre, “The History of the
                        Buddhāvataṃsaka-Sūtra: Shorter and Larger Texts.” In: Hamar, Imre (ed.), <title xml:lang="en">Reflecting
                            Mirrors: Perspectives on Huayan Buddhism</title> (Asiatische Forschungen Vol. 151), Wiesbaden:
                        Harrassowitz, pp.159-161 (2007). <lb/>Tāranātha, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam pa’i chos rin po che ’phags pa’i
                            yul du ji ltar dar ba’i tshul gsal bar ston pa dgos ’dod kun ’byung</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya gar chos ’byung</title> from Degé xylographs), Tezu, A.P., India: Tibetan Nyingma Monastery
                        (1974), ff. 47a-48b. Translation in Chimpa, L. et al. (trans.), <title xml:lang="en">Tāranātha's History
                            of Buddhism in India</title>, Atlantic Highlands, N.J.: Humanities Press (1981), pp. 140-143.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>