<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon brtsegs/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Heap of Jewels</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="8">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:28 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Forty-nine selected sūtras on a range of themes, compiled as a separate collection also found in the Chinese
                    Tripiṭaka (Toh 45-93).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Heap of Jewels</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This is a compilation of forty-nine heterogeneous sūtras, present in both the Kangyur and the Chinese
                        Tripiṭaka.</p>
                    <p tid="3">The Heap of Jewels—like the other distinct collection preceding it in the Kangyur, the Ornament of the
                        Buddhas (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title>)—is often described as a sūtra, its full
                        Sanskrit title being <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratnakūṭasūtra</title> (“the Sūtra of the Great Heap of
                        Jewels”), and in Tibetan <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen po’i chos kyi rnam
                            grangs le’u stong phrag brgya pa</title> (“the Noble Dharma Discourse of the Great Heap of Precious
                        Jewels with a Hundred Thousand Chapters”). Unlike the Ornament of the Buddhas, however, its component
                        texts or chapters are explicitly presented as independent works. Many of them are individually cited in
                        the treatises of the great Indian masters and are known to have circulated as sūtras in their own right;
                        only five are still extant in Sanskrit.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-2"/>
                    <p tid="4">Although the name <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> (“heap of jewels” or, more exactly, “piled-up
                        jewels”) seems quite appropriate for such a compilation of precious scriptural works, it is in fact the
                        name by which just one of the texts in the collection, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title> (Toh 87) was originally known, and seems to have been applied to the whole
                        collection only later. Citations from a <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭasūtra</title> in works by
                        Asaṅga, Śāntideva, and other authors all refer to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title>,
                        which is sometimes therefore designated the “old” <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-3"/>
                    <p tid="5">The history of the Heap of Jewels remains unclear. Tibetan historical tradition, as mentioned briefly in
                        the Degé Kangyur catalogue and recounted more fully by Tāranātha, tells us that the originally much larger
                        collection (with a thousand chapters, or even the hundred thousand of the full title) was reduced to its
                        current forty-nine texts by an arson attack on the library at Nālandā. The date of this event, said to
                        have been responsible for the decimation of many other scriptures, too (including the Buddhāvataṃsaka), is
                        placed some time before the lives of Asaṅga and Vasubandhu, along with accounts of other calamitous
                        episodes during a period of political turbulence and unstable patronage for Buddhist institutions in
                        India.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-4"/>
                    <p tid="6">According to modern historical methods, while the Heap of Jewel's component texts can be traced back in
                        some cases to dates early in the appearance of Mahāyāna texts, evidence that the collection as a whole
                        existed in India (i.e. before it appeared in China) is present but sparse. The earliest mention of it is
                        in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśabhūmikavibhāṣa</title>, attributed to Nāgārjuna and translated into
                        Chinese by Kumārajīva in the early 5th century. The 6th century Gandhāran translator Jñānagupta seems to
                        have spoken of it, and the famous Chinese traveler Xuanzang was asked to translate it in 664, although he
                        only made a start. It was Bodhiruci who collected and translated it into Chinese in the first decade of
                        the 8th century, using 23 texts already circulating in Chinese and adding 26 new translations of his own;
                        it is reasonable to assume that he was using an Indian (or perhaps central Asian) prototype. The Tibetan
                        collection follows the Chinese closely in structure and composition, but most of the texts were evidently
                        translated directly from Sanskrit originals (with a few exceptions, namely Toh 51, 57, 58, and 84, which
                        are known to have been translated from the Chinese). The Tibetan translation is mentioned with a full list
                        of its present component texts in the early 9th century <title xml:lang="en">Denkarma</title> catalogue,
                        though surprisingly the other early inventory, the <title xml:lang="en">Pangthangma</title> (which is
                        thought to be of a slightly later date) lists only nine works under that heading (the other forty being
                        listed in more general size-ranked categories), and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>
                        names some of the Ratnakūṭa sūtras without any mention of the collection’s name.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14667-5"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtras in the collection cover a wide range of subjects and have diverse origins. Two (Toh 57 and 58)
                        are Śrāvakayāna works from the Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinaya; one (Toh 90) is a Prajñāpāramitā sūtra; and two
                        (Toh 49 and 50) are Pure Land works. The majority are Mahāyāna sūtras dealing with classic themes such as
                        emptiness, compassion, wisdom, the bodhisattva's vows and path. The very variety of its works suggests
                        that it may have been deliberately compiled as an anthology representing many topics.</p>
                    <p tid="8">For further details, see: Pedersen, K. Priscilla, “Notes on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> collection,” JIABS vol. 3 no. 2, 60-67 (1980).
                        Nattier, Jan, <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men: the Bodhisattva Path According to The Inquiry of
                            Ugra (Ugraparipṛcchā)</title>, University of Hawaii Press (2003).
                        Tāranātha, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam pa’i chos rin po che ’phags pa’i yul du ji ltar dar ba’i
                            tshul gsal bar ston pa dgos ’dod kun ’byung</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya gar chos
                                ’byung</title>, from Degé xylographs), Tezu, A.P., India: Tibetan Nyingma Monastery (1974), ff.
                        47a-48b. Translation in Chimpa, L. et al. (trans.), <title xml:lang="en">Tāranātha's History of
                            Buddhism in India</title>, Atlantic Highlands, N.J.: Humanities Press (1981), pp. 140-143.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>