<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">General Sūtra Section</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="9">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:23:03 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The principal collection of 266 sūtras, varied in length, subject, interlocutors and origins (Toh 94-359).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">General Sūtra Section</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This large section of the Kangyur is also sometimes called <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo mang</title> (“the
                        many sūtras”) or <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sna tshogs</title> (“miscellaneous sūtras”). In the Degé
                        Kangyur it contains 266 works, while in other Kangyurs the contents and their order vary somewhat. The
                        texts range in length from a few lines to more than 2,000 pages.</p>
                    <p tid="3">It is thought that many of these works circulated in Tibet, during the centuries preceding the evolution
                        and establishment of the different Kangyurs, in the form of varying compilations of sūtra works called
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo mang</title>, some of which have survived.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-2"/>
                    <p tid="4">According to the Degé Kangyur catalogue, the works in this section are arranged with Mahāyāna sūtras (Toh
                        94-286) first, followed by Śrāvakayāna works (Toh 287-359)—although not all Kangyurs and commentators
                        agree on which texts should be assigned to these two broad groups. As Situ Paṇchen Chökyi Jungné, the 18th
                        century editor of the Degé Kangyur, observes, sūtras of the Buddha’s third turning of the wheel of Dharma
                        tend to predominate at first, but such categorizing is not always applicable and he himself, as he laid
                        out the Degé Kangyur, simply respected the precedent set by past scholars who arranged the texts of the
                        Tshalpa Kangyur. Their schema differs significantly from the way the texts are grouped in the early 9th
                        century inventory, the Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan kar ma</title>), and the slightly later
                        Pangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang thang ma</title>), both of which order the texts first by
                        vehicle and source language, and then place them in order of physical size, starting with the longest.
                        Nevertheless, in the Degé as in many other Kangyurs, the longer files still tend to be grouped in the
                        earlier volumes.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-3"/>
                    <p tid="5">The sūtras in this General Sūtra section take many different forms. A large number of them relate dialogues
                        between the Buddha and individual disciples, whether bodhisattvas, kings, ordinary men and women, gods, or
                        nāgas. Some are teachings given by the Buddha at a particular occasion on particular topics. Sometimes
                        they relate miraculous manifestations, describe elevated states of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</foreign>, teachings given by buddhas in other realms, detailed lists of ethical or
                        philosophical points for reflection, summaries of important doctrine, explanations of individuals' past
                        lives or predictions of their future awakening, and so forth—often including several such elements in a
                        single work.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-4"/>
                    <p tid="6">Among the best known large sūtras are the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrakalpika</title> (Toh 94), which
                        lists the names, vows, and other details of the thousand buddhas of the present eon; the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title> (Toh 95), the story of the Buddha's birth, youth, awakening,
                        and first teachings; two versions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra</title> (Toh 107 and 108,
                        from the Sanskrit and Chinese respectively); the two sūtras known as <title xml:lang="en">The White
                            Lotus</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇāpuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 112) and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmapuṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113), often known as the “Lotus Sūtra” and highly
                        influential in China and Japan; and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samādhirāja</title> (Toh 127).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-5"/>
                    <p tid="7">The section contains two versions of the important <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇasūtra</foreign> (Toh 119 and 120), translated in the early period from Chinese and
                        Sanskrit respectively. The latter is only one quarter of the length of the former but represents those
                        parts of the sūtra of which fragments in Sanskrit have been found—perhaps an earlier, core version. There
                        is also a fragment (Toh 121) of a later translation by Kamalagupta and Rinchen Zangpo. The Narthang,
                        Lhasa, Stog Palace and Shelkar Kangyurs place the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇasūtra</foreign> in its own, separate division.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-6"/>
                    <p tid="8">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharmasmṛtyupasthāna</title> (Toh 287) and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmaśataka</title> (Toh 340) are the longest works in the Śrāvakayāna category of the section, the
                        latter among a group of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avadāna</title> narrative works illustrating the effects
                        of karma from one life to another.</p>
                    <p tid="9">Sūtras known to have been translated from Chinese include Toh 108, 119, 122, 123, 128, 135, 199, 216, 237,
                        239, 242, 248, 256, 264, 341, 351, and 353.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14668-7"/>
                    <p tid="10">The sūtras considered part of the Mahāsannipāta, a distinct group recognised in the Chinese tradition, are
                        Toh 138, 147, 148, 152, 169, 175, 230, and 257.</p>
                    <p tid="11">The Mahāsūtras, Toh 288-294, (together with Toh 653 and 656, which are found in the Tantra Collection and
                        duplicated as Toh 1061 and 1062 in the Incantations) form a special group with a particular function. They
                        are thought to have been brought to Tibet as part of the Vinaya transmission, and are listed in the
                        Denkarma separately from the other Śrāvakayāna works. They are probably extracted from the Āgamas of the
                        Mūlasarvāstivāda, and their regular recitation by ordained monks is recommended in the monks’ <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavibhaṅga</title> (Toh 3). For details, see Skilling, Peter, <title xml:lang="en">The Mahāsūtras: Great Discourses of the Buddha</title>, 2 vols., Bristol: Pali Text
                        Society (1997).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>