<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar 'gyur/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Thirteen late translated sūtras</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="10">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC12924"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:05 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">A group of Theravāda sūtras translated into Tibetan in the 14th century (Toh 31-43).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Thirteen late translated sūtras</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">These thirteen sūtras are to be found in most Kangyurs of the Tshalpa tradition grouped at the end of the
                        final, “miscellaneous sūtra” volume of the Perfection of Wisdom division (despite being unrelated to the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</title> literature). In other Kangyurs, they are placed in the
                        General Sūtra section—at the end in the Narthang and Lhasa Kangyurs, and in the penultimate volume in most
                        Kangyurs of the Thempangma tradition.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">They are called “newly translated” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar du ’gyur ba</foreign>) in the catalogue
                        of the Degé Kangyur, and the same epithet was used by Butön in the 14th century, as well as by Terdak
                        Lingpa and the Lithang Kangyur editors in the 17th century. The Lhasa Kangyur catalogue also calls them
                        “the group of thirteen sūtras” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo tshan bcu sum po</title>). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">They are, in fact, the last group of sūtras ever to enter the sūtra section of the Kangyur, and are not
                        present in some of the peripheral Kangyurs that may represent earlier compilations, such as the Phuktrak
                        and Newark Batang Kangyurs.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">As their colophons record, they were translated in the first decade of the 14th century at the monastery of
                        Tharpa Ling (not far from Zhalu in Central Tibet), by a translator from Ceylon, Ānandaśrī, and the Tibetan
                        translator Tharpa Lotsawa Nyima Gyaltsen Palzangpo, who was one of Butön's teachers.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The thirteen sūtras all have closely matching equivalents in the Pāli Canon, and—although they have at
                        times been thought to be translations of Sarvastivādin texts in Sanskrit, as are many other Śrāvakayāna
                        works in the Kangyur—it is almost certain that they were translated from Pāli, and are Theravāda texts,
                        i.e. from the literature of the Theravāda school. Together with a translation of the third chapter of the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimuttimagga</title> that, despite being an extract of a treatise, is
                        included for unknown reasons in the General Sūtra section (Toh 306), these are the only Pāli Theravāda
                        works represented in the Kangyur (along with another translation by Ānandaśrī and Tharpa Lotsawa, a
                        version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitrīsūtra</title> closely related to Toh 35 but found only in
                        the Berlin, Lhasa, Narthang, and Peking Kangyurs).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">Two of the thirteen texts, Toh 33 and 34, are the Theravāda equivalents of two of the ten Mūlasarvāstivādin
                        Mahāsūtras, Toh 656/1061 and Toh 653/1062 respectively.</p>
                    <p tid="8">The thirteen works are sometimes referred to as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paritta</foreign> texts, i.e.
                        texts read aloud for protection, a status they hold in the Theravāda tradition; their association with
                        auspiciousness may also partly explain why they were placed at the conclusion of the Perfection of Wisdom
                        section.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14714-7"/>
                    <p tid="9">For further details and analysis, see Skilling, Peter (1993), “Theravādin Literature in Tibetan
                        Translation,” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the Pāli Text Society</title>, vol. 19, pp 69-201.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>