<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Tantra</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="11">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC11494"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:44 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The scriptures of the Vajrayāna intended for experienced practitioners, often cryptic and hard to understand
                    without commentary (Toh 360-845).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="warning">
                <p tid="14">Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are restrictions and commitments concerning tantra.</p>
                <p tid="15">Practitioners who are not sure if they should read translations in this section are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage.</p>
                <p tid="16">The responsibility for reading these texts or sharing them with others—and hence the consequences—lies in the hands of readers.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Tantra</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">In this broad category of canonical works we have grouped three of the traditional divisions of the
                        Kangyur:</p>
                    <p tid="3">The main <label>Tantra Collection</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud ’bum</title>), containing 468
                        canonical tantra works (Toh 360-827), mainly translations from the period of the “later spread” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi dar</foreign>), and studied and practiced principally by the New
                        Schools (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar ma pa</foreign>).</p>
                    <p tid="4"/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-2"/>
                    <p tid="5">A section of <label>Old Tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnying rgyud</title>), found only in
                        Kangyurs of the Tshalpa tradition, containing a small selection (Toh 828-844) of the many tantras of the
                        “ancient tradition of the early translations” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snga ’gyur rnying ma</title>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-3"/>
                    <p tid="6">A section known as the <label>Wheel of Time Commentary</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus ’khor ’grel
                            bshad</title>), containing a single explanatory commentary (Toh 845) on the Kālacakratantra,
                        traditionally accorded its own section in the Kangyur despite being a treatise or <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāstra</foreign>. Note that the texts of the Kālacakratantra itself are to be found
                        in the main Tantra Collection section, and that there are other Kālacakratantra commentaries in the
                        Tengyur.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Unrestricted access</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-4"/>
                    <p tid="7">The decision to publish tantra texts without restricted access has been considered carefully. First of all,
                        it should be noted that all the original Tibetan texts of the Kangyur, including those in this Tantra
                        section, are in the public domain. Some of the texts in this section (but by no means all of them) are
                        nevertheless, according to some traditions, only studied with authorization and after suitable
                        preliminaries.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-5"/>
                    <p tid="8">It is true, of course, that a translation makes the content accessible to a far greater number of people;
                        84000 has therefore consulted many senior Buddhist teachers on this question, and most of them felt that
                        to publish the texts openly is, on balance, the best solution. The alternatives would be not to translate
                        them at all (which would defeat the purposes of the whole project), or to place some sort of restriction
                        on their access. Restricted access has been tried by some Buddhist book publishers, and of course needs a
                        system of administration, judgment, and policing that is either a mere formality, or is very difficult to
                        implement. It would be even harder to implement in the case of electronic texts—and even easier to
                        circumvent. Indeed, nowadays practically the whole range of traditionally restricted Tibetan Buddhist
                        material is already available to anyone who looks for it, and is all too often misrepresented, taken out
                        of context, or its secret and esoteric nature deliberately vaunted.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-6"/>
                    <p tid="9">84000’s policy is to present carefully authenticated translations in their proper setting of the whole body
                        of Buddhist sacred literature, and to trust the good sense of the vast majority of readers not to misuse
                        or misunderstand them. Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
                        restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read
                        translations in this section are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility,
                        and hence consequences, of reading these texts and/or sharing them with others who may or may not fulfill
                        the requirements lie in the hands of readers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Translation and editing of the titles</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-7"/>
                    <p tid="10">The titles (as in all sections) have been translated on the basis of the short Tibetan title given in the
                        Degé Kangyur, taking into account the Sanskrit.</p>
                    <p tid="11">The original Sanskrit titles of the various major tantras are well attested and pose only a few problems
                        here and there. However, in the case of the many lesser known works, the Sanskrit, as given at the
                        beginning of the various Tibetan works in the Degé canon (D) and reproduced with some corrections in the
                        Tōhoku Catalogue (Toh), is often problematic. Not infrequently it is a back translation from the Tibetan
                        title, with Sanskrit adjectives in the wrong places, compounds that are inverted, and other evidence that
                        it was composed following the Tibetan and adopting its word order.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-8"/>
                    <p tid="12">We have done our best to interpret such titles in the most likely fashion, but that has often meant
                        privileging the Tibetan rather than following the Sanskrit word order. In rendering the Sanskrit titles,
                        we have added some word breaks and corrected simple and obvious mistakes such as missing or wrong saṃdhi,
                        wrong long and short vowels, missing retroflex consonants, etc. Many, but not all, of the amendments made
                        by the Tōhoku Catalogue have been adopted. Where the title already contains one or more words with case
                        endings, we have added the case endings to the final words (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tantra</foreign>, etc.) in the interest of
                        consistency. We have not, however, attempted to rearrange odd Sanskrit word order or make other such
                        substantial changes. It seemed better to correct only what was obviously wrong in the Sanskrit and leave
                        the rest more or less as it was, not attempting what would, in effect, be a retranslation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14716-9"/>
                    <p tid="13">For attested proper names we have used the Sanskrit; the rest (including obscure cases) we have translated.
                        In general, the difficulties involved in translating the tantra titles are in many respects much greater
                        than in the case of the sūtras. That said, we consider this a needed start, even if certainly not a final
                        result. In short, what we present here is provisional and should be taken as such.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>