<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyud 'bum/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Tantra Collection</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC20565"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="12">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14716"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-26T11:39:07.561Z" user="admin">26/02/2019 11:39:07</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The principal tantra collection of 468 canonical tantras, mainly from the “later spread” of Vajrayāna to Tibet,
                    arranged by level (Toh 360-827).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="warning">
                <p tid="2">
                    <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there
                    are restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                    translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                    or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about" tid="18">Tantra Collection</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20565-1"/>
                    <p tid="3">This section, one of the main traditional divisions of the Kangyur, contains 468 canonical tantra works
                        (Toh 360-827), mainly translations from the period of the “later spread” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi dar</foreign>), and studied and practiced principally by the New Schools
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar ma pa</foreign>). Although this very large section is
                        present in all Kangyurs without explicit subsections, it has here been subdivided for convenience into
                        four levels of tantra and one group of concluding dedication prayers, following the catalogue (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign>) of Situ Panchen Chökyi Jungné, the 18th century
                        editor of the Degé Kangyur. These subdivisions are, in fact, implicit in the sequence in which the works
                        of this section are placed.</p>
                    <p tid="4">The <label>Unexcelled Yoga tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla med rgyud</title>, Toh 360-478)
                        are tantras of the highest class according to the New Schools, and include the non-dual tantras of
                        Kālacakra, the mother tantras of Cakrasaṃvara and Hevajra, and the father tantras of Guhyasamāja and
                        Vajrabhairava.</p>
                    <p tid="5">The <label>Yoga tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor gyi rgyud</title>, Toh 479-493) are a
                        relatively small group, the highest of the three lower tantra classes; the best known is the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Tattvasaṃgraha</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de kho na nyid bsdus
                        pa</title>).</p>
                    <p tid="6">The <label>Conduct tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod pa’i rgyud</title>, Toh 494-501) are the
                        smallest group, and include tantras centered on Vairocana and Vajrapāṇi.</p>
                    <p tid="7">The <label>Action tantras</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ba’i rgyud</title>, Toh 502-808) are the
                        largest group. In general, they focus on worship of deities external to the practitioner and the practice
                        of a wide variety of rituals for specific purposes, worldly as well as spiritual.</p>
                    <p tid="8">Finally, a group of 19 works or extracts from larger works on the theme of
                            <label>Dedication-aspiration</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsngo smon shis brjod</title>, Toh
                        808-827) is found at the end of the Tantra Collection as a conclusion, many of them prayers for dedicating
                        the merit of practice and other spiritual activities or verses expressing auspiciousness.</p>
                    <p tid="9">Fourfold classifications for tantric works such as this one, used by many Kangyur editors—and various
                        similar taxonomies, some more detailed—were established by Tibetan scholars on the basis of passages in
                        certain tantra texts and explanatory treatises. Four different levels of tantra are traditionally
                        explained as existing for practitioners of four different faculties, inclinations, degrees of ability and
                        endeavor, four castes, four mistaken views, four philosophical outlooks, four emotional obscurations, and
                        four kinds of desire; and also to purify four different states of existence, periods of the day, divine
                        realms, and so forth. Most of the numerous tantra texts brought to Tibet came without inherent indications
                        of their place in such schemes, and the placing of individual texts is not always definitive or
                        universally agreed upon. Even the classification of certain texts as sūtra or tantra is debatable, and a
                        few works are found in both sections.</p>
                    <p tid="10">For further details on the Tibetan tradition’s classification of tantras, see section 6, chapter 4 in:
                        Jamgön Kongtrul (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam mgon kong sprul blo gros mtha’ yas</title>), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes bya kun khyab</title>, Delhi: Shechen Publications (1997). Translated as
                        Guarisco, E. and McLeod, I (trans.), <title xml:lang="en">The Treasury of Knowledge: Book 6, Part 4,
                            Systems of Buddhist Tantra</title>, Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications (2005), especially chapters 2 and
                        15.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="19">Unrestricted access</head>
                    <p tid="11">The decision to publish tantra texts without restricted access has been considered carefully. First of all,
                        it should be noted that all the original Tibetan texts of the Kangyur, including those in this Tantra
                        section, are in the public domain. Some of the texts in this section (but by no means all of them) are
                        nevertheless, according to some traditions, only studied with authorization and after suitable
                        preliminaries.</p>
                    <p tid="12">It is true, of course, that a translation makes the content accessible to a far greater number of people;
                        84000 has therefore consulted many senior Buddhist teachers on this question, and most of them felt that
                        to publish the texts openly is, on balance, the best solution. The alternatives would be not to translate
                        them at all (which would defeat the purposes of the whole project), or to place some sort of restriction
                        on their access. Restricted access has been tried by some Buddhist book publishers, and of course needs a
                        system of administration, judgment, and policing that is either a mere formality, or is very difficult to
                        implement. It would be even harder to implement in the case of electronic texts—and even easier to
                        circumvent. Indeed, nowadays practically the whole range of traditionally restricted Tibetan Buddhist
                        material is already available to anyone who looks for it, and is all too often misrepresented, taken out
                        of context, or its secret and esoteric nature deliberately vaunted.</p>
                    <p tid="13">84000’s policy is to present carefully authenticated translations in their proper setting of the whole body
                        of Buddhist sacred literature, and to trust the good sense of the vast majority of readers not to misuse
                        or misunderstand them. Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
                        restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read
                        translations in this section are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility,
                        and hence consequences, of reading these texts and/or sharing them with others who may or may not fulfill
                        the requirements lie in the hands of readers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="20">Translation and editing of the titles</head>
                    <p tid="14">The titles (as in all sections) have been translated on the basis of the short Tibetan title given in the
                        Degé Kangyur, taking into account the Sanskrit.</p>
                    <p tid="15">The original Sanskrit titles of the various major tantras are well attested and pose only a few problems
                        here and there. However, in the case of the many lesser known works, the Sanskrit, as given at the
                        beginning of the various Tibetan works in the Degé canon (D) and reproduced with some corrections in the
                        Tōhoku Catalogue (Toh), is often problematic. Not infrequently it is a back translation from the Tibetan
                        title, with Sanskrit adjectives in the wrong places, compounds that are inverted, and other evidence that
                        it was composed following the Tibetan and adopting its word order.</p>
                    <p tid="16">We have done our best to interpret such titles in the most likely fashion, but that has often meant
                        privileging the Tibetan rather than following the Sanskrit word order. In rendering the Sanskrit titles,
                        we have added some word breaks and corrected simple and obvious mistakes such as missing or wrong saṃdhi,
                        wrong long and short vowels, missing retroflex consonants, etc. Many, but not all, of the amendments made
                        by the Tōhoku Catalogue have been adopted. Where the title already contains one or more words with case
                        endings, we have added the case endings to the final words (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tantra</foreign>, etc.) in the interest of
                        consistency. We have not, however, attempted to rearrange odd Sanskrit word order or make other such
                        substantial changes. It seemed better to correct only what was obviously wrong in the Sanskrit and leave
                        the rest more or less as it was, not attempting what would, in effect, be a retranslation.</p>
                    <p tid="17">For attested proper names we have used the Sanskrit; the rest (including obscure cases) we have translated.
                        In general, the difficulties involved in translating the tantra titles are in many respects much greater
                        than in the case of the sūtras. That said, we consider this a needed start, even if certainly not a final
                        result. In short, what we present here is provisional and should be taken as such.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>