<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anuttarayoga / Yoganiruttaratantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Unexcelled Yoga tantras</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="">bla med rgyud/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="13">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20565"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-26T11:38:34.839Z" user="admin">26/02/2019 11:38:34</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Tantras of the highest class, divided into “non-dual,” “mother,” and “father,” and within the two latter
                    categories into six “families” of principal deities (Toh 360-478).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="warning">
                <p tid="2">
                    <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there
                    are restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                    translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                    or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about" tid="27">Unexcelled Yoga tantras</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <p tid="3">The works in this subsection are classified as belonging to the highest of the four classes of tantra
                        according to the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar ma</foreign> (“new”) traditions. The Tibetan
                        term for the Unexcelled Yoga class, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor bla na med pa’i rgyud</title>, has
                        traditionally been back-translated into Sanskrit as <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anuttarayogatantra</title>,
                        but this term is not attested in Sanskrit texts; using forms that are attested, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoganiruttaratantra</title> or <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogottaratantra</title> are preferable.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-1"/>
                    <p tid="4">The Unexcelled Yoga tantras are characterized by the practices of the two phases of generation and
                        completion, by their approach to the deity as inseparable in all respects from the practitioner, and by
                        their emphasis on wisdom or awareness (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes</foreign>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-2"/>
                    <p tid="5">Tantras of this class are subdivided into three main groups: non-dual tantras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyis med kyi rgyud</title>), mother tantras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma’i rgyud</title>), and
                        father tantras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha’i rgyud</title>). The mother tantras emphasize wisdom (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab</title>), while the father tantras
                        emphasize method or skillful means (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</title>), and these two categories were initially the only divisions within the Unexcelled Yoga
                        tantras. As Situ Paṇchen’s Degé Kangyur catalogue mentions, the third category, non-dual tantras,
                        emphasizing the union of wisdom and means, was thought necessary by Butön to accomodate the
                        Kālacakratantra in particular. The placing of tantras in these categories, and the criteria on which such
                        classifications should be based, were far from being universally agreed upon by Tibetan scholars, and even
                        between the Degé Kangyur and Tengyur there are considerable differences.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-3"/>
                    <p tid="6">
                        <label>I. The Non-dual tantras</label>, Toh 360-365, comprise the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjusrīnāmasaṃgīti</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālacakra</title> tantras:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-4"/>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="7">(a) The <label>Mañjusrīnāmasaṃgīti</label> (Toh 360) was translated into Tibetan in the imperial, “early” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snga dar</title>) period and again in the “later” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi dar</title>)
                                period, the translation in the Degé Kangyur being the later one. Situ Paṇchen notes that while
                                some (i.e. Nyingma) scholars consider the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjusrīnāmasaṃgīti</title> to
                                be part of the samādhi section of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyājāla-Guhyagarbha</title> cycle
                                and would classify it as father tantra, others follow a statement in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā</title> (Toh 845, the commentary on the Kālacakra Laghutantra) according to
                                which it represents the ultimate meaning of all the tantras and, in particular, the essence of the
                                Kālacakra, and place it, as here, at the head of the whole tantra division.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-5"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="8">(b) The texts of the <label>Kālacakra</label> (Toh 361-365), traditionally said to have their
                                origin in the land of Shambhala, were translated into Tibetan in the 11th century. The original
                                Root Tantra, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūla</title> or <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramādibuddha</title>, has not survived in Sanskrit and was not translated, but Toh 362 is
                                the abridged five-chapter version (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghutantra</title>) compiled by the
                                Shambhala King Mañjuśrī Yaśas, and is said to have been translated into Tibetan no less than 16
                                times, the version here being that of Somanātha and Dro Sherab Drak. Toh 361 and 365 are extracts
                                from the Mūlatantra on the subject of the empowerment. See also the separate Kālacakra Commentary
                                section.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-6"/>
                    <p tid="9">Note that in the Tantra section of the Tengyur, in contrast to that of the Kangyur, commentaries and
                        liturgical works on the Hevajra tantras (see below) are placed first in the order of texts and are
                        classified (in the Tengyur Catalogue) as non-dual.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-7"/>
                    <p tid="10">
                        <label>II. The 76 Mother tantras</label>, Toh 366-441, are often referred to as the Yoginītantras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor ma’i rgyud</title>), and are divided into seven subgroups in terms of six
                        families (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rigs drug</title>):</p>
                    <list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-8"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="11">(a) Those in which <label>the six families are taught to be equal</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rigs drug ka mnyam par ston pa</title>, Toh 366 and 367), the tantras of
                                Ḍākinījālaśaṃvara.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-9"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="12">(b) The <label>heruka family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">he ru ka’i rigs</title>), comprising
                                the tantras associated with five deities: 1. <label>Śaṃvara</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde
                                    mchog</title>): the root or <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghutantra</title> (Toh 368) is said to be
                                condensed from much longer original texts of 300,000 and 100,000 stanzas. Among the explanatory
                                tantras (Toh 369-382) are the important <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidhānottara</title> (Toh 369),
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dākarṇava</title> (Toh 372), and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śaṃvoradaya</title> (Toh 373). This section also contains a distinct corpus of 32 short
                                explanatory tantras (Toh 383-416) translated by Drokmi Shākya Yeshé and known collectively as the
                                Rali tantras (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ra li’i rgyud</title>). 2. <label>Hevajra</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kye rdor</title>, Toh 417-423) 3. <label>Buddhakapāla</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas thod pa</title>, Toh 424) 4. <label>Mahāmāyā</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma hA mA yA</title>, Toh 425) 5. <label>Vajrārali</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje A ra li</title>, Toh 426-427)</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-10"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="13">(c) The <label>Vairocana (or Buddha) family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam snang gi
                                rigs</title>), comprising tantras centered on: 1. <label>Vairocana</label> (Toh 428-430) 2.
                                <label>Caṇḍamahāroṣaṇa</label> (Toh 431) 3. <label>Acala</label> (Toh 432-434).</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-11"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="14">(d) The <label>Vajrasūrya (or Ratna) family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje nyi ma’i
                                rigs</title>), here a single tantra of Vajrāmṛta (Toh 435)</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-12"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="15">(e) The <label>Lotus Lord family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad+ma gar dbang gi
                                rigs</title>), comprising an extract from the <title xml:lang="en">Great Tantra of the Blazing
                                    Lotus</title> (Toh 436) and the <title xml:lang="en">Practice Manual of Kurukullā</title> (Toh
                                437).</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-13"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="16">(f) The <label>Aśvottama family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rta mchog</title>, “Supreme
                                Horse”), comprising the <title xml:lang="en">Praise of Tārā in Twenty-One Homages</title> (Toh
                                438), a fragment from the Vajrakīlaya root tantra (Toh 439), and the <title xml:lang="en">Tantra
                                    of Mahākāla</title> (Toh 440).</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-14"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="17">(g) The <label>Vajradhara family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje ’chang gi rigs</title>),
                                here a single tantra, the <title xml:lang="en">Extant Khasama Tantra</title> (Toh 441).</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-15"/>
                           <p tid="18">
                        <label>III. The 37 Father tantras</label>, Toh 442-478, are divided (in theory, at least) into six
                        subgroups, of which two are not represented:</p>
                    <list>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-16"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="19">(a) The <label>Akṣobhya family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi bskyod pa’i rigs</title>, Toh
                                442-465), including the root tantra of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhyasamāja</title> (Toh 442)
                                and its explanatory tantras (Toh 443-447 and 450). Of these, Toh 444 and 447 are mainly
                                exegetical, while Toh 445 and 446 focus on the yogic practices of the subtle body. Toh 447 and Toh
                                450 have the same title. The section also includes a number of tantras related to Vajrapāṇi (Toh
                                452-457 and 463-464).</p>
                            <p tid="20">The two tantras of Tārāyoginī (Toh 448 and 449), present only in later printings of the Degé and
                                inserted at the end of volume 81, are not mentioned in the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar
                                    chag</title>; they clearly do not belong to this group but were placed here for
                                convenience.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-17"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="21">(b) The <label>Vairocana family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam snang gi rigs</title>), Toh
                                466-475), mostly comprising tantras of Yamāri (or Yamāntaka) and Vajrabhairava, but starting with
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyājāla</title>.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-18"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="22">(c) The <label>Ratnasambhava family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin ’byung gi rigs</title>),
                                not represented in the Kangyur.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-19"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="23">(d) The <label>Amitābha family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag med kyi rigs</title>),
                                represented by the single tantra of Ekajaṭa (Toh 476).</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-20"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="24">(e) The <label>Amoghasiddhi family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don yod grub pa’i
                                rigs</title>), also not represented in the Kangyur.</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-21"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="25">(f) The <label>Vajradhara family</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje ’chang gi rigs</title>),
                                here a single tantra, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraguhyatilakatantra</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla gsang thig le’i rgyud</title>, Toh 477).</p>
                        </item>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC21412-22"/>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="26">An extra work, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Raktayamāritantra</title> (Toh 478), was added to the
                                end of volume 83 in later printings of the Degé Kangyur, but presumably belongs to the Vairocana
                                family rather than that of Vajradhara.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>