<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yogatantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Yoga tantras</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="">rnal ’byor gyi rgyud/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC21413"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="14">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20565"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:21:18 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Tantras of the Yoga class based mainly on meditational practices, including those emphasizing skillful means
                    followed by those emphasizing wisdom (Toh 479-493).</p>
            </div>
            <div type="warning">
                <p tid="2">
                    <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there
                    are restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                    translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                    or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Yoga tantras</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <p tid="3">The Yoga tantras are the highest of the three groups of so-called “outer” tantras. Compared to the two
                        lower groups, they place more emphasis on the cultivation of internal meditative practices than on
                        external, ritual purity. These internal practices are characterized by the combination of the relative,
                        the method or skillful means (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign>) of the practice of visualizing oneself as the deity, with the
                        ultimate, the state of non-conceptual wisdom (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>,
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab</foreign>) inseparable from the deity’s appearances.
                        The principal deity here is Vairocana.</p>
                    <p tid="4">The relatively small number of tantras of this class (fifteen, Toh 479-493) are subdivided into two main
                        groups: those emphasizing method or skillful means, and those emphasizing wisdom.</p>
                    <p tid="5">
                        <label>I. The 8 tantras emphasizing skillful means</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs gtso bor ston
                            pa’i rgyud</title>):</p>
                    <list>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="6">(a) The root tantra, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattvasaṃgraha</title> (Toh 479), the main tantra
                                of this group and an important early tantric work very influential in the development of tantra in
                                China and Japan as well as in Tibet.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="7">(b) Three explanatory tantras (Toh 480-482).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="8">(c) Four supporting (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cha mthun</title>) tantras (Toh 483-486). </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <label>II. The 7 tantras emphasizing wisdom</label> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab gtso bor ston pa’i
                            rgyud</title>, Toh 487-493). Among these are duplicates of two of the “tantric” Prajñāpāramitā works
                        (Toh 489 and 491).</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>