<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus 'khor 'grel bshad/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālacakra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Wheel of Time Commentary</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC20567"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="20">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14716"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:30 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">A single commentary on the Kālacakratantra, traditionally accorded its own section in the Kangyur despite being
                    a treatise or śāstra (Toh 845).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Wheel of Time Commentary</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20567-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This section is one of the traditional primary divisions of the Degé Kangyur, despite only containing a
                        single text which is not, strictly speaking, Buddha-word, being a treatise. The Lithang, Degé, and Urga
                        Kangyurs include this text, which in most other cases is found only in the Tengyur.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20567-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">The text in question is the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabha</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med
                        ’od</title>), a commentary on the Kālacakra <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghutantra</title> (Toh 362)
                        said to have been written by King Puṇḍarīka, eighth king of Shambhala and son of King Yaśas (who compiled
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghutantra</title> itself). It was first translated into Tibetan from
                        Sanskrit in the 11th century by the Kashmiri scholar Somanātha and Sherab Trak, and later revised by
                        Zhangtön Dodé Pal, Tsultrim Dar, and Shongtön.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20567-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign> explains that “although it belongs with the
                        treatises, as it is the sovereign of all the tantra commentaries that unravel the most definitive, secret,
                        highest of all mantra systems, it has been published here—just as past scholars have placed it—in order to
                        honor it as the equivalent of the Teacher’s own word.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20567-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The division is placed by the compilers of the Tōhoku catalogue between the Old Tantras and the
                        Incantations, and although it is clearly intended to come right at the end of the Degé Kangyur, as its
                        final fifth chapter shares a volume with the Kangyur <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar
                            chags</foreign> (catalogue), we have placed it here along with the other Tantra sections for
                        convenience and to maintain the sequence of Toh numbers.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>