<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs 'dus/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Compendium of Incantations</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="23">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14717"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:07 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">The actual collection of 249 dhāraṇī texts (Toh 846-1093).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Compendium of Incantations</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC20568-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The 249 texts in this section all belong to the genre of “Incantations,” a somewhat unsatisfactory
                        translation of the Sanskrit term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> (Tibetan
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs</foreign>. This term can mean “memory” or “retention” as
                        well as designating a formulaic sequence of syllables or words (of the kind that characterizes these
                        texts) understood to have a power greater than their mere semantic content.</p>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇī</foreign> in the sense of “retention” refers to a quality
                        of mind or accomplishment said to be attained by arhats and bodhisattvas that allows them to memorize long
                        teachings and instructions, one method of so doing being to compress them into a few words or syllables
                        which then provide a key or mnemonic for their later recall. These words or syllables therefore contain
                        all the potency of the material of which they are the quintessence, and can be deployed in rituals for a
                        wide variety of purposes. Although such <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> are often
                        taken to be of a tantric nature (and many of them are indeed of tantric origin), their use is widespread
                        in many Buddhist traditions outside any tantric influence. The term is thus distinct from the related term
                        “mantra.”</p>
                    <p tid="4">Works of this genre almost always include more than simply such a formula or set of formulae (usually in
                        Sanskrit). Typically, an introductory narrative may explain their history and the reasons for their being
                        taught, and a concluding section may describe how they should be used and what results and benefits will
                        ensue.</p>
                    <p tid="5">A total of 108 <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> texts are listed in the early 9th
                        century Denkarma catalogue, including a set headed the “Five Great Incantations,” a miscellaneous group of
                        103 other works, and a set of nine works centered on the recital of the 108 names of a deity or
                        bodhisattva.</p>
                    <p tid="6">The slightly later Pangthangma inventory lists the same “Five Great Incantations,” 13 miscellaneous
                        incantations with rituals, a set of 89 incantations ranked in order of their different size, a group of
                        nine “essence” mantra-incantations extracted from larger texts elsewhere, and a final mixed group of 34
                        texts, some with 108 names, some praises, expressions of auspiciousness, or aspiration prayers.</p>
                    <p tid="7">In most Kangyurs, works categorized as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> are to be
                        found in the General Sūtra section and in several subdivisions of the Tantra Collection. But in addition,
                        Kangyurs of the Tshalpa tradition contain the present Compendium of Incantations as a separate collection.
                        Nevertheless, almost all of the works it contains are duplicates of works in other divisions of the
                        Kangyur. Only 13 titles in this section are unique to this part of the Kangyur: Toh 846, 862, 865, 912,
                        952, 953, 987, 1059, 1059A, 1066, 1067, 1090, and 1091.</p>
                    <p tid="8">As well as works conforming to the usual structure of a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign>, the section also includes texts containing the 108 names of the Buddha (Toh 873),
                        the Eight Bodhisattvas (Toh 874-881), Tāra (Toh 1000), and the wealth god Jambhala (Toh 972); sūtras
                        recited for ritual and protective purposes, including three of the Mahāsūtras (Toh 1061-2 and 1093); texts
                        that essentialize much longer works, whether sūtra or tantra (Toh 932-934 and 939-945); and a number of
                        praises and invocations.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>