<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="pseudo-section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka' 'gyur dkar chag</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Kangyur Catalogue</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC114941JC14718"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W22084" sort-index="25">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC11494"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:41 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Historical and descriptive catalogue of the Degé Kangyur by its 18th century editor Situ Paṇchen Chökyi Jungné
                    (Toh 4568).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Kangyur Catalogue</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14718-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">Most of the final, 103rd volume of the Degé Kangyur is taken up by this historical and descriptive
                        catalogue, written by the 18th century editor responsible for compiling and arranging the Degé edition,
                        Situ Paṇchen Chökyi Jungné (while the last 230 pages or so of the volume contain the fifth and final
                        chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā</title>—see the Wheel of Time Commentary
                        section).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14718-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">The first three chapters, well over half of the work, provide a detailed history of the scriptures, from
                        their first teaching and the manner in which they were preserved and spread in India, their translation
                        into Tibetan, and how they were collected, edited and compiled as the Kangyur.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14718-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The catalogue and index itself comes in the fourth chapter. Situ Paṇchen lists the content of each section
                        and volume, recording the Tibetan title of each work, its length measured in <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ślokas</foreign> (units of 32 syllables) and fascicles (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalāpa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bam po</foreign>, bound
                        bundles of palm leaf or birch bark folios), the number of chapters (if any), and its translators and
                        editors. For some texts, he adds notes on their origin or on known variants, and in some sections he
                        explains how and why he has chosen to present the texts in a particular order.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC114941JC14718-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The fifth and final chapter explains the needs that are met by the publication of the canonical texts, and
                        concludes with a long dedication in verse.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>