<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anuttarayoga / Yoganiruttaratantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Unexcelled Yoga tantra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="">bla med rgyud/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W23703" sort-index="4">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC76301JC7704"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:23:20 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Commentaries on tantras of the highest class, divided into “non-dual,” “wisdom,” and “skillful means” tantras
                    (Toh 1180-2502).</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Unexcelled Yoga tantras</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The texts in this subsection are works on tantras classified as belonging to the highest of the four
                        classes of tantra according to the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar ma</foreign> (“new”) traditions. The
                        Tibetan term for the Unexcelled Yoga class, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor bla na med pa’i
                            rgyud</foreign>, has traditionally been back-translated into Sanskrit as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anuttarayogatantra</foreign>, but this term is not attested in Sanskrit texts; using forms that are
                        attested, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoganiruttaratantra</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogottaratantra</foreign> are preferable.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">The Unexcelled Yoga tantras are characterized by the practices of the two phases of generation and
                        completion, by their approach to the deity as inseparable in all respects from the practitioner, and by
                        their emphasis on wisdom or awareness (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes</foreign>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">Tantras of this class are subdivided into three main groups: non-dual tantras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyis med kyi rgyud</foreign>), mother tantras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma’i rgyud</foreign>), and
                        father tantras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha’i rgyud</foreign>). The mother tantras emphasize wisdom
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab</foreign>), while
                        the father tantras emphasize method or skillful means (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign>), and a third category, non-dual tantras—placed above the
                        other two—emphasize the union of wisdom and means.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The elements taught in different tantras, and statements made in them, have been used by Tibetan scholars
                        in a variety of ways to classify them into these three groups, which were probably never explicitly
                        recognized or defined in India. Nor, indeed, did Tibetan scholars always agree on the categories
                        concerned, as can be seen from the differences even between the Kangyur and Tengyur in the way individual
                        tantra cycles are placed by their editors in their respective catalogues (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar
                            chag</foreign>).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">For further details on the Tibetan tradition’s classification of tantras, see:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">Jamgön Kongtrul (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam mgon kong sprul blo gros mtha’ yas</title>), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes bya kun khyab</title>, Delhi: Shechen Publications (1997), section 6, chapter
                        4. Translated as Guarisco, E. and McLeod, I (trans.), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">The Treasury of Knowledge:
                            Book 6, Part 4, Systems of Buddhist Tantra</title>, Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications (2005), especially
                        chapters 2 and 15.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21609-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">Tsongkhapa, <title xml:lang="en">A Lamp to Illuminate the Five Stages</title>, tr. Kilty, Gavin. Library of
                        Tibetan Classics; Boston: Wisdom Publications (2013). Chapter Two, “The Two Types of Tantra,” discusses
                        different views on the division of tantras into “mother” (wisdom) and “father” (method) types.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>