<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyis med rgyud/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Non-dual tantra</title>
                </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC76301JC21614"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W23703" sort-index="5">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC76301JC21609"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-12-12T10:40:07.561Z" user="john">12/12/2019 10:40:07</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Commentaries and liturgical works related to the tantras of Hevajra and Kālacakra (Toh 1180-1400)</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about" tid="5">Non-dual tantra</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21614-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">This initial subsection on non-dual tantra—and thus the whole tantra section of the Tengyur—gives pride of
                        place to works related to the Hevajratantra (Toh 1180-1345), as Zhuchen Tsültrim Rinchen in his Degé
                        Tengyur catalogue (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign>) follows the view that the Hevajra
                        should be classified as a non-dual tantra. This is in contrast to the order in the Kangyur, where it is
                        found among the “mother” or wisdom tantras. The extensive Hevajra commentaries and liturgies here fill
                        nine volumes of the Tengyur.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21614-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">The next group of works on non-dual tantra, filling over four volumes, are those of the Kālacakratantra
                        (Toh 1346-1394), including not only the treatises and liturgical works but also the abridged root tantra
                        itself (Toh 1346) and its commentary, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā</title>, also found in the
                        Kangyur.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21614-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">This section also includes a small group of works on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrīnāmasaṃgīti</title>, which heads the non-dual tantra section in the Kangyur (and is
                        considered by some traditions to be related to the Kālacakra). Other works on this tantra are found in the
                        Skillful means tantra subdivision, in the Yoga tantra section, and in the “Other works on tantra”
                        collections.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>