<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/current/section.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc type="section">
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Other skillful means tantras</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="">thabs rgyud skor sna tshogs/</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Published in 84000 Reading Room</p>
                <idno xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622"/>
                <date>2010</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc work="W23703" sort-index="11">
                <p>Derived from previous outline file from TBRC</p>
                <bibl>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC76301JC21616"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 06/09/2018 at 11:22:52 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="abstract">
                <p tid="1">Commentaries and liturgical works related to father tantras centered on Yamāri, Vajrabhairava,
                    Mañjuśrīnāmasaṃgīti, Ekajaṭa, and Vajrapāṇi (Toh 1918-2216)</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="about">
                <head type="about">Other skillful means tantras</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-1"/>
                    <p tid="2">The 301 works in this subsection, taking up some five volumes of the Degé Tengyur, are related to seven
                        further cycles of skillful means (or father) tantras other than the Guhysamāja works, which were grouped
                        in the preceding subsection.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-2"/>
                    <p tid="3">I. The 172 works related to Yamāri (or Yamantaka) and Vajrabhairava (the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar
                            chag</foreign> counts 180, probably by counting separately some multi-part liturgical works that the
                        Tōhoku catalogue treats as a single text), in six subgroups:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">a) the 52 works related to Black Yamāri (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje gshed nag po</foreign>, Toh
                        1918-1969); the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> counts 54. The first 5 works (Toh
                        1918-1922) are commentaries, and the remaining 47 (Toh 1923-1969) are liturgical works and other
                        instructions;</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">b) the 44 works related to Vajrabhairava (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje ’jigs byed</foreign>, Toh
                        1970-2013); the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> counts 47. The first 5 works are
                        commentaries, and the remaining 39 are liturgical works and other instructions;</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">c) the 3 works related to Six-Faced Yamāri (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje gshed gdong drug
                            pa</foreign>, Toh 2014-2016); the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> counts 4;</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">d) the 70 works related to Red Yamāri (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje gshed dmar po</foreign>, Toh
                        2017-2086); the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> counts 72. Included here is a set of 36
                        sādhanas (Toh 2047-2083) by Prajñārakṣita (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab skyong</foreign>);</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">e) the 3 works related to Yamakālāyuṣpāti (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje gshed tshe bdag nag
                            po</foreign>, Toh 2087-2089).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">II. The 32 works related to the Mañjuśrīnāmasaṃgīti (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal mtshan yang dag
                            par brjod pa</foreign>, Toh 2090-2121) elucidated according to Unexcelled Yoga tantra; the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> counts 33. The first 5 works are commentaries, and the remaining
                        27 (or 28) are liturgical works and other instructions. Note that other works on this tantra are found in
                        the Non-dual tantra subdivision of this Unexcelled Yoga group, in the Yoga tantra section, and in the
                        “Other works on tantra” collections.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">III. The 25 works related to Ekajaṭā (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde chen ral gcig</foreign>, Toh
                        2122-2146). The <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</foreign> (which counts 26 works here) mentions that
                        some of these tantras might seem to be better classified as mother tantras, but have been traditionally
                        placed here. It also appears to describe Ekajaṭā as an Unexcelled Yoga form of Avalokiteśvara, and this
                        group of works includes several sādhanas of the various forms of Avalokiteśvara and Hayagrīva as well as
                        works related to Amitāyus.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="O1JC76301JC21622-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">IV. The 70 works related to Vajrapāṇi (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag na rdo rje</foreign>, Toh
                        2147-2216) elucidated according to Unexcelled Yoga tantra.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>