<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos dbyings rang bzhin dbyer med bstan pa'i mdo/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་རང་བཞིན་དབྱེར་མེད་པ་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadhātu­prakṛtyasambheda­nirdeśa</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས་ཀྱི་རང་བཞིན་དབྱེར་མེད་པ་བསྟན་པཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi dbyings kyi rang bzhin dbyer med pa bstan pa zhes bya
                    ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the
                    Realm of Phenomena”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dharmadhātu­prakṛtyasambheda­nirdeśa­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-54">Thomas Doctor</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-45">Khenpo Tsöndrü Sangpo</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-229">Jon Solomon</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Tom Tillemans</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1 <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-040-003"/>
                <date>2018-07-10</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh52" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 52</ref>
                    <biblScope>Toh 52, Degé Kangyur, vol 40 (dkon brtsegs, kha), folios 140.b–164.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="47">
                        <start volume="40" page="282"/>
                        <end volume="40" page="329"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11581" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:32:22 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="229">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-1"/>
                <p tid="1">While the Buddha is in the Jeta Grove, he asks Mañjuśrī to teach on the nature of reality. Mañjuśrī’s
                    account upsets some of the monks present in the gathering, who subsequently leave. Nevertheless, by means of
                    an emanation, Mañjuśrī skillfully teaches the distraught monks, who return to the Jeta Grove to express their
                    gratitude. The monks explain that their obstacle has been a conceited sense of attainment, of which they are
                    now free. At the request of the god Ratnavara, Mañjuśrī then teaches on nonduality and the nature of the
                    bodhisattva. Next, the Buddha prophesies the future awakening of Ratnavara and other bodhisattvas present in
                    the gathering. However, the prophecies cause Pāpīyān, king of the māras, to appear with his army. In a
                    dramatic course of events, Mañjuśrī uses his transformative power on both Pāpīyān and the Buddha’s pious
                    attendant, Śāradvatīputra, forcing both of them to appear in the form of the Buddha himself. He then makes
                    Pāpīyān and Śāradvatīputra teach the profound Dharma with the perfect mastery of buddhahood. Numerous
                    bodhisattvas appear from the four directions, pledging to practice and uphold the sūtra’s teaching. The Buddha
                    grants his blessing for the continuous transmission of the sūtra among bodhisattvas in the future.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="230">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche.
                    Thomas Doctor produced the translation and wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the draft
                    translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text. Khenpo Tsöndrü Sangpo from Ka-Nying Shedrub Ling
                    Monastery assisted by resolving several difficult passages. Jon Solomon provided comparisons with the Chinese
                    version of the sūtra. Tom Tillemans gave valuable philological references and helped establish both the text
                    in general and its vocabulary.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="231">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</title> has survived in Chinese and
                        Tibetan translations but, like all except five of the forty-nine texts belonging to the <title xml:lang="en">Heap of Jewels</title>, is no longer extant in Sanskrit.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-294"> The sūtra is also included in the Mongolian and Korean (K22-8)
                            canons.</note> The Chinese translation (Taishō 310-8, scroll 21) was produced in 503 by the itinerant
                        monk Mandrasena, who became an influential translator in China, having been invited there from his native
                        Cambodia to assist with the translation of Buddhist scriptures into Chinese.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-295"> Cambodia was at that time culturally influenced by India and home to a
                            thriving Buddhist culture under royal patronage in the fifth and sixth centuries.</note> The Tibetan
                        translation appeared approximately three centuries later during the early ninth century and was made,
                        according to the colophon, by the great translator-editor Yeshé Dé in collaboration with the Indian
                        paṇḍiṭas Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi. This English translation was made based primarily on the Tibetan Degé edition, with consultation of the Comparative Edition and the Stok Palace manuscript edition.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-4"/>
                    <p tid="4">It is hard to estimate the influence of <title xml:lang="en">The Indivisible Nature of the Realm of
                            Phenomena</title> in India and Tibet, because the sūtra does not appear to be frequently cited or
                        referred to. An important exception is the <title xml:lang="en">Precious Lamp of the Middle
                            Way</title>,<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-296"> Skt. *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyamakaratnapradīpa</title>, Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu ma rin po che’i sgron
                                ma</title>. Although attributed to Bhāviveka (fl. 6th century) this Indian work, extant only in
                            Tibetan translation (Toh 3854), refers to both Dharmakīrti and Candrakīrti (both fl. 7th century) and
                            the attribution is hence contested. See Ruegg 2010, p. 23–24.</note> which is in fact delivered in
                        explicit response to this sūtra’s critique of the principle of relative versus ultimate truth.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-297"> See the opening discussion in Bhāviveka, folios
                            259.b–260.a.</note> As an example of reliance on the sūtra in the works of influential Tibetan
                        authors, we may note that Dolpopa Sherab Gyaltsen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dol po pa shes
                            rab rgyal mtshan</foreign>, 1292–1361) presents the arguments of a proponent of intrinsic emptiness
                        (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rang stong</foreign>) based on its teaching.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-298"> Dolpopa Sherab Gyaltsen, folio 198.b. English translation in
                            Dol-bo-ba Shay-rap-gyel-tsen 2006, p. 392.</note> To our knowledge no academic research has been
                        specifically concerned with <title xml:lang="en">The Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</title>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-5"/>
                    <p tid="5">The setting of the sūtra is the renowned Jeta Grove at Śrāvastī, a site donated to the Buddha and
                        his Saṅgha by the wealthy benefactor Anāthapiṇḍada, where the Buddha subsequently spent many annual
                        monsoon retreats. As the sūtra opens, we learn that eight thousand monks, twelve thousand bodhisattvas,
                        and thirty-two thousand gods who practice the mind of awakening have assembled around the Blessed One. The
                        god Ratnavara is also present in the assembly, and we witness him forming the wish that the Buddha may
                        inspire Mañjuśrī to teach the Dharma. Knowing Ratnavara’s thoughts, the Buddha turns to Mañjuśrī and
                        encourages him to explain the “realm of phenomena.” Mañjuśrī’s playful and profound response is to wonder
                        whether the very idea of such a teaching is at all intelligible. How could that which is present
                        everywhere possibly be singled out and set apart from anything? How could it be identified in any
                        meaningful way?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-6"/>
                    <p tid="6">The “realm of phenomena,” the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmadhātu</foreign>
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi dbyings</foreign>), about which the Buddha asks
                        Mañjuśrī to teach, is thus one of the key principles in this text. The treatise <title xml:lang="en">Distinguishing the Middle from Extremes</title> (Skt. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyāntavibhāga</title>)—attributed to Maitreya and transmitted by Asaṅga—enumerates this term among
                        five synonyms for emptiness, and goes on to explain that this particular term is constructed in
                        consideration of the way the perception of emptiness serves as the basis for attaining the qualities of
                        the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āryas</foreign> or “noble beings.”<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-315">See Maitreya-Asaṅga, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyāntavibhāga</title>,
                            I.14-15, folio 41.a.2.</note> In the sūtras and śāstras the bodhisattva’s liberation upon the first of
                        the ten stages is moreover typically described as the result of perceiving—directly and for the first
                        time—the omnipresent nature of the realm of phenomena.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-316">See Maitreya-Asaṅga, II.14, folio 42.a.1, and Vasubandhu’s commentary,
                            folio 9.a.6–9.b.2.</note> Thus, in responding to the Buddha’s request, Mañjuśrī takes up the
                        implications of this notion of omnipresence. He argues that given its constant and pervasive presence,
                        ultimate reality turns out to be indivisibly one with everything from which we may otherwise want to set
                        it apart: the flawed, the seeming, and the unreal. How could the true nature of things then be
                        distinguished or known in any way? This paradox is also discernible in the sūtra’s title: in declaring
                        that its objective is to show the indivisible nature of reality and ordinary experience, the sūtra
                        ventures to treat a theme that arguably, by definition, cannot even be identified as a topic. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-7"/>
                    <p tid="7">This short-circuiting of the dichotomy between relative and ultimate truths—or of the distinction
                        between appearance and reality—recurs throughout the sūtra in a number of variations. Thus, as an upshot
                        of its radically nondual approach, the sūtra identifies the very notion of spiritual attainment as an
                        obstacle. The sense of having gained a superior result is hence classified as an affliction and associated
                        with saṃsāra. Yet the sūtra also teaches that exact knowledge of affliction and saṃsāra is itself the
                        purification of the latter two. The idea of a path from ignorance to awakening is further undermined when
                        Mañjuśrī, in reply to Ratnavara’s questions, for example, identifies the “beginner bodhisattva” in terms
                        of a realization that transcends both time and space. “Long-term experience,” on the other hand, Mañjuśrī
                        sees as descriptive only of beings who suffer in saṃsāra, and thus not of bodhisattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-8"/>
                    <p tid="8">The sūtra acknowledges the potentially intimidating and alienating effects of its teaching of
                        nonduality, yet its response can be seen as both unrelenting and genuinely concerned. As the Buddha warns
                        Mañjuśrī that his teaching is likely to cause fear in the audience, Mañjuśrī replies, “Those who become
                        afraid are themselves of the nature of the realm of phenomena, and the nature of the realm of phenomena
                        does not become frightened.” Yet as a group of monks ends up leaving in distress, Mañjuśrī dispatches an
                        emanation of himself who, appearing to sympathize with the dejected monks in their dismissal of the
                        teaching, finally succeeds in showing them its deeper truth. It should also be noted that despite the
                        repeated rejection of the principles of liberation and spiritual accomplishment, we are repeatedly
                        informed about the liberating effects of the sūtra’s teaching when each section of discourse concludes, as
                        in many sūtras, with a statement of the resulting attainments of the attending monks, bodhisattvas, or
                        gods.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-9"/>
                    <p tid="9">The sūtra’s story line is dramatic and culminates in the transformation of both Pāpīyān—the ruler
                        of the māras, who create obstacles for those following the Dharma—and Śāradvatīputra (also known as
                        Śāriputra), who is the very image of spotless piety and adherence to the word of the Buddha. Starkly
                        against their wishes, both Pāpīyān and Śāradvatīputra are transformed and appear instead as awakened
                        buddhas. Once present as such, they engage in an astonishing Dharma dialogue, explaining to each other and
                        the audience the profound intent of Mañjuśrī’s teaching. Subsequent to this very graphic illustration of
                        the omnipresent nature of the realm of phenomena, the sūtra concludes with the Buddha asking Mañjuśrī to
                        bless the sūtra so that in future times it will be widely practiced. In a manner reminiscent of his
                        initial response to the Buddha’s call at the opening of the sūtra, Mañjuśrī wonders how he should
                        understand such a request, given the unborn and unceasing nature of all phenomena. Might the Blessed One,
                        Mañjuśrī wonders, perhaps also ask him to bless the unborn and unceasing element of space so that it may
                        remain unaffected by fire? Mañjuśrī instead chooses to entreat the Blessed One himself to bless the sūtra.
                        The Buddha complies and, having granted his blessing for the sūtra to be widely taught and practiced, he
                        asks Ānanda to recollect the sūtra, and also provides it with three alternative names. While for the most
                        part its teaching has been delivered by bodhisattvas, monks, and even by the king of māras, the sūtra ends
                        as is traditional with everyone rejoicing in the words of the Blessed One.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="232"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="233">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="234">The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-10"/>
                    <p tid="10">
                        <ref cRef="F.140.b"/>
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="11">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was in the Jeta Grove, in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park at
                        Śrāvastī. He was residing there together with a great saṅgha of eight thousand monks, and with twelve
                        thousand bodhisattvas from various buddha realms, and thirty-two thousand gods, who had all genuinely
                        entered into unexcelled and perfect awakening. Youthful Mañjuśrī and the god Ratnavara had also joined the
                        gathering and were present there. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-12"/>
                    <p tid="12">Ratnavara at that time thought to himself, “If the Blessed One encourages youthful Mañjuśrī to
                        teach the Dharma, he will surely teach so that all the abodes of the māras will be subdued and Māra the
                        evil one will despair. He will teach so that all opponents are defeated, and so that those possessed of
                        excessive pride will become free of their pride and reveal their knowledge.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-299"> Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes pa brda sprod pa ’gyur ba</title>.
                            This complex term appears frequently in this sūtra. Following <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> 6419, the Sanskrit equivalent is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ājñāvyākaraṇa</foreign>. In Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ājñā</foreign> means
                            “instruction,” “command,” or “order,” and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyākaraṇa</foreign>
                            and the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyākaroti</foreign> mean “explain/explanation,”
                            “prophesy/prophecy,” “analyze/analysis,” “elucidate/elucidation,” or just “show,” “reveal/revelation,”
                            or “manifest/manifestation” (see Monier-Williams s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyākaraṇa</foreign>). However, in the <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and
                                Dictionary</title> (Edgerton 1953) s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ājñā</foreign>, we
                            see that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ājñā</foreign> (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shes pa</foreign>), in Buddhist texts, has the sense of “correct knowledge,” and that
                            it is a usage close to the Pāli equivalent <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">aññā</foreign>, meaning
                            the sort of knowledge that comes with being an <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arhat</foreign>.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">Aññaṅ vyākaroti</foreign> is explained in <title xml:lang="en">The Pali Text Society’s Pali-English Dictionary</title> as “to manifest one’s Arahantship (by a
                            discourse or by mere exclamation).” See Pali Text Society s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">aññā</foreign>: “knowledge, recognition, correct knowledge, philosophic insight, knowledge par
                            excellence, viz., Arahantship.” Based on these considerations, we translate <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyākaraṇa</foreign> as “reveal” and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ājñā</foreign> as “knowledge,” thus here arriving at “will… reveal their knowledge.” </note> He
                        will teach so that those engaged in yogic practices will achieve their fruition, and so that those who
                        have already achieved fruition will gain further distinction. In this way the lineage of the Buddha,
                        Dharma, and Saṅgha will continue unbroken so that numerous beings will arouse the mind set on awakening.
                        The awakening that the Thus-Gone One has gained over incalculable eons will long remain and expand.
                        Whether the Thus-Gone One remains or passes entirely into nirvāṇa, the teaching of the Dharma <ref cRef="F.141.a"/> will cause those who hear it to pass quickly beyond suffering by means of whichever
                        vehicle may inspire them. Would it not be wonderful were youthful Mañjuśrī to deliver such a
                        teaching!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-13"/>
                    <p tid="13">The Blessed One knew in his mind what the god Ratnavara was thinking, and so he said to youthful
                        Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, the gathering here wishes to hear the Dharma from you. Therefore, please go ahead and
                        speak some words to those who are gathered here.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-14"/>
                    <p tid="14">In response youthful Mañjuśrī inquired, “Blessed One, where should I begin my teaching?”</p>
                    <p tid="15">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “you should begin by teaching the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-15"/>
                    <p tid="16">“But Blessed One,” replied youthful Mañjuśrī, “all phenomena are the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena. Hence, Blessed One, the nature of the realm of phenomena cannot possibly be a topic of
                        discourse or study. So, Blessed One, how could I begin my teaching with the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena?”</p>
                    <p tid="17">The Blessed One said, “Mañjuśrī, if those who are possessed of excessive pride hear that teaching,
                        it will frighten them.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-17"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Those who become afraid,” said Mañjuśrī, “are themselves of the nature of the realm of phenomena,
                        and the nature of the realm of phenomena does not become frightened.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-19"/>
                    <p tid="19">At that point the venerable Śāradvatīputra addressed youthful Mañjuśrī. “Mañjuśrī,” he said, “you
                        say that all phenomena are the nature of the realm of phenomena. But within the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena there is no affliction, nor is there purification. How is it, then, that sentient beings get
                        afflicted, or purified?”</p>
                    <p tid="20">Mañjuśrī replied, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, childish and ordinary beings are stricken by the
                        errors of the view of the transitory collection. In those who persist in the belief in ‘I’ and ‘mine’
                        there arises the conception of self and other. <ref cRef="F.141.b"/> In those who conceive of self and
                        other there arise a virtuous and unvirtuous mind and the mental states that arise from it; that mind and
                        the factors arising from it then condition the formation of virtuous and unvirtuous actions, and for them,
                        that cause and those conditions bring about their particular forms of ripening according to their
                        particular natures.<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-300"> The Degé Kangyur here reads:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de dag la rgyu de dang rkyen de dang ngo bo nyid de’i rnam
                                par smin pa nyid mngon par ’grub par ’gyur ro</foreign>. However, the Stok Palace Kangyur has:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de dag la rgyu de dang rkyen de dag ngo bo nyid de’i rnam
                                par smin pa nyid mngon par ’grub par ’gyur ro</foreign>, which seems more likely to be correct,
                            although it is notable that the Shey Kangyur reads the same as the Degé. The Kangxi, Lithang, and
                            Choné Kangyurs hedge their bets with …<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgyu de dang rkyen de
                                dag dang ngo bo nyid</foreign>… </note> Venerable Śāradvatīputra, for as long as such beings take
                        birth within the realms of existence, that is what we call affliction.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-21"/>
                    <p tid="21">“However, venerable Śāradvatīputra, affliction is the very nature of the realm of phenomena.
                        Hence, to know that affliction is indeed the very nature of the realm of phenomena is what we call
                        purification. Ultimately there is no affliction or purification and nothing is afflicted or purified.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-22"/>
                    <p tid="22">When youthful Mañjuśrī gave this teaching, one hundred proud monks liberated their minds from
                        defilement with no further appropriation. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-23"/>
                    <p tid="23">Venerable Śāradvatīputra then said to youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, as you gave this teaching, one
                        hundred proud monks liberated their minds from defilement with no further appropriation. Mañjuśrī, the
                        realm of phenomena is flowing from you!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-314"/>
                    <p tid="24">Mañjuśrī said, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, what do you think? Is the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena something that was bound in the past and later liberated?”</p>
                    <p tid="25">“Mañjuśrī, the nature of the realm of phenomena was not bound in the past, nor is it later
                        liberated.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-26"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Well, venerable Śāradvatīputra, from what mind state were those monks liberated?”</p>
                    <p tid="27">“Mañjuśrī, the Thus-Gone One has trained many hearers, and so their minds are liberated from
                        defilement with no further appropriation.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-28"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Venerable Śāradvatīputra, are you one of the Thus-Gone One’s hearers?” <ref cRef="F.142.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="29">“I am, Mañjuśrī. I am one among the Thus-Gone One’s hearers.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-30"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Venerable Śāradvatīputra, is your mind free from appropriation and liberated from
                        defilements?”</p>
                    <p tid="31">“Indeed, Mañjuśrī, it is liberated.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-32"/>
                    <p tid="32"> “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, was your mind liberated in the past, will it be in the future, or is
                        it being liberated at present? Venerable Śāradvatīputra, the characteristic of past mind is that it has
                        ceased, the characteristic of future mind is that it has not yet occurred, and the characteristic of
                        present mind is that it does not remain. That being so, venerable Śāradvatīputra, in which of these is
                        that liberation of your mind?”</p>
                    <p tid="33">Venerable Śāradvatīputra replied, “Mañjuśrī, this mind was not liberated in the past, is not being
                        liberated at present, nor will it be in the future.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-34"/>
                    <p tid="34">Mañjuśrī responded, “Well then, venerable Śāradvatīputra, what is this liberated mind of
                        yours?”</p>
                    <p tid="35">To this Śāradvatīputra answered, “Mañjuśrī, it is only in relative terms that a mind is said to be
                        liberated. Ultimately there is no bound or liberated mind to be observed.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-36"/>
                    <p tid="36">Mañjuśrī asked him, “Would you say that the nature of the realm of phenomena is relative or
                        ultimate?”</p>
                    <p tid="37">Śāradvatīputra replied, “Mañjuśrī, within the nature of the realm of phenomena neither the
                        relative nor the ultimate can be observed.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-38"/>
                    <p tid="38">Mañjuśrī asked him, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, how, then, can you declare that the mind is
                        liberated in relative terms?”</p>
                    <p tid="39">So Śāradvatīputra asked, “Mañjuśrī, is there, then, never any mind that is liberated at all?”</p>
                    <p tid="40">Mañjuśrī answered, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, if there were a mind to be observed inside, outside,
                        or in between, then there could also be a liberated mind. However, venerable Śāradvatīputra, there is no
                        mind to be observed inside, outside, or in between, and therefore there is no bondage or liberation
                        whatsoever.” <ref cRef="F.142.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-41"/>
                    <p tid="41">At that point two hundred monks from that retinue heard this teaching by Mañjuśrī and rose from
                        their seats, getting ready to leave. They said, “If nobody was ever liberated and nobody ever will be,
                        what is the point of our going forth and taking vows to become monks? If there is no such thing as
                        deliverance at all, then what purpose would it serve to train on the path?” Disapproving and disconcerted,
                        they then left the gathering. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-42"/>
                    <p tid="42">Considering what ought to be done to train those monks, youthful Mañjuśrī projected an emanation
                        in the form of a monk on the road in front of them. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-43"/>
                    <p tid="43">When they encountered the emanation, the monks asked him, “Where do you come from, venerable
                        one?”</p>
                    <p tid="44"> “Venerable ones,” he replied, “I do not wish to participate in the Dharma teaching that youthful
                        Mañjuśrī is now giving. I do not understand it, I am not interested in it, and I do not believe in it.
                        Hence, I have left the gathering.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-45"/>
                    <p tid="45">The two hundred monks concurred, “We do not wish to be present at Mañjuśrī’s Dharma teaching,
                        either. We do not understand it, we are not interested in it, and we do not believe in it. Therefore, we
                        have also left the gathering.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-46"/>
                    <p tid="46">Addressing the two hundred monks, the emanated monk asked them, “What were the disagreeable points
                        in youthful Mañjuśrī’s Dharma teaching that made you leave the gathering?”</p>
                    <p tid="47">The monks replied, “Venerable one, youthful Mañjuśrī declared that nobody ever achieves anything,
                        and that there is no such thing as gaining realization and liberation. At that point we thought, if nobody
                        ever gains any attainment, realization, or liberation, then what purpose would there be in our going
                        forth, and why should we have taken vows to become monks? <ref cRef="F.143.a"/> Why should we observe
                        celibacy? If there were no such thing as deliverance at all, what purpose would it serve to train on the
                        path? It was with these thoughts in mind that we left the gathering.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-48"/>
                    <p tid="48">The emanated monk asked the group, “Venerable ones, did you simply leave because you did not
                        appreciate what was being said? Or did you reject the teaching and express your displeasure in words?”</p>
                    <p tid="49">They replied, “We just left because we did not like it. We did not reject the teaching, nor as we
                        left did we say anything unpleasant.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-50"/>
                    <p tid="50"> “Well done,” said the emanated monk. “Venerable ones, to refrain from dispute is the foremost
                        training for spiritual practitioners. Therefore, without saying anything offensive and without arguing
                        against this teaching, let us try to follow it for a while.</p>
                    <p tid="51">“Venerable ones, would you say that the mind is blue, or is it yellow? Or is it red or white? Or
                        would you say that it is similar to the color of madder, or of a crystal? Is it real, or should we call it
                        unreal? Is it permanent, or would you say that it is impermanent? Does it have a form, or would you say
                        that it is formless?”</p>
                    <p tid="52">The monks replied, “Venerable one, the mind does not have any form and it cannot be shown. It has
                        no appearance yet is unimpeded. It has no dwelling and is imperceptible.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-52"/>
                    <p tid="53">The emanated monk then asked the group, “Venerable ones, the mind that has no form and cannot be
                        shown, that has no appearance, is unimpeded, has no dwelling, and is imperceptible—do you think that it is
                        to be observed as something that can be said to dwell inside? Or to dwell outside? Or to dwell in
                        between?”</p>
                    <p tid="54">“No, it is none of these,” said the monks.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-54"/>
                    <p tid="55">So the emanation continued, “If the mind has no form, cannot be shown, has no appearance, is
                        unimpeded, <ref cRef="F.143.b"/> without dwelling, and imperceptible, if it is not to be observed inside,
                        nor outside, nor in between, do you think it is real and established?”</p>
                    <p tid="56">“No, it is not,” answered the monks.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-56"/>
                    <p tid="57">“Do you then think, venerable ones, that a mind that is not real and not established can
                        nevertheless be liberated?”</p>
                    <p tid="58">“No, it cannot,” they replied.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-58"/>
                    <p tid="59">“Venerable ones,” the emanation continued, “now consider youthful Mañjuśrī’s teaching. He said
                        that within the nature of the realm of phenomena there is neither affliction nor purification. Venerable
                        ones, the minds of childish and ordinary beings stricken by errors give rise to the belief in ‘I’ and
                        ‘mine.’ As they persist in that belief in ‘I’ and ‘mine,’ they continuously engage with objects and abide
                        on them. As such, a mind that arises from observation comes into being; but when that observation ends,
                        that mind will also end, disintegrate, and no longer remain. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-59"/>
                    <p tid="60"> “It is the observing mind that goes forth, takes vows, and becomes a monk. Yet the mind that
                        practices the path has no intrinsic existence, is not real, and does not occur. And that which is
                        nonexistent, unreal, and non-occurring knows neither arising, disintegration, nor remaining. That which
                        neither arises, disintegrates, nor remains cannot be bound and cannot be liberated. It knows neither
                        attainment nor realization. Venerable ones, it was with this in mind that youthful Mañjuśrī said, ‘Within
                        the nature of the realm of phenomena there is neither affliction nor purification. Nobody ever attains
                        anything; there is no realization and no liberation.’ ”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-60"/>
                    <p tid="61">When the emanated monk had given them this teaching <ref cRef="F.144.a"/> the minds of the monks,
                        with no further appropriation, were liberated from defilement. With their minds liberated, they now
                        returned to youthful Mañjuśrī. Covering themselves with their upper robes, they addressed him as follows:
                        “Mañjuśrī, you have protected us! We have avoided giving up the Dharma and henceforth we will never
                        relinquish the practice of the profound Vinaya Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-61"/>
                    <p tid="62">Hearing this, venerable Subhūti asked the monks, “What are your attainments, and what type of
                        realization have you gained, that you now cover yourselves with your upper robes before Mañjuśrī?”</p>
                    <p tid="63">The monks replied, “Venerable Subhūti, we have neither attained nor realized anything at all. That
                        is why we now cover ourselves with our upper robes before Mañjuśrī. Venerable Subhūti, when we had the
                        sense of having attained something we rose from our seats and left the gathering. Now, free from that
                        sense of attainment, we are here again.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-63"/>
                    <p tid="64"> “Venerable ones,” inquired Subhūti, “what makes you say this?”</p>
                    <p tid="65">They replied, “Venerable Subhūti, to speak of ‘attainment’ is boastful and conceited. And whoever
                        is boastful and conceited has neither attainment nor realization. Venerable Subhūti, one who has neither
                        any attainment nor realization has truly vanquished all forms of conceit.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-65"/>
                    <p tid="66">“Venerable ones,” asked venerable Subhūti, “who has trained you?”</p>
                    <p tid="67">“Eminent Subhūti,” they replied, “we have been trained by him who has no attainment or
                        realization, for whom there is no birth and no passing beyond suffering, and who is neither composed nor
                        distracted.” <ref cRef="F.144.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-67"/>
                    <p tid="68">“How,” Subhūti asked, “did you get trained?”</p>
                    <p tid="69">“Ask Mañjuśrī,” they replied. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-69"/>
                    <p tid="70">So the venerable Ānanda now inquired, “Mañjuśrī, who has trained these monks?”</p>
                    <p tid="71">In reply Mañjuśrī explained, “Venerable Ānanda, these monks have been trained by one for whom
                        there are no aggregates, no elements, and no sense sources; one who is neither an ordinary being, nor
                        someone who trains, nor someone beyond training; one who is neither a hearer, nor a bodhisattva, nor a
                        thus-gone one; one who has no body, no speech, and no mind; one for whom there is neither connection nor
                        separation.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-71"/>
                    <p tid="72"> “What sort of teacher is that?” inquired Ānanda. </p>
                    <p tid="73">In reply Mañjuśrī asked, “Venerable Ānanda, what do you think: if the Thus-Gone One produces an
                        emanation, is that emanation connected with something?”</p>
                    <p tid="74">“No,” replied Ānanda, “such an emanation would not be connected with any phenomenon, yet neither
                        would it be separate from anything.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-74"/>
                    <p tid="75">Mañjuśrī asked, “Venerable Ānanda, are all phenomena essentially like emanations?”</p>
                    <p tid="76">“Yes, Mañjuśrī, they are,” replied Ānanda. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-76"/>
                    <p tid="77">“Venerable Ānanda,” Mañjuśrī said, “these monks were trained by an emanation, and whenever hearers
                        are trained, it is like being trained by an emanation. Venerable Ānanda, whenever training occurs in that
                        way, the training is genuine. Know that those who have no interest in this very Dharma training are
                        excessively proud.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-77"/>
                    <p tid="78"> “Mañjuśrī,” said venerable Ānanda, “how can monks who have no such interest be seen to have
                        excessive pride?”</p>
                    <p tid="79">Mañjuśrī replied, “Venerable Ānanda, monks who conceitedly consider themselves pure because of
                        their pure aggregate of discipline <ref cRef="F.145.a"/> are excessively proud. Those who conceitedly
                        think of themselves as pure because they have pure aggregates of absorption, insight, liberation, and
                        liberated wisdom vision—such individuals should be seen as excessively proud. Thinking, ‘I have gained the
                        attainments and achieved direct perception,’ they pride themselves on those achievements. Such thoughts
                        should be viewed as excessive pride.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-79"/>
                    <p tid="80">“Those who are fearful of the view of the transitory collection and relish the taste of the one
                        path to be traveled should be viewed as excessively proud. Why is that? Because that emptiness by virtue
                        of which the view of the transitory collection is empty is also the emptiness by virtue of which the
                        single traversed path is empty. So those who do not engage correctly with such empty things because of
                        their emptiness should be seen as excessively proud. Moreover, venerable Ānanda, you should understand
                        that monks who use emptiness to make the emptiness of the view of the transitory collection the same
                        emptiness as the emptiness of the one path to be traveled are excessively proud. Why is that? Because,
                        venerable Ānanda, emptiness and the view of the transitory collection are not two different things; the
                        view of the transitory collection is itself emptiness. Nor are emptiness and the path two different
                        things; the path is itself emptiness.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-80"/>
                    <p tid="81"> “Moreover, venerable Ānanda, any monk who fears ignorance and the cravings of existence and
                        relishes the taste of liberation from ignorance should also be seen as excessively proud. Why is that?
                        Because, venerable Ānanda, whoever engages in them with the perception that they are two things is not
                        liberated. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-81"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Venerable Ānanda, some monks are frightened by desire, anger, and delusion and relish the taste
                        of the three gateways of liberation. Some are frightened by the four errors and hence relish the taste of
                        the four perceptions. Some are frightened by the five obscurations and so relish the taste of the five
                        faculties. <ref cRef="F.145.b"/> Some are frightened by the six sense sources and instead relish the six
                        super-knowledges. Some are frightened by the seven bases of consciousness and instead relish the taste of
                        the seven branches of awakening. Some are frightened by the eight flaws and hence relish the taste of the
                        eight-fold path of the noble ones. Some are frightened by the nine conditioned entities<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-301"> This may refer to the nine realms of existence within
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saṃsāra</foreign>: the realm of desire plus the four form
                            realms and the four formless realms.</note> and instead relish the taste of the nine successive
                        attainments. Some are frightened by the path of action associated with the ten non-virtues and instead
                        relish the experience of the ten qualities of no-more-training. Some are frightened by the conditioned
                        elements and instead relish the taste of the unconditioned elements. All such monks should be known to be
                        excessively proud. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-82"/>
                    <p tid="83">“And why? Venerable Ānanda, because all of that amounts to boasting, conceit, and construction.
                        Venerable Ānanda, however much a monk is involved in boasting, conceit, construction, thoughts of
                        something high, thoughts of something low, appropriation, relinquishment, conceptualization, dependence,
                        clinging, and superimposition—that much will he be afflicted by excessive pride. Hence, venerable Ānanda,
                        all such monks should be known as excessively proud. And why is that? Because, venerable Ānanda, anyone
                        who does not engage with emptiness—the emptiness that is the emptiness of the conditioned elements and the
                        emptiness that is the emptiness of the unconditioned elements—as sameness must be known as excessively
                        proud.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-83"/>
                    <p tid="84">Venerable Ānanda then asked youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, how, then, is a monk who is not
                        excessively proud?”</p>
                    <p tid="85">Mañjuśrī replied, “Venerable Ānanda, a monk who, because he himself is at peace within, sees all
                        outer objects as at peace—such a monk has no conceited ideas about ‘the same’ or ‘not the same,’
                        ‘knowledge’ or ‘ignorance,’ ‘perception’ or ‘non-perception,’ ‘the conditioned’ or ‘the unconditioned.’
                            <ref cRef="F.146.a"/> He does not think, does not conceive, does not divide things in two, does not
                        unite them in one, does not accept, does not reject, does not scatter, and does not cling. He truly
                        observes that while all phenomena are the same as the limit of reality, they are the same through a
                        sameness that is beyond being the same or being not the same, and as there is nothing whatsoever to be
                        made the same or to be made not the same, he does not truly observe anything that is that sameness. Hence,
                        as he has no conceit, does not think, does not conceive, and does not cling, it goes without saying that
                        he is without any conceit regarding his attainment, his understanding, or his realization. There is no
                        basis for it.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-85"/>
                    <p tid="86"> “Venerable Ānanda, such a monk is free from excessive pride. For him, there is no remedy and no
                        position. He is free of a position for himself and a position for others. All feelings have been
                        interrupted. He is free from feeling, from all absence of feeling, from all perceptions, all thoughts, and
                        all ways of directing the mind. He has no bondage and no appropriation. He is at peace, thoroughly at
                        peace, utterly at peace. Since he has no thought of ‘I’ or ‘mine,’ he does not truly observe that there is
                        any quality to relinquish, understand, or realize. When a monk is like this, he does not harbor any
                        excessive pride.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-86"/>
                    <p tid="87"> “When he understands the sameness of all phenomena by means of the sameness of the element of
                        space, he will not superimpose on any phenomena that they are ‘virtuous’ or ‘unvirtuous,’ ‘evil’ or
                        ‘good,’ ‘defiled’ or ‘undefiled,’ ‘mundane’ or ‘supramundane,’ <ref cRef="F.146.b"/> ‘conditioned’ or
                        ‘unconditioned.’ While not making such superimpositions, he will also not develop conceit about them, will
                        not think them, and will not conceive of them, for he does not truly observe them. Without superimposing
                        anything on phenomena, he understands that they are all the same in their very sameness, the very same
                        just like space. Venerable Ānanda, any monk who becomes inspired in this way is known as truly and fully
                        liberated; that is why he is not proud. It is with this in mind that the Blessed One has taught, ‘Space
                        does not stick to the palm of one’s hand; so too, are a spiritual practitioner’s qualities.’”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-87"/>
                    <p tid="88">When Mañjuśrī had given this teaching, two hundred monks experienced their minds’ liberation from
                        defilement with no further appropriation.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-88"/>
                    <p tid="89">At that point the god Ratnavara inquired of youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, how should a bodhisattva
                        who is free from pride reveal his knowledge?”</p>
                    <p tid="90">In reply, Mañjuśrī explained, “Divine being, the omniscient mind, the mind that is equal to the
                        unequaled, the mind that is superior to all of the three worlds, the mind that is entirely beyond the
                        hearers and solitary buddhas—when bodhisattvas do not perceive that mind to be present inside, outside, or
                        both, such bodhisattvas do not perceive any movement of the mind toward external objects or any abiding
                        there, and yet their mind does move for the sake of accumulating roots of virtue, ripening sentient
                        beings, and upholding the sacred Dharma. Thus their omniscient mind expresses itself to other sentient
                        beings and to other persons while they understand that that mind, too, has the essential nature of the
                        limit of reality. When asked, they reply that through the essential nature of their mind they understand
                        the essential nature of all beings. Through the essential nature of all beings, <ref cRef="F.147.a"/> they
                        understand the essential nature of all phenomena. Through the essential nature of all phenomena, they
                        understand the essential nature of all roots of virtue. Through the essential nature of all roots of
                        virtue, they reveal the essential nature of a bodhisattva. This, divine being, is the bodhisattvas’
                        revelation of their correct knowledge.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-90"/>
                    <p tid="91"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas, as they practice generosity, give by relinquishing
                        the gift, the giver, the recipient, the context of giving, and the purpose of the gift, such bodhisattvas
                        rely on nothing and do not remain fixed on anything. They have no attachment, do not hope for anything, do
                        not focus on anything, and do not truly observe anything. When asked, they reply that they understand that
                        the essential nature of giving is utter relinquishment, utter absence of goals, and utter emptiness.
                        Through the essential nature of giving they understand the essential nature of the limit of reality.
                        Through the essential nature of the limit of reality they understand the essential nature of all
                        phenomena. Through the essential nature of all phenomena they understand the essential nature of all
                        beings, and through the essential nature of all beings they reveal the essential nature of a bodhisattva.
                        This, divine being, is the bodhisattvas’ revelation of their correct knowledge purified through
                        generosity.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-91"/>
                    <p tid="92"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas, being physically at peace, understand that discipline
                        is at peace; and being verbally and mentally at peace, understand that discipline is at peace; and being
                        physically, verbally, and mentally at peace, understand that awakening is at peace; and as awakening is at
                        peace, understand that all sentient beings are at peace; and as all sentient beings are at peace,
                        understand that all phenomena are at peace; and as all phenomena are at peace, understand that the limit
                        of reality is known as “at peace;” for them, as the limit of reality is at peace, they are at peace,
                        thorough peace, and utter peace. <ref cRef="F.147.b"/> Hence, when asked, they reveal that all phenomena
                        are at peace. This, divine being, is the bodhisattvas’ revelation of their correct knowledge purified
                        through discipline. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-92"/>
                    <p tid="93"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas understand the utterly fleeting, momentary, and hollow
                        nature of reality, they are patient regarding all the woes that sentient beings may cause, and patient
                        without their minds being actuated externally or internally;<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-302"> The Degé Kangyur here reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gang
                                gi tshe phyi nang gi sems kun nas mi slong bar bzod pa dang /</foreign>, but the Stok Palace and
                            Narthang have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gang gis phyi nang gi sems</foreign>… .</note>
                        and without directing any aggressive contemplation externally they are patient regarding all the misdeeds
                        of sentient beings. They understand that the essential nature of all beings is the essential nature of
                        patience; that the essential nature of patience is the essential nature of awakening; and that the
                        essential nature of awakening is the essential nature of all phenomena. They thus understand also that all
                        phenomena are of the essential nature of the limit of reality. When asked, they reply that because they
                        understand the fleeting, momentary, and hollow nature of reality, they reveal their patience by not being
                        moved. This, divine being, is the bodhisattva’s revelation of his correct knowledge purified through
                        patience.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-93"/>
                    <p tid="94"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas understand the teaching<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-303"> The word <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>) here could be understood in several other ways,
                            including “quality,” “factor,” “the Dharma,” or perhaps “phenomena.” </note> of disengagement from all
                        contemplation and are free of superimpositions, their diligence will have equanimity and they will truly
                        observe that whatever exertion they might undertake is itself disengagement. With this inward
                        disengagement, without moving outwardly they move to ripen others. Through the disengagement of their
                        diligence they understand the disengagement of sentient beings. Through the disengagement of sentient
                        beings they understand the disengagement of awakening. Through the disengagement of awakening they
                        understand the disengagement of all phenomena. Through the disengagement of all phenomena they understand
                        the disengagement of the limit of reality. When asked, they reveal that their diligence is disengaged in
                        just the same way as all those things are, by their nature, disengaged. <ref cRef="F.148.a"/> This, divine
                        being, is the bodhisattva’s revelation of his correct knowledge purified through diligence.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-94"/>
                    <p tid="95"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas practice concentration on all phenomena being the same
                        and having no differences, they do not place their minds to remain in that concentration and make their
                        consciousness dwell on it. Without their consciousness dwelling on it they understand, through the
                        sameness of mind, that concentration is sameness. Through the sameness of their concentration they
                        understand the sameness of awakening. Through the sameness of awakening they understand the sameness of
                        all sentient beings. Through the sameness of all sentient beings they understand the sameness of all
                        phenomena. They know that it is in this way that all phenomena are said to be the same. When asked, they
                        reveal that, because they are all of just that sameness by nature, all phenomena are sameness. This,
                        divine being, is the bodhisattva’s revelation of his correct knowledge purified through concentration.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-95"/>
                    <p tid="96"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas see all phenomena through their pure wisdom by means
                        of the eye of insight, they do not truly see any phenomenon. When they see in that way, in which they do
                        not truly see any phenomena, there is nothing at all. Having attained an understanding of there not being
                        anything at all, they do not move, proceed, or transfer anywhere. Having interrupted all moving,
                        proceeding, and transferring, they do not transmigrate; they do not transmigrate at all. Why is that? It
                        is because they have interrupted what sets transmigration in motion—desire, craving, and wishing. Without
                        pursuing any desires at all, they intentionally move through various births in order to ripen beings,
                        gather the factors of awakening, uphold the sacred Dharma, and ensure the unbroken continuity of the
                        lineage of the Three Jewels. <ref cRef="F.148.b"/> They move without moving and without upsetting the
                        characteristic purity of the nature of all phenomena. As this is their insight, through the nature of
                        insight they understand awakening. Through the nature of awakening they understand the nature of sentient
                        beings. Through the nature of sentient beings they understand the nature of all phenomena, and they also
                        know that all phenomena are of the nature of the limit of reality. When asked, they reveal the indivisible
                        nature of the realm of phenomena. This, divine being, is the bodhisattva’s revelation of his correct
                        knowledge purified by means of the eye of insight.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-96"/>
                    <p tid="97"> “Divine being, moreover, when bodhisattvas observe the body and apply mindfulness, they know that
                        the body of the past was unborn. They know that the body of the future does not transfer. And they
                        understand that the present body is similar in essence to grass, trees, walls, rocks, or visual
                        aberrations. When they observe the body, they understand that the nature of the body is non-arising, and
                        so they do not instigate any contemplation that involves notions of the body. Those who do not instigate
                        contemplation will not dwell on any concerns. Free from concerns and with a consciousness that does not
                        dwell, they train in observing the body and applying mindfulness to it, yet they neither cultivate nor
                        eliminate any phenomena at all. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-97"/>
                    <p tid="98"> “Having understood that all phenomena are without reality, they observe the body with the
                        understanding that the mind that observes the body is also just like a magical illusion or an echo. With
                        this insight they are neither attached to pleasant feelings nor hostile to painful ones, <ref cRef="F.149.a"/> and since they are also not confused with respect to feelings that are neither
                        painful nor pleasant, they are not predisposed to ignorance. When they are no longer ravished by feelings,
                        then this is their application of mindfulness to the observation of feelings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-98"/>
                    <p tid="99"> “As they observe and dwell on feelings, their minds are not moved by any movement of their
                        feelings about phenomena, and as their minds therefore do not dwell upon any phenomenon, they do not
                        abandon, discard, or relinquish the mind of awakening. This is their application of mindfulness to the
                        observation of the mind.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-99"/>
                    <p tid="100"> “With their knowledge of phenomena actualized, they observe phenomena. At that point they are
                        free from mindfulness and contemplation, and so they understand the intrinsic nature. They no longer
                        entertain any notions, contemplation, views, or entanglements with respect to body, feelings, mind, or
                        phenomena. This is their application of mindfulness to the observation of phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-100"/>
                    <p tid="101"> “They understand all phenomena to be intrinsically non-arising and devoid of substance, like the
                        essential nature of space. Hence, when asked, they reveal their applications of mindfulness through being
                        free of mindfulness and conditioning. This, divine being, is the bodhisattva’s revelation of his correct
                        knowledge purified by means of the applications of mindfulness.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-101"/>
                    <p tid="102"> “Divine being, moreover, the correct knowledge of bodhisattvas is what causes them to assimilate
                        the mind of omniscience, to notice it, stabilize it, ensure that it is not lost, ensure that there is no
                        distraction from it, and ensure that it is not forgotten. At the beginning it precedes all roots of
                        virtue. It is free from stinginess and relinquishes all possessions. It abandons attitudes of flawed
                        discipline and in the aggregate of discipline it is without dwelling. It harbors no wish to harm any
                        being, is free of strife, <ref cRef="F.149.b"/> and inflicts no injury with body, speech, or mind. It does
                        not practice the diligence of a listener or a solitary buddha but does undertake the diligence of the
                        Great Vehicle. It does not direct the mind to unvirtuous phenomena or pay attention to them but cultivates
                        non-dwelling in any concentration or equilibrium. It does not move toward all the aspects of a view and
                        does not project out to phenomena; it engages with all phenomena without mediation. It engages with the
                        thoughts of sentient beings. It does not move toward objects. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-102"/>
                    <p tid="103"> “It adheres to noble beings and does not associate with those who are not noble. It is
                        irreproachable with respect to the actions of body, speech, and mind. It is assiduously careful and
                        pursues the qualities of the buddhas. Without needing direction, it comprehends all needs. It is pure,
                        having relinquished desire, anger, and bewilderment. Since its discipline is flawless, it is free from all
                        torments, and is not involved with mistaken practices. Because of its complete inner purity, it is free
                        from hypocrisy, and because of its purity with respect to speech, it knows no flattery. Content with what
                        it finds, it does not search. Having abandoned negative forms of livelihood, it does not take over others’
                        property. Content with the bare necessities, it knows no deceit. Not aiming for the three worlds, it has
                        modest wishes. Free from unvirtuous wishes, it is content. Inclined to the disengagement of all phenomena,
                        it is disengaged. Having relinquished mundane activities, it keeps few things. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-103"/>
                    <p tid="104"> “Having cut through all mental constructs, it is free from thoughts. Without intention, anger,
                        fear, or bewilderment, it is immutable. Having conquered pride, it takes delight in the Dharma. With a
                        well-trained mind, it is noble. With the aggregate of discipline, it is guarded in all respects. <ref cRef="F.150.a"/> With the aggregate of absorption, this mind does not dwell anywhere. With the
                        aggregate of insight, this mind is liberated. Never does it abandon the lineage of the noble ones, nor
                        does it ever spoil the vow of the mind of awakening. It does not pursue gain and honor, nor does it pander
                        to others. It guards itself for the sake of guarding others. Being certain of its own intentions, it does
                        not seek the mistakes of others. Observing discipline, it is free from all fears. Without being
                        tightfisted, it shares the Dharma. It protects the mental activities of all beings. At the beginning it
                        precedes all virtuous dharmas. Experiencing all phenomena as of one taste, it is beyond differences with
                        respect to activity. Having conquered all forms of conceit, it is free from conceit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-104"/>
                    <p tid="105"> “In the discernment that there is no birth, it intentionally takes birth in order to ripen
                        sentient beings; and in the discernment that all phenomena are empty from the beginning, too, it also
                        ripens sentient beings so as to subdue all views. While acting in full acquaintance with the absence of
                        marks, it nevertheless considers all sentient beings who engage with marks. Without any wishes, it
                        nevertheless perfects all aspirations for the sake of omniscient wisdom. In the discernment of the absence
                        of formations, it is nevertheless insatiable in forming roots of virtue. Since it sees entities as
                        nonentities, it comprehends both entity and nonentity. Free from any concerns, it does not keep anything
                        in mind. Leading sentient beings to the absence of self, it knows the self to be without self.
                        Relinquishing affliction while not relinquishing sentient beings, it is both relinquishing and
                        non-relinquishing. Cultivating skillful means and insight, it is peaceful beyond both peace and lack of
                        peace. <ref cRef="F.150.b"/> In distinction from hearers and solitary buddhas, it proceeds without
                        proceeding. Beyond the paths of the māras, this is the path of no path. In distinction from childish,
                        ordinary beings, this is the activity of non-action. As it understands all phenomena, it is sameness that
                        neither raises things up nor puts them down. Without any conceited superiority over others, it does not
                        make proclamations regarding itself. Perfecting all the qualities of a buddha, it is an unequaled
                        understanding. Accepting all phenomena as unborn and unceasing, it is the acceptance of the non-arising of
                        phenomena. Divine being, such is the knowledge of bodhisattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-105"/>
                    <p tid="106"> “Divine being, being unborn and unoriginated is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds embrace birth within cyclic existence and perfect the qualities of a buddha. </p>
                    <p tid="107">“Being despondent and free from desire is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds take delight, supreme delight, in correctly knowing the qualities of a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-107"/>
                    <p tid="108">“Being without connection to future existences is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds know the way to take birth. </p>
                    <p tid="109">“A complete severance is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds are a
                        continuity of roots of virtue. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-109"/>
                    <p tid="110"> “A lack of concern for the roots of virtue is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds are insatiable for the roots of virtue. </p>
                    <p tid="111">“Relinquishing the process of taking birth within the three realms is not what bodhisattvas’
                        minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds knowingly take birth to ripen sentient beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-111"/>
                    <p tid="112">“Eliminating only their own afflictions is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds work diligently to eliminate the afflictions of all sentient beings. <ref cRef="F.151.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="113">“Acting for themselves is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds act
                        to pacify the suffering of all sentient beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-113"/>
                    <p tid="114"> “Leaving anyone uncared for is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’
                        minds reach out to ripen sentient beings. </p>
                    <p tid="115">“Exhausting desire, anger, bewilderment, and affliction is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like.
                        Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds have complete knowledge of desire, anger, bewilderment, and affliction. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-115"/>
                    <p tid="116">“Actualizing the qualities of cessation is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds have complete familiarity with cessation. </p>
                    <p tid="117">“Exhausting defilements is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds are
                        familiar with defilement by means of roots of virtue. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-117"/>
                    <p tid="118"> “Actualizing the three gateways of liberation is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds are familiar with the three gateways of liberation. </p>
                    <p tid="119">“Putting down the load of the five aggregates is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather,
                        bodhisattvas’ minds cause all beings to put down their loads. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-119"/>
                    <p tid="120">“Blocking the six faculties is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds
                        know all the different faculties of beings, whether superior or not. </p>
                    <p tid="121">“Bringing an end to birth is not what bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds
                        engage in the process of taking birth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-121"/>
                    <p tid="122">“Attaining the result that is the liberation of hearers and solitary buddhas is not what
                        bodhisattvas’ minds are like. Rather, bodhisattvas’ minds sustain all beings with the result of liberation
                        at the seat of awakening.” <ref cRef="F.151.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-122"/>
                    <p tid="123">When Mañjuśrī delivered this section of teaching on the revelation of correct knowledge, ten
                        thousand beings within the gathering gave rise to the mind of unexcelled and perfect awakening. The
                        Blessed One also expressed his approval to youthful Mañjuśrī, saying, “Well said, Mañjuśrī, well said. You
                        have explained the bodhisattvas’ revelation of their knowledge well. Mañjuśrī, any bodhisattva who hears
                        this teaching on the revelation of knowledge and is inspired, fearless, is unafraid and does not panic
                        will awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood and reveal the correct knowledge of the thus-gone ones.”
                            <ref cRef="B2" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-123"/>
                    <p tid="124">Now the god Ratnavara asked youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, do you reveal this knowledge?”</p>
                    <p tid="125">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, had I attained or relinquished something I might also reveal
                        knowledge. But, divine being, since I have not attained or relinquished anything, what sort of knowledge
                        could I reveal?”</p>
                    <p tid="126">The god asked, “But Mañjuśrī, have you not gained or realized anything from following those
                        blessed buddhas who are more abundant than the number of grains of sand in the River Ganges?”</p>
                    <p tid="127">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, the blessed buddhas do not teach the Dharma for the sake of
                        attainment and realization.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-127"/>
                    <p tid="128">“But how, Mañjuśrī, do they then teach the Dharma?”</p>
                    <p tid="129">Mañjuśrī said, “Divine being, the blessed buddhas teach the Dharma by means of the indivisible
                        nature of the realm of phenomena. They do not teach the Dharma for the sake of no arising, no ceasing, no
                        raising up, no putting down, no coming, no going, no sentient beings, <ref cRef="F.152.a"/> separation
                        from sentient beings, affliction, purification, cyclic existence, or the transcendence of suffering.
                        Divine being, this is how the blessed buddhas teach the Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-129"/>
                    <p tid="130">The god asked, “But Mañjuśrī, if the blessed buddhas do not teach the Dharma for the sake of the
                        transcendence of suffering, then why do they appear?”</p>
                    <p tid="131">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, the buddhas appear so that the essential nature of the view of
                        the transitory collection may be realized. Divine being, the buddhas appear in order to reveal the
                        essential nature of ignorance and craving within existence. Divine being, the buddhas appear for the sake
                        of the realization of the essential nature of desire, anger, and delusion. Divine being, the buddhas
                        appear in order to show that the nature of error is sameness. Divine being, the buddhas appear so that all
                        features of the various views may be realized. Divine being, the buddhas appear in order to reveal that
                        the essential nature of the aggregates, elements, and sense sources is the realm of phenomena. Divine
                        being, the expression ‘the buddhas appear’ is a reference to all phenomena being unborn. Where no
                        phenomena at all are born, there is neither any cyclic existence nor any transcendence of suffering.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-131"/>
                    <p tid="132">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, if that is so, then those sentient beings who don armor for the sake of
                        unexcelled and perfect awakening have no need for that armor. Why? Because the appearance of the buddhas
                        does not benefit anyone.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-132"/>
                    <p tid="133">Mañjuśrī asked, “Divine being, tell me, how is benefit differentiated?”</p>
                    <p tid="134">“Mañjuśrī,” replied Ratnavara, “benefit is differentiated through formation.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-134"/>
                    <p tid="135">“Divine being, do you then also claim that the thus-gone ones are subject to formation?” <ref cRef="F.152.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="136">“No, Mañjuśrī, I do not. Formation does not pertain to the thus-gone ones. They have discovered
                        the unconditioned and are unconditioned, and formation is therefore not relevant to them.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-136"/>
                    <p tid="137">“Divine being,” declared Mañjuśrī, “according to your contention, neither benefit nor harm can be
                        observed with respect to the unconditioned.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-137"/>
                    <p tid="138">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, you should not deliver this Dharma teaching when beginners are present.
                        Why would I say so? Because if they hear it, they will become frightened, and when frightened they will
                        regress.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-138"/>
                    <p tid="139">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, the fear and regression of beginner bodhisattvas abide within
                        irreversibility itself.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-139"/>
                    <p tid="140">“Mañjuśrī, what makes you say that?”</p>
                    <p tid="141">“Divine being, frightened by the levels of the hearers and solitary buddhas, beginner
                        bodhisattvas turn back from stinginess, flawed discipline, hostility, laziness, distraction, and misguided
                        intelligence. That is how they genuinely abide within irreversibility.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-141"/>
                    <p tid="142"> “Mañjuśrī, what do you mean by ‘genuinely abide’?”</p>
                    <p tid="143">“Divine being, genuinely abiding is to abide neither evenly nor not evenly.’”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-143"/>
                    <p tid="144">“Mañjuśrī, how does a beginner bodhisattva abide?”</p>
                    <p tid="145">“Divine being, when one rests in sameness by means of non-abiding within the sameness of the
                        realm of phenomena—that is the abiding of a beginner bodhisattva.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-145"/>
                    <p tid="146">“Mañjuśrī, when is one a beginner bodhisattva?”</p>
                    <p tid="147">“Divine being, one is referred to as a beginner bodhisattva when, for the very first time, one
                        becomes inspired by the Dharma of emptiness, <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> the absence of marks, the absence of
                        wishes, no arising, and no origination.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-147"/>
                    <p tid="148">“Mañjuśrī, what is a bodhisattva with extensive experience?”</p>
                    <p tid="149">“Divine being, childish and ordinary beings are the ones who have extensive experience, because
                        the beginning of their cyclic existence cannot be observed.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-149"/>
                    <p tid="150">“Mañjuśrī, how do bodhisattvas maintain their conduct?”</p>
                    <p tid="151">“Divine being, bodhisattvas maintain their conduct by engaging in activities of desire in order
                        to ripen those who experience desire, yet they do not dwell on the experience of desire. For the sake of
                        ripening those who experience anger they engage in activities of anger, yet they do not dwell on the
                        experience of anger. For the sake of ripening those who experience bewilderment they engage in activities
                        of bewilderment, yet they do not dwell on the experience of bewilderment. For the sake of ripening those
                        who experience all the afflictions, they engage in activities of all of the afflictions, yet they do not
                        dwell on any of the afflictions. Divine being, for the sake of ripening sentient beings the bodhisattvas
                        engage with all the features of sentient beings’ experiences, yet bodhisattvas do not disturb the
                        characteristics of the realm of phenomena. Hence, when this is the case one maintains the conduct of a
                        bodhisattva.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-151"/>
                    <p tid="152">“Mañjuśrī, what is an irreversible bodhisattva?”</p>
                    <p tid="153">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, a bodhisattva who neither fears anything nor is attached to
                        anything, and who realizes the nature of the realm of phenomena by means of fearlessness and freedom from
                        attachment—that is an irreversible bodhisattva. Divine being, moreover, whenever a bodhisattva turns back
                        or enters, he is an irreversible bodhisattva. <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> Why is that? Because bodhisattvas
                        return to the realm of desire and they enter the concentrations. Divine being, moreover, whenever a
                        bodhisattva realizes what was not realized before and wholeheartedly refrains from dispute, he is an
                        irreversible bodhisattva. Why? Because when the constituents of sentient beings, phenomena, and oneself,
                        which were not realized, become directly perceptible, one becomes irreversible with respect to all
                        phenomena. Such a person is referred to as irreversible. Without having to rely on the statements of
                        others, one becomes free from hesitation, doubt, and uncertainty with respect to the qualities of a
                        buddha. Hence one is stainless and pure from the beginning. In the absence of afflictions, the light of
                        insight shines, one gains mastery with respect to all phenomena, and one actualizes all the qualities of a
                        buddha. That is why one is referred to as irreversible.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-153"/>
                    <p tid="154">“Mañjuśrī, what are bodhisattva great beings, who have only one birth remaining, like?”</p>
                    <p tid="155">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, such bodhisattvas know all births to be devoid of birth and yet
                        at the same time they know of the death and birth of all beings. For the sake of ripening sentient beings
                        they display birth throughout all lives, accepting birth yet remaining free from appropriation. Free from
                        appropriation throughout all births and lifetimes, such bodhisattvas are beyond death and birth. They do
                        not waver from or pass beyond the sameness of all phenomena. They understand the significance of causes
                        and conditions coming together. Their bodies are the same as the bodies of all beings. Their minds are the
                        same as the minds of all beings. Their voices are the same as the voices of all sentient beings. Their
                        realm is the same as the realm of all beings. They abide within the domain of the buddhas. They realize
                        the domain of the realm of phenomena. They are the same due to the sameness of the realm of phenomena.
                            <ref cRef="F.154.a"/> They know the thoughts of beings, are aware of time, and reach the ultimate seat
                        of awakening. Divine being, this is what it means to be a bodhisattva who has only one birth
                        remaining.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-155"/>
                    <p tid="156">The god Ratnavara asked youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, what are bodhisattvas, who are free from
                        evil and beyond reproach, like?”</p>
                    <p tid="157">Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine being, when bodhisattvas act by means of wisdom and not through pride,
                        they are bodhisattvas who are free from evil and beyond reproach. Moreover, divine being, when giving away
                        all their possessions based on the superior intent of the mind of awakening, they are free from evil. When
                        not involved in stinginess, they are irreproachable. When observing the ascetic practices, trainings,
                        disciplines, and all the commitments, they are free from evil. When not involved in flawed discipline,
                        they are irreproachable. When not harboring anger toward anyone, they are free from evil. When not
                        involved in the latent tendencies for covetousness and ill will, they are irreproachable. When they
                        manifest the diligence that brings forth all roots of virtue, they are free from evil. When not involved
                        in laziness, they are irreproachable. When resting in concentration and attainment, they are free from
                        evil. When they do not relish the blissful taste of concentration, they are irreproachable. When
                        diligently pursuing the learning that leads to insight, they are free from evil. <ref cRef="F.154.b"/>
                        When not associated with misguided knowledge, they are irreproachable. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-157"/>
                    <p tid="158"> “When not retaliating when hurt by others, they are free from evil. When not retaliating when
                        wounded by others, they are irreproachable. When saying things as they are, they are free from evil. When
                        acting accordingly, they are irreproachable. When at peace within, they are free from evil. When not
                        stained by outer objects, they are irreproachable. When not having different views with respect to the
                        mind of omniscience, they are free from evil. When not having any interest in the lesser vehicles, they
                        are irreproachable. When recognizing the works of the māras, they are free from evil. When thwarting the
                        works of the māras, they are irreproachable. When attaining illumination within the world, they are free
                        from evil. When unstained by worldly qualities, they are irreproachable. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-158"/>
                    <p tid="159"> “When not acting in conflict with what should be done, they are free from evil. When avoiding
                        what should not be done, they are irreproachable. When free from pride, conceit, and arrogance, they are
                        free from evil. When in possession of perfect wisdom, intelligence, and the truths of the noble ones, they
                        are irreproachable. With steadfast resolve, they are free from evil. When living by their pledges, they
                        are irreproachable. When being in harmony with the way of dependent origination, they are free from evil.
                        When not grasping at the phenomena of dependent origination, they are irreproachable. <ref cRef="F.155.a"/> When comprehending the empty nature of all phenomena by means of insight and wisdom, they are free from
                        evil. When skillfully gathering all roots of virtue, they are irreproachable. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-159"/>
                    <p tid="160"> “When engaging in all activities by means of great compassion, they are free from evil. When
                        abiding in liberation with respect to all phenomena, they are irreproachable. When not observing any
                        phenomena, they are free from evil. When teaching the Dharma for the sake of abandoning views that involve
                        observation, they are irreproachable. When engaged in proper conduct without truly observing any phenomena
                        they are free from evil. When manifesting the attainment of the fruition, they are irreproachable. When
                        discerning the realm of phenomena to be empty, they are free from evil. When never giving up on any
                        sentient being, they are irreproachable. When not dwelling in the three realms, they are free from evil.
                        When not transcending suffering because of seeing sentient beings, they are irreproachable.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-160"/>
                    <p tid="161"> “Divine being, moreover, as much as one makes use of words, reflects by means of words,
                        understands by means of words, and is attached to words—that much one is at fault. Divine being, as much
                        as one understands that all phenomena are beyond explanation, engagement, reflection, thinking,
                        conception, and expression, and as much as one does not pass beyond suffering in order not to abandon
                        sentient beings—that much one is free from evil and irreproachable. Divine being, someone who is free from
                        evil and irreproachable is beyond words. That which is beyond words is inexpressible, and the
                        inexpressible meaning is free from evil and beyond reproach. <ref cRef="F.155.b"/> Therefore, divine
                        being, since bodhisattvas, who base themselves on the inexpressible meaning, emphasize their own minds,
                        they are free from evil and beyond any reproach from noble beings.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-161"/>
                    <p tid="162">When youthful Mañjuśrī had given this teaching, the Blessed One expressed his approval. “Well
                        said, Mañjuśrī, well said. You have explained well how bodhisattvas are free from evil and irreproachable.
                        Mañjuśrī, when bodhisattvas become free from evil and beyond reproach in this way, the blessed buddhas
                        prophesy their unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-162"/>
                    <p tid="163">When they heard this teaching, five hundred bodhisattvas within the gathering gained acceptance
                        of the non-arising of phenomena. The Blessed One also delivered a prophecy regarding their unexcelled and
                        perfect awakening, specifying their individual buddha realms and declaring their names as thus-gone
                        ones.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-163"/>
                    <p tid="164">At that time some gods within the gathering wondered, “When might the god Ratnavara awaken to
                        unexcelled and perfect buddhahood? What might his buddha realm be like? And under what name will he attain
                        awakening?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-164"/>
                    <p tid="165">Then, by the power of the Buddha, venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One, “When will the god
                        Ratnavara awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood? What will his buddha realm be like? And under what
                        name will he attain awakening?”</p>
                    <p tid="166">The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.156.a"/> one hundred thousand eons from now,
                        during the eon known as Ratnasaṃvara, in a world to the east known as Pritivyūha, the god Ratnavara will
                        awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood; and so it will be that the thus-gone one, the worthy one, the
                        perfect buddha Ratnavyūha will appear in the world. Ānanda, the Pritivyūha world will be rich, vast, and
                        delightful. There will be bountiful harvests, and it will be filled with gods and humans. It will know no
                        unfree states or lower realms. Ānanda, in that world there will be no stones, pebbles, or gravel. The
                        ground will be smooth like the palm of a hand and covered with three precious substances: beryl, crystal,
                        and the gold of the Jambū River. Delightful to behold, it will be decorated with lattices of gold. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-166"/>
                    <p tid="167"> “Ānanda, the humans of that realm will experience enjoyments comparable to those of the gods in
                        the Heaven of Delighting in Emanations. In that world food and drink will manifest simply by the mere
                        thought of them. In that realm, ‘hearers’ and ‘solitary buddhas’ will be unheard of. The bodhisattvas
                        there will enjoy various Dharma delights, Dharma liberations, concentrations, absorptions, attainments,
                        and miraculous manifestations. They will experience nothing but the best, highest, and most delightful
                        Dharma joys; that is why this realm will be known as Pritivyūha, ‘Array of Joy.’ The lifespan of the
                        future buddha Ratnavyūha <ref cRef="F.156.b"/> will be six hundred million years, and his bodhisattva
                        saṅgha will consist of six hundred million ordained bodhisattvas and innumerable bodhisattvas living as
                        householders. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-167"/>
                    <p tid="168"> “When the Thus-Gone One Ratnavyūha teaches the Dharma to the bodhisattvas of that realm he will
                        ascend into the sky to a height of eight hundred million palm trees. There his crossed legs will cover the
                        entire celestial world and he will shine hundreds of thousands of light rays throughout the entire buddha
                        realm. A rain of divine flowers, incense, and colored powder will fall from the sky while the gods sing
                        hundreds and thousands of songs accompanied by the sounds of big and small cymbals. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-168"/>
                    <p tid="169"> “As those sounds are heard throughout the buddha realm, the bodhisattvas will receive a Dharma
                        teaching in the form of a dhāraṇī gateway known as the inexhaustible gateway. What is that dhāraṇī gateway
                        of the inexhaustible gateway? It teaches the disengagement of body and mind and is a gateway to the
                        disengagement of all phenomena. It teaches the definitive understanding of phenomena and is a gateway to
                        the comprehension of all phenomena. It teaches the pacification of all phenomena and is a gateway to
                        connecting with the way all phenomena are. It teaches how phenomena are free from evil and is a gateway to
                        genuine exertion with respect to all phenomena. It teaches the light of insight concerning phenomena and
                        is a gateway to illuminating all phenomena. It teaches the absence of difference among phenomena and is a
                        gateway to the sameness of all phenomena.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-169"/>
                    <p tid="170">“It teaches the absence of distraction with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to tranquility
                        with regard to all phenomena. It teaches the absence of conflict with respect to phenomena and is a
                        gateway to special insight with regard to all phenomena. It teaches the non-disturbance of phenomena and
                        is a gateway to the ascertainment of all phenomena. <ref cRef="F.157.a"/> It teaches the absence of
                        forgetfulness with regard to phenomena and is a gateway to the recollection of all phenomena. It teaches
                        the understanding of the meaning of phenomena and is a gateway to the understanding of all phenomena. It
                        teaches the mind’s purity with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to intelligence concerning all
                        phenomena. It teaches the way to conquer all the various views about phenomena and is a gateway to the
                        emptiness of all phenomena. It teaches the peace of phenomena and is a gateway to the absence of marks
                        with respect to all phenomena.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-170"/>
                    <p tid="171"> “It teaches the elimination of all transmigration with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to
                        the absence of wishes with respect to all phenomena. It teaches the lack of formation of phenomena and is
                        a gateway to the absence of formation with respect to all phenomena. It teaches the lack of establishment
                        of phenomena and is a gateway to the non-arising of all phenomena. It teaches the non-dual nature of all
                        phenomena and is a gateway to the non-occurrence of all phenomena. It teaches non-conceptuality regarding
                        phenomena and is a gateway to freedom from desire for phenomena. It teaches the direct cognition of
                        phenomena and is a gateway to the absence of constructs with respect to all phenomena. It teaches how all
                        phenomena are free from duality and is a gateway to the non-duality of all phenomena. It teaches the
                        immutability of all phenomena and is a gateway to the baseless nature of all phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-171"/>
                    <p tid="172"> “It teaches the sameness of sentient beings pertaining to phenomena and is a gateway to the
                        absence of sentient beings pertaining to all phenomena. It teaches the unchanging nature of phenomena and
                        is a gateway to non-doing with regard to all phenomena. It teaches the absence of activity with respect to
                        phenomena and is a gateway to the non-appropriation of all phenomena. It teaches how to crush the ground
                        of phenomena and is a gateway to the groundlessness of all phenomena. It teaches the absence of concerns
                        with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to certainty about all phenomena. <ref cRef="F.157.b"/> It
                        teaches how to accomplish the fruition of phenomena and is a gateway to the cause of all phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-172"/>
                    <p tid="173">“It teaches the lack of forgetfulness of phenomena and is a gateway to diligence with respect to
                        all phenomena. It teaches the absence of aggression with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to the
                        deliverance of all phenomena. It teaches the unmistaken suchness of phenomena and is a gateway to the
                        suchness of all phenomena. It teaches the indivisible nature of phenomena and is a gateway to the limit of
                        reality of all phenomena. It teaches the one taste of phenomena and is a gateway to the realm of phenomena
                        of all phenomena. It teaches the sameness of the three times with regard to phenomena and is a gateway to
                        the actual state of all phenomena. It teaches non-attachment to the sounds and verbal expressions
                        associated with phenomena and is a gateway to the inexpressible nature of all phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-173"/>
                    <p tid="174">“It teaches the pacification of all phenomena and is a gateway to the concentrations that pertain
                        to all phenomena. It teaches the absence of a person with respect to phenomena and is a gateway to the
                        reality of all phenomena. It teaches the understanding of the sameness of phenomena and is a gateway to
                        the awakening of all phenomena. </p>
                    <p tid="175">In this way, Ānanda, without arising from the center of space, the Thus-Gone One Ratnavyūha will
                        teach the bodhisattvas these dhāraṇī gateways known as ‘the inexhaustible gateway,’ doing so in an
                        elaborate and genuine manner. Thereby bodhisattvas beyond number and count will gain acceptance.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-174"/>
                    <p tid="176">Venerable Ānanda then exclaimed to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, the wisdom of the thus-gone
                        ones is spontaneously accomplished and beyond formation. They therefore possess a wisdom vision that
                        unimpededly perceives all phenomena—whether past, future, or present. What a wonder this is!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-175"/>
                    <p tid="177">The Blessed One responded, “Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.158.a"/> this wisdom of the thus-gone ones,
                        spontaneously accomplished and beyond formation, which unimpededly perceives all phenomena of the past,
                        future, and present, is indeed unique.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-176"/>
                    <p tid="178">Venerable Ānanda then turned to the god Ratnavara with the following words: “Divine being, the
                        Thus-Gone One has prophesied your awakening to true and perfect buddhahood. You have gained something
                        excellent.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-177"/>
                    <p tid="179">The god replied, “Venerable Ānanda, nothing can be observed to which any such prophecy could
                        apply. How is that? Form is not the bodhisattva, and hence form is not something that can receive a
                        prophecy. Neither are feeling, perception, formation, or consciousness the bodhisattva. Therefore, they
                        also cannot receive any prophecy. The earth element is not the bodhisattva, and hence it does not receive
                        any prophecy. The elements of water, fire, and wind are not the bodhisattva either, and therefore those
                        elements also do not receive any prophecy. Just as the eyes are not the bodhisattva and therefore cannot
                        receive any prophecy, the same is the case with the ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind. Name and form are
                        not the bodhisattva, and hence name and form cannot receive any prophecy. The events of the past, future,
                        and present are not the bodhisattva, and therefore the three times cannot receive any prophecy. Causes and
                        views are not the bodhisattva. Therefore, causes and views cannot receive any prophecy either. Arising and
                        disintegration are not the bodhisattva, and hence arising and disintegration cannot receive any prophecy. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-178"/>
                    <p tid="180"> “Venerable Ānanda, the term <distinct>bodhisattva</distinct> is a designation that functions as
                        a basis for communication. <ref cRef="F.158.b"/> That, in turn, is the basis for peace. That which is at
                        peace cannot in any way be prophesied. Venerable Ānanda, the term <distinct>prophecy</distinct> is a
                        synonym for the fact that no phenomena can be grasped. Venerable Ānanda, it is when bodhisattvas do not
                        grasp any phenomena—whether inner or outer, virtuous or unvirtuous, conditioned or unconditioned—that they
                        receive a prophecy. Venerable Ānanda, the so-called prophecy for bodhisattvas is a declaration of the fact
                        that no phenomena can be grasped at all. The prophecy declares that it is impossible to grasp any
                        phenomena. The prophecy declares that all phenomena are devoid of abiding. The prophecy declares that all
                        phenomena are unborn. The prophecy teaches the inconceivability of all phenomena; it shows them to be
                        beyond thought. Venerable Ānanda, such is the prophecy for bodhisattvas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-179"/>
                    <p tid="181">At this point the Blessed One expressed his approval to the god Ratnavara: “Excellent, divine
                        being, excellent! It is indeed to bodhisattvas who realize such a teaching that the blessed buddhas
                        prophesy awakening to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-180"/>
                    <p tid="182">When the Blessed One had spoken these words, Māra Pāpīyān appeared with his armies, mounts, and
                        retinue. When they all had gathered at the site where the Blessed One was residing, Māra Pāpīyān addressed
                        the Blessed One: “Blessed One, why do you give prophecies to bodhisattvas instead of to listeners?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-181"/>
                    <p tid="183">The Blessed One replied, “Pāpīyān, bodhisattvas are well known and acknowledged by gods and
                        humans throughout the great trichiliocosm. <ref cRef="F.159.a"/> This is why bodhisattvas receive such
                        prophecies. Hearers are not acknowledged among gods and humans and hence they do not receive this
                        prophecy. Evil māra, when a bodhisattva receives the prophecy, numerous sentient beings will arouse the
                        mind aimed at unexcelled and perfect awakening. Yet if a listener received a prophecy, that would not be
                        the case. As for those sentient beings who have entered the Great Vehicle, they will become irreversible.
                        That, too, is why bodhisattvas and not hearers receive a prophecy.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-182"/>
                    <p tid="184">Mañjuśrī asked, “Pāpīyān, why have you come to this assembly?”</p>
                    <p tid="185">Māra Pāpīyān replied, “Mañjuśrī, when the Blessed One prophesied that the god Ratnavara will
                        fully awaken to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood and become the Thus-Gone, worthy, perfect Buddha
                        Ratnavyūha, some words could be heard in my realm. From all my palaces with their windows and archways,
                        from our jewel trees, and from all our delightful and enjoyable places, the following words rang out: ‘The
                        Blessed, Thus-Gone Śākyamuni has prophesied that the god Ratnavara will attain unexcelled and perfect
                        awakening. More such prophecies will be given to other bodhisattvas. So, Pāpīyān, you should go
                        there!’”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-184"/>
                    <p tid="186">“Pāpīyān,” asked Mañjuśrī, “do you not rejoice in the prophecies of the bodhisattvas?”</p>
                    <p tid="187">Māra Pāpīyān replied, “Mañjuśrī, if it were prophesied that all the inhabitants of Jambudvīpa
                        were to become worthy ones, I would indeed rejoice. But it is a different matter when even one single
                        bodhisattva <ref cRef="F.159.b"/> is prophesied for unexcelled and perfect awakening. Why is that?
                        Mañjuśrī, when a bodhisattva is given the prophecy of awakening to unexcelled and perfect buddhahood, all
                        of my realms are threatened. Moreover, by means of the three vehicles such a bodhisattva will deliver a
                        limitless, countless, and boundless number of sentient beings from the three realms. Mañjuśrī, this
                        thought brings me to despair.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-186"/>
                    <p tid="188">Mañjuśrī replied, “Pāpīyān, whether you come here or not, you will not be able to create any
                        obstacles for a bodhisattva who has set out with superior intent, who is endowed with skillful means, and
                        who has departed by means of the perfection of insight. Why not? Because a bodhisattva who has set out
                        with superior intent, who is endowed with skillful means, and who has departed by means of the perfection
                        of insight is truly beyond the paths of the māras.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-187"/>
                    <p tid="189">By the power of the Buddha, Māra Pāpīyān then asked Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, how does one set out
                        with superior intent, how does one become endowed with skillful means, and how does one depart by means of
                        the perfection of insight?”</p>
                    <p tid="190">Mañjuśrī replied, “Pāpīyān, when a bodhisattva does not pursue any trifling activities at all,
                        such a bodhisattva will have set out with superior intent. When a bodhisattva sees that all the
                        afflictions and all the activities of the māras are aids to the attainment of unexcelled and perfect
                        awakening, such a bodhisattva is endowed with skillful means. When a bodhisattva does not keep company
                        with any of the afflictions, such a bodhisattva will have departed by means of the perfection of insight. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-189"/>
                    <p tid="191">“Pāpīyān, moreover, when a bodhisattva with superior intent <ref cRef="F.160.a"/> dons the great
                        armor for the sake of liberating all beings, such a bodhisattva will have set out with superior intent.
                        When a bodhisattva gathers sentient beings through the four means of attraction, such a bodhisattva is
                        endowed with skillful means. When a bodhisattva comprehends that the nature of all beings is the complete
                        transcendence of suffering, such a bodhisattva will have departed by means of the perfection of
                        insight.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-190"/>
                    <p tid="192">“Pāpīyān, moreover, when a bodhisattva is motivated by the superior intent of the mind of
                        awakening and thereby gives away all possessions without concern for any inner or outer entities, such a
                        bodhisattva will have set out with superior intent. When a bodhisattva perceives all beings as worthy
                        recipients of gifts, such a bodhisattva is endowed with skillful means. When a bodhisattva considers the
                        giver and the recipient to be the sameness of the limit of reality, such a bodhisattva will have departed
                        by means of the perfection of insight. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-191"/>
                    <p tid="193">“Pāpīyān, moreover, when a bodhisattva cannot be turned back from the practice of engendering
                        roots of virtue, such a bodhisattva will have set out with superior intent. When bodhisattvas are occupied
                        with the wellbeing of others and set aside their own welfare, such bodhisattvas are endowed with skillful
                        means. When a bodhisattva relies on the meaning and not on words and letters, such a bodhisattva will have
                        departed by means of the perfection of insight. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-192"/>
                    <p tid="194">“Pāpīyān, moreover, when a bodhisattva sees a beggar and responds with appreciation rather than
                        anger, such a bodhisattva will have set out with superior intent. When a bodhisattva gathers roots of
                        virtue and dedicates them to omniscience, such a bodhisattva is endowed with skillful means. When a
                        bodhisattva fully understands that all phenomena are of the nature of awakening, such a bodhisattva will
                        have departed by means of the perfection of insight.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-193"/>
                    <p tid="195">The god Ratnavara now said to Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, if Māra Pāpīyān, along with his armies, <ref cRef="F.160.b"/> mounts, retinue, and realm, were placed in confinement, then they could not create
                        any obstacles for the noble sons and daughters who have entered the Great Vehicle.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-194"/>
                    <p tid="196">Mañjuśrī replied, “Noble son, placing Māra Pāpīyān in confinement is not becoming for a
                        bodhisattva. Noble son, instead I shall transform Māra Pāpīyān so that he will come to possess all the
                        physical marks of a buddha, be endowed with supreme bliss, sit on a lion throne, and teach the Dharma with
                        the eloquence of a buddha.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-195"/>
                    <p tid="197">When Māra Pāpīyān heard these words, he attempted to become invisible and escape. However, due to
                        the power of youthful Mañjuśrī, he was unable to become invisible and escape. At that point Mañjuśrī
                        decided that the entire gathering should witness Māra Pāpīyān residing on a lion throne, adorned with all
                        the physical marks of a buddha, so he said to Māra Pāpīyān, “Pāpīyān, you have attained the awakening of
                        the thus-gone ones! You have the physical marks of a buddha and reside on a lion throne!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-196"/>
                    <p tid="198">Due to Mañjuśrī’s power, Māra Pāpīyān replied, “Mañjuśrī, when even the Blessed One himself has
                        not attained awakening, how could I possibly have done so? Why is that? Awakening is characterized by an
                        absence of desire for attainment. Therefore, in that absence of desire there is no attainment and no
                        realization. Awakening is an attainment of the unconditioned, and the unconditioned is characterized by no
                        attainment. Awakening is characterized by the realization of emptiness, yet emptiness cannot truly realize
                        emptiness. Awakening is characterized by the absence of marks, <ref cRef="F.161.a"/> yet the absence of
                        marks cannot truly realize the absence of marks. Awakening is characterized by the absence of wishes, yet
                        the absence of wishes cannot truly realize the absence of wishes. Awakening is the nature of the realm of
                        phenomena, yet that nature cannot truly realize that nature. Awakening is characterized by indivisible
                        suchness, yet suchness cannot truly realize suchness. Awakening abides within the limit of reality, yet
                        the limit of reality cannot truly realize the limit of reality. Awakening is the essence of the lack of a
                        self, a sentient being, a life force, a soul, a being, and a person. Therefore, it is not in any way
                        something that can be fully realized. Mañjuśrī, moreover, bodhisattvas who hear this teaching on the
                        characteristics of awakening without disturbing the characteristics of the essential nature of all
                        phenomena should be declared to have awakened.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-197"/>
                    <p tid="199">When the māra gave this teaching, five hundred bodhisattvas attained acceptance of the
                        non-arising of phenomena.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-198"/>
                    <p tid="200">Venerable Śāradvatīputra then addressed youthful Mañjuśrī: “Mañjuśrī, due to your power, Māra
                        Pāpīyān now has the complexion and physical marks of a thus-gone one and resides on a lion throne,
                        teaching such profound matters—what a wonder this is!</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-199"/>
                    <p tid="201">Mañjuśrī replied, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, if I were to bless them in the same manner, even
                        inanimate objects, such as the trees, grass, and forest here would display those features and teach the
                        Dharma with the eloquence of a buddha. Likewise, were I to bless you, the elder Śāradvatīputra, you would
                        also take the form of a buddha, displaying all the physical marks, <ref cRef="F.161.b"/> and you would
                        also teach the Dharma with the eloquence of a buddha.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-200"/>
                    <p tid="202">At this point venerable Śāradvatīputra thought to himself, “If youthful Mañjuśrī were to
                        transform me into the form and appearance of a buddha, a hearer would take the form of the Teacher, which
                        would not be appropriate. I should therefore disappear from this gathering.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-201"/>
                    <p tid="203">However, due to Mañjuśrī’s power, he could not disappear. Knowing venerable Śāradvatīputra’s
                        thoughts, Mañjuśrī now blessed Śāradvatīputra so that he appeared to the entire retinue in the form and
                        appearance of a buddha seated upon a lion throne. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-202"/>
                    <p tid="204">Mañjuśrī then said, “Now, venerable Śāradvatīputra, together with Māra Pāpīyān, please teach the
                        Dharma, just like the Thus-Gone One does.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-203"/>
                    <p tid="205">Hence venerable Śāradvatīputra, in the form and appearance of a buddha, said to Māra Pāpīyān, who
                        likewise was present in the form of a buddha, “Pāpīyān, how is the awakening of the thus-gone ones
                        distinguished?”</p>
                    <p tid="206">Pāpīyān replied, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, the awakening of the blessed buddhas is distinguished
                        by a realization of the sameness of all phenomena. It is distinguished by an understanding of the
                        non-duality of Dharma and non-Dharma. It is distinguished by the consecration of the wisdom of
                        omniscience. It is distinguished by a realization of the mental conduct of all beings. It is distinguished
                        by a realization of all entities and nonentities. It is not distinguished by the destruction of entities.
                        It is not distinguished by familiarization and the absence of entities. Still, it is not distinguished,
                            <ref cRef="F.162.a"/> yet also not undistinguished either. It is without movement, free from movement,
                        and the interruption of all movement, and so it does not come or go.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-205"/>
                    <p tid="207">Māra Pāpīyān then asked venerable Śāradvatīputra, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, what is the abode of
                        the thus-gone ones?”</p>
                    <p tid="208">Venerable Śāradvatīputra replied, “Pāpīyān, the thus-gone ones abide in the sameness of cyclic
                        existence. They abide in the absence of conceit because of the transcendence of suffering. They abide in
                        the characteristics of the essential nature of all views. They abide in the abode of all afflictions. They
                        abide in the true and fundamental abode of all phenomena. They abide in the abode of the non-duality of
                        the conditioned and the unconditioned. They abide by not abiding within any abodes. Pāpīyān, such is the
                        abode of the thus-gone ones.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-207"/>
                    <p tid="209">Again, venerable Śāradvatīputra asked Māra Pāpīyān, “Pāpīyān, how should one pursue
                        awakening?”</p>
                    <p tid="210">Māra Pāpīyān said, “Venerable Śāradvatīputra, awakening is present at the root of the view of the
                        transitory collection. It must be pursued from ignorance, the bonds of craving for existence, the fetters
                        of error, obscurations, and hindrances.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-209"/>
                    <p tid="211">“Pāpīyān, what do you have in mind when you say this?”</p>
                    <p tid="212">“Awakening, venerable Śāradvatīputra, is to understand these phenomena correctly as they
                        are.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-211"/>
                    <p tid="213">When this teaching was given, the minds of eight hundred monks were liberated from defilements
                        without any further appropriation. Among the gods who had faith in Śāradvatīputra and the gods who had
                        faith in the factions of the māras, there were thirty-two thousand beings who aroused the mind set upon
                        unexcelled and perfect awakening. It was for the sake of training those gods that youthful Mañjuśrī <ref cRef="F.162.b"/> caused Māra Pāpīyān and the elder Śāradvatīputra to appear with the body and physical
                        marks of a buddha. Now youthful Mañjuśrī withdrew his power, and the elder Śāradvatīputra and Māra Pāpīyān
                        both resumed their usual form. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-212"/>
                    <p tid="214">From various buddha realms in the four directions many thousands of bodhisattvas now arrived.
                        Descending from the sky, they all gathered before the Blessed One, worshipping him by bowing their heads
                        to his feet. Having all circumambulated him three times, they took their place in the gathering to one
                        side. </p>
                    <p tid="215">Sitting there, those bodhisattvas said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, we heard this Dharma
                        teaching on the indivisible nature of the realm of phenomena, so now we have come here to uphold the
                        sacred Dharma. Blessed One, we shall uphold this Dharma teaching. We shall hold it, read it, and master
                        it. So that the sacred Dharma may be upheld, we shall also teach it abundantly and correctly to
                        others.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-213"/>
                    <p tid="216">Addressing the Blessed One, venerable Ānanda asked, “Blessed One, from where have all these
                        bodhisattvas come?”</p>
                    <p tid="217">The Blessed One said, “Ānanda, they have gathered here from different buddha realms. Youthful
                        Mañjuśrī ripened them and this Dharma teaching on the indivisible nature of the realm of phenomena has
                        ripened them. Therefore, because of the gratitude and appreciation they feel for this Dharma teaching,
                        they have come here to see the Thus-Gone One, <ref cRef="F.163.a"/> pay homage to him, and venerate him.
                        They have also come to venerate Mañjuśrī and rejoice in this Dharma teaching. Ānanda, after I have passed
                        beyond suffering, these bodhisattvas will uphold the sacred Dharma by spreading this Dharma teaching in
                        Jambudvīpa. Ānanda, these bodhisattvas are diligently upholding the sacred Dharma of many hundreds of
                        thousands of buddhas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-215"/>
                    <p tid="218">At that time Śakra, Brahmā, and all the guardians of the world, who were present in the
                        gathering, said, “Blessed One, we shall serve and venerate all holy beings, noble sons, noble daughters,
                        and anyone else who upholds the sacred Dharma. We shall endeavor to protect them, guard them, and keep
                        them from harm.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-216"/>
                    <p tid="219">The Blessed One then expressed his approval to Śakra, Brahmā, and the guardians of the world.
                        “Friends, it is indeed excellent that you will exert yourselves in this way to protect the holy beings who
                        uphold the sacred Dharma. Those who apply themselves to upholding the sacred Dharma are worshipping the
                        buddhas of the past, the future, and the present.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-217"/>
                    <p tid="220">The Blessed One then spoke to Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, you must by all means bless this Dharma
                        teaching, so that in future times it will be widely practiced in Jambudvīpa.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-218"/>
                    <p tid="221">Mañjuśrī replied, “Blessed One, you would not ask me, for example, to bless the element of space
                        so that it would not get scorched during the eon of fire. <ref cRef="F.163.b"/> Similarly, Blessed One,
                        since all phenomena are of the nature of the element of space, they are not subject to birth or cessation.
                        That which is not born and does not cease, does not in any way have a nature that can be blessed. Blessed
                        One, since no phenomenon can be blessed, their very essence is blessed. Nevertheless, Blessed One, in
                        order that those noble sons and daughters, who revere the Dharma, who advance by means of the Dharma, and
                        who are suitable vessels for such a profound discourse, may create roots of virtue, I request that the
                        Thus-Gone One himself may bless this Dharma teaching. Blessed One, by all means, please grant your
                        blessing so that all māras and opposing forces are overcome, so that there are no obstacles, and so that
                        in the future this Dharma teaching will be practiced in Jambudvīpa.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-219"/>
                    <p tid="222">At that point the Blessed One radiated a golden light from his body, which was so bright that it
                        illuminated the entire great trichiliocosm. </p>
                    <p tid="223">The Blessed One then said to youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, this light of the Thus-Gone One
                        reaches everywhere. Just like that light, this Dharma teaching will also spread and pass into the hands of
                        noble sons and daughters who have unimpaired knowledge and concern for the Dharma of the buddhas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-220"/>
                    <p tid="224">The Blessed One said to venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you should remember this Dharma teaching. You
                        should hold it, recite it, and master it. You should teach it to others on a vast scale. In that way you
                        will be worshipping the blessed buddhas of the past, the future, <ref cRef="F.164.a"/> and the
                        present.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-221"/>
                    <p tid="225">Ānanda inquired, “Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma teaching and how should it be
                        remembered?”</p>
                    <p tid="226">The Blessed One declared, “Ānanda, you should remember this Dharma teaching as <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</title>. You should
                        also remember it as <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of the God Ratnavara</title>. You should also
                        remember it as <title xml:lang="en">Youthful Mañjuśrī’s Instructions</title>.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-223"/>
                    <p tid="227">When the Blessed One had spoken these words, venerable Ānanda, youthful Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva
                        Ratnavara, the bodhisattvas who had arrived from all the various buddha realms, as well as the world with
                        its gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="235">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-224"/>
                    <p tid="228">This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi
                        and the translator-editor, the venerable Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="236">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="237">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="238">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-226">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi dbying kyi rang bzhin dbyer med pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 52, Degé Kangyur, vol. 40 (dkon brtsegs, kha), folios
                        140.b–164.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-227">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi dbying kyi rang bzhin dbyer med pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i
                        bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the
                        China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China
                        Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 40, pp. 391–448.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-318">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi dbyings kyi rang bzhin dbyer med pa bstan pa zhes byaba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. In bka’ ’gyur (stog pho brang bris ma). vol. 36 (dkon brtsegs, kha), folios 206a – 241b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-228"> Bhāviveka. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu ma rin po che’i sgron ma</title>.
                        Toh 3854, Degé Tengyur, vol. 97 (dbu ma, tsha), folios 259.b–289.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-229"> Dolpopa Sherab Gyaltsen (dol po pa shes rab rgyal mtshan). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri chos nges don rgya mtsho zhes bya ba mthar thug thun mong ma yin pa’i man
                            ngag</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">The ’Dzam-thang Edition of the Collected Works (Gsung-’bum)
                            of Kun-mkhyen Dol-po-pa Shes-rab rgyal-mtshan</title>, vol. 1. Delhi: Shedrup Books, 1992, vol. 3, pp.
                        191–739.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-230"> Maitreya-Asaṅga. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbus dang mtha’ rnam par ’byed
                            pa’i tshig le’ur byed pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyānthavibhāgakārikā</title>). Toh 4021,
                        Degé Tengyur, vol. 123 (mdo ’grel, phi), folios 40.a–45.a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-231"> Vasubandhu. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbus dang mtha’ rnam par ’byed pa’i
                            ’grel pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyāntavibhāga-bhāṣya</title>). Toh 4027, Degé
                        Tengyur, vol. 226 (mdo ’grel, bi), folios 1.a–27.a.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="239">Secondary Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-304"> Boucher, Daniel. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattvas of the Forest and the
                            Formation of the Mahāyāna: A Study and Translation of the Rāṣṭrapālaparipṛcchā-sūtra</title>.
                        Honolulu: University of Hawai’i Press, 2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-313"> Braarvig, Jens. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamatinirdeśa-sūtra</title>. (Two volumes). Oslo: Solum
                        Forlag, 1993. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-305"> Chang, Garma C. C. (ed.). <title xml:lang="en">A Treasury of Mahāyāna
                            Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>. University Park: Pennsylvania State
                        University Press, 1983. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-306">Dol-bo-ba Shay-rap-gyel-tsen. Jeffrey Hopkins (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Mountain Doctrine: Tibet’s Fundamental Treatise on Other-Emptiness and the Buddha Matrix</title>.
                        Boston: Shambhala Publications, 2006. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-307"> Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar
                            and Dictionary</title>, vols. 1–2. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1953. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-308"> Monier-Williams, M. <title xml:lang="en">A Sanskrit-English
                            Dictionary</title>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1899. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-309"> Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men: The Bodhisattva Path
                            According to the Inquiry of Ugra</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ugraparipṛcchā</title>). Honolulu:
                        University of Hawaii Press, 2003. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-310"> Pali Text Society. <title xml:lang="en">The Pali Text Society’s
                            Pali-English Dictionary</title>. London: Chipstead, 1925. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-311"> Ruegg, David Seyfort. <title xml:lang="en">The Buddhist Philosophy of the
                            Middle: Essays on Indian and Tibetan Madhyamaka</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2010. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-040-003-312"> Silk, Jonathan A. <title xml:lang="en">The Origins and the History of the
                            Mahāratnakūta Tradition of Mahayana Buddhism with a Study of the Ratnarāśi Sutra and Related
                            Materials</title>. (Unpublished doctoral dissertation.) University of Michigan, 1994. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-241">
                            <term>buddha realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi zhing </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddha­kṣetra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The realm permeated by a buddha’s teaching and blessing.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-242">
                            <term>god</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva­putra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A being of any of the many levels of celestial or divine realms according to
                                Buddhist cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-243">
                            <term>māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A demonic being opposed to the spread of the Dharma and the happiness of
                                beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-244">
                            <term>relative</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun rdzob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་རྫོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃvṛti</term>
                            <term type="definition">Of seeming and apparent truth or reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-245">
                            <term>ultimate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don dam pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོན་དམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">para­mārtha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Of final truth or reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-246">
                            <term>great trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po'i 'jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­mahāsāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A universe containing one billion worlds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-247">
                            <term>acceptance of the non-arising of phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">An attainment characteristic of the effortless and spontaneous wakefulness of
                                the 8th ground of the bodhisattvas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-248">
                            <term>three gateways of liberation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par thar pa'i sgo gsum</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པའི་སྒོ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par thar pa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཐར་པ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trīṇi vimokṣa­mukhāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Absence of marks, absence of wishes, and emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-249">
                            <term>realm of phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for emptiness or the ultimate nature of things (see i.4). This term
                                is interpreted variously—given the many connotations of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>—as the sphere,
                                element, or nature, of phenomena, reality, or truth. In this text it is used with this general,
                                Mahāyāna sense, not to be confused with its rather different meaning in the Abhidharma as one of
                                the twelve sense sources (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āyatana</foreign>) and eighteen
                                elements (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhātu</foreign>) related to mental
                                perception.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-250">
                            <term>view of the transitory collection</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig tshogs la lta ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་ཚོགས་ལ་ལྟ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">satkāyadṛṣṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The construction of personal identity in relation to the five
                                aggregates.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-251">
                            <term>affliction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas nyon mongs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃkleśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The process of karma, <term type="ignore">afflictions</term> of the mind, and
                                suffering.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-252">
                            <term>purification</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par byang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyavadāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">purification</term> of affliction.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-253">
                            <term>four errors</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyin ci log bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catvāro viparyāsāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Taking what is impermanent to be permanent, what is painful to be delightful,
                                what is unclean to be clean, and what is no self to be a self.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-254">
                            <term>excessive pride</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon pa’i nga rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པའི་ང་རྒྱལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhimāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A conceited, false sense of attainment. One of seven types of pride related to
                                the spiritual path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-255">
                            <term>five obscurations</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañca­nivaraṇāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">A set of mental factors that hinder discipline, concentration, and
                                insight.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-256">
                            <term>six super-knowledges</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaḍabhijñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Six modes of clairvoyant cognition.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-257">
                            <term>six sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaḍāyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The five faculties along with the mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-258">
                            <term>seven branches of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta­bodhyaṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">The set of seven factors that characteristically manifest on the path of
                                seeing.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-259">
                            <term>eight flaws</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">log pa nyid brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལོག་པ་ཉིད་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭamithyātva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eight misunderstandings of the way things are.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-260">
                            <term>eight-fold path of the noble ones</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa'i lam yan lag brgyad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པའི་ལམ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāṣṭāṅga­mārga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eight factors whereby the training on the path of cultivation takes
                                place.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-261">
                            <term>nine successive attainments</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthar gyis gnas pa’i snyoms par ’jug pa dgu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐར་གྱིས་གནས་པའི་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་དགུ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">navānupūrva­vihāra­samāpatti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four concentrations, the four formless states, and the equilibrium of
                                cessation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-262">
                            <term>limit of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term has three meanings: (1) a synonym for the ultimate nature, (2) the
                                experience of the ultimate nature, and (3) the quiescent state of a worthy one (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arhat</foreign>) to be avoided by bodhisattvas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-263">
                            <term>four perceptions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du shes bzhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་ཤེས་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catuḥ-saṃjñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The factual perceptions of that which is impermanent, painful, unclean, and
                                devoid of self.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-264">
                            <term>factors of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi phyogs kyi chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhi­pakṣya­dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Thirty-seven practices that lead the practitioner to the awakened state: the
                                four applications of mindfulness, the four thorough relinquishments, the four bases of miraculous
                                power, the five faculties, the five powers, the eightfold path, and the seven branches of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-265">
                            <term>disengagement</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vivikta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viviktatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term usually has to do with a subjective state of ‘isolation,’
                                ‘separation,’ or ‘withdrawal,’ rather than a metaphysical idea. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamatinirdeśa-sūtra</title> contains a more or less parallel discussion of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dben pa nyid</foreign> in connection with diligence: “<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de la ’jug pa gang zhe na gang dge ba’i rtsa ba thams cad rtsom
                                    pa’o/ gnas pa gang zhe na. gangs sems dben pa’o</foreign>.” Jens Braarvig translates this
                                passage: “What then is activity? Undertaking all roots of good. What then is stillness? Aloofness
                                of thought.” (Braarvig, vol. 1, pp. 175-76; vol. 2, p. 50.) Here <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems dben pa</foreign> is glossed in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamatinirdeśaṭīkā</title> (of Vasubandhu or perhaps Sthiramati) as: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sems dben pa ni mi dge ba spangs pa dang dge ba rtsom pa gang
                                    la yang mi rtog pa’o</foreign>. This can be translated as, “<term type="ignore">Disengagement</term> of one’s thought is not thinking at all about giving up the non-virtuous
                                and undertaking the virtuous.” In any case, the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">viviktatā</foreign> in this context and in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamatinirdeśa</title> does not seem to be about emptiness, but more about a type of aloof
                                or disengaged diligence that does not conceptualize the virtues and non-virtues of the actions
                                undertaken.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-266">
                            <term>Heap of Jewels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon mchog brtsegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A collection of texts comprising a section of the Kangyur as well as of the
                                Chinese Buddhist canon. See the <ref target="http://read.84000.co/section/O1JC114941JC14667.html#summary">Reading Room
                                    “About”</ref> tab notes for details.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-267">
                            <term>ten stages</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabhūmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The tenfold division of the progressive levels of realization attained and
                                obscurations removed as a bodhisattva travels the path toward buddhahood. Also called the ten
                                grounds or levels.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-268">
                            <term>aggregate of discipline</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims kyi phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla­skandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five undefiled aggregates (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pañca anāsravaskandha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zag med kyi phung po
                                    lnga</foreign>), also known as the five aggregates beyond the world (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lokottaraskandha</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’jig rten las ’das pa’i phung po lnga</foreign>), the others being the aggregates
                                of absorption (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhi</foreign>), insight (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñā</foreign>), liberation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vimukti</foreign>), and liberated wisdom vision (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vimuktijñānadarśana</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-269">
                            <term>ascetic practices</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyangs pa’i yon tan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱངས་པའི་ཡོན་ཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhūtaguṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">An optional set of practices that monastics can adopt in order to cultivate
                                greater detachment. The list of practices varies in different sources. When thirteen practices are
                                listed, they consist of 1) wearing patched robes made from discarded cloth rather than from cloth
                                donated by laypeople; 2) wearing only three robes; 3) going for alms; 4) not omitting any house
                                while on the alms round, rather than begging only at those houses known to provide good food; 5)
                                eating only what can be eaten in one sitting; 6) eating only food received in the alms bowl,
                                rather than more elaborate meals presented to the Saṅgha; 7) refusing more food after indicating
                                one has eaten enough; 8) dwelling in the forest; 9) dwelling at the root of a tree; 10) dwelling
                                in the open air, using only a tent made from one’s robes as shelter; 11) dwelling in a charnel
                                ground; 12) satisfaction with whatever dwelling one has; and 13) sleeping in a sitting position
                                without ever lying down.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-317">
                            <term>appropriation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">len pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ādana, upādana</term>
                            <term type="definition">Also means “grasping” or “clinging;” but has a particular meaning as the ninth
                                of the twelve links of dependent arising, between craving (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tṛṣṇā</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sred pa</foreign>) and becoming or
                                existence (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhava</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid pa</foreign>). </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-270">
                            <term>ten qualities of no-more-training</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi slob pa’i chos bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སློབ་པའི་ཆོས་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśa-aśaikṣadharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">The eight practices of the eight-fold path of the noble ones as well as
                                liberation and wisdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-271">
                            <term>seven bases of consciousness </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par shes pa’i gnas bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པའི་གནས་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta-vijñānasthiti</term>
                            <term type="definition">Seven categories that describe living beings in the higher realms, from humans
                                up to the formless realm: 1) those different in body and different in perception; 2) those
                                different in body and equal in perception; 3) those equal in body but different in perception; 4)
                                those equal in body and equal in perception; 5) those reborn in the sphere of boundless space; 6)
                                those reborn in the sphere of boundless consciousness; and 7) those reborn in the sphere of
                                nothingness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-273">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term type="definition">Benefactor of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-274">
                            <term>Ratnavara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen mchog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་མཆོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnavara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva god whose wish sets off the teaching of the
                                sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-275">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A great bodhisattva, one of the eight “close sons” of the Buddha, the
                                embodiment of wisdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-276">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha’s cousin and principal attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-277">
                            <term>Ratnavyūha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bkod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་བཀོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnavyūha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name by which Ratnavara will be known when he becomes a buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-278">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ra dwa ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་ར་དྭ་ཏིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha, renowned for his pure observance
                                of discipline. Also known as Śāriputra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-279">
                            <term>Pāpīyān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdig can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྡིག་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pāpīyān</term>
                            <term type="definition">Demonic being (his name means “the wicked one”) who resides in the the Heaven
                                of Making Use of Others’ Emanations.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-280">
                            <term>Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་འབྱོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-281">
                            <term>Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha of this age; the historical buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-282">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the Heaven of the Thirty Three; equivalent to, or
                                identified with, Indra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-283">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the Brahma realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-284">
                            <term>Jinamitra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra </term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍiṭa resident in Tibet during the late 8th and early 9th
                                centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-285">
                            <term>Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">su ren dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍiṭa resident in Tibet during the late 8th and early 9th
                                centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-286">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late 8th and early 9th
                                centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-288">
                            <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Ancient city of northern India.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-289">
                            <term>Jeta Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jetavana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A park outside Śrāvastī. It was donated to the Buddha by Anāthapiṇḍada, who
                                purchased it at great cost from Prince Jeta.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-290">
                            <term>Pritivyūha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba bkod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བ་བཀོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pritivyūha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The world within which Ratnavara will attain enlightenment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-291">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent to the south of Mt. Sumeru, where according to Buddhist
                                cosmology “the world as we know it” is located.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-292">
                            <term>Jambū river</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu chu bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་ཆུ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambūnadī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine river.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-040-003-293">
                            <term>Heaven of Delighting in Emanations</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phrul dga’</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕྲུལ་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirmāṇarati</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second highest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>