<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag bzangs kyis zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ལག་བཟངས་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subāhuparipṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ལག་བཟངས་ཀྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled: The Inquiry of Subāhu</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryasubāhuparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <author ref="" role="translatorMain">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-140">Dr. Gyurme Dorje</editor>
            <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-62">Chloé Cramer</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-60">Ben Ewing</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-67">Lowell Cook</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-72">Oriane Lavole</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-276">Sarah Evers</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                    non-profit initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words
                    into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons
                            CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                            copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or
                            personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative
                            Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-043-007"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2019-07-19</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh70" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 70</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 154.a–180.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dānaśīla</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="54">
                        <start volume="43" page="309"/>
                        <end volume="43" page="362"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11608" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-07-20T00:54:20.631Z" user="admin">20/07/2019 00:54:20</note>
            <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.c" date-time="2019-05-20T16:20:49.651Z" user="konchog">2.c</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2019-07-19T11:49:24.7Z" user="james">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2019-07-19T16:28:45.352Z" user="john">2.a</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <front>
         <div type="summary">
            <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-1"/>
            <p tid="2">
               <title xml:lang="en">In this scripture </title>
               <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Śākyamuni</hi> Buddha describes how a bodhisattva should ideally train in the six perfections. Set in Veṇuvana by Rājagṛha, the Buddha teaches this sūtra in response to a single question posed to him by the bodhisattva Subāhu: how many qualities should a bodhisattva have in order to progress to perfect awakening? The Buddha responds by first listing the six perfections of generosity, ethical discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and insight, and then expounding in greater detail on each perfection in turn.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgment">
            <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-2"/>
            <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. This translation was produced by Chloé Cramer, Ben Ewing, Lowell Cook, Oriane Lavole, and Sarah Evers. The translation was then checked against the Tibetan and edited by James Gentry, who also wrote the introduction.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head tid="6">Main Section</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-3"/>
               <p tid="7">
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> is a Great Vehicle sūtra in which <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Śākyamuni</hi> Buddha teaches how a bodhisattva should ideally practice the six perfections. According to the opening and closing phrases appended to its Tibetan translation, it constitutes “the twenty-sixth section among the hundred thousand sections of Dharma discourse in the noble Mahāratnakūṭa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen po</foreign>)” collection of Great Vehicle sūtras. Although little can be known for certain about the Indian provenance of <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title>, there is some indication that it was well known in India; in addition to being translated into Tibetan as part of the Ratnakūṭa collection, <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> was also rendered into Chinese, Korean, and Mongolian, and the Degé edition of the Tibetan Tengyur also includes an aspiration prayer derived from it.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-4"> 
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa’i mdo las byung ba’i smon lam</title>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, Toh 4381 (vol. 207) (sna tshogs, nyo), folios 310a5–310b2.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </hi> 
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-5"/>
               <p tid="8">The Mahāratnakūṭa collection, as Jonathan Silk (1994) has argued based on the work of Nagao and others, probably formed around the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title>, which was perhaps originally the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭasūtra</title>. Moreover, Silk (ibid.) demonstrates in his study of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnarāśisūtra</title>, another text in the Mahāratnakūṭa collection with affinities to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapaparivarta</title>, that their shared features point toward the characteristics of a specific kind of “textual community.” This textual community was perhaps one of many that were influential in the rise of the Great Vehicle. Three of the defining features of this proposed textual community that can be gleaned from the work of Silk and others (Nattier 2003, Boucher 2008) are an absence of discernible antagonism between śrāvaka (hearer) and bodhisattva practitioners; an emphasis on monastic ideals; and a concomitant valorization of renunciation and the ascetic life. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-6"/>
               <p tid="9">
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> corresponds only in small part to this pattern. The ideal bodhisattva, as the Buddha describes in response to the titular inquiry of Subāhu, should strive to preserve the integrity of and even acquire his own “great saṅgha of hearer attendants”; and throughout, he presents the “vehicle of the hearers” as a perfectly viable approach, even instructing that a bodhisattva should teach the vehicles of the hearers, solitary buddhas, and bodhisattvas, as appropriate. Nonetheless, there is also a discernible hierarchy in the Buddha’s presentation that reflects the presumed superiority of the bodhisattva vehicle. Moreover, Subāhu, as the sūtra’s opening frame seems to suggest, is probably a lay bodhisattva, and the stipulations for the bodhisattva’s ideal performance of generosity and ethical discipline thus reflect a resolutely lay orientation. For instance, a bodhisattva should give gifts as extravagant as land; he should never give in a way that harms his children, wives, male and female slaves, or servants and laborers; and his ethical discipline should consist primarily of observing the five lay vows of an upāsaka. Moreover, the Buddha presents along with the ideal performance of each perfection a path of gradual training for those who presently lack the capacity to implement the ideal. The Buddha then concludes each of these passages by stating that the aspiration to implement the ideal is itself the highest form of each perfection. All of these features taken together suggests an open appeal to an audience that extends beyond the circle of strict ascetics.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-7"/>
               <p tid="10">
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> also diverges from another type of “textual community” that was prominent in the rise of the Great Vehicle. This type, which Gregory Schopen (2005) has characterized as the “cult of the book,” foregrounds the act of preaching, the preacher, and the physical object of the scriptural book itself as the center of Buddhist cultic life. The cult of the book has found expression in formulas that appear repeatedly throughout many Great Vehicle sūtras, which promise to fulfill pragmatic and soteriological aims, including bringing the Buddha into presence, simply through the copying, reciting, preaching, carrying, or wearing of texts. <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> lacks any such formulations, but it does stipulate that bodhisattvas should build and worship stūpas, which was another and perhaps older way of bringing the Buddha into presence after his passing (Trainor 1997). All told, then, the ideal audience for <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> appears to have been primarily, but not exclusively, lay Buddhist practitioners connected to monastic communities that consisted of both hearer and bodhisattva practitioners, and had stūpas in their care. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-8"/>
               <p tid="11">To briefly summarize this work’s contents, the sūtra is set in Veṇuvana, at the Kalandakanivāpa, near Rājagṛha, where the Buddha is staying in the company of a large assembly of monks. A bodhisattva great being by the name of Subāhu, with servants in tow, visits the Buddha from the nearby town of Rājagṛha to pose a single question: how many qualities should bodhisattvas have in order to progress to perfect awakening? The entire sūtra consists of the Buddha’s response to this question. He begins by simply listing the six perfections of generosity, ethical discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and insight, and then he expounds in greater detail on each perfection in turn. Each of the six sections of the ensuing discourse stipulates first how bodhisattvas should ideally practice the relevant perfection, and then how bodhisattvas should gradually train in that perfection if they lack the requisite capacity to undertake it as ideally stipulated. Each section ends by emphasizing how simply the aspiration to ideally undertake the relevant perfection is in fact the most sublime form of the perfection; it is the cultivation of this mental attitude, stresses the Buddha, suffused with compassion for all beings, that will enable bodhisattvas to swiftly and easily complete the perfections.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-9"/>
               <p tid="12">
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> is no longer extant in Sanskrit but fortunately we still have the abovementioned translations into</hi> Chinese, Korean, Tibetan, and Mongolian<hi type="wordfile-remnant">. The Chinese translation </hi>(<fix>Shanbipusahui</fix> 善臂菩薩會, Taishō 310 (26)) <hi type="wordfile-remnant">which is the earliest of these, was produced by the famed translator Kumārajīva (344–413 CE), who completed his work sometime during the years 402–412 CE, when he resided at what was then the Chinese capital of Chang’an (modern day Xi’an). </hi>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-10"/>
               <p tid="13">
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The present translation is based mainly on the Tibetan version of the sūtra present in the Degé Kangyur, in consultation with the variant readings presented in the Comparative Edition (</hi>
                  <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">) and the Stok Palace version. According to its colophon, </hi>
                  <title xml:lang="en">The</title>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>
                  <title xml:lang="en">Inquiry of Subāhu</title> was translated into Tibetan, edited, and finalized, based on revisions done according to the language reform, by a translation team consisting of the Indian preceptors Dānaśīla and Jinamitra, and the Tibetan chief editor-translator venerable Yeshé Dé, who were active in Tibet in the late eighth and early ninth centuries. Indeed, the sūtra is listed in the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan</foreign>/<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhan dkar ma</foreign> imperial translation catalogue (Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, 30, no. 51), whose compilation Herrmann-Pfandt (Ibid. xviii–xx) argues was most likely completed in 812. Moreover, the mention of the “language reform,” the imperial edict reflected in the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title> (Halkias 2004) whose first appearance Scherrer-Schaub (2002, 285) dates to 783 or 795 under the reign of Trisong Detsen (khri srong lde btsan, r. 756–c. 797, c. 798–c. 800),<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-11"> Brandon Dotson, “’Emperor’ Mu rug btsan and the <fix>’Phang thang ma Catalogue</fix>,” <fix>Journal of the International Association of Tibetan Studies</fix>, no. 3 (December 2007): 2n4.</note>
                  </hi> suggests that <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Subāhu</title> may have been finalized only after 783/795. </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="translation">
            <head type="translation" tid="14"> The Translation </head>
            <head type="titleHon" tid="15">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled:</head>
            <head type="titleMain" tid="16">The Inquiry of Subāhu</head>
            <!--In the rare case that there is initial text before the first chapter begins, the script will place the
                        text here. However, this will cause the two headings for the "Honorific Title" and "Main Title" to be duplicated below
                        as <p> elements. Markup Editors, please delete these initial duplicated <p> elements along with their milestones and delete this comment.-->
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-12"/>
            <p tid="17">
               <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled:</hi> 
            </p>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-13"/>
            <p tid="18">
               <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The Inquiry of Subāhu</hi>
            </p>
            <div>
               <head tid="19">Main Section</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-14"/>
               <p tid="20">[F.154.a] [B1]</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-15"/>
               <p tid="21">Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-16"/>
               <p tid="22">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Veṇuvana, at the Kalandakanivāpa, near Rājagṛha, together with a great assembly of monks. At that time a bodhisattva great being named Subāhu set out with his servants from the city of Rājagṛha for Veṇuvana, at the Kalandakanivāpa, where the Blessed One was staying. As soon as he arrived, Subāhu touched his head to the feet of the Blessed One, circumambulated him three times, and sat down to one side. With palms joined, the bodhisattva great being Subāhu bowed to the Blessed One and asked him, “Blessed One, how many qualities should bodhisattva great beings possess in order to swiftly and completely awaken to unsurpassed and perfect awakening?” </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-17"/>
               <p tid="23">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva great being Subāhu as follows: “Subāhu, in order for bodhisattva great beings to swiftly and perfectly awaken, they must constantly and relentlessly complete the six perfections. What are these six? They are the perfection of generosity, the perfection of ethical discipline, the perfection of patience, the perfection of diligence, [F.154.b] the perfection of concentration, and the perfection of insight. Subāhu, bodhisattva great beings must constantly and relentlessly complete these six perfections. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="24">Perfection of Generosity</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-18"/>
               <p tid="25">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattva great beings complete the perfection of generosity? Subāhu, they seek resources in accordance with the Dharma, and not contrary to the Dharma. They perform generosity without bias, and not with bias. They perform generosity without harming or causing distress to creatures or other beings. It is not done for fame, reputation, or praise. It is not done out of cowardice, fear, hoping for reward, or for the sake of a high rebirth. It does not involve hypocrisy, pretense, or disdain. Bodhisattvas respect, venerate, serve, and honor the recipients no matter whether or not they are particularly worthy, have superknowledge,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-19">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> D: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par shes pa</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (“superknowledge”); N, H: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par grags pa </foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">(“famous”).</hi>
                     </note>
                  </hi> have ethical discipline, are familiar to them, or are their relatives. With great inspiration, intense joy, and strong faith, they give little if they possess<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-20">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> D: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bdog</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (“possess”); K</hi>
                        <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, K: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’dod</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (“want,” “desire”).</hi> 
                     </note>
                  </hi> but little, they give much if they possess much, they give excellent things if they possess excellent things,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-21"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, N:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">-bzang du bdog na yang bzang du sbyin</foreign> (missing, “they give excellent things if they possess excellent things”). <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> ahāy Vehicle sion their identityesexistencerly </hi>
                     </note>
                  </hi> they give modest things if they possess but modest things, and they give exquisite things if they possess exquisite things. Subāhu, just as bodhisattvas give one hundred thousand gifts with a magnanimous and cheerful attitude, so do they give a simple coin with a magnanimous and cheerful attitude.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-22"/>
               <p tid="26">“To enable all beings to gain stability through the strength of the unsurpassed wisdom of omniscience, bodhisattvas give nourishment to those who desire nourishment. [F.155.a] To enable all beings to gain the strength that entirely quenches the thirst of afflictions, they give drinks to those who desire drinks. To enable all beings to acquire the clothing of shame and decency, they give clothing to those who desire clothing. To enable all beings to acquire the vehicle of bodhisattvas and the unsurpassed vehicle of complete buddhas, they give mounts to those who desire mounts. To enable all beings to acquire the fragrance of the buddhas’ ethical discipline, they give perfume to those who desire perfume. To enable all beings to acquire the unsurpassable flower of the thus-gone ones’ seven branches of awakening, they give flowers to those who desire flowers. To enable all<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-23"> N, H:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">-thams cad</foreign> (missing “all”).</note>
                  </hi> beings to gain the strength of overcoming the stench of wrongdoing, they give fragrant powder to those who desire fragrant powder. To enable all beings to acquire the unguent of faultless ethical discipline and conduct, they give scented unguents to those who desire scented unguents. To enable all beings to acquire the strength that thoroughly pacifies any torment of afflictions, they give parasols to those who desire parasols. To enable all beings to attain the unsurpassable comfort of superknowledge,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-24"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">-shes pa</foreign> (missing “knowledge”). This clause would then read, “To enable all beings to truly attain unsurpassable comfort.”</note>
                  </hi> they give shoes to those who desire shoes. To enable all beings to gain the strength to prepare for the comfort of bedding in the abodes of the gods, Brahmā, and the noble ones, they give bedding to those who desire bedding. To enable all beings to acquire the throne of the Hero, the seat of awakening unmoved by all the obstacles of māras and afflictions, they give seats to those who desire seats. To enable all beings to attain bodies that will serve as shelter, abode, protection, and refuge, they give shelter to those who desire shelter. [F.155.b] To enable all beings to attain bodies that will serve as reservoirs for the Dharma, they give pots, vases, and utensils to those who desire them. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-25"/>
               <p tid="27">To enable all beings to attain all the absorptions and attainments of unsurpassed tranquility and quiescence, bodhisattvas give the gift of ascetic groves to the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha. To enable all beings to attain the thirty-two major and eighty minor marks of a great man, they give the gift of adornments to stūpas. To enable all beings to gain the limitless divine vision of the thus-gone ones, they give the gift of lamps at darkened stūpas and paths. To enable all beings to acquire the limitless divine hearing of the thus-gone ones, they give the gift of melodious music in their worship of the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha. To enable all beings to gain unsurpassed, exquisite appearance, ethical discipline, and conduct, bodhisattvas give the gift of alms bowls and monastic robes. To enable all beings to gain the power to give relief, they give the gift of sieves. To enable all beings to attain the completion of the accumulation of great insight, they give the gift of reed brushes, ink, palm leaves, and Dharma seats. To eliminate all the illnesses of afflictions from all beings, bodhisattvas give the gift of medicines to cure the sick and other standard resources. To enable all beings to attain the ground of the three kinds of awakening and the ground of the expanse of ambrosia, they give the gift of land. To enable all beings to obtain the lofty, sublime Dharma without a teacher, [F.156.a] they build lofty stūpas and statues. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-26"/>
               <p tid="28">“To enable all beings to quickly acquire the different kinds of superknowledge upon seeing what they have acquired, bodhisattvas give gifts quickly and without reluctance.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-27"> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yongs su nyon mongs par ma gyur pa</foreign>; probably renders <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">parikliṣṭha</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> To enable beings to attain complete awakening without hindrance, they give suitable gifts, not unsuitable ones. To enable all beings to acquire unimpeded great eloquence, they give gifts limitlessly. To enable all beings to acquire unparalleled great compassion, they give equally to all beings. To enable all beings to perfectly and completely awaken to the Dharma that cannot be destroyed or harmed by any māras or non-Buddhists, bodhisattvas give gifts that do no harm to others. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-28"/>
               <p tid="29">“Subāhu, if bodhisattvas are without the wealth and means to give these gifts, they make aspirations, mentally yearning and wishing to give these limitless, immeasurable gifts to all beings throughout all world systems. Subāhu, whether or not bodhisattvas have the capacity to give these gifts, they make aspirations, mentally yearning and wishing as follows: ‘May all beings throughout all world systems become connected to and filled with my own happiness! May absolutely all their intentions be effortlessly fulfilled in all ways,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-29"> J, K, C:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">-thams cad kyi thams cad rnam pa</foreign>; D:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">+thams cad kyi thams cad rnam pa</foreign>. There is also the alternate reading in K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">-thams cad kyi</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> and may all their wishes without exception be fulfilled, so that they may abide in happiness! May this aspiration of mine be auspicious! May this aspiration of mine be virtuous!’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-30"/>
               <p tid="30">“Bodhisattvas make such aspirations, [F.156.b] yearning and wishing to give oceans of jewels to all beings throughout all world systems. Bodhisattvas make aspirations, yearning and wishing to give endless, immeasurable mountains of wealth, mountains of gold, mountains of clothing, mountains of all utensils, oceans of food, oceans of drink, and finely wrought abodes where one can comfortably dwell. They also delight and rejoice at least three times a day in all the acts of giving, offering, and bestowing material possessions, protection from fear, and the gifts of Dharma performed by all beings of the past, future, and present throughout all the world systems in the entirety of cyclic existence.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-31"/>
               <p tid="31">“Even if bodhisattvas are unable to give wealth to those who request it, they offer them their own share of food, provide them with assistance, or show them the means to seek what they want, and then eradicate their desire with a Dharma discourse. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-32"/>
               <p tid="32">“Should bodhisattvas even just wish to give those gifts, they dedicate this generosity to unsurpassable, perfect, and complete awakening so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may transcend suffering, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. Having offered their gift, they again dedicate this generosity to unsurpassable, perfect, and complete awakening so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may transcend suffering, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-33"/>
               <p tid="33">“Should bodhisattvas lack the capacity to train in giving, offering, and bestowing, this is how they properly train: From time to time, [F.157.a] or little by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating attachment, stinginess, and fear of giving. From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training, developing, and perfecting the acts of giving, offering, and bestowing. Even when they take another birth, they do not lose heart or become discouraged. Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve to awaken, their recollection and cultivation of the resolve to awaken, and their wishes and aspirations to awaken are themselves their immeasurable, incalculable great acts of giving, offering, and bestowing. Why is that? It is because among all acts of giving, offering, and bestowing, the foremost and supreme is the wish to give, offer, and bestow to all beings in all world systems a shower of sublime Dharma and a shower of the expanse of ambrosia. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-34"/>
               <p tid="34">“Subāhu, in this way bodhisattvas will very quickly complete the perfection of generosity, with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-35"/>
               <p tid="35">“Subāhu, bodhisattvas do not cut off limbs or other body parts when requested by beggars, nor would they offer them to beggars, even if they were cut off. Why is that? Because by that very act the beggars would fall into the severe hells and incur more<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-36"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">che ba</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">cher</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> severe non-virtuous deeds. [F.157.b] Yet it is not the case that they would not surrender their own limbs and body parts for the sake of other beings, or their benefit. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-37"/>
               <p tid="36">“Subāhu, if beggars ask bodhisattva great beings for all their possessions, bodhisattvas do not give away all their possessions in a way that harms, neglects, or causes suffering for their parents, or in a way that harms, neglects, or causes suffering for their children, wives, male and female slaves, or servants and laborers.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-38"/>
               <p tid="37">“Why is that? Bodhisattvas love all beings equally. Just as they practice generosity without harming, neglecting, or causing suffering for their parents, and without harming, neglecting, or causing suffering for their children, spouses, male and female slaves, or servants and laborers, so do they care the same for all beings. Yet, it is also not the case that they would not surrender all their possessions for the sake and benefit of other beings. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-39"/>
               <p tid="38">“Subāhu, the thus-gone ones have not praised generosity that brings harm to beings. Therefore, how could they do so regarding bodhisattvas’ cutting off of limbs?</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="39">Perfection of Ethical Discipline</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-40"/>
               <p tid="40">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattvas complete the perfection of ethical discipline? Subāhu, even at the cost of their own lives, the bodhisattvas do not beat, kill, or rejoice in the killing of other creatures and beings. Even at the cost of their own lives, they do not take what is not given, incite others to take what is not given, or rejoice in the taking of what is not given. Even at the cost of their own lives, they do not engage in sexual misconduct, incite others to engage in sexual misconduct, [F.158.a] or rejoice in sexual misconduct. Even at the cost of their own lives, they do not tell lies, incite others to tell lies, or rejoice in the telling of lies. Even at the cost of their own lives, they do not drink alcohol, incite others to drink alcohol, or rejoice in the drinking of alcohol. They practice these five moral precepts, adhering to them at length, resolutely, firmly, and without lapsing. Similarly, they endeavor to abandon, discard, and relinquish the activities of tilling fields and having others till fields; tethering beings and having others tether beings; entrapping beings and having others entrap beings; beating beings and having others beat beings; or slaughtering beings and having others slaughter beings. Thus do they practice these five moral precepts at length, resolutely, firmly, and without lapsing. They similarly abandon, discard, and relinquish divisive words, harsh speech, and idle chatter.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-41"/>
               <p tid="41">“Bodhisattvas train in the following line of thinking: ‘All creatures and all beings are just like my parents. They are just like a beloved only son. If my parents or my beloved only son were to harm me, I would not harm them back. Even if my parents or beloved only son were to strike me with their hands, clods of earth, sticks, knives, or arrows, I would not strike them back. Even if they attempted to kill me, I would not attempt to kill them back. Just as I would not harm my parents or beloved only son even if they were to harm me, I would not strike back even if all people and all beings were to strike me with their hands, clods of earth, sticks, knives, or arrows. Even if they attempted to kill me, I would not attempt to kill them back.’ Just as when one is, for example, glad and overjoyed upon seeing one’s father, mother, or only beloved son return after traveling abroad for a long time, [F.158.b] so too, Subāhu, bodhisattva great beings are pleased and overjoyed upon seeing all creatures and beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-42"/>
               <p tid="42">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of abandoning killing in order to establish all beings in the ethical discipline of abandoning killing at the level of no-more-training. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning taking what is not given in order to establish all beings in the ethical discipline of abandoning taking what not is given at the level of no-more-training. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning sexual misconduct in order to establish all beings in the ethical discipline of pure conduct at the level of no-more-training. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning lying in order to establish all beings in the ethical discipline of abandoning lying at the level of no-more-training. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning alcohol in order to establish all beings in the ethical discipline of abandoning alcohol at the level of no-more-training. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-43"/>
               <p tid="43">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of abandoning tilling fields and having others till fields so that all beings may attain undivided, vajra-like absorption. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning tethering and having others tether so that all the bonds of afflictions may be shorn from all beings. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning entrapping and having others entrap so that all beings may be prevented from and divested of the five destinies.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-44"> In this enumeration, the jealous gods are taken to be part of the god realm.</note>
                  </hi> Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of abandoning beating and inciting beatings so that all beings may attain the intrinsic nature that is not overpowered by any of the obstacles of māras and afflictive obscurations. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning cutting and having others cut so that all beings may be protected in all actions of body, speech, and mind.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-45"/>
               <p tid="44">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of abandoning divisive speech in order to obtain an undivided great saṅgha of hearer<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>attendants. [F.159.a] They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning harsh speech in order to acquire the melodiousness of Brahmā, imbued with a voice that has the five aspects of clarity. They keep the ethical discipline of abandoning idle chatter for the sake of acquiring unimpeded speech that is worthy of retaining.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-46"/>
               <p tid="45">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of sheltering those terrified by death in order to thoroughly pacify for all beings their fear of birth, aging, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and despair. They keep the ethical discipline of guarding against the squandering and destruction of others’ wealth and belongings so that all beings may obtain the unsurpassable wealth of the factors conducive to awakening.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-47"/>
               <p tid="46">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of giving up attachment to others’ spouses and enabling others to give up such attachment for the sake of obtaining the unwavering intrinsic nature. They keep the ethical discipline of giving up exerting control over others and having others exert control so that all beings may obtain mastery over their own minds. They keep the ethical discipline of untying bonds and of having others untie bonds in order to destroy all the fetters of the armies of māras and the afflictions on the throne of the Hero, the seat of awakening. Their ethical discipline of leaving the household is in order to attain a liberated, undefiled mind. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-48"/>
               <p tid="47">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of confessing<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-49"> D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’chags</foreign> (“confess”); K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tshugs</foreign>; J, C: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’chugs</foreign>; N: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ’jug</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> to striking others for the sake of uprooting fear through the four kinds of fearlessness. They keep the ethical discipline of averting quarrels<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-50"> J, C: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsod</foreign> (“quarrel”); D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gcos</foreign> (“cutting”).</note>
                  </hi> in order to obtain the four features of protection. They keep the ethical discipline of using non-deceptive speech in order to obtain the intrinsic nature that cannot be controverted by any obstacles of māras or afflictive obscurations, while on the throne of the Hero, the seat of awakening. They keep the ethical discipline of reconciling those who are divided and stabilizing relations so that there is no schism in the great saṅgha of noble hearer attendants. [F.159.b] They keep the ethical discipline of using gentle and pleasant words so that truthful speech that is melodious and pleasing may reach the ears of all beings. They keep the ethical discipline of harmonious speech so that they may receive fruitful Dharma teachings that are inviolable and worthy of retention. They keep the ethical discipline of praising the qualities of the Buddha so that they may obtain a great saṅgha entourage<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-51"> D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gyi</foreign>; N: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dang</foreign>. The reading of N would be alternately rendered as “a great saṅgha of monks and attendants.”</note>
                  </hi> endowed with the qualities of the noble ones.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-52"/>
               <p tid="48">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of prostrating three times a day to the innumerable, immeasurable buddhas, dharmas, saṅghas, and bodhisattvas of the past, present, and future throughout all world systems, touching the five points of their bodies to the ground. This is so that all beings may obtain the five sublime properties of supreme faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and insight, which are so stable that beings will be unwavering and firm on the throne of the Hero, the seat of awakening. They keep the ethical discipline of venerating all stūpas of the buddhas three times a day so that they may attain the fulfillment of all the qualities of a buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-53"/>
               <p tid="49">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of extolling the qualities of the Dharma three times a day so that the unsurpassable, non-abiding wheel of Dharma will be turned. They keep the ethical discipline of extolling the qualities of the saṅgha three times a day, in order to obtain the great entourage of an undivided saṅgha of noble ones. They keep the ethical discipline of going for refuge to the supreme Three Jewels three times a day, for the sake of giving unsurpassable refuge to all beings. They keep the ethical discipline of supplicating three times a day that all world systems may never be bereft of the Three Jewels and bodhisattvas, in order to attain perfect awakening, which is certain to be exclusively pleasant. [F.160.a] They keep the ethical discipline of supplicating three times a day that all the buddhas teach the Dharma for an eon, in order to attain the tenth bodhisattva level, the Cloud of Dharma.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-54"> Skt. Dharmamegha.</note>
                  </hi> They keep the ethical discipline of confessing, forsaking, and condemning every misdeed three times a day, in order to destroy the entire sequence of habitual tendencies. They keep the ethical discipline of taking up all roots of virtue three times a day, in order to complete all the perfections. They keep the ethical discipline of rejoicing three times a day in all the roots of virtue of the past, present, and future buddhas, solitary buddhas, noble saṅgha of hearers, bodhisattvas, and all beings in all destinies belonging to all world systems, in order to complete the infinite, immeasurable accumulations of awakening. They keep the ethical discipline of aspiring for complete awakening three times a day, in order to reach certainty in attaining perfect awakening. They keep the ethical discipline of dedicating all roots of virtue to the attainment of perfect awakening three times a day, solely in order to obtain the different kinds of power and fearlessness of the thus-gone ones. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-55"/>
               <p tid="50">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of serving<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-56">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> J, K, N, C, D:-</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yongs su spyad par byed pa’i</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">; D:+</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yongs su spyad par byed pa’i</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> their parents, teachers, elders, preceptors, and masters in order to attain the unassailable intrinsic nature. They keep the ethical discipline of comforting the frightened, the terrified, the destitute, and the defenseless, in order to become skilled in tirelessly elucidating the answers to all questions. They keep the ethical discipline of protecting and helping those who are immersed in suffering caused by kings, thieves, fire, water, or retribution, [F.160.b] in order to obtain the protection<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-57">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> N, H: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsrung </foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">(“protection”); D: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bskang</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (“fulfillment”)</hi>.</note>
                  </hi> of the great states, levels, and perfections. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-58"/>
               <p tid="51">“Bodhisattvas keep the ethical discipline of praising the miraculous feats performed by the buddhas, solitary buddhas, noble hearers, and bodhisattvas, in order to obtain the unsurpassable miraculous powers of the thus-gone ones. They keep the ethical discipline of performing bodily actions that are conducive to protecting the minds of others, bodily actions that delight and gladden others’ minds, verbal actions conducive to protecting the minds of others, and verbal actions that delight and gladden others’ minds, in order to obtain the infinite power of the thus-gone ones to know the minds of others. They keep the ethical discipline of properly engendering mindfulness of the goal of this life, other lifetimes, the hearer vehicle, the solitary buddha vehicle, and the vehicle of perfect awakening, as well as the ethical discipline of making this mindfulness arise in those who are forgetful and careless, in order to attain the unforgettable intrinsic nature. They keep the ethical discipline of listening to, retaining, cultivating, and expounding the Dharma in order to attain the discriminations and perfections.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-59"/>
               <p tid="52">“Should they even just wish to take up and practice ethical discipline, bodhisattvas dedicate all of their roots of virtue of body, speech, and mind so that all beings [F.161.a] are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. While taking up and practicing ethical discipline, and again after having done so, they dedicate it so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-60"/>
               <p tid="53">“Should they lack the capacity to train in that ethical discipline without breaching, violating, or corrupting it, this is how they properly train: From time to time, or little by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating non-virtue. From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training in, developing, and perfecting virtue. Even when they take another rebirth, they do not lose heart or become discouraged.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-61"/>
               <p tid="54">“Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve to awaken, their recollection and cultivation of the resolve to awaken, and their wishes and aspirations to awaken are themselves the bodhisattvas’ incalculable and immeasurable acts of undertaking and engaging in ethical discipline.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-62"/>
               <p tid="55">“Why is that? It is because among all the ways of undertaking and engaging in virtuous ethical discipline, foremost and supreme is the wish to engender undefiled ethical discipline and ethical discipline at the level of no-more-training, and to do so perfectly, in all beings throughout all world systems. [F.161.b]</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-63"/>
               <p tid="56">“Subāhu, in this way bodhisattvas will very quickly complete the perfection of ethical discipline, with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="57">Perfection of Patience</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-64"/>
               <p tid="58">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattvas complete the perfection of patience? Subāhu, even if others take their life, steal all their possessions, ravish their spouse, or lie, slander, speak harshly, or idly gossip about them—even if they abuse them, kill them, seize them, hit them, or cut them—bodhisattvas do not retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor animosity or resentment toward them. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-65"/>
               <p tid="59">“This is how they train: They think, ‘This is the result of the negative actions I have committed and accumulated in previous lives and in this one. This is their karmic ripening. Why should I retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor animosity or resentment, when I am experiencing the results and karmic ripening of my own actions?’ </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-66"/>
               <p tid="60">“Furthermore, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking the following: ‘Even if others were to take my life, steal all my possessions, ravish my spouse, or lie, slander, speak harshly, or idly gossip about me—even if they were to abuse me, kill me, seize me, hit me, or cut me—should I retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor animosity or resentment toward them, I will incur the further unwanted, unpleasant, and disagreeable suffering of fully ripened effects and effects similar to their cause that are more severe than this unwanted, unpleasant, and disagreeable sensation of suffering—that are a hundred times greater, or a thousand times, [F.162.a] or more.’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-67"/>
               <p tid="61">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking as follows: ‘Because I have life, my life is taken. Because I have possessions, my possessions are stolen. Because I have an ear faculty, I hear lies, slander, harsh words, and idle gossip. Because I have a body, my body is led along, fettered, seized, beaten, and cut. Since I myself have assumed the life faculty, the ear faculty, and the body that form the substance and basis of my suffering, how could I retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor hostility or enmity?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-68"/>
               <p tid="62">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking the following: ‘For example, the defining feature of the earth element is solidity. That is its identity, its character, and its nature. The defining feature of the water element is moisture. The defining feature of the fire element is heat. The defining feature of the wind element is lightness and movement. These are their identities, their characters, their natures. In the same way, all life forms have the character of exhaustion, abandonment, and extinction. Moreover, all faculties are characterized by contact with suffering and the experience of suffering. All bodies, for that matter, have the quality of suffering, the quality of contact with suffering, and the quality of the experience of suffering. That is their identity, their character, and their nature. How could I retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor hostility or enmity just because<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-69"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">pas</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">pa’i</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> the life faculty, which is characterized by exhaustion, abandonment, and extinction, is exhausted, dissolved, and extinguished, or because the six faculties, which are characterized by suffering, contact with suffering, and the experience of suffering, [F.162.b] are in contact with suffering? Why is that? It is because that is their identity, their character, and their nature.’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-70"/>
               <p tid="63">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking as follows: ‘My eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind are neither “me” nor “mine.” Others’ eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind are also neither them nor theirs. Such being the case, how could the wise, knowing the eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind to be neither them nor theirs, delight in, be attached to, or truly enjoy them? And how could they retaliate by hitting, harming, getting angry, or harboring hostility or enmity toward others?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-71"/>
               <p tid="64">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking as follows: ‘The sufferings experienced by humans are few and minor. Yet, the sufferings of anguished spirits are much more terrible and difficult to endure, while the sufferings of the animal realm and the hells are even more terrible and difficult to endure than those. Such being the case, why would I, on account of just a few minor sufferings, retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor hostility or enmity?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-72"/>
               <p tid="65">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train by thinking as follows: ‘I<hi type="wordfile-remnant">t is unreasonable and improper for someone who wishes only for their own happiness and welfare to retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor hostility or enmity. Such being the case, how much more unreasonable and improper would it be for someone who wishes for the happiness of all worlds, wishes to benefit all worlds, has donned the great armor, has taken a vow with great resolve, has entered [F.163.a] the Great Vehicle, and who wishes to perfect the vast qualities of a buddha?</hi> One will not gather, develop, or perfect the qualities of a buddha by being impatient, retaliating, getting angry in return, or harboring hostility or enmity. Rather, one will gather, develop, and perfect the qualities of a buddha through having patience, not retaliating, not getting angry in return, and not harboring hostility or enmity.’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-73"/>
               <p tid="66">“Subāhu, sons or daughters of noble family who wish to fulfill all the qualities of a buddha should not retaliate, get angry in return, or harbor hostility and enmity, even if they are subjected to the sufferings of the Hell of Endless Torment, let alone the sufferings of humans. Even if they are insulted, reviled, deprecated, or disgraced, they endure and embrace it in order to acquire the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and the immaculate, pure, and pristine awakened mind of the thus-gone ones. Even if they are dragged away, bound, and captured, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and in order to crack the shell of the obscuration of ignorance for a single instant. Even if they are beaten, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and to divest all beings of their passion and aggression. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-74"/>
               <p tid="67">“Even if their ears are cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and to engender in all beings the ear for Dharma that arouses faith. Even if their nose is cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and to enable all beings to enjoy the exquisite and unsurpassable qualities of ethical discipline. [F.163.b] Even if their legs are cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and for all beings to obtain the thus-gone ones’ four bases of miraculous power. Even if their hands are cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and for all beings to obtain the generosity of the outstretched<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-75"> 
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi>
                        <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, J, K, C: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brkyang ba</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (“extended”); D: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bkyang ba </foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">(“unattested”).</hi>
                     </note>
                  </hi> hand of the Dharma—peace and tranquility. Even if all their limbs are cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and in order to complete all the major and minor limbs of the six perfections. Even if their eyes are gouged out, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and for all beings to obtain the eternal eye of vigilance. Even if their head is cut off, they endure and embrace it for the sake of the sentiment of love, the sentiment of compassion, and for all beings to obtain the summit of Dharma—omniscience.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-76"/>
               <p tid="68">“Should they even just wish to focus upon and bring to mind these kinds of patience and acquiescence, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. While focusing upon and bringing them to mind, and again after, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-77"/>
               <p tid="69">“Should they lack the capacity to be unwavering, flawless, and uncorrupted in training in these kinds of patience and acquiescence, this is how they properly train: From time to time, or little [F.164.a] by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating their lack of patience and acquiescence. From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training, developing, and perfecting their patience and acquiescence. Even when they take another rebirth, they neither lose heart, nor get discouraged. Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve set on awakening, their recollection and cultivation of the resolve for awakening, and their wishes and aspirations for awakening are themselves the bodhisattvas’ immeasurable and incalculable virtues of practicing and truly accomplishing patience.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-78"/>
               <p tid="70">“Why is that? It is because among all the virtues of practicing and truly accomplishing patience, foremost and supreme is the wish to engender undefiled patience and patience at the level of no-more-training, and to do so perfectly, in all beings throughout all world systems.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-79"/>
               <p tid="71">“Subāhu, in this way bodhisattvas very quickly complete the perfection of patience with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="72">Perfection of Diligence</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-80"/>
               <p tid="73">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattvas complete the perfection of diligence? Subāhu, bodhisattvas properly train in this by thinking as follows: ‘In each of the ten directions, there are infinite and limitless world systems, and in each of these world systems there are infinite beings. Thus, this infinite and limitless multitude of beings has neither limit nor end. I shall don armor to benefit this infinite multitude of beings. [F.164.b] If I don armor to bring happiness to the infinite multitude of beings, then even when I am careless, distracted, or asleep, the infinite roots of virtue from the infinite goal of benefiting and bringing happiness to all beings will grow, expand, and be perfected<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-81"> D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rdzogs pa </foreign>(“perfection,” “completion”); K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtogs pa</foreign> (“realization”). </note>
                  </hi> in each and every moment of thought, throughout the day and night. Thus, since in each and every moment of thought there will arise infinite roots of virtue and infinite heaps of accumulations conducive to awakening, it will not be difficult to obtain perfect awakening. That being the case, I shall now sincerely tend to the infinite growth and expansion of these roots of virtue in each and every moment of thought. On that basis, I will ensure that perfect awakening will not be difficult to obtain. In so doing, why would I slacken my diligence, even at the cost of my own life, when it enables me to attain perfect awakening?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-82"/>
               <p tid="74">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas train properly by thinking as follows: ‘Even those who wish to eliminate and overcome only the suffering of aging on behalf of the infinite multitude of beings will have roots of virtue grow and expand in each and every moment of thought. Such being the case, how much more so will that be the case for those who wish to eliminate the infinite multitude of beings’ suffering of birth and death, their suffering of being separated from what they like and encountering what they dislike, their suffering of not acquiring what they want, the suffering of animal births and Yama’s world, and the suffering of the hells, the cold hells, and the hot hells?’ [F.165.a] </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-83"/>
               <p tid="75">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas train properly by thinking as follows: ‘Even those who wish to eliminate the infinite multitude of beings’ suffering for just a single moment of thought will have infinite roots of virtue grow and expand in each and every moment of thought. Such being the case, how much more so will that be the case for those who wish to eliminate all the suffering—from the suffering of birth up to that of becoming<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-84"> This is a reference to the twelve links of dependent origination, i.e., the first to the last (if starting with birth). This sentence has a lot of very different variants and might indicate a place of some uncertainty. K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sdug bsngal nas srid pa’i sdug bsngal gstsal</foreign>; J, C: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">skye ba’i sdug bsngal srid pa’i sdug bsngal gyi bar du bsal</foreign>; K: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">skye ba'i sdug bsngal srid pa’i sdug bsngal gyi bar dud pa'i sdug bsngal gstsal</foreign>; N: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">skye ba’i sdug bsngal nas srid pa'i sdug bsngal gyi bar du brtsal</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi>—of the infinite multitude of beings throughout the infinite and immeasurable eons that have yet to come and go?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-85"/>
               <p tid="76">“In addition, Subāhu, bodhisattvas train properly with the following thought: ‘Even those who wish for the qualities of a solitary buddha or a hearer will have roots of virtue grow and expand throughout each and every moment of thought. Such being the case, how much more so will that be the case for the sons or daughters of noble family who seek, wish, and aspire to perfect the mastery<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-86"> 
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">chub pa</hi> likely renders the Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paryavāpti</foreign> (“mastery,” “comprehension”; cf. Edgerton, p.334 ).</note>
                  </hi> of the infinite and boundless qualities and powers of a buddha? For even when they are careless or asleep, the four causes,<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>four conditions, and four aims will grow and expand in each and every moment of thought into four infinite and boundless heaps of roots of virtue and four infinite and boundless heaps of accumulations conducive to awakening. With the emergence in each and every moment of thought of the four infinite heaps of roots of virtue and the four infinite and boundless heaps of accumulations conducive to awakening it will not be difficult to attain awakening. Therefore, I shall now tend to the four infinite heaps of roots of virtue [F.165.b] and the four infinite heaps of accumulations for perfect awakening in each and every moment of thought. On that basis, I will ensure that perfect awakening will not be difficult to obtain. In so doing, why would I slacken my diligence, even at the cost of my own life, when it enables me to attain perfect awakening?</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-87"/>
               <p tid="77">“ ‘The four great oceans are evidently finite and limited in the east. They are obviously finite and limited as well in the south, west, north, nadir, and zenith. Yet, the four infinite and boundless great oceans of the accumulations of roots of virtue and factors conducive to awakening have neither end nor limit. Thus, given that I will attain perfect awakening once these four great oceans of the accumulations of roots of virtue and factors conducive to awakening have grown and expanded throughout each and every moment of thought, why would I slacken my diligence, even at the cost of my life?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-88"/>
               <p tid="78">“Furthermore, Subāhu, bodhisattvas train properly by thinking as follows: ‘If even lions, tigers, dogs, jackals, vultures, curlews, crows, owls, worms, bees, horseflies, and gadflies can perfectly and completely awaken to buddhahood, then as a human being, why should I slacken my diligence, even at the cost of my own life, when it allows me to attain perfect awakening?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-89"/>
               <p tid="79">“Moreover, Subāhu, bodhisattvas train properly by thinking as follows: ‘If even a hundred or a thousand people can realize and attain buddhahood, why should I not also realize and attain buddhahood now? Thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas equal in number to the grains of sand in the Ganges River have also realized and attained it. If thus-gone ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas equal in number to the grains of sand in the Ganges River have realized and attained it, then [F.166.a] why should I slacken my diligence, even at the cost of my life, when it allows me to attain perfect awakening?’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-90"/>
               <p tid="80">“Furthermore, Subāhu, bodhisattvas have applied diligence, whenever they constantly and perpetually listen to, ascertain, and reflect upon—as though their hair and clothes were on fire—any Dharma teaching that is reported to be a teaching by a buddha, whether it be taught by a buddha, explained by a worthy one, explained by a bodhisattva, or even explained by madmen, as well as any Dharma teaching that leads to the completion of the perfections of generosity, ethical discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and insight, and that leads to the attainment of the qualities of a buddha, and the attainment of perfect awakening and omniscience.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-91"/>
               <p tid="81">“By carefully heeding and keeping in mind the Dharma, the wise and industrious constantly and perpetually receive, master, explain, recite, contemplate, teach, and convey to others those Dharma teachings as if their own hair and clothes were on fire, even if they are turned back with spears.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-92"/>
               <p tid="82">“By carefully heeding and keeping in mind the Dharma, the wise and industrious use their own bodies as instruments in the service of all beings’ welfare and to perform any activity connected with the Dharma<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-93"> N, H:-<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos can</foreign>; D:+<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos can</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> for happiness in this and other worlds, whether they are turned back with spears, or whether they have been entrusted with this or not. Just as the four great elements, unobstructed and unbound, are like instruments in the service of all beings, likewise, Subāhu, do bodhisattvas use their own bodies as instruments in the service of all beings. For they are distinguished by venerating the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha; serving bodhisattvas, preceptors, and teachers; and attending upon [F.166.b] the elderly, sick, and defenseless. As if their hair and clothes were on fire, they attract others, inspiring faith in them by being agreeable with them through speech that brings joy to others’ hearts and minds; by acting in conformity with them; by sharing liberally with them, supporting them, and serving as their companions; and by acting in harmony with virtue. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-94"/>
               <p tid="83">“They induct, tame, and establish in the Hearer Vehicle those suited to the Hearer Vehicle. They induct, tame, and establish in the Solitary buddha Vehicle those suited to the Solitary buddha Vehicle. They induct, tame, and establish in the vehicle of perfect awakening those suited to the vehicle of perfect awakening. Even if they are turned back with spears, the wise and industrious act as if their hair and clothes were on fire, disregarding cold for the sake and purpose of the sublime Dharma, for the sake and purpose of the six perfections, and for the sake and purpose of virtue. They also disregard heat, hunger, thirst, gadflies, horseflies, wind, sun, encounters with scorpions and snakes, others’ offensive words, insulting names, leisure, misfortune, sleep, displeasure, their body, and their life. For the sake and purpose of perfect awakening, the wise and industrious, even if turned back with spears, also disregard the sufferings of gods; the sufferings of asuras, humans, and anguished spirits; and the sufferings of the animal realms and hells. The wise and industrious, even if turned back with spears, maintain firm diligence and courage in order to attain the fulfillment of the unequaled qualities of a buddha [F.167.a] and to attain the completion of all conduct and perfections. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-95"/>
               <p tid="84">“Should they even just wish to focus on and apply this diligence and courage, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. While focusing upon and applying diligence and courage, and again after having done so, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-96"/>
               <p tid="85">“Should they lack the capacity to be unwavering, flawless, and uncorrupted in training in this diligence, bodhisattvas train as follows: From time to time, or little by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating indolence and laziness. From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training, developing, and perfecting diligence and courage. Even when they take another rebirth, they become neither disheartened nor discouraged. Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve set on awakening, their recollection and cultivation of the resolve for awakening, and their wishes and aspirations for awakening are themselves the bodhisattvas’ immeasurable and incalculable virtues of diligence and exertion. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-97"/>
               <p tid="86">“Why is that? It is because among all the virtues of diligence and exertion, foremost and supreme is the wish to engender undefiled diligence and diligence at the level of no-more training, [F.167.b] and to do so perfectly, in all beings throughout all world systems. Subāhu, in this way bodhisattvas very quickly complete the perfection of diligence with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="87">
                  <lb/>Perfection of Concentration</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-98"/>
               <p tid="88">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattvas complete the perfection of concentration? Subāhu, when bodhisattvas see sights with their eyes they do not cling to their characteristics and features. They are attentive and vigilant about restraining the mind’s movements toward worldly covetousness, unhappiness, and factors connected with evil deeds and non-virtues that occur when the eye faculty is left uncontrolled by restraint. Thus, they control the eye faculty with the eye faculty. Similarly, when their ears hear sounds, their nose perceives smells, their tongue experiences tastes, their body feels contact, and their mind cognizes phenomena, they do not cling to characteristics and features. They are attentive and vigilant about restraining the mind’s movements toward worldly covetousness, unhappiness, and factors connected with evil deeds and non-virtues that occur when the mental faculty is left uncontrolled by restraint. Thus, they control the mental faculty with the mental faculty.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-99"/>
               <p tid="89">“Whether they are walking, standing, sitting, lying, or silent, bodhisattvas neither dispense with nor forsake the states of meditative equipoise and calm abiding. Whether they are in solitude or not, their behavior is uncorrupted: their hands are not restless, they do not talk nonsense, they do not speak too much, their eyes and other sense faculties are neither distracted nor agitated, they do not indulge in idle talk, and they are constant physically, verbally and mentally. [F.168.a] They are content with their amenities of food, drink, bedding, mat, dwelling place, and medicines to cure sicknesses, no matter what they are; they are easily sustained, easily satisfied, and easily served; their conduct and personal associations are virtuous, and in their personal associations they are withdrawn from society.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-100"> This phrase ( <hi type="wordfile-remnant">du ’dzi las dben pa’i spyod yul</hi>) conveys the sense of being unaffected by social affairs even when steeped in them (cf. Edgerton, p. 215). </note>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-101"/>
               <p tid="90">“Bodhisattvas remain neutral and unchanged with regard to obtaining or not obtaining things; they are neither proud nor humble. They remain neutral and unchanged with regard to happiness and suffering, praise and blame, fame and anonymity, and life and death; they are neither proud nor humble. They remain neutral and unchanged with regard to loved ones and enemies, fortune and misfortune, pleasant agreeable things and unpleasant disagreeable things, noble and ignoble things, and solitude and crowds; they are neither proud nor humble. Likewise, attractive and unattractive sights are neither agreeable nor disagreeable to bodhisattvas. Attractive and unattractive sounds, smells, tastes, tangibles, and mental phenomena are also neither agreeable nor disagreeable to them. Since objects of desire are experienced based on misconception, driven by their own mind, bodhisattvas<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="25" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-102"> Here reading K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de’i</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> think of them as skeletons. Since objects of desire are a host of enemies, they think of them as lumps of flesh.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="26" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-103"> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sha snag gu</foreign>/<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sna gu</foreign> is most likely the same as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sha snag bu</foreign>: “tumor,” or “lump of flesh” (see Negi, vol. 16: 6791 and Monier Williams: 805). Note that there are two variants: K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sha sneg </foreign>and N, H:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term"> sha sna</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> Since one suffers when indulging in desires, but is happy when forsaking them, they think of them as a brush fire.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="27" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-104"> Variant readings include K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtswa tham</foreign> (“scattered grass”) and N: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsa me</foreign> (“channel/nerve fire”).</note>
                  </hi> Since desires cause much harm, they think of them as fruits on the tips of trees. Since desires are not under control, they think of them as beggars.<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>Since one takes pleasure in desires due to momentary confusion, they think of them as dreams. Since desires are produced by the distorted perception of suffering as happiness, they think of them as leprosy. Since desires are the object of all evil behavior, [F.168.b], and cause one to fall into negative destinies and reach the brink of hell, they think of them as metal hooks. Since desires do not satiate but only increase one’s thirst, they think of them as salt water. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-105"/>
               <p tid="91">“Bodhisattvas perfect and settle into the first concentration—a state secluded from desires, secluded from any factors connected with evil deeds and non-virtues, accompanied by reflection and analysis, and imbued with the joy and pleasure born of seclusion.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-106"/>
               <p tid="92">“When they have brought about the cessation of reflection and analysis, they become inwardly serene, and therefore their mind becomes concentrated. Through this they perfect and settle into the second concentration, which is free of reflection and analysis and is imbued with the joy and pleasure born of meditative absorption.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-107"/>
               <p tid="93">“Through disenchantment with joy, they remain impartial, maintain mindfulness and introspection, and experience physical pleasure. They thus perfect and settle into the third concentration. The noble ones call such people <distinct>an impartial one dwelling on pleasure that is imbued with mindfulness</distinct>. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-108"/>
               <p tid="94">“Through also relinquishing pleasure, and having formerly relinquished pain in the past, both happiness and unhappiness vanish. Thus they perfect and settle into the fourth concentration, which is pure impartiality and mindfulness, unconnected with pleasure or pain.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="28" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-109"> This passage on the four concentrations can also be found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara Sūtra</title> and in all the long <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāpāramitā</title> sūtras, among others. </note>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-110"/>
               <p tid="95">“By bringing to mind the perception of happiness for all beings, bodhisattvas perfect and settle into immeasurable love. By bringing to mind the perception of the suffering of all beings, they perfect and settle into immeasurable compassion. By bringing to mind the perception of rejoicing for all beings, they perfect and settle into immeasurable joy. By bringing to mind neither pain nor pleasure with respect to any being, they perfect and settle into immeasurable impartiality.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-111"/>
               <p tid="96">“By bringing to mind the perception of form as coarse, and the perception of space as tranquil, bodhisattvas perfect and settle into the sphere of infinite space. [F.169.a] By bringing to mind the perception of consciousness as tranquil, they perfect and settle into the sphere of infinite consciousness. By bringing to mind the perception of absolute nothingness as tranquil, they perfect and settle into the sense sphere of absolute nothingness. By bringing to mind the perception of a state with neither perception nor non-perception as tranquil, they perfect and settle into the sphere of neither perception nor non-perception. By bringing to mind the perception of their inhalations and exhalations of shorter duration as having shorter duration and those of longer duration as having longer duration, precisely in accordance with how long their inhalations and exhalations last and endure, they perfect and settle into the mindfulness of breathing. By bringing to mind the marks of repulsiveness in the bodies of beings, they perfect and settle into the perception of repulsiveness. By bringing to mind the marks of death, they perfect and settle into the perception of death. By bringing to mind the marks of sickness and aging, they perfect and settle into the perception of their defects. By bringing to mind that the search for food and its transience are causes for disease and harm, they perfect and settle into the perception of food as disagreeable. By bringing to mind the marks of the entire world, with its households, villages, cities, and countries, as devoid of wealth and devoid of wondrous forests and delightful groves, they perfect and settle into the perception that the entire world is unpleasant.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-112"/>
               <p tid="97">“With a perception of internal physical matter, bodhisattvas bring to mind a small amount of external physical matter characterized by appealing and unappealing colors, and thereby perfect and settle into the first stage of mastery over the senses. With a perception of internal physical matter, they bring to mind an immeasurable amount of external physical matter characterized by appealing and unappealing colors, and thereby perfect and settle into the second stage of mastery over the senses. They cultivate and accomplish disintegration as the perception that, due to wind or water, even the ash of a cremated corpse does not remain, [F.169.b] and as the perception that after something has broken and disintegrated even powder and dust do not remain. Thus, with a perception that there is no internal physical matter, bodhisattvas bring to mind a minute amount of external physical matter characterized by appealing and unappealing colors, and thereby perfect and settle into the third stage of mastery over the senses. Similarly, with a perception that there is no internal physical matter, they bring to mind an immeasurable amount of external physical matter characterized by appealing and unappealing colors, and thereby perfect and settle into the fourth stage of mastery over the senses. Similarly, with a perception that there is no internal physical matter, they bring to mind an immeasurable amount of external physical matter characterized by an immeasurable and attractive blue color, and thereby perfect and settle into the fifth stage of mastery over the senses. Similarly, with a perception that there is no internal physical matter, they bring to mind an immeasurable amount of external physical matter characterized in turn by an immeasurable and attractive yellow, red, and white color, and thereby perfect and settle into the sixth, seventh, and eighth stages of mastery over the senses. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-113"/>
               <p tid="98">“Saying, ‘The earth element is limitless,’ bodhisattvas bring its characteristics to mind and thereby perfect and settle into the totality of earth. Saying, ‘Water, fire, wind, blue, yellow, red, white, space, and consciousness are limitless,’ they bring their characteristics to mind and thereby perfect and settle within the totality of water, the totality of fire, the totality of wind, the totality of blue, the totality of yellow, the totality of red, the totality of white, the totality of space, and the totality of consciousness. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-114"/>
               <p tid="99">“Upon settling into equilibrium, bodhisattvas apply their minds to focus on all roots of virtue. They apply their minds to focus on<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>great compassion, on obtaining the sublime Dharma, on ensuring that the tradition of the Three Jewels is not cut off, on the body and ornaments of the Buddha, [F.170.a] on the Brahmā-like voice of the Buddha’s speech, on previous aspirations, on ripening all beings, on purifying all the worlds, on the arrangement of the seat of awakening, on turning the wheel of Dharma, and on conquering the afflictions in all beings. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-115"/>
               <p tid="100">“When practicing concentration, they practice it free from the four objects of consciousness.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="29" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-116"> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par shes pa’i gnas bzhi</foreign> (nor brang o rgyan, vol. 1, 708) can refer to either (1) forms, (2) sensations, (3) formations, and (4) perceptions, or, alternatively, (1) consciousness, (2) sensations, (3) perceptions, and (4) formations. Given the mention of “forms” just below, it appears to be the former classification in this context. </note>
                  </hi> They practice concentration without dwelling on the element of earth, the element of water, the element of fire, the element of wind, the element of space, the element of consciousness, this world, or future worlds. In order to attain all unsurpassed states of absorption and equilibrium, they settle into concentration and delight in it. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-117"/>
               <p tid="101">“Should bodhisattvas even just wish to practice concentration and rest in equilibrium with respect to those concentrations and absorptions, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. While doing these practices, and again after doing them, they dedicate this so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may attain omniscience and perfect all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-118"/>
               <p tid="102">“Should they lack the capacity to train in those concentrations and absorptions then this is how they properly train:<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> F</hi>rom time to time, or little by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating distraction and non-absorption. [F.170.b] From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training, developing, and perfecting the practice of single-pointedly focusing their minds and resting them in equipoise. Even when they take another rebirth, they do not become disheartened or discouraged. Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve set on awakening, their recollection and cultivation of the resolve set on awakening, and their aspirations and prayers for awakening are themselves the bodhisattvas’ incalculable and immeasurable virtues of resting their minds in equipoise and focusing their minds single-pointedly.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-119"/>
               <p tid="103">“Why is that? It is because the wish to engender undefiled concentration and concentration at the level of no-more-training, and to do so perfectly, in all beings throughout all world systems, is the infinite and boundless virtue of resting one’s mind in equipoise and focusing one’s minds single-pointedly.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-120"/>
               <p tid="104">“Subāhu, in this way bodhisattvas complete the perfection of concentration, with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head tid="105">Perfection of Insight</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-121"/>
               <p tid="106">“Subāhu, how do bodhisattvas complete the perfection of insight? Subāhu, even if they are turned back with spears, they approach, rely upon, and venerate individuals who are learned, retain what they have learned, and have collected what they have learned, as well as those who understand the content, are well-spoken, are discerning, and who have reflected upon<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-122"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, J, C, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtog </foreign>(“reflect upon,” “consider”); D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtogs</foreign> (“realize,” “understand”). </note>
                  </hi> the significance of what they have learned. For the sake of learning, explanations, content, reflecting upon the significance, and venerating masters and preceptors, [F.171.a] they disregard cold, heat, hunger, thirst, gadflies, horseflies, wind, sun, encounters with scorpions and snakes, others’ offensive words and insulting names, violent, rough, or unbearable physical sensations, and even being killed. They maintain the perception that Dharma teachings are precious jewels. They observe the perception that Dharma preachers are treasuries of precious jewels. They observe the perception that listening to the Dharma is discovering something rare. They observe the perception that retaining the Dharma is as important as life. They observe the perception that amassing the qualities of Dharma is vitally important. They observe the perception that reflecting on the Dharma is an opportunity that will not be found again within a hundred lifetimes. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-123"/>
               <p tid="107">“When bodhisattvas hear those Dharma teachings, and, retaining them, study and reflect upon them, they will come to know the constituents. They will also come to know the aggregates, the sense spheres, the truths of noble beings, dependent origination, time, the vehicles, and the accumulation of virtue. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-124"/>
               <p tid="108">“How do bodhisattvas understand the constituents? The constituents are twofold, known as conditioned and unconditioned. These are the two constituents. What are conditioned and unconditioned constituents? A <distinct>conditioned constituent</distinct> is anything whatsoever that arises, remains, and ceases. An <distinct>unconditioned constituent</distinct> is anything whatsoever that does not arise, remain, or cease. Thus do they understand the conditioned and unconditioned constituents. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-125"/>
               <p tid="109">“Moreover, bodhisattvas know the three constituents: virtuous, non-virtuous, and neutral constituents. What are virtuous, non-virtuous, and neutral constituents? A <distinct>virtuous constituent</distinct> is anything whatsoever that lacks attachment or is associated with a lack of attachment, anything whatsoever that lacks anger or is associated with a lack of anger, and anything whatsoever that lacks ignorance [F.171.b] or is associated with a lack of ignorance. A <distinct>non-virtuous constituent</distinct> is anything whatsoever that has attachment or is associated with attachment, anything whatsoever that has anger or is associated with anger, and anything whatsoever that has ignorance or is associated with ignorance. <distinct>Neutrality</distinct> is anything not included within those two. Thus do bodhisattvas understand the three constituents. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-126"/>
               <p tid="110">“Moreover, bodhisattvas know the three realms. What are the three? The desire realm, the form realm, and the formless realm. What is the desire realm? The <distinct>desire realm</distinct> comprises the beings in the hells, animals, anguished spirits, asuras, humans, and the gods of the Heaven of the Four Great Kings, Heaven of the Thirty-Three, Heaven Free from Strife, Heaven of Joy, Heaven of Delighting in Emanations, and Heaven of Making Use of Others’ Emanations, as well as anyone who yearns for, is attached to, is angry at, is ignorant of, wishes for, makes aspirations for, or conditions themselves to those types of beings. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-127"/>
               <p tid="111">“What is the form realm? The <distinct>form realm</distinct> comprises the gods in the Brahmā Realm, and the gods in the heavens of the High Priests of Brahmā, Mahābrahmā, Limited Light, Limitless Light, Luminous, Limited Virtue, Limitless Virtue, Perfected Virtue, Cloudless, Increased Merit, Great Fruition, Concept-Free Beings, Unlofty, No Hardship, Sublime, Gorgeous, and Highest, as well as anyone who yearns for, is attached to, is angry at, is ignorant of, wishes for, makes aspirations for, or conditions themselves to those types of beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-128"/>
               <p tid="112">“What is the formless realm? The <distinct>formless realm</distinct> comprises the gods who move about in the Sphere of Infinite Space, the gods who move about in the Sphere of Infinite Consciousness, the gods who move about in the Sphere of Absolute Nothingness, the gods who move about in the Sphere of Neither Perception nor Non-Perception, [F.172.a] as well as anyone who yearns for, is attached to, is angry at, is ignorant of, wishes for, makes aspirations for, or conditions themselves to those types of beings. Thus do bodhisattvas know the three realms. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-129"/>
               <p tid="113">“Moreover, they know the four realms. What are the four? The four are known as the desire realm, the form realm, the formless realm, and the unconditioned realm. Thus do they know the four realms. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-130"/>
               <p tid="114">“Moreover, they know the six realms. What are the six? They are the realms of desire, malice, harm, deliverance, freedom from malice, and freedom from harm. Thus do they know the six realms. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-131"/>
               <p tid="115">“In addition to that, they know the six elements. What are the six? They are the elements of earth, water, fire, wind, space, and consciousness. They know these six elements. Among them, the earth element bears the qualities of being impermanent, unstable, and subject to change—and that which is impermanent is suffering, and that which is suffering is selfless. In the same way, the elements of water, fire, wind, space, and consciousness also bear the qualities of being impermanent, unstable, and subject to change—and that which is impermanent is suffering, and that which is suffering is selfless. Accordingly, they know the six elements as such. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-132"/>
               <p tid="116">“When bodhisattvas hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the five aggregates. These five are the aggregates of forms, sensations, perceptions, formations, and consciousness. [F.172.b] </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-133"/>
               <p tid="117">“As for forms, they are like bubbles: worthless, fragile, and fleeting. Sensations are like foam on water: worthless, fragile, and fleeting. Perceptions are like a mirage: worthless, fragile, and fleeting. Formations are like the plantain tree: worthless, fragile, and fleeting. Consciousness is like an illusion: worthless, fragile, and fleeting. Thus do bodhisattvas understand the five aggregates.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-134"/>
               <p tid="118">“When bodhisattva hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the six inner sense spheres. The six inner sense spheres are known as the inner sense spheres of the eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-135"/>
               <p tid="119">“Among them, bodhisattvas understand that the inner sense sphere of the eyes is subject to sickness, aging, and death; is empty of both ‘me’ and ‘mine’; is ablaze with the fires of desire, aversion, and ignorance; is ablaze with birth, aging, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and despair; and is ablaze with suffering.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-136"/>
               <p tid="120">“Likewise, bodhisattvas know that the inner sense spheres of the ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind are also subject to sickness, aging, and death; are empty of both ‘me’ and ‘mine’; are ablaze with the fires of desire, aversion, and ignorance; are ablaze with birth, aging, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and despair; and ablaze with suffering. Thus do they understand the six inner sense spheres.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-137"/>
               <p tid="121">“Furthermore, bodhisattvas understand the six outer sense spheres [F.173.a] as the forms cognized through the eyes, the sounds cognized through the ears, the smells cognized through the nose, the tastes cognized through the tongue, the tangibles cognized through the body, and the phenomena cognized by the mind. These six are known as the outer sense spheres. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-138"/>
               <p tid="122">“Among them, the outer sense sphere of forms cognized through<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="31" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-139"> 
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi>
                        <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, K, N, H:</hi> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gis</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">; D: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gi</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">. This reading matches with previous and later internal patterns of this text.</hi> 
                     </note>
                  </hi> the eyes is unreliable, undependable, powerless, and fragile, for it utterly lacks permanence, solidity, endurance, reality, unmistaken reality, or incontrovertible reality. All that it has is illusion, the creation of illusion, and the capacity to delude the mind. Likewise, the outer sense spheres of the sounds cognized through the ears, the smells cognized through the nose, the tastes cognized through the tongue, the tangibles cognized through the body, and the phenomena cognized by the mind are unreliable, undependable, powerless, and fragile, for they utterly lack permanence, solidity, endurance, reality, unmistaken reality, or incontrovertible reality. All that they have is illusion, the creation of illusion, and the capacity to delude the mind. Thus do bodhisattvas understand the six outer sense spheres.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-140"/>
               <p tid="123">“So, when bodhisattvas hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the four truths of noble beings. What are the four? They are the truths, according to noble beings, of suffering, the source of suffering, the cessation of suffering, and the path to the cessation of suffering. Those are known as the truths of noble beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-141"/>
               <p tid="124">“The five aggregates, six sensory elements, six inner sense spheres, [F.173.b] and six outer sense spheres are known as <distinct>suffering</distinct>. The bodhisattva regards suffering as impermanent, intolerable, sickly, tumorous, painful, sinful, selfless, and perishable by nature. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-142"/>
               <p tid="125">“The <distinct>truth of the source of suffering</distinct> 
                  <fix>of </fix>
                  <distinct>noble beings</distinct> refers to desire, aversion, delusion, and pride; fixation on the notion of ‘I’; fixation on the notion of ‘this is my self’; and fixation on self with regard to the following notions: it will emerge; it will not emerge; it will have form; it will be formless; it will have perception; it will not have perception; it will neither have perception, nor will it not have perception; the self is the aggregates; the self is separate from the aggregates; the self is in the aggregates; the aggregates are in the self; the self is the elements and sense spheres;<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="32" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-143"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, C, N, H, U: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skye mched</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skyed mched</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> the self is separate from the sense spheres; the self is in the sense spheres; the sense spheres are in the self; the self is sensation; the self is what feels; the self is a tiny material entity; the self is a tiny formless entity; the self is an infinite material entity; the self is an infinite formless entity; the self is permanent; the self is impermanent; the self is both permanent and impermanent; the self is neither permanent nor impermanent; the self is finite; the self is infinite; the self is both finite and infinite; the self is neither finite nor infinite; the self will emerge after death; the self will not emerge after death; [F.174.a] the self will and will not emerge after death; the self will neither emerge nor not emerge after death; life is the body; life and the body are separate; where does this being come from and where will it go after death?; beings are cut off from existence in that they perish and cease to exist; the doer is the experiencer; the doer and the experiencer are separate; because the self exists, what belongs to the self also exists; the self exists because what belongs to the self exists; the self is present here in this manner; the self is turning into something else; it will be the same; it will turn into something else; it will emerge here; it will emerge in that manner; it will emerge elsewhere; the self was here in the past; the self has now emerged; or the self emerged before as something else. Thus, the truth of the source of suffering of noble beings includes false views about perishable composites, egotistical pride, mental states, fixation, latent impulses of pride, arrogance, self-aggrandizement, assertions in which a self is propounded, desire, aversion, delusion, and all kinds of pride; actions of body, speech, or mind that are meritorious,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="33" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-144"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nye bar ’gro ba</foreign> probably renders Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upasarpati</foreign>, “to approach.”</note>
                  </hi> non-meritorious, or unchanging; as well as everything else included in the desire, form, or formless realms. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-145"/>
               <p tid="126">“The <distinct>truth of the cessation of suffering</distinct> 
                  <fix>of </fix>
                  <distinct>noble beings</distinct> refers to the exhaustion of desire, aversion, delusion, and pride, as well as the absence of fixation on the self and assertions in which a self is propounded. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-146"/>
               <p tid="127">“The <distinct>truth of the path to the cessation of suffering</distinct> 
                  <fix>of </fix>
                  <distinct>noble beings</distinct> is attentiveness to suffering as suffering, the source as the source, [F.174.b] cessation as cessation, and the path as the path; it is regarding conditioned phenomena as faulty and maintaining that observation; it is regarding nirvāṇa as beneficial and maintaining that observation; as well as the right view of seeing things as they are and having discernment regarding actions performed, right intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right absorption. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-147"/>
               <p tid="128">“These are the four truths of noble beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-148"/>
               <p tid="129">“When, upon analyzing and reflecting on those four truths of noble beings, bodhisattvas comprehend and cultivate<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="34" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-149"> MV: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par ’jig pa</foreign>; this likely renders the Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vibhāvanā</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> them, they regard conditioned elements as impermanent, painful, empty, and selfless. They also regard unconditioned elements as a shelter, abode, protection, and refuge; yet, they do not make manifest the uncompounded elements. Thus do they understand the four truths of noble beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-150"/>
               <p tid="130">“So, when bodhisattvas hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand dependent origination. Ignorance creates the condition for formations. Formations create the condition for consciousness. Consciousness creates the condition for name and form. Name and form create the condition for the six sense spheres. The six sense spheres create the condition for contact. Contact creates the condition for sensation. Sensation creates the condition for craving. Craving creates the condition for grasping. Clinging creates the condition for becoming. Becoming creates the condition for birth. Birth creates the condition for aging and death. This process is known as dependent origination.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-151"/>
               <p tid="131">“<distinct>Ignorance</distinct> refers to not understanding and not recognizing the four truths of noble beings and dependent origination.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-152"/>
               <p tid="132">“<distinct>Formations</distinct> refers to any action of the body, speech, and mind, no matter how minor, that is meritorious, non-meritorious, or unchanging, [F.175.a] or anything that leads to the desire, form, or formless realms.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-153"/>
               <p tid="133">“<distinct>Consciousness</distinct> is the mind or mental faculty<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="35" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-154"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, J, C, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yid</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yod</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> that arises from even the most minor formation.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-155"/>
               <p tid="134">“<distinct>Name and form</distinct> refers to both ‘name’—any sensation, perception, thought, contact, or consideration of any kind that comes from consciousness—and ‘form’—any embryonic form, miraculous form, or perceptible form of any kind that appears together with ‘name.’</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-156"/>
               <p tid="135">“The <distinct>six sense spheres</distinct> refers to the eyes, ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind that emerge from name and form. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-157"/>
               <p tid="136">“<distinct>Contact</distinct> refers to the convergence of eye, form, and eye consciousness, where the eye consciousness arises based on the eyes and form. It also refers to the convergence of the triad of mental consciousness, mind, and mental objects, where the mental consciousness arises based on the mind and mental objects, as well as the other triads inclusive of ears, nose, tongue, and body.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-158"/>
               <p tid="137">“<distinct>Sensation, which is of three types, </distinct>refers to the painful, pleasurable, and neutral sensations that arise from contact. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-159"/>
               <p tid="138">“<distinct>Craving</distinct> refers to the desire, attachment, and infatuation that arise from sensation.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-160"/>
               <p tid="139">“<distinct>Clinging</distinct> refers to the yearning, beliefs, ethical discipline, asceticism, and claims about self that arise from craving. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-161"/>
               <p tid="140">“<distinct>Becoming</distinct> refers to the forms, sensations, perceptions, formations, and consciousness that arise from clinging. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-162"/>
               <p tid="141">“<distinct>Birth</distinct> refers to the emergence, birth, and formation of whatever has come into existence. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-163"/>
               <p tid="142">“<distinct>Aging</distinct> refers to the change, decay, and degeneration of whatever has come into existence.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-164"/>
               <p tid="143">“<distinct>Death</distinct> refers to the passing away and separation of whatever has come into existence.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-165"/>
               <p tid="144">“When, upon analyzing and reflecting on dependent origination, bodhisattvas comprehend and cultivate it, they do not make assumptions. [F.175.b] They do not make assumptions about earth. They do not make the assumption that earth belongs to them. Nor do they delight in earth. They also do not make any assumption that water, fire, wind, sky, and consciousness are singular, different, visible, hearable, distinguishable, perceivable, and beyond suffering. Neither do they make assumptions about nirvāṇa, assuming that nirvāṇa is theirs, or delight in nirvāṇa.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-166"/>
               <p tid="145">“When they consider dependently arisen phenomena, they comprehend and cultivate the three gates of liberation: the emptiness, signlessness, and wishlessness of phenomena.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-167"/>
               <p tid="146">“When they consider<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>dependently arisen phenomena, they comprehend and cultivate the cessation of dependent origination as follows: the cessation of ignorance will cause the cessation of formations. The cessation of formations will cause the cessation of consciousness. The cessation of consciousness will cause the cessation of name and form. The cessation of name and form will cause the cessation of the six sense spheres. The cessation of the six sense spheres will cause the cessation of contact. The cessation of contact will cause the cessation of sensation. The cessation of sensation will cause the cessation of craving. The cessation of craving will cause the cessation of clinging. The cessation of clinging will cause the cessation of becoming. The cessation of becoming will cause the cessation of birth. The cessation of birth will cause the cessation of aging and death.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-168"/>
               <p tid="147">“Although they consider the cessation of dependent origination in that manner, they do not make manifest the cessation of dependent origination; thus do bodhisattvas understand the cessation of dependent origination.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-169"/>
               <p tid="148">“So, when bodhisattvas hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the three times. What are the three? They are the past, the future, and the present; these are known as the three times. <distinct>The past</distinct> refers to any conditioned phenomenon that has ceased. [F.176.a] <distinct>The future</distinct> refers to any conditioned phenomenon that has not yet come into existence and arisen. <distinct>The present</distinct> refers to any conditioned phenomenon that has arisen and exists currently.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-170"/>
               <p tid="149">“So, when bodhisattvas recollect the roots of their past non-virtues, they revile and condemn them, giving them up for good.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-171"/>
               <p tid="150">“They regard even the most miniscule root of their future non-virtues as coming to fruition unequivocally, and becoming something repulsive, unpleasant, and frightening; they then settle into that observation.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-172"/>
               <p tid="151">“Bodhisattvas do not provide the opportunity for their roots of non-virtue to develop presently; they control with restraint their body, speech, mind, and six senses. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-173"/>
               <p tid="152">“Bodhisattvas recollect the roots of their past virtue, their resolve set on awakening, their wishes and aspirations for the mind of awakening and, with fervent yearning, joy, and faith, they dedicate these so that all beings are ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may completely transcend suffering, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-174"/>
               <p tid="153">“With fervent yearning, joy, and faith they wish, long, and aspire that their future roots of virtue, intention set on awakening, and wishes and aspirations for awakening may also enable all beings to be ferried across, liberated, and relieved, and so that they may completely transcend suffering, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-175"/>
               <p tid="154">“So that all sentient beings may be ferried across, liberated, and relieved, [F.176.b] and so that they may attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha, bodhisattvas never ever forsake, diminish, forget, or neglect their present virtuous stream and train of thought. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-176"/>
               <p tid="155">“All past aggregates, sensory elements, and sense spheres are past, done, absent, and no longer exist. Thus, presently, they are devoid of a self and anything belonging to a self. All future aggregates, sensory elements, and sense spheres have not yet arisen, appeared, or come into existence. Thus, presently, they are devoid of a self and anything belonging to a self. All present aggregates, sensory elements, and sense spheres neither remain nor endure. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-177"/>
               <p tid="156">“Why is that? It is because the world does not remain for more than a moment. And that moment itself, whose time of arising, remaining, and ceasing are all separate, neither remains nor endures. The duration of a moment is in terms of the inner and outer aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense spheres. The inner and outer aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense spheres exist in terms of duration. The present aggregates, sensory elements, and sense spheres neither remain nor endure for even a mere moment, and that which neither remains nor endures is devoid of a self and anything belonging to a self. Moreover, the future has not arisen, appeared, or come into existence, so it is devoid of a self and anything belonging to a self. Moreover, the past is over, not arisen, and does not exist, so it is naturally devoid of a self and anything belonging to a self. Since the lack of a self and the lack of anything belonging to a self has never arisen or come into existence throughout the three times, it is inappropriate for the wise and circumspect to believe in a self, thinking, ‘This is mine,’ ‘This is me,’ or ‘This possession of mine exists.’ </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-178"/>
               <p tid="157">“Bodhisattvas maintain the perception that all existences and conditioned phenomena are devoid of self, the perception of being free of attachment toward them, [F.177.a] the perception of having discarded them, and the perception of their cessation; it is not the case, however, that cessation is made manifest. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-179"/>
               <p tid="158">“When bodhisattvas, who thus understand the three times, hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the three vehicles. What are the three? The <distinct>three vehicles</distinct> refers to the vehicle of gods, the vehicle of Brahmā, and the vehicle of the noble ones. The vehicle of gods is the first concentration, as well as the second, third, and fourth concentrations. The vehicle of Brahmā is love, as well as compassion, joy, and impartiality. The vehicle of the noble ones is the eightfold path of the noble ones: right view, right intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right absorption. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-180"/>
               <p tid="159">“Bodhisattvas sometimes cultivate the vehicle of gods and establish beings in it; sometimes they cultivate the vehicle of Brahmā and establish beings in it; and sometimes they cultivate the vehicle of noble ones and establish beings in it. And yet, they do not make manifest the liberation of the noble ones. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-181"/>
               <p tid="160">“Furthermore, they also know three further vehicles. What are the three? These three vehicles are the vehicle of hearers, the vehicle of solitary buddhas, and the great vehicle. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-182"/>
               <p tid="161">“The <distinct>vehicle of hearers</distinct> pertains to those with lesser inclinations and faculties who have not a mere moment’s interest in existence, and do not perpetuate existence, but reject it. Through seeing the advantages of attaining nirvāṇa, it is as if their hair and clothes were on fire—they acquire the strongest of intentions and efforts to comprehend and realize<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="36" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-183"> N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtogs</foreign> (“to realize”); D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtog</foreign> (“to consider”). </note>
                  </hi> the four truths of noble beings.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-184"/>
               <p tid="162">“The <distinct>vehicle of solitary buddhas</distinct> pertains to those with middling inclinations and faculties, who delight in solitude, are devoted to their own aims, strive to dwell in the concentrations and attainments, [F.177.b] are skilled in discerning dependent origination, and wish and make aspirations for their own awakening. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-185"/>
               <p tid="163">“The <distinct>great vehicle</distinct> pertains to those with especially exalted inclinations and faculties, who wish to fulfill all the qualities of a buddha and all six perfections so that all sentient beings may be ferried across, liberated, relieved, and obtain omniscience. It pertains to those who, for the benefit of the world, disregard the suffering of saṁsāra, and have much contempt for the pleasures of saṁsāra, let alone its sufferings. It pertains to those who observe superior conduct and ethical discipline, and who endeavor to chant, recite, explain, and reflect upon<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="37" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-186"> 
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi>
                        <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, N, H:- </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnams</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (plural particle); D:+</hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnams</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> the sūtras about the vehicle of perfect awakening. It also pertains to bodhisattva great beings who are virtuous spiritual friends, train in the four kinds of blessing—truth, generosity, tranquility, and insight—and hear, receive, memorize, and enjoy analyzing all objects of knowledge. It pertains to those who wish to authentically cultivate all absorptions and attainments, who disregard their own welfare and strive for the welfare of the world, and who wish to establish, and delight in establishing, all beings in the three vehicles in accordance with their capacity. It also pertains to those who themselves firmly adhere to the vehicle of awakening, and with steadfast, unshakable, and vajra-like minds, continuously wish and make aspirations for awakening. This is how bodhisattvas understand the three vehicles. [F.178.a] </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-187"/>
               <p tid="164">“When bodhisattvas hear those teachings and, retaining them, study and consider them, they come to understand the virtuous method: prostrating to the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha. They do so by observing as follows: ‘I prostrate to all the past, future, and present buddhas, dharmas, and saṅghas throughout all the world systems.’ When performing a single prostration, they form the intention of awakening, imagining that they prostrate boundlessly and immeasurably. When aspiring for awakening, they dedicate it so that all beings may be ferried across, liberated, relieved, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. Similarly, when going for refuge they also form the intention of awakening. When performing any activity—walking, standing, sitting, sleeping, washing, eating, drinking, plowing the fields, or planting seeds—they form and cultivate the mind of awakening through making aspirations for awakening boundlessly and immeasurably. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-188"/>
               <p tid="165">“When practicing meditative equipoise and concentration, they also form and cultivate the mind of awakening by making aspirations for awakening, boundlessly and immeasurably, that all beings may be ferried across, liberated, relieved, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-189"/>
               <p tid="166">“They arouse and cultivate the mind of awakening by making aspirations to completely perfect all the qualities of a buddha—an omniscient one who is supreme throughout the whole world, a tamer of all beings, a peerless one, an incomparable one, a reliever of the whole world, a liberator of the whole world, a [F.178.b] truly complete buddha. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-190"/>
               <p tid="167">“Whatever virtue bodhisattvas perform, they dedicate it so that all beings will be free of fear, their chain of bad destinies will be severed, their sufferings and afflictions will be utterly pacified, and they will attain nirvāṇa.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-191"/>
               <p tid="168">“They dedicate it so that those belonging to the vehicle of hearers now and in the future will complete the hearer vehicle. They dedicate it so that those belonging to the vehicle of solitary buddhas now and in the future will complete the solitary buddha vehicle. They dedicate it so that those belonging to the vehicle of bodhisattvas now and in the future will complete the bodhisattva vehicle. They dedicate it so that past, future, and present thus-gone ones throughout all world systems will remain for an eon, teach the Dharma for an eon, and their saṅghas will be harmonious for an eon.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-192"/>
               <p tid="169">“Bodhisattvas also understand that establishing beings on the path of the higher realms, the path of hearers, the path of solitary buddhas, or the path of perfect awakening; or conforming with beings through generosity, pleasant speech, meaningful conduct, or practicing what they preach; or anything else, for that matter, as appropriate, can truly give rise to virtuous factors and become roots of virtue and the like.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-193"/>
               <p tid="170">“Bodhisattvas think, ‘I will perform these Dharma verses three times daily.’ The verses are as follows: [F.179.a]</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-194"/>
               <p tid="171">“Wherever<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="comment_to_markup_editor" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-195">FOR MARKUP: I tried to format this verse section, but when I tried to replace paragraph breaks with line breaks, it broke up the text all across the page. I tried it both before and after tagging with the Verse style, but the same thing happened. So, I’m commending it to your capable hands. </note>
                  </hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="38" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-196"> 
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi>
                        <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, K: </hi>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gang ’gro</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">; D: </hi> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gan ’gro</foreign>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">; N: </hi> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ngan ’gro</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> I wander, I bow my head infinite times</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-197"/>
               <p tid="172">To the perfect buddhas, dharmas, saṅghas,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-198"/>
               <p tid="173">And bodhisattvas dwelling</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-199"/>
               <p tid="174">Throughout every world system.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-200"/>
               <p tid="175">“I reverentially go for refuge infinite times </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-201"/>
               <p tid="176">To all those whose qualities are unequaled among beings, </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-202"/>
               <p tid="177">To the sources of incomparable qualities,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-203"/>
               <p tid="178">And to those possessing immeasurable qualities. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-204"/>
               <p tid="179">“I make infinite supplications</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-205"/>
               <p tid="180">That no world system whatsoever,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-206"/>
               <p tid="181">Even rarely, be bereft</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-207"/>
               <p tid="182">Of the Buddha, Dharma, Saṅgha, and bodhisattvas!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-208"/>
               <p tid="183">“I reverentially make infinite supplications</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-209"/>
               <p tid="184">To the blissful ones throughout all the world systems,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-210"/>
               <p tid="185">So that they remain for every eon</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-211"/>
               <p tid="186">Teaching the tranquil Dharma!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-212"/>
               <p tid="187">“I condemn</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-213"/>
               <p tid="188">And abandon all evil deeds—</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-214"/>
               <p tid="189">Each and every negative deed I have ever committed</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-215"/>
               <p tid="190">In the past and present, however momentary!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-216"/>
               <p tid="191">“I will wholly embrace virtue,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-217"/>
               <p tid="192">However momentary.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-218"/>
               <p tid="193">In this life, for as long as I shall live,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-219"/>
               <p tid="194">May I abide by all virtues! </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-220"/>
               <p tid="195">“May all the virtues </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-221"/>
               <p tid="196">Of the buddhas and bodhisattvas,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-222"/>
               <p tid="197">Past, present, and yet to come to this world,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-223"/>
               <p tid="198">Who turn the wheel of the Dharma of awakening,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-224"/>
               <p tid="199">As well as the ethical discipline, insight, absorption,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-225"/>
               <p tid="200">Liberation, life, and qualities</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-226"/>
               <p tid="201">Of all the victorious and noble ones,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-227"/>
               <p tid="202">Bring benefit to all world systems!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-228"/>
               <p tid="203">“I repeatedly and reverentially rejoice, infinite times, </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-229"/>
               <p tid="204">In the virtues </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-230"/>
               <p tid="205">Of all beings of the five destinies, </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-231"/>
               <p tid="206">Past, present, and yet to come!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-232"/>
               <p tid="207">“I make infinite aspirations</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-233"/>
               <p tid="208">That each and every being without exception,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-234"/>
               <p tid="209">Myself included, [F.179.b] may have all those </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-235"/>
               <p tid="210">Authentic qualities and infinite virtues!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-236"/>
               <p tid="211">“Through all my virtue</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-237"/>
               <p tid="212">From the past, present, and future,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-238"/>
               <p tid="213">May the Three Jewels always appear</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-239"/>
               <p tid="214">In every world system!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-240"/>
               <p tid="215">“May we not be bereft for eons</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-241"/>
               <p tid="216">Of the Three Jewels’ and bodhisattvas’ presence!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-242"/>
               <p tid="217">May we complete awakening</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-243"/>
               <p tid="218">And the perfections without hindrance!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-244"/>
               <p tid="219">“May beings have every happiness,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-245"/>
               <p tid="220">Be without fear, transcend the lower realms,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-246"/>
               <p tid="221">Be free from all non-virtues,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-247"/>
               <p tid="222">And perfect all roots of virtue!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-248"/>
               <p tid="223">“May they fulfill their aspiration prayers</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-249"/>
               <p tid="224">According to all of the three vehicles!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-250"/>
               <p tid="225">May they have long life, liberation,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-251"/>
               <p tid="226">And fulfill their extraordinary purpose!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-252"/>
               <p tid="227">“When making aspirations for complete awakening,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-253"/>
               <p tid="228">May they be cast infinitely and immeasurably!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-254"/>
               <p tid="229">May the suffering and afflictions</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-255"/>
               <p tid="230">Of all beings be utterly quelled!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-256"/>
               <p tid="231">“I offer my own body with conviction </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-257"/>
               <p tid="232">To all victorious ones and bodhisattvas</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-258"/>
               <p tid="233">Of each and every world system</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-259"/>
               <p tid="234">For use in actions whose purpose is Dharma!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-260"/>
               <p tid="235">“I will make infinite aspirations</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-261"/>
               <p tid="236">That in the future, until attaining<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="39" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-262"> K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, N, H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’gyur bar</foreign>; D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gyur par</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> perfect awakening,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-263"/>
               <p tid="237">I may serve the Three Jewels</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-264"/>
               <p tid="238">In each and every lifetime!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-265"/>
               <p tid="239">“May I worship the Three Jewels and bodhisattvas</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-266"/>
               <p tid="240">Of each and every world system</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-267"/>
               <p tid="241">With sublime, divine perfume, garlands, and bouquets of flowers</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-268"/>
               <p tid="242">Equal to the reaches of the sky! </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-269"/>
               <p tid="243">“May I give them heaps of silver and gold,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-270"/>
               <p tid="244">Clothing and precious substances,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-271"/>
               <p tid="245">Infinite chariots with steeds,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="40" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-272"> C, H, U: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bzhon</foreign> (“mount,” “steed”); D: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon</foreign> (“youth”).</note>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-273"/>
               <p tid="246">And infinite bedding and food, equal to the reaches of Mount Sumeru!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-274"/>
               <p tid="247">“May I be like a sanctuary, a foundation,<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                     <note place="end" index="41" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-275"> Here, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lus</foreign> most likely translates <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āśraya</foreign>.</note>
                  </hi> and a parent to beings,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-276"/>
               <p tid="248">Fulfilling their wishes through the path!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-277"/>
               <p tid="249">May I delight in patience, be pure in ethical discipline,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-278"/>
               <p tid="250">And teach the Dharma to beings!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-279"/>
               <p tid="251">“May I discover the sublime vehicle of awakening [F.180.a]</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-280"/>
               <p tid="252">And don sturdy armor for the sake of the Three Jewels!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-281"/>
               <p tid="253">May I complete the perfections</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-282"/>
               <p tid="254">And the qualities of a buddha!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-283"/>
               <p tid="255">“May I be free of all evil deeds</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-284"/>
               <p tid="256">And may my activities of body, speech, and mind be supremely virtuous!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-285"/>
               <p tid="257">May I not regress from awakening!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-286"/>
               <p tid="258">May I delight in awakening and become a bodhisattva!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-287"/>
               <p tid="259">“I will train in all the virtues of the buddhas and bodhisattvas,</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-288"/>
               <p tid="260">In each and every existence!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-289"/>
               <p tid="261">And I will also orient all worlds </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-290"/>
               <p tid="262">Toward all of those qualities!</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-291"/>
               <p tid="263">“Thus do bodhisattvas understand the accumulation of their own and others’ roots of virtue.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-292"/>
               <p tid="264">“Should bodhisattvas so much as wish to turn toward and bring to mind that insight and wisdom, they dedicate this so that all beings may be ferried across, liberated, relieved, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha. While turning toward it and bringing it to mind, as well as after having done so, they dedicate this so that all beings may be ferried across, liberated, relieved, attain omniscience, and perfect all the qualities of a buddha.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-293"/>
               <p tid="265">“Should bodhisattvas lack the capacity to train in that insight and wisdom, then this is how they properly train: From time to time, or little by little, they strive and exert themselves in abandoning, forsaking, and eliminating misunderstanding and ignorance. From time to time, or little by little, they also strive and exert themselves in training in, developing, and perfecting insight and wisdom. Even when they take another rebirth, they do not become disheartened or discouraged. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-294"/>
               <p tid="266">“Subāhu, bodhisattvas’ formation of the resolve set on awakening [F.180.b], their recollection and cultivation of the resolve for awakening, and their aspiration and prayers for awakening are themselves the immeasurable, incalculable virtues of insight and wisdom.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-295"/>
               <p tid="267">“Why is that? It is because among all the virtues of insight and wisdom, foremost and supreme is the wish to engender undefiled insight and wisdom at the level of no-more-training, and to do so perfectly, in all beings throughout all world systems.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-296"/>
               <p tid="268">“Subāhu, thus do bodhisattvas quickly complete the perfection of insight with ease and pleasure, little difficulty, and little pain. Bodhisattvas who complete all the perfections will quickly and perfectly awaken to unsurpassable, perfect, and complete awakening.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-297"/>
               <p tid="269">“When this Dharma discourse is taught, the goals of the three vehicles and birth in the higher realms are accomplished for all the countless and unfathomable divine and human beings.”</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-298"/>
               <p tid="270">After the Blessed One had thus spoken, the bodhisattva great being Subāhu, the other bodhisattvas, the great hearers, and the world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-299"/>
               <p tid="271">Thus concludes “The Inquiry of Subāhu,” the twenty-sixth chapter among the hundred thousand-chapter Dharma discourse of the Noble Ratnakūṭa.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="colophon">
               <head tid="272">Colophon</head>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-043-007-300"/>
               <p tid="273">This was translated, edited, and finalized, based on revisions done according to the language reform, by the Indian preceptors Dānaśīla and Jinamitra, and the chief editor-translator venerable Yeshé Dé.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="notes">
            <head type="notes" tid="274">Notes</head>
            <list type="abbreviations">
               <head tid="275">Abbreviations</head>
               <fix/>
               <!-- In this section, markup editors need to move the expanded form of the
                            abbreviation out of the "abbr" element and put it into the "expan" element. Delete
                           this comment and the "fix" tag when you are done. If there are no abbreviations in 
                            this text, then delete this entire "list" element, but leave the "div" and "head"
                            entitled "notes"-->
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-301">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Siglum Name in Pedurma</hi>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-302">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">C</hi> Choné PK <fix>co</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-303">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">D</hi> Degé PK</abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-304">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">H</hi> Lhasa (zhol) PK <fix>zhol</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-305">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">J</hi> ’jang sa tham / Lithang PK <fix>li</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-306">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi> Peking Kangxi 1684/92 PK <fix>pe</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-307">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">K</hi>
                     <hi rend="subscript">Y</hi> Peking Yongle PK <fix>g.yung</fix> 
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-308">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">N</hi> Narthang PK <fix>snar</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-309">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">S</hi> Stok Palace MsK</abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
               <item xml:id="UT22084-043-007-310">
                  <abbr>
                     <hi type="wordfile-remnant">U</hi> Urga PK <fix>khu</fix>
                  </abbr>
                  <expan/>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="listBibl">
            <head type="listBibl" tid="276">Bibliography</head>
            <div type="section">
               <head tid="277">Primary sources:</head>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-311">
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-subāhuparipṛcchā-nāma-mahāyānasūtra</title>). Toh 70. Degé Kangyur vol. 43 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 154a.1–180b.7.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-312"> 
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-subāhuparipṛcchā-nāma-mahāyānasūtra</title>). Toh 70. stog pho brang bris ma dka’ ’gyur vol. 39 (dkon brtsegs, ca), folios 275a.1–314b.2. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-313">
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa shes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-</title>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-314">
                  <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">subāhuparipṛcchā-nāma-mahāyānasūtra</title>). (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 43, pp. 433–510.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-315">
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa lag bzangs kyis zhus pa’i mdo las byung ba’i smon lam</title>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, Toh 4381, </hi>Degé Tengyur, vol. 207, <hi type="wordfile-remnant">(sna tshogs, nyo), folios 310a5–310b2.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head tid="278">Secondary sources:</head>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-316">Boucher, Daniel. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattvas of the Forest and the Formation of the Mahāyāna: A Study and Translation of the Rāṣṭrapālaparipṛcchā-sūtra</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press, 2008. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-317">Dotson, Brandon. “’Emperor’ Mu rug btsan and the <fix>’Phang thang ma Catalogue</fix>.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of Tibetan Studies</title>, no. 3 (December 2007): 1–25.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-318">Edgerton, Franklin. <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary</hi>. 2 vols. New Haven: Yale University Press,1953.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-319">Halkias, Georgios. “Tibetan Buddhism Registered: A Catalogue from the Imperial Court of ’Phang Thang.” <title xml:lang="en">The Eastern Buddhist</title> 36 (2004): 46–105. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-320">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <fix>Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten</fix> 
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-321">
                  <fix>buddhistischen Texte. </fix>Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-322">Monier-Williams, M. <hi type="wordfile-remnant">A Sanskrit-English Dictionary</hi>. Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1899</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-323">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press, 2003. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-324">Negi, J.S., ed.<hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Tibetan Sanskrit Dictionary</hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> </hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">(</hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Bod skad dang legs sbyar gyi tshig mdzod chen mo</hi>
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">)</hi>. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-325">16 vols. Sarnath: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies, 1993–2005.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-326">Scherrer-Schaub, Cristina. “Enacting Words. A Diplomatic Analysis of the Imperial Decrees (<hi type="wordfile-remnant">bkas </hi>
               </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-327">
                  <hi type="wordfile-remnant">bcad</hi>) and their Application in the Sgra sbyor bam po gñis pa Tradition.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 25, nos. 1–2 (2002): 263–340.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-328">Schopen, Gregory. <title xml:lang="en">Figments and Fragments of Mahayana Buddhism in India: More Collected Papers</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press, 2005.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-329">Silk, Jonathan. “The Origins and Early History of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāratnakūṭa </title>Tradition of Mahāyāna Buddhism with a Study of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnarāśisūtra </title>and Related Materials.” PhD diss., University of Michigan, 1994. </bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-043-007-330">Trainor, Kevin. <title xml:lang="en">Relics, Ritual and Representation</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1997.</bibl>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>