<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pas zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Question of Maitreya”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­maitreya­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-16">
                    Translated by Karen Liljenberg<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000:
                    Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-115">Dr. Karen Liljenberg</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-116">Dr. Ulrich Pagel</consultant>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.02 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-044-005"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh85" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 85</ref>, <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 104.b–116.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra </author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <location count-pages="25">
                        <start volume="44" page="210"/>
                        <end volume="44" page="234"/>
                        
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11630" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-08T00:18:32.601Z" user="laura">08/03/2019 00:18:32</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="127">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>, the bodhisattva Maitreya asks the Buddha what
                    qualities a bodhisattva needs to attain enlightenment quickly. The Buddha outlines several sets of qualities,
                    foremost among them the altruistic intention of perfect bodhicitta. The Buddha then recounts to Ānanda how, in
                    a former life, Maitreya revered a previous Buddha and, wishing to become just like him, at once realized that
                    all phenomena are unproduced. Ānanda asks why Maitreya did not become a buddha sooner, and in answer the
                    Buddha compares Maitreya’s bodhisattva career with his own, listing further sets of qualities that
                    differentiate them and recounting examples of the hardships he himself faced in previous lives. Maitreya, on
                    the other hand, has followed the easy bodhisattva vehicle using its skillful means, such as the seven branch
                    practice and the training in the six perfections; the aspirations he thus made are set out in the famous
                    “Prayer of Maitreya” for which this sūtra is perhaps best known. The Buddha declares that Maitreya will become
                    enlightened when sentient beings have fewer negative emotions, in contrast to the ignorant and turbulent
                    beings he himself vowed to help. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="128">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This sūtra was translated by Dr. Karen Liljenberg, with Dr. Ulrich Pagel acting as consultant. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="129">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā</title>),<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-200"> In D this
                            title, included within the text, is preceded by this introductory sentence: “From <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Dharma Discourse, the Great Heap of Jewels</title> in one hundred thousand sections, section 41: ‘The Noble Elucidation of the Question of Maitreya’ in one fascicle” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen
                                po’i chos kyi rnam grangs le’u stong phrag brgya pa las le’u bzhi bcu rtsa gcig pa ste / ’phags pa
                                byams pas zhus pa lung bstan pa / bam po gcig pa</foreign>).</note> like most of the sūtras that
                        comprise the Ratnakūṭa collection, was translated into Tibetan from a
                        Sanskrit original that is now lost, but that may have dated back as far as the first or second centuries <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>,
                        i.e., several centuries before the collection itself was compiled. Apart from the Tibetan Kangyur version,
                        translated in the ninth century, and a fragment in Sanskrit found in Central Asia,<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-201">A fragment of the Stein collection, published in 1911 by Louis
                            de La Vallée Poussin, was identified as part of this sūtra (corresponding to D, F.108.b–110.a) by
                            Hisashi Matsumura in 1993 (see bibliography).</note> the sūtra is extant only in an earlier Chinese
                        translation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Both the work translated here and the work that follows it in the collection, <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>,<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-202">They are sūtra numbers 41 and 42 in the Tibetan version of the Ratnakūṭa collection, but are numbered 85 and 86 respectively in the
                            Tōhoku catalogue of the Degé Kangyur as a whole.</note> focus on the important figure of the
                        bodhisattva Maitreya, who is generally accepted as destined to be the future Buddha of this
                        world-system.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">In <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>, the Buddha predicts that Maitreya will
                        attain enlightenment due to having applied the skillful means of the Bodhisattva Vehicle (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhisattvayāna</foreign>), a synonym for the Mahāyāna. This vehicle,
                        its entry, and its path are described as “easy,” in contrast to the difficulties encountered by the Buddha
                        himself. His hardship is detailed in a passage that is unusual for its portrayal of the harsh rejection of
                        the Buddha and his teachings by some of his contemporaries.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtra’s stories of the Buddha’s great sacrifices in three of his former lives derive from
                        earlier Jātaka literature. Although influential to some extent in forming the ideal of the bodhisattva,
                        such supreme heroic acts were doubtless too daunting for most people. The reader is led to infer that by
                        following the example of Maitreya future bodhisattvas will be able to attain enlightenment with relative
                        ease. Thus, the sūtra implicitly promotes the Mahāyāna, without devaluing earlier Buddhist traditions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">The sūtra is probably best known for an aspiration prayer in verse that, the Buddha tells Ānanda,
                        was used by Maitreya six times daily as he was training on the bodhisattva path (F.114.a–F.115.a, see
                        milestones <ptr target="#UT22084-044-005-77"/><!-- 1.67-->–<ptr target="#UT22084-044-005-100"/><!--1.90-->). This prayer is widely known as <title xml:lang="en">The Prayer of Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam</title>) or <title xml:lang="en">The Sovereign Prayer of
                            Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­praṇidhana­rāja</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam gyi rgyal po</title>); at least in Tibetan Buddhism, its importance as a general
                        Mahāyāna aspiration prayer is perhaps second only to Samantabhadra’s <title xml:lang="en">Prayer of Good
                            Action</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang spyod smon lam</title>, from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍavyūhasūtra</title>), and it is recited daily in many monasteries. The verses
                        are also found as an independent text (but with this sūtra mentioned in the colophon as their source) both
                        in the Dhāraṇī section of the Kangyur (Toh 1096), and in the Tengyur (Toh 4378). Although no Indian
                        commentaries on this prayer are known, it seems to have been recognized as a distinct feature of the sūtra
                        at least as far back as the early translation period, as evidenced by the sūtra’s description in the
                        Phangthangma catalogue (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>) as “the longer <title xml:lang="en">Noble [Sūtra] of the Question of Maitreya</title> containing the aspiration” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa chen po smon lam can</title>). It is also, presumably,
                        the “Former Prayer that is Truly Noble” that the Buddha gives Ānanda as an alternative title for the sūtra
                        (see 1.95). The prayer is the topic of several commentaries in the Tibetan literature, notably those of
                        Shākya Chokden (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA kya mchog ldan</foreign>, 1428-1507); Drukpa Padma Karpo
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’brug pa pad ma dkar po</foreign>, 1527-1592); Tāranātha (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tA ra nA tha</foreign>, 1575-1634), who adds comments on the significance of the
                        whole sūtra; Choné Trakpa Shedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne grags pa bshad sgrub</foreign>,
                        1675-1748); Ngulchu Dharmabhadra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngul chu dhar ma bha dra</foreign>,
                        1772-1851); and Kyedor Khenpo Ngawang Khedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kye rdor mkhan po ngag dbang
                            mkhas grub</foreign>, 1779-1838).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">It is difficult to determine the precise historical relationship of <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Question of Maitreya</title> with the much shorter sūtra that follows it, <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> (Toh 86). Their themes are closely linked—in both,
                        Maitreya questions the Buddha about the bodhisattvas’ qualities. However, their geographic settings
                            differ: <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title> is delivered in a relatively obscure
                        location, Mount Śuśumāra in the country of the Bhargas, while <title xml:lang="en">The Question of
                            Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> is set on Vulture Peak Mountain near Rājagṛha, like many other
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title> sūtras. The two texts also have different colophons. The
                        translation of the longer sūtra is attributed to Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi, under the editorial
                        supervision of Yeshé Dé, which would date its Tibetan translation to the early ninth century. <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>, however, is said to have been
                        translated by Jinamitra and Danaśila, while Yeshé Dé is said to have corrected it using the revised
                        terminology (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skad gsar</foreign>). This may imply a slightly later
                        date for this translation, but could also indicate the existence of an earlier Tibetan translation of
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> which required updating
                        in its terminology.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">Other sūtras in which previous lives of Maitreya are recounted include the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharma­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113),<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-203">See Roberts and Bower (forthcoming).</note>
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­praṣṭhāna</title> (Toh 198),<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-204">See Dharmachakra Translation Committee (forthcoming).</note> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suvarṇaprabhāsa</title> (Toh 556-7). The story of his obtaining the prophecy of his
                        future buddhahood (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyākaraṇa</foreign>) at the time of the Buddha
                        Ratnaśikhin is told in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinaya</title> (in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>,<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-205">See
                            Yao (forthcoming).</note> the sixth chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh
                        1)—the same account being found in the non-canonical <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>
                        collection—and in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­vyākaraṇa</title>, a text found in several
                        Sanskrit manuscripts, in a Chinese translation, and in a Tibetan version in the Peking (P 1011) and
                        Narthang Kangyurs, but not included in the Degé Kangyur.</p>
                    <p tid="11">These two sūtras in the Ratnakūṭa, which are both often simply called <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Question of Maitreya</title>, are not to be confused with a third sūtra of the same name in the
                        General Sūtra (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>) section, Toh 149, a short work also set in
                        Rajagṛha in which Maitreya asks a quite different question.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">The main Tibetan text used for the present translation was the Degé edition of the Kangyur. Other
                        Tibetan editions were also consulted but no significant variations were found except for the single one
                        noted. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="130">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="131">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="132">The Question of Maitreya</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">
                        <ref cRef="F.104.b"/> Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was staying in the Country of the Bhargas, on Mount
                        Śuśumāra in a fearsome forest of wild animals, together with a great saṅgha of about 500 monks, eminent
                        śrāvaka-elders who possessed clairvoyance. These included the omniscient venerable Kauṇḍinya, and the
                        venerables Aśvajit, Vaṣpa, Mahānāman, Bhadrika, Vimala, Pūrṇa, Gavāṃpati, Mṛgaśiras, Uruvilva Kāśyapa,
                        Nadīkāśyapa, Gayākāśyapa, Jaṅghā Kāśyapa, Mahākāśyapa, Amogharāja, Sumati, Śāriputra, the eminent
                        Maudgalyāyana, Parvatarāja, Nanda, Upananda, Ānanda, Rāhula, and so on. <ref cRef="F.105.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">Maitreya and 10,000 other bodhisattva mahāsattvas endowed with clairvoyance had also assembled
                        there. These included the bodhisattvas Vardhamāna­mati, Sumati, Sthiramati, Viśālamati, Pratibhāna­kūṭa,
                        Avalokiteśvara, Mahā­sthāma­prāpta, Kusumaśrī, Mañjuśrī, Abhi­jñā­puṣpa­supari­pūrṇa,
                        An­upalambha­manasi­kāra, Prasādavat, Ratnaketu, Indradeva, Varuṇadeva,<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-206">This inclusion of Indradeva and Varuṇadeva, Vedic deities, among the
                            assembly of attendant bodhisattvas is unusual. It is, however, paralleled in another Ratnakuṭa sūtra,
                            the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathā­gata­cintya­guhya­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 47).</note> Mṛdusvara,
                        Kṣetra­viśodhana, Merukūṭa, Prati­bhāna­saṃpad, Indraśrī, Nimiṃdhara, Scourer of the Hell-Dwellers,
                        Abandoner of Unfavorable Rebirths, Ratnakesarin, and others. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">The Blessed One, surrounded by this retinue of many hundreds of thousands, surveyed those before
                        him, and taught the Dharma. At that time, the bodhisattva Maitreya was present in that very retinue. He
                        surveyed the great assembly of bodhisattvas, rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder,
                        set his right knee on the ground, and paid homage with palms joined toward the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">He asked the Blessed One, “Would the Blessed One, if he has time, please answer a certain question
                        that I would like to put to the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the completely and perfectly enlightened Buddha?” </p>
                    <p tid="18">The Blessed One then replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya, <ref cRef="F.105.b"/> the Tathāgata always has time to answer such questions. Ask whatever you wish,
                        Maitreya. What I shall say in response to your question will cause you to rejoice.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-16"/>
                    <p tid="19">So the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, how many qualities
                        do bodhisattvas need to possess in order to abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of
                        sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha?” </p>
                    <p tid="20">The Blessed One answered the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya, you have served the
                        victorious ones of the past, cultivated the roots of virtue, recalled your past lives, acquired eloquence,
                        and for a long time, lived chastely. Maitreya, you work for the benefit of many people, bring happiness to
                        many people, and are compassionate toward the world. You live to bring welfare, benefit, and well-being to
                        ordinary beings, gods, and men, and to assist the noble sons and daughters, present and future, who belong
                        to the vehicle of the bodhisattvas. It is indeed good that you have thought of asking the Blessed One a
                        question on this subject. Therefore, Maitreya, listen well and carefully, and retain all that I say in
                        your mind.” </p>
                    <p tid="21">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya assented to the Blessed One, and listened as the Blessed One
                        had instructed. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-17"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Blessed One said, “Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess one single quality, they will abandon
                        all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme,
                        perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. What is that single quality? Having the altruistic intention
                            <ref cRef="F.106.a"/> of excellent bodhicitta. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess this single
                        quality, they will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but
                        swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-18"/>
                    <p tid="23">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess two qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What two qualities? Thoroughly applying themselves in calm abiding and
                        developing skill in insight. If bodhisattvas possess these two qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-19"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess three qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What three qualities? Attaining great compassion and having definitive
                        understanding of the teaching of emptiness, yet without being arrogant. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas
                        possess these three qualities, they will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of
                        sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-20"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess four qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What four qualities? Observing moral conduct, having no doubt about the
                        whole of the Dharma, delighting in seclusion, and not wavering from the undertaking to which they have
                        committed themselves. <ref cRef="F.106.b"/> Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these four qualities, they
                        will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-21"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess five qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What five qualities? Dwelling in emptiness, not seeking the delusions
                        of others, investigating the self, delighting in the Dharma, and being committed to helping others.
                        Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these five qualities, they will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall
                        into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a
                        buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-22"/>
                    <p tid="27">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess six qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What six qualities? Being without attachment, aversion, and ignorance;
                        immediately answering questions correctly and properly; being tireless in their ritual observance; and
                        experiencing emptiness. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these six qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-23"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess seven qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What seven qualities? Being learned in mindfulness and <ref cRef="F.107.a"/> in the Dharma. Being diligent in their undertakings, joyful, mentally supple, and
                        skilled in meditative concentration and analysis through wisdom. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess
                        these seven qualities, they will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful
                        associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-24"/>
                    <p tid="29">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess eight qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What eight qualities? Possessing right view, right thought, right
                        speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right concentration.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-207">These eight, of course, comprise the noble
                            eightfold path.</note> Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these eight qualities, they will abandon all
                        evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-25"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess nine qualities, they will abandon all evil
                        rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. What nine qualities? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-26"/>
                    <p tid="31">“Maitreya, those bodhisattvas distance themselves from desires and from sinful, non-virtuous things.
                        They investigate, examine, and possess the joy and happiness that arise from solitude. Thus, they                        accomplish the first meditative absorption and maintain it.<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-208">This section outlines the system of the eight meditative absorptions
                            (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">jhāna</foreign>), which are progressively deeper states of meditation. The first four are termed
                            “form” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa</foreign>) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">jhānas</foreign> because the absorption takes place within the fine material sphere (Skt.
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">rūpaloka</foreign>). The final four are called “formless” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpa</foreign>) because they take place in the formless spheres (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpyadhātu</foreign>; Pali <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">arūpaloka</foreign>), and are also known as the four attainments (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāpatti</foreign>). For a presentation of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">jhāna</foreign> system followed in the present-day Theravāda, see Gunaratana (1988
                            pp. 9-20.)</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-27"/>
                    <p tid="32">“They are free from thinking or examining, and possess inner serenity. Because their mindstreams are
                        one-pointed, they do not think <ref cRef="F.107.b"/> or examine. Endowed with the joy and happiness that
                        arise from meditative concentration, they then accomplish the second meditative absorption and maintain
                        it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-28"/>
                    <p tid="33">“Because they are free from attachment to joy, they maintain equipoise and possess mindfulness and
                        awareness. They experience the physical happiness of which the noble ones say, ‘To possess mindfulness and
                        remain in happiness is equanimity.’<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-209">This is a
                            citation from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭā­daśa­sāhasrikā­prajñā­pāramitā</title> (<title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in 18,000 Lines</title>), (Toh 11, vol. 29, F.162b). The
                            preceding passage is also found there.</note> Free of joy they then accomplish the third meditative
                        absorption and maintain it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-29"/>
                    <p tid="34">“They renounce happiness after already renouncing suffering. Because both mental happiness and
                        mental displeasure decline, there is neither happiness nor suffering. They then accomplish the fourth
                        meditative absorption and maintain it, with immaculate equipoise and mindfulness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-30"/>
                    <p tid="35">“They transcend conceptions of form in all aspects, and their conceptions of materiality decline.
                        When they do not fabricate conceptions of any kind, they think, ‘This is the infinity of space,’ and then
                        accomplish the sphere of the infinity of space and maintain it. After they have transcended the sphere of
                        the infinity of space in all aspects, they think, ‘This is the infinity of consciousness,’ and then
                        accomplish the sphere of the infinity of consciousness and maintain it. After they have transcended the
                        sphere of the infinity of consciousness in all aspects, they think, ‘This is nothingness,’ and then
                        accomplish the sphere of nothingness and maintain it. After they have transcended the sphere of
                        nothingness in all aspects, they then accomplish the sphere of neither perception nor non-perception and
                        maintain it. After they have transcended the sphere of neither perception nor non-perception in all aspects,
                        they then accomplish the cessation of perception and feeling and maintain it.<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-210">This is a fifth accomplishment sometimes added to the four formless
                            absorptions.</note> Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these nine qualities, they will abandon all
                        evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-31"/>
                    <p tid="36">“Furthermore, Maitreya, if bodhisattvas <ref cRef="F.108.a"/> possess ten qualities, they will
                        abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. What ten qualities? Having vajra-like meditative
                        concentration, meditative concentration that is assiduous regarding what is correct and incorrect,
                        meditative concentration of going via methods, illuminating meditative concentration, all-illuminating
                        meditative concentration, manifest meditative concentration, precious moon meditative concentration,
                        moon-lamp meditative concentration, meditative concentration without afflictive emotions, and
                        victory-banner finial meditative concentration. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these ten qualities,
                        they will abandon all evil rebirths and not fall into the clutches of sinful associates, but swiftly realize
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-32"/>
                    <p tid="37">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was then satisfied and delighted. Joyful and pleased, he rose
                        from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, set his right knee on the ground, and bowed to the
                        Blessed One with joined palms. He praised the Blessed One with these fitting verses: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-33"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>“In former times, you practiced generous giving. </l>
                        <l>Giving away dear sons, food and drink, </l>
                        <l>And even your head and eyes, </l>
                        <l>You perfected the total generosity of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-34"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“For a long time, like a yak its tail,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-211">This
                                odd, seemingly culturally Himalayan simile does not appear to be due to any corruption in the
                                text: N and H merely offer <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul ring(s)</foreign> instead of
                                D <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yun ring</foreign>. Indeed, the same simile is found in
                                other Kangyur texts, again in the context of guarding moral conduct.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>You observed unimpaired moral conduct. </l>
                        <l>Peerless in your conduct,</l>
                        <l>You wholly perfected the conduct of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-35"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“You generated the power of patience,</l>
                        <l>And patiently endured the wrong deeds of ignorant people. <ref cRef="F.108.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Possessing all the powers of patience,</l>
                        <l>You wholly perfected the patience of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-36"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“You generated the power of diligence,</l>
                        <l>Then found unsurpassed peace and happiness.</l>
                        <l>Powerful due to your diligence,</l>
                        <l>You wholly perfected the diligence of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-37"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>“After burning up all sins, </l>
                        <l>You, great guide and being, took pleasure in your meditation.</l>
                        <l>Powerful due to the power of meditation,</l>
                        <l>You wholly perfected the meditation of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-38"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>“Through wisdom that realizes </l>
                        <l>That phenomena are by nature empty</l>
                        <l>And that nothing intrinsically arises, </l>
                        <l>You reached the other shore and wholly perfected the wisdom of a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-39"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>“Wise One, beneath the Bodhi tree</l>
                        <l>You subdued clawed demons</l>
                        <l>And attained the supreme goal.</l>
                        <l>As the Buddha, you vanquished the evil gathering of demons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-40"/>
                    <lg tid="45">
                        <l>“Great being, at Vārāṇasī</l>
                        <l>You turned the wheel of the Dharma.</l>
                        <l>You terrified the assembly of evil unbelievers,</l>
                        <l>And, as the Buddha, vanquished the unbelievers’ gatherings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-41"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>“Unsurpassed for your vast wisdom,</l>
                        <l>Utterly without compare,</l>
                        <l>You teach the Jewel of the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>O guide and Buddha, you bring about illumination.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-42"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>“You are peerless in generosity,</l>
                        <l>Strength of moral conduct, patience, and diligence.</l>
                        <l>You have accomplished the perfection of everything.</l>
                        <l>You excel, O Buddha, with your many qualities.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="48">After the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya had praised the Blessed One in verse with such fitting
                        words, he stood to one side. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-43"/>
                    <p tid="49">The venerable Ānanda then said to the Blessed One, “Lord, Blessed One, it is wonderful that the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya is so supremely eloquent, and that he teaches the Dharma with such words
                        of certainty, that he teaches the Dharma with such matching words and letters, that he teaches the Dharma
                        with such profound words, that he teaches the Dharma with words that explain it so well, <ref cRef="F.109.a"/> and that he teaches the Dharma with such memorable words.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-44"/>
                    <p tid="50">“Exactly, Ānanda,” replied the Blessed One. “It is just as you have said—it is wonderful that the
                        bodhisattva Maitreya is so supremely eloquent, that the bodhisattva Maitreya teaches the Dharma with such
                        words of certainty, and all of what you said, up to his teaching the Dharma with such memorable words.
                        Ānanda, this is not the first time that the bodhisattva Maitreya has praised me with such fitting verses.
                        Why? Formerly, Ānanda, in times gone by, at a time when ten countless ages had passed, there came into the
                        world <!--modularPassage type=tathāgataDescription1-->a tathāgata, arhat, completely and perfectly
                        enlightened buddha, endowed with perfect knowledge and perfect conduct, established in a state of bliss,
                        commanding all worldly knowledge, an unsurpassed guide who converted all beings, a teacher of gods and
                        men<!--/modularPassage-->, the Buddha Arhat named Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña.<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-212">The Sanskrit name of this tathāgata is attested in the Sanskrit fragment
                            mentioned in the introduction (see also Matsumura 1993). The name is also a component of the names of
                            two of the 35 “tathāgatas of confession,” found in a liturgy much used in the Tibetan tradition and
                            extracted from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya­viniścayopāli­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 68); the
                            Tibetan of the equivalent part of the names in the latter text is slightly different, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer rnam par rol pa mngon par mkhyen pa</foreign> (see Python 1973, pp. 34
                            and 100).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-45"/>
                    <p tid="51">“At that time, there lived a brahmin boy named Bhadraśuddha,
                        <!--modularPassage type=handsomeness-->good-looking, handsome, and beautiful to behold, endowed with a
                        supremely good complexion and excellent figure<!--/modularPassage-->. He was going to a pleasure grove,
                        when between the villages he saw the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the completely and perfectly enlightened Buddha
                        Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña. <!--modularPassage type=buddhaQualities-->The Tathāgata was handsome and
                        charismatic, controlled in his faculties and in his mind. He had attained excellence in control and calm
                        abiding, and superiority in control and calm abiding. He guarded his faculties, elephant-like in control
                        of his passions, and was radiant, unsullied, and clear like a lake. His body was adorned with the
                        thirty-two marks of a great being, and with the eighty minor marks, like the blossoming flower of a royal
                        sal tree, and towering like Mount Meru, the king of mountains. His face was as calm as the sphere of the
                        moon, <ref cRef="F.109.b"/> and radiantly clear and brilliant like the sphere of the sun. His body was
                        proportioned like a nyagrodha tree, blazing with light and great splendor.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-46"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Seeing him, Bhadraśuddha developed an attitude of faith toward the Blessed One. With this
                        attitude of faith, he thought, ‘How marvelous! How wondrously this body of the Tathāgata is adorned in its
                        complexion and splendor. It blazes with glory, the marks of buddhahood, and clear, brilliant radiance.’
                        The brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha then spoke out loud, ‘How marvelous! May I also, in the future, come to
                        possess such a body, blazing like this in complexion, magnificence, splendor, the marks of buddhahood,
                        and with clear, brilliant radiance!’ </p>
                    <p tid="53">“After he had prayed thus, he lay on the ground and thought, ‘If in the future I shall come to possess such a body, blazing like this in complexion, magnificence, splendor, marks of buddhahood, and with
                        clear, brilliant radiance, may the Tathāgata touch me with his foot.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-47"/>
                    <p tid="54">“Then, Ānanda, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the completely and perfectly enlightened Buddha
                        Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña, learning of the noble intention of the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha, approached him and
                        touched him with his foot. As soon as the Tathāgata Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña had touched the brahmin boy
                        Bhadraśuddha with his foot, at that very moment the boy attained acceptance of the fact that all phenomena
                        are unproduced. Ānanda, the Tathāgata Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña looked behind him and addressed the monks,
                        ‘Monks, on no account should you tread on the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha with your feet. Why? Because he is
                            <ref cRef="F.110.a"/> a bodhisattva mahāsattva who has accepted the fact that all phenomena are
                        unproduced.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-48"/>
                    <p tid="55">“At that very moment, the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha obtained the knowledge of the divine eye,
                        knowledge of the divine ear, knowledge of the thoughts of others, and knowledge recollecting his past
                        lives, and also accomplished miraculous powers. In the presence of the Tathāgata Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña he
                        spoke the following fitting verses of praise: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-49"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“ ‘Though I roamed and searched in all the cardinal and intermediate directions, </l>
                        <l>There is no lord such as you in all the worlds. </l>
                        <l>The perfect Buddha is supreme in all realms of existence. </l>
                        <l>O great self-arisen guide, to you I pay homage. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-50"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“ ‘Just as the bright sun in the sky, </l>
                        <l>In all worldly realms of the cardinal and intermediate directions, </l>
                        <l>Illuminates all these worlds with its light, </l>
                        <l>So do your splendid qualities—O Buddha, to you I pay homage. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-51"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“ ‘Just as a lion roaring in the deep forests </l>
                        <l>Subdues the fox and all other ordinary animals, </l>
                        <l>So you, the noblest and most powerful of men, </l>
                        <l>Subdue all the great assemblies of unbelievers. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-52"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“ ‘The Sugata’s fair ringlet between his eyebrows, </l>
                        <l>Endlessly splendid like a hoard of silver or snow, </l>
                        <l>Illuminates all these worlds. </l>
                        <l>In all the worlds there is nobody who equals you, O Buddha. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-53"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“ ‘Best of beings, you possess celestial wheels </l>
                        <l>Bright and fair, with a thousand spokes and spinning rims, </l>
                        <l>On your feet: these marks cause the earth, with its mountains and forests, to tremble. </l>
                        <l>O Sage, you are unrivaled by ordinary beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-54"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“ ‘Your great knowledge discards afflictive emotions and abandons everything. </l>
                        <l>Noble One, you discovered the path of deliverance; <ref cRef="F.110.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Possessing every wealth, rich in qualities, </l>
                        <l>You array the wealth of a noble one as you please.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-55"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“ ‘You are comparable to the earth, and without equal as a recipient of offerings. </l>
                        <l> You have obtained mastery of all good qualities, and your moral conduct is pure. </l>
                        <l>Just as hands cannot grasp or capture space, </l>
                        <l>So too, in the worlds you possess no attachment or anger.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-56"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“ ‘Reaching ultimate acceptance,<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-213">This
                                translation of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa zad kyis gtugs pa</foreign> is
                                tentative.</note> you learnt that all objects and phenomena </l>
                        <l>Are without essence, fictitious, and impure. </l>
                        <l>In all those arrogant sentient beings that migrate in saṃsāra, </l>
                        <l>You found no life force or substance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-57"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“ ‘Adapting to their dispositions and actions, and knowing their thoughts, </l>
                        <l>You are a wondrous lamp that discerns them. </l>
                        <l>Since you witnessed beings carried away by the great river, </l>
                        <l>You formerly produced the power of firm strength of diligence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-58"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“ ‘You possess a mind that rejects rebirth and pacifies afflictive emotions; </l>
                        <l>Your vast mind brought birth, old age, and death to an end. </l>
                        <l>Like the sphere of space you are without attachment; </l>
                        <l>Untainted by worldly qualities, you roam the three worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-59"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“ ‘O great being, your wisdom brings illumination, </l>
                        <l>Dispelling every darkness that has gathered. </l>
                        <l>You calm the dust of attachment and dispel the darkness </l>
                        <l>Of the various stains of anger and ignorance—to you I pay homage.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-60"/>
                    <p tid="67">“Ānanda, this does not yet exhaust the miraculous displays and supernormal powers of the brahmin
                        boy Bhadraśuddha.</p>
                    <p tid="68">“Ānanda, <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether the brahmin boy Bhadraśuddha
                        was then, at that time, someone else, or you are of two minds about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why?
                        Because the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya himself was then, at that time, the brahmin boy
                        Bhadraśuddha<!--/modularPassage-->, <ref cRef="F.111.a"/> who uttered these verses of praise to the
                        Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly enlightened Buddha Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-61"/>
                    <p tid="69">The venerable Ānanda asked, “Blessed One, if this bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya developed
                        acceptance so long ago of the fact that all phenomena are unproduced, why did he not quickly realize
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-62"/>
                    <p tid="70">The Blessed One replied to the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, the bodhisattvas set in place and
                            protect<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-214">The Tibetan terms provisionally
                            translated here as “set in place” and “protect” are <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkod
                                pa</foreign> and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su gzung ba</foreign>. </note> two
                        things. What two things? They set in place and protect sentient beings, and they set in place and protect
                        their buddha realms. But of these two, when formerly the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was engaged in
                        the conduct of a bodhisattva, he set in place, consecrated, and protected his buddha realm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-63"/>
                    <p tid="71">“Ānanda, when I myself was formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, I set in place and
                        protected sentient beings, and I also set in place and protected my buddha realm. Ānanda, I knew through
                        foresight that forty-two eons after the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya entered the path I would first
                        arouse the mind of supreme, perfect enlightenment. Ānanda, with the knowledge that, ninety-four eons after
                        that good eon had passed, I would realize supreme, perfect enlightenment, I applied myself, Ānanda, with
                        burning diligence <ref cRef="F.111.b"/> and quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a
                        buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-64"/>
                    <p tid="72">“Ānanda, it was by means of ten qualities that I quickly accomplished supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and became a buddha. What ten qualities? I abandoned and let go of all doubts, abandoned and
                        let go of my spouse, abandoned and let go of my child, abandoned and let go of my head, abandoned and let
                        go of my eyes, abandoned and let go of my kingdom, abandoned and let go of my wealth, abandoned and let go
                        of my blood, abandoned and let go of my bones and marrow, and abandoned my limbs. By letting go of
                        everything I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, it was by means
                        of those ten qualities that I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-65"/>
                    <p tid="73">“Ānanda, it was also by means of a further ten qualities that I quickly accomplished supreme,
                        perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. What ten qualities? Ānanda, I adhered to the teaching of the
                        qualities of moral conduct, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha.
                        Ānanda, I possessed the power of patience, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                        became a buddha. Ānanda, I applied ardent diligence, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I adhered to the qualities of meditation, and so I quickly
                        realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. <ref cRef="F.112.a"/> Ānanda, I adhered to
                        the perfection of wisdom, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha.
                        Ānanda, I did not abandon any sentient being in any way, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I was skillful in my means, and so I quickly realized supreme,
                        perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I treated all sentient beings equally, and so I quickly
                        realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I realized the teaching of emptiness,
                        and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and became a buddha. Ānanda, I realized the
                        teaching of signlessness and wishlessness, and so I quickly realized supreme, perfect enlightenment and
                        became a buddha. Ānanda, it was by means of those ten qualities that I quickly realized supreme, perfect
                        enlightenment and became a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-66"/>
                    <p tid="74">“Ānanda, if you were aware of how harsh and severe were the sensations of suffering by which I
                        realized supreme and completely perfect enlightenment, perfect buddhahood, you, Ānanda, would not be so
                        forthright. The reason, Ānanda, is that formerly, in times gone by, there lived a prince named Giver of
                        All Wealth, good-looking, handsome, and beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely good complexion,
                        excellent figure, and with the great wealth and power of a king. He was going to a pleasure grove when he
                        saw between the villages a man afflicted with suffering and seriously ill. At this sight, he felt
                        compassion, approached the man, and asked, <ref cRef="F.112.b"/> ‘You, sir, what are you suffering from?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-67"/>
                    <p tid="75">“The man said, ‘Your Highness, I have contracted an illness.’ </p>
                    <p tid="76">“ ‘What will assuage your illness, my good man?’ asked the prince. ‘What shall I give you?’ </p>
                    <p tid="77">“ ‘Your Highness,’ replied the man, ‘if I were to drink just enough of the blood from your body to
                        satisfy me, my illness would be assuaged.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-68"/>
                    <p tid="78">“Then, Ānanda, Prince Giver of All Wealth took a sharp knife, cut himself, and gave the man the
                        blood that drained from the wound to drink. Ānanda, as soon as the man drank it, his illness was cured.
                        Ānanda, even though Prince Giver of All Wealth cut himself and all his blood drained out, he never had a
                        moment’s regret. Ānanda, <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether Prince Giver of All
                        Wealth was then, at that time, someone else, or you are of two minds about it, or doubtful, do not see him
                        so. Why? Because I myself was then, at that time, Prince Giver of All Wealth.<!--/modularPassage-->
                        Ānanda, all the water of the four great oceans can be measured, but the blood that I have given to
                        sentient beings as I sought supreme, completely perfect enlightenment cannot. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-69"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Ānanda, formerly, in times gone by, there lived a prince named Puṣpa, good-looking, handsome, and
                        beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely good complexion, excellent figure, and with the great wealth
                        and power of a king. He was going to the site of a pleasure grove when he saw between the villages a man
                        who had contracted dropsy, afflicted with suffering and seriously ill. </p>
                    <p tid="80">“At this sight, he felt compassion and approached the man, and asked, ‘My good man, what will assuage this
                        illness of yours? What shall I give you?’ </p>
                    <p tid="81">“The man replied, <ref cRef="F.113.a"/> ‘Your Majesty, if I were to get just enough of the marrow
                        from your body to satisfy me, my illness would be assuaged.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-70"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Prince Puṣpa was satisfied and delighted; he rejoiced, and then pleasure and happiness arose in
                        him. He beat his own body, then gouged out the marrow and smeared it on that man’s body. Ānanda, as soon
                        as he smeared it on him, the man’s illness was cured. Ānanda, even though Prince Puṣpa beat his own body
                        so that the marrow dripped out, he felt no regret in his mind. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-71"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Ānanda, <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether Prince Puṣpa was then, at that
                        time, someone else, or you are of two minds about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because I myself
                        was then, at that time, Prince Puṣpa.<!--/modularPassage--> Ānanda, all the water of the four great oceans
                        can be measured, but the marrow that I have given to sentient beings as I sought supreme, completely
                        perfect enlightenment cannot. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-72"/>
                    <p tid="84">“Ānanda, formerly in times gone by there lived a king named Candraprabha, good-looking, handsome
                        and beautiful to behold, endowed with a supremely good complexion, excellent figure, and with the great
                        wealth and power of a king. He was going to a pleasure grove, when between the villages he saw a poor, eyeless
                        blind man, a destitute beggar. At this sight, he felt compassion. </p>
                    <p tid="85">“That man then approached King Candraprabha and said, ‘Your Majesty, you are happy. Your Majesty,
                        you are joyful, but I suffer. I am blind; I have no eyes. I am poor and destitute. I am a beggar without
                        refuge.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-73"/>
                    <p tid="86">“Then, Ānanda, King Candraprabha saw the man again, and after listening to his words again he
                        wept, and still in tears, asked him, ‘My good man, what do you need? <ref cRef="F.113.b"/> Should I give you food
                        or drink? A riding-mount? Jewelry? Gold, gems, pearls, or various kinds of precious things? Tell me
                        whatever you need.’ </p>
                    <p tid="87">“The man replied, ‘I beg you, please give me your eye.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-74"/>
                    <p tid="88">“So, Ānanda, King Candraprabha plucked out his eye and gave it to the man. But, Ānanda, although
                        King Candraprabha had plucked out his eye and given it to the man, he did not become regretful. Ānanda,
                        <!--modularPassage type=pastLifeWho-->if you wonder whether King Candraprabha was then, at that time
,                        someone else, or you are of two minds about it, or doubtful, do not see him so. Why? Because I myself was
                        then, at that time, King Candraprabha.<!--/modularPassage--> Ānanda, Mount Meru, the king of mountains,
                        can be measured, but the eyes that I have given to sentient beings as I sought supreme, completely perfect
                        enlightenment are too great and cannot. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-75"/>
                    <p tid="89">“Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was formerly engaged in the conduct of a
                        bodhisattva, because the vehicle is easy, the entry is easy, and the path is easy,<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-215">We have not found the phrase <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa bde ba ’jug pa bde ba lam bde ba</foreign> attested elsewhere.</note> he
                        perfectly accomplished supreme, perfect enlightenment. Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya
                        was formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva he did not let go of his arms, legs, or marrow. He
                        did not renounce and let go of his spouse, or his child, village, town, city, royal palace, or retinue.
                        But, Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was formerly engaged in the conduct of a
                        bodhisattva, because he fully embraced skillful means, through the easy vehicle, the easy entry, and the
                        easy path <ref cRef="F.114.a"/> he accomplished supreme, perfect enlightenment.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-76"/>
                    <p tid="90">Then the venerable Ānanda asked, “Blessed One, what were the skillful means to which the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya adhered, thus accomplishing supreme, perfect enlightenment?” </p>
                    <p tid="91">The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, when formerly the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya engaged in the
                        conduct of a bodhisattva, he would drape his shawl over one shoulder, set his right knee on the ground,
                        and put the palms of his hands together three times during the day and three times during the night.
                        Making all the buddhas visible, he would then speak to them in these words: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-77"/>
                    <lg tid="92">
                        <l>“ ‘Homage to all the buddhas! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the bodhisattvas,</l>
                        <l>Those sages with the divine eye—</l>
                        <l>And to the śrāvakas, too. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-78"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>“ ‘Homage to the mind of enlightenment,</l>
                        <l>Which reverses all negative rebirths,</l>
                        <l>Shows the path to higher rebirths,</l>
                        <l>And leads beings to the state without aging or death.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-79"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>“ ‘Whatever negative actions I have done</l>
                        <l>Under the influence of mind,</l>
                        <l>Here in the presence of the buddhas</l>
                        <l>I confess them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-80"/>
                    <lg tid="95">
                        <l>“ ‘Whatever accumulation of merit</l>
                        <l>I have produced through the three kinds of action,<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-216">
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las rnam pa gsum</foreign>, “the three [kinds of] actions”
                                is interpreted by Dharmabhadra and Ngawang Khedrup to mean meritorious actions of body, speech,
                                and mind, but by Padma Karpo to be meritorious actions causing rebirth as a human, meritorious
                                actions causing rebirth as a god, and “non-transferring” actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi g.yo ba’i las</foreign>) causing rebirth in the two higher realms (of
                                form and no-form). </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>May it be the seed of my omniscience</l>
                        <l>And inexhaustible enlightenment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-81"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>“ ‘Whatever offerings to the buddhas </l>
                        <l>Arise in all realms throughout the ten directions,</l>
                        <l>The buddhas know and rejoice in them,</l>
                        <l>And at that I myself rejoice.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-82"/>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>“ ‘I confess all negative actions.</l>
                        <l>I rejoice in all meritorious acts.</l>
                        <l>I pay homage to all the buddhas.</l>
                        <l>May I attain supreme awareness! <ref cRef="F.114.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-83"/>
                    <lg tid="98">
                        <l>“ ‘I exhort the bodhisattvas</l>
                        <l>Of all ten directions,</l>
                        <l>Who abide on the ten bodhisattva levels,</l>
                        <l>To attain supreme enlightenment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-84"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>“ ‘May they become truly enlightened buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Overcoming negative influences of every kind,</l>
                        <l>And then, to benefit living beings,</l>
                        <l>May they turn the wheel of the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-85"/>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>“ ‘Through the sound of the great Dharma drum,</l>
                        <l>May they bring the suffering of sentient beings to an end.</l>
                        <l>For unimaginable millions of eons,</l>
                        <l>May they teach the Dharma and continue to remain in this world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-86"/>
                    <lg tid="101">
                        <l>“ ‘I beg you, best of all humans,</l>
                        <l>Look upon those who are trapped in the swamp of desire,</l>
                        <l>And tightly bound by the cords of craving,</l>
                        <l>Fettered in every kind of bond.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-87"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>“ ‘Buddhas, do not belittle</l>
                        <l>Those whose minds are defiled,</l>
                        <l>But with loving intent toward all sentient beings,</l>
                        <l>Save them from the sea of existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-88"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“ ‘May I train in the footsteps</l>
                        <l>Of the perfect buddhas—those present now,</l>
                        <l>Those of the past, and those of the future—</l>
                        <l>And may I engage in the conduct of the bodhisattvas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-89"/>
                    <lg tid="104">
                        <l>“ ‘May I complete the six perfections</l>
                        <l>And liberate beings of the six realms.</l>
                        <l>May I realize the six supernormal powers</l>
                        <l>And reach supreme enlightenment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-90"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“ ‘Unproduced and non-arising,</l>
                        <l>Without self-nature or location,</l>
                        <l>Neither mental cognition, nor substance—</l>
                        <l>May I realize the teaching of emptiness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-91"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>“ ‘Just like the Buddha, the great sage,</l>
                        <l>May I realize the teaching of non-self:</l>
                        <l>A sentient being does not exist, nor does a living being,</l>
                        <l>Nor does an individual, or a person.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-217">“Person”
                                here is a translation of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gso ba</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-92"/>
                    <lg tid="107">
                        <l>“ ‘May I not dwell on there being anything substantial, </l>
                        <l>A belief in a self, or what I take to be mine,</l>
                        <l>But in order to make all sentient beings happy,</l>
                        <l>May I give everything away without miserliness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-93"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>“ ‘Since material objects do not really exist,</l>
                        <l> May my wealth be spontaneously accomplished.</l>
                        <l>Since all material objects decay,</l>
                        <l> May I complete the perfection of generosity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-94"/>
                    <lg tid="109">
                        <l>“ ‘Possessing conduct that is flawless,</l>
                        <l>Conduct that is perfect,</l>
                        <l>And conduct that is without arrogance, <ref cRef="F.115.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>May I complete the perfection of moral conduct.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-95"/>
                    <lg tid="110">
                        <l>“ ‘Like the elements of earth, water, fire,</l>
                        <l>And wind, not dwelling on anything,<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-218">The
                                commentaries differ considerably in their interpretations of these two lines, with Padma Karpo
                                emphasizing simply the inanimate nature of the four elements, and most of the others detailing
                                particular qualities of patience for which each of the four is a simile. Despite the syntax, most
                                agree that “not dwelling” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi gnas pa</foreign>) refers
                                principally to the wind element. The translation here is an attempt to remain open to more than
                                one interpretation. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>With patience and<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-219">D and most other Kangyurs
                                have <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa’am</foreign> here in Toh 85, but <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa’ang</foreign> in the versions in the Dhāraṇī section
                                (Toh 1096) and in the Tengyur (Toh 4378), which makes more sense; S has simply <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa</foreign>.</note> free of anger,</l>
                        <l>May I complete the perfection of patience.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-96"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“ ‘Through assiduous application of diligence,</l>
                        <l>May I have constant enthusiasm without laziness,</l>
                        <l>And with strength of body and mind,</l>
                        <l>May I complete the perfection of diligence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-97"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“ ‘Through magic-like meditative concentration,</l>
                        <l>Meditative concentration of bravery,</l>
                        <l>And vajra-like meditative concentration,</l>
                        <l>May I complete the perfection of meditation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-98"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“ ‘Actualizing the three gates to liberation,</l>
                        <l>The sameness of the three times,</l>
                        <l>And the threefold knowledge,<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-220"><!--KB-->According to
                                Tāranātha’s commentary, the threefold knowledge (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa
                                    gsum</foreign>) comprises (1) knowledge of the whole of the past (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngon gyi mtha’ rig pa</foreign>), (2) knowledge of the whole of the future
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyi ma’i mtha’ rig pa</foreign>), and (3) knowledge of
                                the exhaustion of defilements (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag zad rig pa</foreign>);
                                the other commentaries, however, take the three kinds of knowledge as knowledge of the minds,
                                mental events, and their causes, of all sentient beings in the past, present, and future.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>May I complete the perfection of wisdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-99"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“ ‘May I be praised by all the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>And blaze with light and splendor;</l>
                        <l>Through the diligence of a bodhisattva,</l>
                        <l>May my intention be fulfilled.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-100"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“ ‘Thus engaging in such conduct,</l>
                        <l>May I, who am known as Maitreya,</l>
                        <l>Complete the six perfections</l>
                        <l>And dwell on the ten bodhisattva levels.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-101"/>
                    <p tid="116">“Ānanda, those are the skillful means through which the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, by
                        adhering to them, through the easy vehicle, the easy entry, and the easy path, perfectly accomplished
                        supreme, perfect, and complete enlightenment. Ānanda, when the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was
                        formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, he thought to himself, ‘How I wish that sentient beings,
                        having less desire, anger, and ignorance, might acquire the path of the ten virtuous actions! In the
                        future, may I perfectly accomplish supreme, perfect, and complete enlightenment and become a buddha.’ It
                        was thus that he consecrated his buddha realm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-102"/>
                    <p tid="117">“Ānanda, such a time and period will come about; then sentient beings will become less desiring,
                        angry, <ref cRef="F.115.b"/> and ignorant, and keep to the path of the ten virtuous actions. After that,
                        the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, due to the power of his prayer, will perfectly accomplish supreme,
                        perfect, and completely enlightened buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-103"/>
                    <p tid="118">“Ānanda, when I formerly engaged in the conduct of a bodhisattva, I made this prayer: ‘When the
                        world is beset with the five degenerations, sentient beings will have great desire, anger, and ignorance.
                        Desire, anger, and ignorance will all increase. Beings will desire and crave irreligious things. They will
                        be overcome by fearsome desire, and adopt false doctrines. They will despise their fathers, their mothers,
                        their cousins, and their siblings, their partners, their relatives, noble beings, abbots, spiritual
                        teachers, themselves, and others. These people will be filthy, wild, and stupid. How wonderful it will be
                        if I can perfectly realize supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha among them!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-104"/>
                    <p tid="119">“Having lived in such a terrible epoch, Ānanda, I have kindled great compassion. Today, when I
                        enter villages, cities, towns, districts and provinces, and the surroundings of royal palaces with great
                        compassion, as soon as I teach the Dharma I am slandered and reviled, harshly abused, and told not to
                        create a gathering. Ānanda, it is even said that I am a nihilist, or that I am an eternalist. They say
                        that those in my retinue have many desires, and that their desires are great. When I enter into houses,
                        earth is thrown at me. I am given food mixed with poison. They even have <ref cRef="F.116.a"/> bonfires
                        made for me.<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-221">One such story is recounted in the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīguptasūtra</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sbas kyi
                            mdo</title>, Toh 217); see bibliography. For a translation, see Liljenberg (forthcoming).</note> So it
                        is. Although I am a buddha, I am denigrated as cohabiting with so-called ‘beautiful women’ and the like.
                        Ānanda, I kindled great compassion, and with great compassion, I now teach the Dharma to such sentient
                        beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-105"/>
                    <p tid="120">The venerable Ānanda then said to the Blessed One, “The Blessed One who teaches the Dharma to
                        such sentient beings, converting those not previously converted by the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly
                        enlightened Buddha, has taken on a great burden, and undergone hardships.” </p>
                    <p tid="121">The Blessed One replied to the venerable Ānanda, “Exactly, Ānanda. It is just as you have said.
                        Ānanda, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly enlightened Buddha has tamed those not previously tamed,
                        taken on a great burden, and himself endowed with every virtuous quality, undergone hardship by teaching
                        the Dharma to such sentient beings. Why? Because this is how much he was gripped by great compassion.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-106"/>
                    <p tid="122">The venerable Ānanda then exclaimed, “That the Blessed One should bestow such a Dharma discourse,
                        that I should hear this Dharma discourse, and hear this topic from the Blessed One, the best of men, is
                        hair-raising and amazing! Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma discourse? How should it be
                        remembered?” </p>
                    <p tid="123">The Blessed One replied, “From now onward, Ānanda, you should remember this Dharma discourse as
                        ‘The Former Prayer that is Truly Noble.’ You should also remember it as ‘The True Arising of the
                        Tathāgata.’ You should also remember it as ‘The Arising of the Intention of Enlightenment.’ You should
                        also remember it as ‘The Question of Maitreya.’ ” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-107"/>
                    <p tid="124">When the Blessed One had spoken, the venerable Ānanda and the bodhisattva Maitreya, together with
                        the five hundred monks <ref cRef="F.116.b"/> and the entire retinue, as well as the worlds of gods and
                        men, demi-gods and gandharvas, rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s words. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="133">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-108"/>
                    <p tid="125">This concludes the “Section of the Question of Maitreya,” the forty-first section of <title xml:lang="en">The Noble
                        Dharma Discourse, the Great Heap of Jewels</title>, in one hundred thousand sections. </p>
                    <p tid="126">This text was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholars Jinamitra and
                        Surendrabodhi, together with the chief editor and translator Yeshé Dé. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="134">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="135">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-044-005-109">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-044-005-110">
                        <abbr>H</abbr>
                        <expan>Lhasa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhol</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-044-005-111">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar thang</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-044-005-112">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</foreign>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="136">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="137">Tibetan texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-113">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­maitreya­pari­pṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>), Toh 85, Degé Kangyur, vol.
                        44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 104b–116b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-114">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>, bka’ ’gyur (dpe
                            bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi
                        bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research
                        Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006-2009, vol. 44, pp. 289–316. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-115">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa khri brgyad stong pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭā­daśa­sāhasrikā­prajñā­pāramitā</title>) [Perfection of Wisdom in 18,000 Lines],
                        Toh 10, Degé Kangyur, vol. 29 F.1a–vol. 31 F.206a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-116">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa’i gsang ba bsam gyis mi khyab pa bstan pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata­cintya­guhya­nirdeśa</title>), Toh 47, Degé Kangyur, vol. 39, F.100a–203a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-117">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sbas kyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīguptasūtra</title>), Toh
                        217, Degé Kangyur, vol. 62, F.269a-284a; for translation, see Liljenberg (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-121"> Choné Trakpa Shedrup (co ne grags pa bshad sgrub). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam gyi rnam par bzhad pa dga’ ldan du bgrod pa’i lam bzang, in co ne grags pa bshad
                        sgrub kyi gsung ’bum.</title> Beijing: Mes po’i shul bzhag series, krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House, 2009). (BDRC W1PD90129). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-119"> Drukpa Padma Karpo (’brug pa pad+ma dkar po). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pa’i smon lam gyi ’grel pa thogs med kyi dgongs pa gsal bar bstan pa</title>. In
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung ’bum</title>, vol. 7 (ja), pp. 349-376. Darjeeling: Kargyud Sungrab
                        Nyamso Khang (1973-1974). (BDRC W10736). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-123"> Kyedor Khenpo Ngawang Khedrup (kye rdor mkhan po ngag dbang mkhas grub).
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam gyi tshig don rnam bshad.</title> In gsung ’bum, vol. 2,
                        pp 315-360. Leh, Ladakh: S.W. Tashigangpa (1972-1974). (BDRC W16912). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-122"> Ngulchu Dharmabhadra (dngul chu d+harma b+hadra). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa’i smon lam gyi ’grel pa’i zin bris.</title> In gsung ’bum, vol. 1. pp. 495 et seq. Ngulchu
                        Chödzong: dngul chu bla brang, 2000? (BDRC W6493). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-118"> Shākya Chokden (shAkya mchog ldan). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pas
                            btab pa’i smon lam gyi rnam par bshad pa byams pa’i chos la ’jug pa’i sgo</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung bum</title>, vol. 8 (nya), pp 407-430. New Delhi: Ngawang Topgyel, (1995).
                        (BDRC W23200). </bibl>                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-120"> Tāranātha (tA ra nA tha). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams smon gyi ’grel
                            pa.</title> In gsung ’bum (blockprints from rtag brtan phun tshogs gling), vol. 13, pp 257-299. Leh,
                        Ladakh: Namgyal &amp; Tsewang Taru (1982-87). (BDRC W22277). </bibl>                 
                    
                   
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="138">Other works</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-124">Dharmachakra Translation Committee (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Maitreya’s
                            Setting Out</title>, Toh 198. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-128">Gunaratana, Henepola. <title xml:lang="en">The Jhānas in Theravāda Buddhist
                        Meditation</title>. Kandy, Śri Lanka: Buddhist Publication Society, 1988. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-125">Liljenberg, Karen (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Śrīgupta Sūtra</title>,
                        Toh 217. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-126">Matsumura, Hisashi. “Marginalia to the Sanskrit Fragments of Some Buddhist
                        Texts,” in <title xml:lang="en">Central Asiatic Journal</title>, vol. 37, no. 1/2 (1993), pp. 120-149.
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 1993. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-127">Python, Pierre. <title xml:lang="fr">Vinaya-viniścaya-upāli-paripṛcchā :
                            Enquête d’Upāli pour une exégèse de la discipline.</title> Paris: Adrien-Maisonneuve, 1973. </bibl>                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-129">Roberts, Peter, and Bower, Emily (trs.). <title xml:lang="en">The White
                            Lotus of the Good Dharma</title>, Toh 113. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha
                        (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-005-130">Yao, Fumi (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">On Medicinal Materials</title>.
                        Chapter 6, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi gzhi</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>), of <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba’i gzhi</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-131">
                            <term>sphere of nothingness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ci yang med pa’i skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཅི་ཡང་མེད་པའི་སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akiñcanyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Third of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-132">
                            <term>four great oceans</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho chen po bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ་མཚོ་ཆེན་པོ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catvaro samudrāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Four oceans believed to surround the central mountain, Mt. Meru, in Indian
                                cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-133">
                            <term>emptiness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūnyatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which realizes the non-self of persons and phenomena;
                                the first of the three doors of liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-134">
                            <term>sphere of neither perception nor non-perception</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du shes med ’du shes med min skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་འདུ་ཤེས་མེད་མིན་སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">naiva­saṃjñānāsaṃjñāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Fourth of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-135">
                            <term>sphere of the infinity of space</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ mtha yas skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་མཐ་ཡས་སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ākāśānantyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">First of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-136">
                            <term>sphere of the infinity of consciousness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam shes mtha’ yas skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཤེས་མཐའ་ཡས་སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vi­jñānānantyāyatanaṃ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Second of the four formless absorptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-137">
                            <term>noble eightfold path</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags lam yan lag brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་ལམ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryaṣṭāṇgamārga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-138">
                            <term>wishlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨོན་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">praṇihita</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which views nirvāṇa, which is the complete
                                pacification of the aggregates; the third of the Three Doors of Liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-139">
                            <term>signlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་མ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">animitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditative concentration which views the five aggregates, the basis for the
                                conception of a self, as faulty; the second of the three doors of liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-140">
                            <term>calm abiding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śamatha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Meditation technique to calm the mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-141">
                            <term>perfection of wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sixth of the six perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-142">
                            <term>meditative absorption</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསམ་གཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Four levels of meditation within the Form Realm.</term>
                            <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-044-005-208"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-143">
                            <term>sal tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing sA la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་སཱ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A hardwood tree, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">Shorea robusta</foreign>,
                                widespread on the Indian subcontinent.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-144">
                            <term>nyagrodha tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing nya gro dha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ཉ་གྲོ་དྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nyagrodha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tree, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">Ficus benghalensis</foreign>,
                                native to the Indian subcontinent, that can cover large areas by putting down aerial roots that
                                become subsidiary trunks.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-145">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The cousin and close attendant monk of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-146">
                            <term>Giver of All Wealth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor thams cad phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་ཐམས་ཅད་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-147">
                            <term>Puṣpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Puṣpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-148">
                            <term>Candraprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-149">
                            <term>Kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kauN+Din+ya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀཽཎྜིནྱ།</term>                      
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-150">
                            <term>Aśvajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rta thul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟ་ཐུལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aśvajit</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-151">
                            <term>Vaṣpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rlangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རླངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaṣpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-152">
                            <term>Mahānāman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ming chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིང་ཆེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahānāman</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-153">
                            <term>Bhadrika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrika</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-154">
                            <term>Vimala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-155">
                            <term>Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-156">
                            <term>Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ba lang bdag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བ་ལང་བདག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-157">
                            <term>Mṛgaśiras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri dags mgo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་དགས་མགོ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mṛgaśiras</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-158">
                            <term>Uruvilva Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lteng rgyas ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟེང་རྒྱས་འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Uruvilva Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-159">
                            <term>Nadīkāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu klung ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ཀླུང་འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nadīkāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-160">
                            <term>Gayākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ga ya ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ག་ཡ་འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gayākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-161">
                            <term>Jaṅghā Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byin pa ’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱིན་པ་འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jaṅghā Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-162">
                            <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-163">
                            <term>Amogharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don yod rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོན་ཡོད་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amogharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-164">
                            <term>Sumati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name shared by a close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha, and by a
                                bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-165">
                            <term>Śāriputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Close Śravaka disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-166">
                            <term>Maudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maudgalyāyana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-167">
                            <term>Parvatarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རྒྱལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Parvatarāja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-168">
                            <term>Nanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-169">
                            <term>Upananda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upananda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-170">
                            <term>Rāhula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན་ཟིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-171">
                            <term>Vardhamāna­mati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros ’phel </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་འཕེལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vardhamāna­mati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-172">
                            <term>Sthiramati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་བརྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sthiramati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-173">
                            <term>Viśālamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros yangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་ཡངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśālamati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-174">
                            <term>Pratibhāna­kūṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤོབས་པ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratibhāna­kūṭa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-175">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-176">
                            <term>Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu chen thob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་ཆེན་ཐོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sthāma­prāpta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-177">
                            <term>Kusumaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kusumaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-178">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-179">
                            <term>Abhi­jñā­puṣpa­supari­pūrṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa’i me tog shin tu rgyas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­jñā­puṣpa­supari­pūrṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-180">
                            <term>An­upalambha­manasi­kāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa med pa yid la byed pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ་མེད་པ་ཡིད་ལ་བྱེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">An­upalambha­manasi­kāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-181">
                            <term>Prasādavat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dad ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དད་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasādavat</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-182">
                            <term>Ratnaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaketu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-183">
                            <term>Indradeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོའི་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indradeva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-184">
                            <term>Varuṇadeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Varuṇadeva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-185">
                            <term>Mṛdusvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra dbyangs snyan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་དབྱངས་སྙན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mṛdusvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-186">
                            <term>Kṣetra­viśodhana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhing rnam par sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞིང་རྣམ་པར་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣetra­viśodhana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-187">
                            <term>Merukūṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhun po brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷུན་པོ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Merukūṭa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-188">
                            <term>Prati­bhāna­saṃpad</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spobs pa phun sum tshogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤོབས་པ་ཕུན་སུམ་ཚོགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prati­bhāna­saṃpad</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-189">
                            <term>Indraśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indraśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-190">
                            <term>Nimiṃdhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nimiṃdhara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-191">
                            <term>Scourer of the Hell-dwellers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can dmyal ba skems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེམས་ཅན་དམྱལ་བ་སྐེམས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-192">
                            <term>Abandoner of Unfavorable Rebirths</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan song spong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངན་སོང་སྤོང་།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-193">
                            <term>Ratnakesarin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ze ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཟེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakesarin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-194">
                            <term>Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang bas rnam par rol pa’i mngon par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣང་བས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པའི་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jyoti­vikrīḍitābhijña</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-195">
                            <term>Bhadraśuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang dag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་དག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadraśuddha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-196">
                            <term>Country of the Bhargas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul bha rga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་བྷ་རྒ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bharga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-197">
                            <term>Mount Śuśumāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu srin byis pa gsod lta bu’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་སྲིན་བྱིས་པ་གསོད་ལྟ་བུའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śuśumāragiri</term>
                            <term type="definition">Sometimes has the alternative Sanskrit spelling Śiśumāragiri.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-198">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhra­kūta­parvata</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-005-199">
                            <term>god</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> lha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha’i bu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">devaputra</term>
                            <!--<term type="alternative">demigod</term> Doesn't match tibetan - AAR -->
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>