<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pas chos brgyad zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པས་ཆོས་བརྒྱད་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā­dharmāṣṭa </title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་བྱམས་པས་ཆོས་བརྒྱད་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas chos brgyad zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                    mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Question of Maitreya on the Eight
                    Qualities”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­maitreya­paripṛcchā­dharmāṣṭa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-16" role="translatorMain">
                    Translated by Karen Liljenberg and Ulrich Pagel<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-115">Dr. Karen Liljenberg</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-116">Dr. Ulrich Pagel</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.31 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-044-006"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh86" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 86</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 116.b–119.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra </author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Danaśila</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="6">
                        <start volume="44" page="234"/>
                        <end volume="44" page="239"/>
                        
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14667"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11632" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 16/01/2019 at 10:35:20 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="35">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>, Maitreya asks the
                    Buddha what qualities bodhisattvas need in order to be sure of completing the path to buddhahood. In
                    response, the Buddha briefly lists eight qualities. Starting with the excellent intention to become
                    enlightened, they include loving kindness, as well as realization of the perfection of wisdom, which the
                    Buddha explains in terms of reflection on the twelve links of dependent origination. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="36">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This sūtra was translated by Dr. Karen Liljenberg, with Dr. Ulrich Pagel acting as consultant.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="37">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>,<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-46">In the Degé Kangyur this title, included within the text, is preceded by
                            this introductory sentence: “From <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Dharma
                                Discourse, the Great Heap of Jewels</title> in one hundred thousand sections, section 42: ‘The Noble Elucidation of
                            the Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities’ in a half-fascicle” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’phags pa dkon mchog brtsegs pa chen po’i chos kyi rnam grangs le’u
                                stong phrag brgya pa las le’u bzhi bcu rtsa gnyis pa ste ’phags pa byams pas chos brgyad zhus pa
                                lung bstan pa / bam po phyed pa</foreign>). See i.6 for a discussion of the various titles
                            by which this text is known.</note> like most of the sūtras that comprise the Ratnakūṭa collection, was translated into Tibetan from a Sanskrit original that is now lost,
                        but that may have dated back as far as the first or second centuries <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, i.e., several centuries before the
                        collection itself was compiled. Apart from the Tibetan Kangyur version, translated in the ninth century, the
                        sūtra is extant only in an earlier Chinese translation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Both the work translated here and the work that precedes it in the collection, <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>,<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-47">They are
                            sūtra numbers 42 and 41, respectively, in the Tibetan version of the Ratnakūṭa collection, but are numbered 86 and 85 in the Tōhoku catalogue of the Degé
                            Kangyur as a whole.</note> focus on the important figure of the bodhisattva Maitreya, who is generally
                        accepted as destined to be the future Buddha of this world-system. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">In this sūtra, Maitreya asks the Buddha what qualities bodhisattvas need in order to be sure of
                        completing the whole path to buddhahood. The Buddha responds with a list of eight qualities that, while
                        individually all standard elements of the Mahāyāna path, as a set of eight appear to be
                        specific to this text. The Buddha briefly explains each quality and, in his explanation of the last—the
                        perfection of wisdom—outlines the doctrine of the twelve links of dependent origination in both their
                        “forward” and “reverse” orders, corresponding to causation and cessation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">It is difficult to determine the precise historical relationship of <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title> with <title xml:lang="en">The Question of
                            Maitreya</title> (Toh 85), the longer sūtra that immediately precedes it. Their themes are obviously
                        closely linked—in both, Maitreya questions the Buddha about the bodhisattvas’ qualities. However, their
                        geographic settings differ: <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities</title>
                        takes place on Vulture Peak Mountain near Rājagṛha, like many other Ratnakūṭa sūtras, while <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title> is delivered in
                        a relatively obscure location, Mount Śuśumāra in the country of the Bhargas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">Both texts are included in the Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>) inventory
                        of early translations, dated to a year of the dragon thought to be most likely 824 (but possibly 812), so
                        they must have been translated by that date. The translation of this one, the shorter sūtra, is attributed
                        to Jinamitra and Danaśila, and Yeshé Dé is said to have corrected it using the revised terminology
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skad gsar</foreign>). Since <title xml:lang="en">The Question
                            of Maitreya</title> appears to have needed no such revision, its first Tibetan translation by
                        Jinamitra and Surendrabodhi, under the editorial supervision of Yeshé Dé, may have been slightly later. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">In the Degé Kangyur, the text has two different titles: the first, in the initial line introducing
                        it as the forty-second section of the Ratnakūṭa, calls it “The Noble Elucidation of the Question of Maitreya on
                        the Eight Qualities” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas chos brgyad zhus pa lung bstan
                            pa</title>), while the second, immediately afterwards, is simply “The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra of the
                        Question of Maitreya” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title>), which is the same as the title of the preceding text. The Sanskrit titles of both
                        sūtras, as transliterated in Tibetan in the Degé Kangyur, are also the same: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā</title>. In other Kangyurs, a variety of similar titles are given, while in
                        some—e.g. the Narthang (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar thang</title>) and Stok Palace Manuscript (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</title>) Kangyurs—the Sanskrit title includes mention of the
                        eight qualities: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā­dharmāṣṭa</title>. Whether the reference to
                        the “eight qualities” figured in the title of the Sanskrit original or, if not, at what stage it was
                        integrated into the title as a convenient way of distinguishing this text from the preceding one, is
                        difficult to determine. In the Tibetan title, at least, inclusion of the eight qualities was a feature in
                        some Kangyurs and text catalogues early in the imperial period, even if it was not universal. It is found
                        (as <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa’i chos brgyad pa</title>) in the early ninth
                        century Denkarma inventory mentioned above. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">This sūtra and the preceding one in the Ratnakūṭa section, both
                        often simply called <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>, are not to be confused with a
                        third sūtra of the same name in the General Sūtra (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>) section, Toh
                        149, a short work (also set in Rajagṛha) in which Maitreya asks a quite different question. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">The main Tibetan text used for the present translation was the Degé (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde
                            dge</title>) edition of the Kangyur. Other Kangyurs were also consulted but, apart from the one noted,
                        no significant variations were found. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="38">THE TRANSLATION</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="39">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="40">The Question of Maitreya on the Eight Qualities </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">
                        <ref cRef="F.116.b"/> Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was staying in Rājagṛha, on Vulture Peak Mountain,
                        together with a great saṅgha of 1,250 monks and 10,000 bodhisattvas. The Blessed One, surrounded by a
                        retinue of many hundreds of thousands, surveyed those before him, and taught the Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-13"/>
                    <p tid="14">At that time, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was present among that very retinue. He rose
                        from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, set his right knee on the ground, and paid
                        homage with palms joined toward the Blessed One. He then said to the Blessed One, “Would the Blessed One
                        please, if he has time, answer a certain question that I would like to put to the Tathāgata, the Arhat,
                        the perfectly enlightened Buddha?” </p>
                    <p tid="15">The Blessed One <ref cRef="F.117.a"/> answered the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya, you
                        may put to the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly enlightened Buddha whatever question you wish. What I
                        shall say in response to your question will cause you to rejoice.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">So, since the Blessed One had given him the opportunity, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya asked
                        the Blessed One, “Blessed One, how many qualities do bodhisattva mahāsattvas need to possess in order
                        to become irreversibly set on supreme and perfect enlightenment without regressing, without regressing in
                        the slightest, and to gain special attainments; to vanquish negative and hostile influences; and, while
                        engaging in the conduct of a bodhisattva, to realize the intrinsic characteristics of all phenomena just
                        as they are and therefore be indefatigable in saṃsāra? And, as well as having that indefatigable mind,
                        through the pristine awareness that does not rely on anything else,<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-48">Tentative translation of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhan gyi
                                kha na ma las pa’i ye shes</foreign>.</note> to awaken quickly to supreme, perfect enlightenment
                        and become a buddha?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Very good, Maitreya. It is good
                        that you have thought to ask the Tathāgata a question on this point. Therefore, Maitreya, listen well and
                        retain in your mind what I shall explain to you.” </p>
                    <p tid="18">“Blessed One, please do so,” said the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, and listened as the Blessed
                        One had instructed him. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-16"/>
                    <p tid="19">The Blessed One, in turn, continued, “Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess eight qualities, they
                        will become irreversibly set on supreme and perfect enlightenment <ref cRef="F.117.b"/> without
                        regressing, without regressing in the slightest, and will gain special attainments; they will vanquish
                        negative and hostile influences; and, while engaging in the conduct of a bodhisattva, they will realize the
                        intrinsic characteristics of all phenomena just as they are and therefore be indefatigable in saṃsāra.
                        And, as well as having that indefatigable mind, through the pristine awareness that does not rely on
                        anything else, they will quickly awaken to supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-17"/>
                    <p tid="20">“What are those eight qualities? Well, Maitreya, they are for bodhisattva mahāsattvas to have
                        excellent intention, excellent application, excellent giving, skill in dedicating merit, excellent
                        loving kindness, excellent compassion, skill in methods, and emancipation in the perfection of wisdom. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-18"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have excellent intention? Well, Maitreya, such
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas, whether they hear praises or slander of the Buddha, have the intention to attain
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment. Whether they hear praises or slander of the Dharma, they have the intention to
                        attain supreme, perfect enlightenment. Whether they hear praises or slander of the Saṅgha, they have the
                        intention to attain supreme, perfect enlightenment. This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattvas have excellent
                        intention. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-19"/>
                    <p tid="22">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have excellent application? Well, Maitreya, such
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas renounce killing, theft, <ref cRef="F.118.a"/> sexual misconduct, falsehood,
                        slander, harsh speech, and gossip. This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattva mahāsattvas have excellent
                        application. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-20"/>
                    <p tid="23">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have excellent giving? Well, Maitreya, such bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas give clothes, food, bedding, curative
                        medicines, and necessities to ascetics, brahmins, poor people, and beggars. Their generosity then becomes pure.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-49">The Degé and the other <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshal pa</title> Kangyurs
                            have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sbyin pa dag tu gyur pa yin te</foreign>. The Stok Palace
                            Kangyur has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sbyin bdag tu gyur pa yin te</foreign>, which would
                            mean “he becomes their benefactor.”</note> This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattvas have excellent
                        giving. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-21"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have skill in dedicating merit? Well, Maitreya, such
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas dedicate all the accumulations of roots of virtue that they have created through their                        body, speech, and mind to supreme, perfect enlightenment. This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas have skill in dedicating merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-22"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have excellent loving kindness? Well, Maitreya, such
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas’ physical actions are kind, their verbal actions are kind, and their mental actions
                        are kind. This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattva mahāsattvas have excellent loving kindness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-23"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattvas have excellent compassion? Well, Maitreya, the bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas’ physical actions are without malice, their verbal actions are without malice, and their mental
                        actions are without malice. <ref cRef="F.118.b"/> This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattvas have excellent
                        compassion. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattva mahāsattvas have skill in their methods? Well, Maitreya, such
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas are skilled in conventional truth, they are skilled in the absolute truth, and they are
                        skilled in both. This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattva mahāsattvas have skill in their methods. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-25"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Maitreya, how do such bodhisattva mahāsattvas have emancipation in the perfection of wisdom?
                        Well, Maitreya, such bodhisattva mahāsattvas correctly train as follows. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-26"/>
                    <p tid="29">“They think, ‘Because one thing exists, another one arises; because this is born, that is born.
                        Conditioned by ignorance, karmic formations come into being. Conditioned by karmic formations,
                        consciousness comes into being. Conditioned by consciousness, name and form come into being. Conditioned
                        by name and form, the six sources of perception come into being. Conditioned by the six sources of
                        perception, contact comes into being. Conditioned by contact, feeling comes into being. Conditioned by
                        feeling, craving comes into being. Conditioned by craving, grasping comes into being. Conditioned by
                        grasping, existence comes into being. Conditioned by existence, birth comes into being. Conditioned by
                        birth, aging and death come into being, as well as misery, lamentations, suffering, unhappiness, and
                        agitation. That is how this great heap of suffering comes into being; without these conditions, it does not come into being. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-27"/>
                    <p tid="30">“ ‘When these conditions cease to exist, it
                        also ceases. When ignorance ceases, karmic formations cease. When karmic formations cease, consciousness
                        ceases. When consciousness ceases, name and form cease. When name and form cease, the six sources of
                        perception cease. When the six sources of perception cease, contact ceases. When contact ceases, feeling
                            <ref cRef="F.119.a"/> ceases. When feeling ceases, craving ceases. When craving ceases, grasping
                        ceases. When grasping ceases, existence ceases. When existence ceases, birth ceases. When birth ceases,
                        aging, death, misery, lamentations, suffering, unhappiness, and agitation cease. That is how this great
                        heap of suffering ceases.’ This, Maitreya, is how the bodhisattva mahāsattvas have emancipation in the
                        perfection of wisdom. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-28"/>
                    <p tid="31">“Maitreya, if bodhisattva mahāsattvas possess those eight qualities, they will become
                        irreversibly set on supreme and perfect enlightenment without regressing, without regressing in the
                        slightest, and will gain special attainments; they will vanquish negative and hostile influences; and, while
                        engaging in the conduct of a bodhisattva, they will realize the intrinsic characteristics of all phenomena
                        just as they are and therefore be indefatigable in saṃsāra. And, as well as having that indefatigable
                        mind, through the pristine awareness that does not rely on anything else, they will quickly awaken to
                        supreme, perfect enlightenment and become a buddha.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-29"/>
                    <p tid="32">After the Blessed One had spoken these words, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, together with
                        the monks, as well as all the worlds of gods and men, demigods and gandharvas, rejoiced and praised what
                        the Blessed One had said. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="41">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-30"/>
                    <p tid="33">This concludes “The Question of Maitreya‌ on the Eight
                        Qualities,” the forty-second section of <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Dharma Discourse, the Great Heap of Jewels</title>, in one
                        hundred thousand sections. </p>
                    <p tid="34">The Indian scholars Jinamitra and Danaśila together with the chief editor and translator Yeshé Dé
                        translated, edited, corrected this text using the revised terminology, and finalized it. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="42">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="43">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-006-31">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>, Toh 86,
                        Degé Kangyur, vol. 44 (dkon brtsegs, cha), folios 116b –119a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-006-32">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo, bka’ ’gyur</title> (dpe
                            bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi
                        bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research
                        Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006-2009, vol. 44, pp. 323–329.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-044-006-33">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa byams pas zhus pa chos brgyad pa’i mdo</title>, Stok Palace Manuscript
                        Kangyur (stog pho brang bris ma), vol. 40, folios 198b–202b.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-34">
                            <term>perfection of wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-35">
                            <term>intrinsic characteristics</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngo bo nyid kyi mtshan nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངོ་བོ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མཚན་ཉིད།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-36">
                            <term>intention</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསམ་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-37">
                            <term>application</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyor ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱོར་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-38">
                            <term>giving</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཏོང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-39">
                            <term>emancipation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nges par byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངེས་པར་བྱུང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-40">
                            <term>malice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སེམས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-41">
                            <term>indefatigable</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skyo ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱོ་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-42">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-43">
                            <term>Country of the Bhargas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul bha rga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་བྷ་རྒ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bharga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-44">
                            <term>Mount Śuśumāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu srin byis pa gsod lta bu’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་སྲིན་བྱིས་པ་གསོད་ལྟ་བུའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śuśumāragiri</term>
                            <term type="definition">Sometimes has the alternative Sanskrit spelling Śiśumāragiri.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-044-006-45">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhra­kūta­parvata</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>