<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal rnam par rol pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­vikrīḍita</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Miraculous Play
                    of Mañjuśrī”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­mañjuśrī­vikrīḍita­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་འཇམ་དཔལ་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’jam dpal rnam par rol pa zhes
                    bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-32"> Translated by Jens
                    Erland Braarvig<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating
                    the Words of the Buddha. </author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-195">Jens Erland
                    Braarvig</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-196">David Welsh</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Tom
                    Tillemans</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso
                    Wilkinson</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-197">Fredrik Liland</editor>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-59">Benjamin
                    Collet-Cassart</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-262">David
                    Higgins</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">Dr. John
                    Canti</editor>



            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.3.2 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                    non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages,
                    and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-046-002"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-01-24</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh96" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 96</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 46 (mdo sde, kha), folios 217.a–241.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="50">
                        <volume number="46" start-page="433" end-page="482"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11647" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-03-09T20:50:00.244Z" user="admin">09/03/2020 20:50:00</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.1" date-time="2019-09-26T22:29:18.147Z" user="james"/>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2019-09-26T22:29:18.147Z" user="james">2.a</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="0.2" date-time="2019-09-27T12:08:43.224Z" user="mike">Testing out new version
                    notes</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.01" date-time="2019-10-03T14:48:51.794Z" user="laura">Initial markup and
                    proofing</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2019-10-03T14:48:51.794Z" user="laura">Initial markup and
                    proofing</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.1" date-time="2019-10-07T10:27:24.685Z" user="admin">Publication statement
                    updated</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.5.1" date-time="2019-10-18T19:49:20.446Z" user="john">v 0.5.1</note>
            
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.5.2" date-time="2020-01-06T21:53:27.549Z" user="laura">Laura integrated comments from DH and JC and added Pedurma ref.</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.9.1" date-time="2020-01-22T20:55:06.648Z" user="john">Further final editing by John, now ready.</note>
<note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1.a" date-time="2020-01-22T20:55:06.648Z" user="john">Further final editing by John, now ready.</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.9.2" date-time="2020-01-23T17:44:03.2Z" user="john">Publication date changed</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.1" date-time="2020-01-24T09:33:23.338Z" user="john">No changes, except to status</note>
<note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2020-01-24T09:33:23.338Z" user="john">No changes, except to status</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.2" date-time="2020-01-24T09:42:15.783Z" user="john">Corrected the first publication date to 2020</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.3" date-time="2020-01-25T15:57:56.285Z" user="john">Minor corrections (2) and additions.</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1.4" date-time="2020-02-21T12:36:45.044Z" user="admin">Incorrectly scoped xml:id values updated</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.2.1" date-time="2020-02-26T13:24:35.092Z" user="john">Added a paragraph to the intro and a glossary entry, both to do with the passage on rab tu 'byung ba.</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.3.1" date-time="2020-03-09T20:38:30.673Z" user="john">Embracing the ascetic life changed to going forth throughout</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.3.2" date-time="2020-03-09T20:49:57.759Z" user="john">Minor adjustment</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-1"/>
                <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title> presents 
                    a series of profound teachings within a rich narrative structure involving 
                    a beautiful courtesan’s daughter, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī. A banker’s son 
                    has purchased her favors, but while they are riding together toward a pleasure garden 
                    the girl’s attention is captivated instead by the radiantly attractive Mañjuśrī, 
                    who gives her instructions related to the meaning of the mind set on awakening. 
                    She then expresses her new understanding in a dialogue with Mañjuśrī, in the presence of 
                    King Ajātaśatru, his retinue, and the citizens of Rājagṛha. Meanwhile the banker’s son, 
                    with the help of Mañjuśrī and Śakra, experiences his own realization and receives teaching from the 
                    Buddha himself. The sūtra deals with well-known Mahāyāna themes, but places
                    special emphasis on the emptiness and sameness of all phenomena. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by Jens Erland Braarvig, and edited by David Welsh and Fredrik
                    Liland, at the University of Oslo. This translation was first published on the
                    site Bibliotheca Polyglotta by the Faculty of Humanities, University of Oslo,
                    together with an edition of the Tibetan by Jens Braarvig and the two Chinese
                    translations. The present version has been lightly edited and annotated by the
                84000 editorial team.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-3"/>
                <p tid="6">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title> is a typical
                    Mahāyāna sūtra in the sense that it presents a teaching on the standard Buddhist
                    themes of impermanence and the drawbacks of sensual desires within a narrative
                    framework emphasizing Mahāyāna principles of emptiness and compassion. These
                    teachings are embedded within an interesting frame story, also not unusual for
                    the Mahāyāna style, depicting a person who is otherwise not supposed to be
                    particularly saintly: a courtesan's daughter named 
                    Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-571" index="1">The Tibetan for 
                        “a courtesan’s daughter” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smad ’tshong ma’i bu mo</foreign>) 
                        could also be interpreted as “a girl who was a courtesan.” Her 
                        name in Sanskrit is reconstructed from the Tibetan 
                        (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser mchog ’od dpal</foreign>) and not attested in any manuscript. 
                        For detailed notes on both points see Braarvig 
                        2010, <ref target="https://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=record&amp;vid=20&amp;mid=182032#Nrn1">notes 1 
                            and 2</ref> in the translation text.</note> </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-538"/>
                <p tid="6">This girl, the most beautiful of girls, whose skin shines with a golden hue, is
                    courted by all the boys in the city. One, the banker’s son Bhayadatta (Given to
                    Fear), purchases her favors, but as soon as the girl sees the princely Mañjuśrī, she
                    instantly falls for him instead. The god of riches, Vaiśravaṇa, then appears,
                    introduces Mañjuśrī by name, and, in answer to the girl’s questions, explains what a
                        bodhisatva<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-9" index="2"> We prefer
                        to follow the mainstream Buddhist Sanskrit usage of manuscripts and
                        inscriptions by spelling <distinct>bodhisatva</distinct> with a single
                        rather than a double <distinct>t</distinct>, the latter being a convention
                        of modern editors. See Bhattacharya (2010). Note that this is also the
                        spelling used in Gāndhārī, as well as in Khotanese, in Tibetan lexicography,
                        and in old Thai documents.</note> is. Mañjuśrī is clad in a fine white garment,
                    as is usual for laymen, and the girl asks the bodhisatva whether she can have
                    it. Yes, says the great figure, “if you develop the mind of
                    awakening.” When the courtesan’s daughter asks what that is, Mañjuśrī answers “you
                    yourself are awakening,” and that “all beings are included in awakening.” He goes on to
                list in great detail all the various constituents of mind and body and to equate them 
                all with awakening, in much the same way that the Prajñāpāramitā texts go through so 
                many of the factors identified in the Abhidharma and point to their lack of intrinsic existence.  </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-539"/>
                <p tid="6">Mañjuśrī’s teaching on awakening here accords with the Mahāyāna conviction that truth and awakening are not found in
                    some theoretical system, but in what we are as human beings and in compassionate
                    action toward our fellow beings, whatever their class or status. In this
                    way, the sūtra also goes to great lengths to argue for universal sameness. As
                    elsewhere in the Mahāyāna scriptures, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirvāṇa</foreign> 
                    is the same as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saṃsāra</foreign>, 
                    and so even the afflicted mental states are really the
                    same as awakening—prefiguring a tantric world view. As our text says, “The
                    afflicted mental states are also the adamantine basis of awakening.” This is
                    because understanding the afflicted mental states is in fact awakening. The way
                    to get rid of the afflicted mental states is to understand their emptiness.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-540"/>
                    <p tid="6">Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī now demonstrates her new understanding in public, 
                        in a dialogue with Mañjuśrī that takes place the presence of King Ajātaśatru, 
                        his entire retinue of women and warriors, and the citizens of Rājagṛha.
                    It is even acknowledged by the Buddha himself, who is taking a walk with Ānanda
                    on the slopes of Vulture Peak. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-579"/>
                <p tid="6">Having attained a level of realization, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī feels she should
                    abandon her worldly, laywoman’s life and “go forth,” i.e. take vows as a nun. In an
                    important passage (<ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-192"/> <foreign xml:lang="la">et seq</foreign>.)
                    Mañjuśrī outlines the deeper, inner meanings of going forth for a bodhisatva, and inspires
                    five hundred bodhisatvas to go forth themselves. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-4"/>
                <p tid="7">Having now met the beautiful Mañjuśrī, adopted his teaching, and attained
                    a higher goal in life, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī decides to teach her male friends
                    about the mind of awakening. As a consequence of this, she follows the Mahāyāna
                    call to work tirelessly for the education and welfare of our fellow beings, and
                    thus, in the park where she has gone to amuse herself with the banker’s son,
                    Bhayadatta, she transforms herself into a rotting corpse in accord with the
                    tradition of meditation practice in which one contemplates how this
                    frail human body ends up as a rotting cadaver. Bhayadatta, seeing his beautiful companion
                    thus transformed, is filled with great abhorrence, and then fear—as
                    befits his name. He is afraid not only of the ghastly sight before him but also
                    of being punished by the king’s men, and so he tries to flee the scene and get rid of
                    the corpse, which had been a beautiful girl only a few moments before. At this
                    crucial juncture, the surrounding forest resounds with teachings on impermanence
                    and the illusory nature of phenomena, and with Śakra’s help Bhayadatta turns to the Buddha for
                    guidance. A dialogue ensues between Mañjuśrī and the Blessed One on general
                    Mahāyāna themes. The girl is also present—her death was only a magical creation
                    and an expedient means employed to educate the fearful boy. The boy then seeks
                    refuge in the only reliable and lasting refuge, namely the Blessed One himself,
                    who confirms by his teachings to him that the bodhisatva does indeed seek
                    awakening by seeking the essence of desire, and that fear is just an illusion
                    grounded in attachment to the false idea of a self, just as had been argued in
                    the previous dialogues. The Buddha prophesies Bhayadatta’s future buddhahood.</p>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-5"/>
                <p tid="8">The Sanskrit title of the sūtra, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­vikrīḍita</title>, 
                    literally means “Mañjuśrī’s Amusement”—the verb
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">krīḍ</foreign>- (and thus also
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vikrīḍ</foreign>-) means to amuse
                    oneself and to have fun, but here also to play with the supernatural knowledges
                    and states of meditation. This word also often has a sexual connotation.
                    Mañjuśrī’s games, however, have as their purpose the education of all living beings about awakening
                    and the mind of awakening, and so even the flirtatious games of a courtesan may be
                    transformed into those of a bodhisatva. But although this sūtra might thus appear to be
                    directed mainly toward a lay audience, with the girl even asking in
                    which religious group (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gaṇa</foreign>)
                    the Mahāyāna teachings are to be found—evidently referring to a lay group rather
                    than the saṅgha—its emphasis is on the importance of real engagement and 
                    inner transformation rather than on advocating any particular outer lifestyle. 
                    As Mañjuśrī says, in tune with the message of the text, when his new
                    pupil asks him to help her adopt the monastic way of life (<ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-569"/>), “It is like this,
                    sister. Shaving the hair on your head is not equivalent to going forth as it pertains to 
                    the bodhisatva. Why not? Girl, bodhisatvas go forth
                    by means of the effort to eliminate the afflicted mental states of
                    all beings.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-542"/>
                <p tid="6">The ideal set out here is to engage compassionately in ordinary
                    life with all its imperfections rather than to retreat into isolation.
                    The obligation of the bodhisatva that is espoused here is to practice the
                    altruistic social virtues of compassion, friendliness, and so forth, rather than
                    leading a silent life of meditation. This takes us to the core of the Mahāyāna
                    ideology, shared by a great number of Mahāyāna sūtras: Anyone—courtesans
                    or powerful laymen, even those living licentious lives—may be 
                    great bodhisatvas who have sought such rebirths for the sake of their fellow
                    beings. Birth is really an illusion, suffering is really emptiness, and great
                    compassion is the means by which to reach this radical acceptance, this
                    understanding, which is the same as awakening. </p>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-6"/>
                <p tid="6">The sūtra seems to have been relatively well known in India, being cited in a 
                    number of Indian treatises. Apart from these fragmentary citations,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-558" index="3">See <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-547"/> and <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-550"/>.</note> however, no Sanskrit version 
                    has yet come to light. The text was translated from Sanskrit into Chinese by Dharmarakṣa in 314 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> (Taishō 817) and by Narendrayaśas in 583 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> (Taishō 818). The Tibetan translation (also from the Sanskrit) was made by Surendrabodhi and Yeshé Dé in the late eighth or early ninth century, and is mentioned in the two inventories of translated texts from the imperial period dated to the first decades of the ninth century.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-555"/>
                <p tid="6">The sūtra’s placement, at least in Kangyurs of the Tshalpa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshal pa</foreign>) lineage, among the first few works in the General Sūtra section suggests that it was held in high esteem. Several of its passages are widely quoted in the Tibetan commentarial literature, and its statement about the destructive effect of anger on stores of merit (<ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-173"/>) is particularly well known.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-559" index="4">Many of the citations come from Mañjuśrī’s questioning of the girl, <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-127"/> to <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-189"/>.</note>
                </p>
                <lb/>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-543"/>
                <p tid="9">In producing this translation, we have based our work on the edited
                    Tibetan text published at the Bibliotheca Polyglotta, University of Oslo (Braarvig
                    2010), in consultation with the two Chinese translations,
                    which are also reproduced there and aligned with the Tibetan. Comprehensive notes detailing 
                    the variant readings of the Tibetan text in different Kangyurs can be found in that 
                    edition and have not been reproduced here.</p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="10"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="507">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="12">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-7"/>
                    <p tid="14">
                        <ref type="folio" cRef="F.217.a"/>
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisatvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-8"/>
                    <p tid="15">Thus
                        did I hear at one time. Once, the Blessed One was staying at Vulture Peak in
                        Rājagṛha with a great community of some five hundred monks, and with eight
                        thousand bodhisatvas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-10" index="5"> Here the Chinese (Taishō 817) adds the following: “All of the bodhisatvas
                            were great beings, having acquired the powers of memory and immeasurable
                            eloquence. Whatever discursive knowledge they might establish was the
                            noble knowledge of the three gates of liberation. Their knowledge was
                            unobstructed in the three worlds. Their concentration was undisturbed,
                            and they had perfected the ten powers and fearlessness.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-11"/>
                    <p tid="16">At that time, a courtesan’s daughter, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-576" index="6">See <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-571"/>.</note> who was
                        beautiful, charming, and attractive, was living in the great city of
                        Rājagṛha. Her beautiful complexion was the most abundant of her riches.
                        Because of the roots of virtue she had previously developed, that girl,
                        whose body was the color of gold, was illumined by a light of a similar
                        golden color wherever she stood, sat, or walked. Whatever clothes she put
                        on, whether they were red or white, would shine with precisely the same
                        golden color. That girl was a beloved and comforting friend to all people,
                        and they never tired of looking at her. She had such gentle speech—tender,
                        soft, sweet, and pleasant—and her ever-smiling face, never bunched up in
                        anger, won the respect of all. There was no harshness or roughness in her.
                        All the young princes, the young sons of ministers, the young sons of
                        bankers, and the young sons of householders in the great city of Rājagṛha
                        desired her greatly. She was always in their thoughts, and no matter how
                        much they saw of her, they were never satisfied. Wherever that courtesan’s
                        daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī went—to gardens, to rivers, to lotus ponds,
                        to houses, to boulevards, or to marketplaces—men, women, boys, and girls
                        assembled and followed her out of curiosity. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.217.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-12"/>
                    <p tid="17">One day, a banker’s son named Bhayadatta used some of his wealth to
                        hire the courtesan's daughter, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī. Setting out for a
                        garden, they sat down on a pleasant seat that had been prepared for them in
                        a carriage drawn by four horses, which was decorated with jewels, pearls,
                        cat’s eye gems, and gold, with raised parasols, flags, and banners. It was
                        adorned with flowers, incense, perfume, aromatic powder, and garlands, and
                        its windows were adorned with campaka flowers. The carriage was drawn along
                        by people in front whose thoughts were devoted only to playing around and
                        having fun, accompanied by cymbals and drums, and everyone behind it carried
                        all kinds of things for enjoyment and pleasure. A great crowd of people
                        followed, intent on seeing the woman who so aroused their curiosity, and
                        thus they arrived in the garden.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-13"/>
                    <p tid="18">It was at this time that the princely Mañjuśrī emerged from his
                        meditative absorption. Feeling great compassion for all living beings, he
                        thought, “Who are the living beings, suitable for training, who can be
                        brought to maturity in this Great Vehicle by means of miraculous displays,
                        the miracle of teachings, or the miracle of admonition?” The princely
                        Mañjuśrī saw the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī riding in the
                        carriage with the banker’s son Bhayadatta toward the park. When he saw
                        her, he considered how strong and vigorous she was with regard to her
                        readiness to be trained, and he became aware that she possessed the power of
                        the roots of virtue she had previously
                        developed and the capacity to understand
                        the teachings. So the princely Mañjuśrī produced a miraculous display, a
                        miracle by means of which, as soon as he showed himself, he would outshine
                        even the light of the sun and moon, let alone other sentient beings. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.218.a"/> Revealing just such an embodiment, he
                        appeared clad in all kinds of jewelry and a luminous garment, the luster of
                        which lit up a circular area a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yojana</foreign> across.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-14"/>
                    <p tid="19">Then the princely Mañjuśrī, clothed in that garment and adorned with
                        all that jewelry, placed himself facing the road on which the courtesan’s
                        daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī was traveling. As soon as the princely
                        Mañjuśrī had placed himself there, the carriage belonging to the banker’s
                        son was darkened, as was the whole of the courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī’s body. Just as a piece of cloth soaked with ink
                        would not shine, would not be bright, and would not be radiant if one were
                        to place it next to gold from the Jambu River, in the same way the girl’s
                        body did not shine, was not bright, and was not radiant when the light from
                        the body of the princely Mañjuśrī touched it. The courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī saw the princely Mañjuśrī standing there, looking like
                        a god, his body adorned with jewelry and clothed in his shining garment, and
                        she saw too the light emanating from his garment. As soon as she had seen
                        him, a feeling of contempt for her own body, a feeling of inferiority, arose
                        in her, and she wanted to possess his garment. She thought, “I have had
                        enough of this banker’s son. I will get down from this carriage to amuse
                        myself with, play with, and tease this man instead. Then I can ask him for
                        his garment.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-15"/>
                    <p tid="20">As soon as the girl had these thoughts, however, the great divine
                        king Vaiśravaṇa, who had transformed himself into a man with the help of the
                        magic of the princely Mañjuśrī, said to her, “Young lady, do not think
                        passionate thoughts about this good man! Why not? Because he never seeks
                        pleasure.” <ref type="folio" cRef="F.218.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-16"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Who is he? What is his name?” asked the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="22">“He is a bodhisatva,” Vaiśravaṇa answered, “and he is called the
                        princely Mañjuśrī.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-18"/>
                    <p tid="23">“But what is a bodhisatva?” asked the girl. “Is it a god, or is it a
                        nāga, a yakṣa, a gandharva, a demigod, a garuḍa, a kiṃnara, a mahoraga,
                        Śakra, Brahmā, a protector of the world, or a great king? What is a
                        bodhisatva?” </p>

                    <p tid="24">Vaiśravaṇa replied, “Young lady, a bodhisatva is not a god, a nāga,
                        a yakṣa, a gandharva, a demigod, a garuḍa, a kiṃnara, a mahoraga, Śakra,
                        Brahmā, a protector of the world, or a great king. Young lady, he is called
                        a bodhisatva because he completely fulfills the wishes of all beings. He is
                        called a bodhisatva because he gives to all who ask and does not send
                        anybody away.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-20"/>
                    <p tid="25">Then the girl thought, “So, according to what I've been told,
                        Mañjuśrī will give me his garment.” After the courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī had alighted from the carriage, she spoke to the
                        princely Mañjuśrī: “Mañjuśrī, please give me the garment in which your body
                        is clothed.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-21"/>
                    <p tid="26">She then spoke the following verse:</p>

                    <lg tid="459">
                        <l>“If you have entered awakening, Mañjughoṣa, </l>
                        <l>Please give me this garment. </l>
                        <l>An ungenerous bodhisatva is not attractive. </l>
                        <l>He is like a dry river with no water.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-26"/>
                    <p tid="31">Mañjuśrī replied, “If you enter awakening, young lady, I will give you
                        this garment right away, because the whole world with its gods considers
                        those who unswervingly maintain the mind of awakening to be worthy of
                        offerings.” <ref type="folio" cRef="F.219.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-27"/>
                    <p tid="32">The girl then asked the following in verse:</p>

                    <lg tid="460">
                        <l>“So what, then, is the meaning of the word
                            <distinct>awakening</distinct>? </l>
                        <l>From whom is it attained? Who will grant it? </l>
                        <l>In which religious groups is it taught? </l>
                        <l>Let those who are not clever, those without understanding,
                            understand!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-32"/>
                    <p tid="37">Mañjuśrī said, “Sister, <distinct>awakening</distinct> refers to the
                        inexpressible, the absence of letters, the freedom from the aggregates, the
                        sensory elements, and the sense sources, emptiness, the freedom from marks, the
                        absence of afflictions, peace, tranquility, and complete pacification.”<note xml:id="UT22084-046-002-551" place="end" index="7">This paragraph is probably a later addition, since it is not found in either of the Chinese versions. In the Chinese versions, the section of the text above, <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-21"/> to here, is placed between <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-38"/> and <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-544"/>, which seems to follow more clearly the logic of the narrative.</note>
                    </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-552"/>
                    <p tid="38">The princely Mañjuśrī continued, “Sister, if you develop the mind of
                        awakening, then I will give you this garment.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-34"/>
                    <p tid="39">“What is <distinct>awakening</distinct>,
                        Mañjuśrī?” asked the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="40">“Sister,” replied Mañjuśrī, “you yourself are awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-36"/>
                    <p tid="41">“How am I awakening, Mañjuśrī?” asked the girl. “I don’t understand
                        the meaning of what you have said.”</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-544"/>
                    <p tid="42">“Sister,” replied Mañjuśrī, “this is the Dharma teaching of the
                        current Tathāgata, the worthy one, the perfectly awakened one named
                        Śākyamuni: ‘Just as the body partakes in universal sameness, awakening too
                        partakes in universal sameness. Just as awakening partakes in universal
                        sameness, the body too partakes in universal sameness.’ Therefore, I say to
                        you, sister: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ What is your opinion, sister? Is
                        this body of yours made up of the aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense
                        sources?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-38"/>
                    <p tid="43">When the girl had heard this teaching, the light of the Dharma was
                        born in her as the result of the roots of virtue she had previously
                        developed, and when she had attained that light, she said to Mañjuśrī, “Just
                        so, Mañjuśrī, this body of mine is made up of the aggregates, the sensory elements,
                        and the sense sources.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-39"/>
                    <p tid="44">“What is your opinion, sister?” asked Mañjuśrī. “Does form have
                        mental activity or consciousness?” <ref type="folio" cRef="F.219.b"/>
                    </p>

                    <p tid="45">“Not at all, Mañjuśrī,” replied the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-41"/>
                    <p tid="46">“Awakening too, sister, has no mental activity or consciousness,”
                        said Mañjuśrī. “Therefore, sister, just as form partakes in universal
                        sameness, awakening too partakes in universal sameness. Just as awakening
                        partakes in universal sameness, form too partakes in universal sameness.
                        Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-42"/>
                    <p tid="47">“But sister, what is your opinion? Do feelings, perception,
                        conditioning, or consciousness have mental activity or consciousness?”</p>

                    <p tid="48">“Not at all, Mañjuśrī,” replied the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-44"/>
                    <p tid="49">“Awakening too, sister, has no mental activity or consciousness,”
                        said Mañjuśrī. “Therefore, sister, just as consciousness partakes in
                        universal sameness, awakening too partakes in universal sameness. Just as
                        awakening partakes in universal sameness, consciousness too partakes in
                        universal sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are
                        awakening.’ ” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-45"/>
                    <p tid="50">Mañjuśrī then asked, “What, sister, is your opinion? Is form
                        something inner or outer, or is it both? Is form blue, yellow, red, or
                        white? Is it the color of saffron, crystal, or silver? Can it be shown to be
                        found in any place or direction?” </p>

                    <p tid="51">“Not at all, Mañjuśrī,” replied the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-47"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Awakening too, sister, is not something inner or outer, or both,”
                        said Mañjuśrī. “It is not blue, yellow, red, or white; it does not have the
                        color of saffron, crystal, or silver; and it cannot be shown to be found in
                        any place or direction. Therefore, sister, just as form partakes in
                        universal sameness, awakening too partakes in universal sameness. Just as
                        awakening partakes in universal sameness, form too partakes in universal
                        sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-48"/>
                    <p tid="53">“Likewise, sister, are feelings, perception, conditioning, and
                        consciousness inner or outer, or are they both? Is consciousness blue,
                        yellow, red, or white? Is it the color of saffron, crystal, or silver? <ref type="folio" cRef="F.220.a"/> Can it be shown to be found in any place
                        or direction?”</p>

                    <p tid="54">“Not at all, Mañjuśrī,” replied the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-50"/>
                    <p tid="55">“Awakening too, sister, is not something inner or outer, or both,”
                        said Mañjuśrī. “It is not blue, yellow, red, or white; it does not have the
                        color of saffron, crystal, or silver; and it cannot be shown to be found in
                        any place or direction. Therefore, sister, just as consciousness partakes in
                        universal sameness, awakening too partakes in universal sameness. Just as
                        awakening partakes in universal sameness, consciousness too partakes in
                        universal sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are
                        awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-51"/>
                    <p tid="56">“Further, sister, the five aggregates are like a magical creation.
                        They are nonexistent. They arise from misunderstanding and are nonexistent.
                        They are an erroneous conventional expression. Awakening too is like a
                        magical creation, nothing but a nonexistent and misleading conventional
                        expression. Therefore, sister, just as a magical creation partakes in
                        universal sameness, the aggregates partake in universal sameness. Just as
                        the aggregates partake in universal sameness, a magical creation partakes in
                        universal sameness. Just as a magical creation partakes in universal
                        sameness, awakening partakes in universal sameness. Just as awakening
                        partakes in universal sameness, a magical creation partakes in universal
                        sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-52"/>
                    <p tid="57">“Further, sister, the five aggregates are like a dream, which is not
                        really happening. Awakening too has the nature of a dream, which is not
                        really happening. Therefore, sister, just as a dream partakes in universal
                        sameness, the aggregates partake in universal sameness. Just as the
                        aggregates partake in universal sameness, a dream partakes in universal
                        sameness. Just as a dream partakes in universal sameness, awakening partakes
                        in universal sameness. Just as awakening partakes in universal sameness, a
                        dream partakes in universal sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You
                        yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-53"/>
                    <p tid="58">“Further, sister, the five aggregates are like a mirage, which is
                        brought about by illusory action. Awakening too has the nature of a mirage,
                        as it is beyond the maturation of action. Therefore, sister, just as a
                        mirage partakes in universal sameness, the aggregates partake in universal
                        sameness. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.220.b"/> Just as the aggregates partake
                        in universal sameness, a mirage partakes in universal sameness. Just as a
                        mirage partakes in universal sameness, awakening partakes in universal
                        sameness. Just as awakening partakes in universal sameness, a mirage
                        partakes in universal sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You
                        yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-54"/>
                    <p tid="59">“Further, sister, the five aggregates are like reflections in a
                        mirror: they do not change as long as the object that is mirrored is not
                        changed. Awakening too has the nature of reflections in a mirror: it does
                        not change. Therefore, sister, just as reflections in a mirror partake in
                        universal sameness, the aggregates partake in universal sameness. Just as
                        the aggregates partake in universal sameness, reflections in a mirror
                        partake in universal sameness. Just as reflections in a mirror partake in
                        universal sameness, awakening partakes in universal sameness. Just as
                        awakening partakes in universal sameness, reflections in a mirror partake in
                        universal sameness. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are
                        awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-55"/>
                    <p tid="60">“Further, sister, the five aggregates are just words, and those words are
                        of an unwavering nature. Awakening too, sister, is just a word, and that
                        word is unwavering. Therefore, sister, just as the unwavering partakes in
                        universal sameness, the aggregates partake in universal sameness. Just as
                        the aggregates partake in universal sameness, the unwavering partakes in
                        universal sameness. Just as the unwavering partakes in universal sameness,
                        awakening partakes in universal sameness. Just as awakening partakes in
                        universal sameness, the unwavering partakes in universal sameness.
                        Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-56"/>
                    <p tid="61">“Further, sister, among the aggregates there is no subject that
                        acts, and the meaning of being uncreated is awakening. Among the aggregates
                        there is no essential nature, and the meaning of being without any essential
                        nature is awakening. Among the aggregates there is no origination, and the
                        meaning of being without origination is awakening. Among the aggregates
                        there is no permanence, and the meaning of impermanence is awakening. Among
                        the aggregates there is no happiness, and the meaning of suffering is
                        awakening. Among the aggregates there is nothing pure, and the meaning of
                        impurity is awakening. Among the aggregates there is no self, and the
                        meaning of selflessness is awakening. Further, sister, among the aggregates
                        there is no development, and the meaning of being beyond development is
                        awakening. The aggregates are void, and the meaning of being void is
                        awakening. Among the aggregates there is nothing to grasp, and the meaning
                        of being beyond grasping is awakening. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.221.a"/>
                        Among the aggregates there is no support, and the meaning of being without
                        support is awakening. Among the aggregates there is no coming or going, and
                        the meaning of being beyond coming and going is awakening. Among the
                        aggregates there is nothing that remains in the present, and the meaning of
                        not remaining in the present is awakening. Further, sister, the aggregates
                        are only a pious conventional expression, and awakening too is a pious
                        conventional expression. The aggregates are essentially beyond conventional
                        expressions, and awakening too is beyond conventional expressions. The
                        essential nature of the five aggregates is the essential nature of all the
                        phenomena penetrated by the Tathāgata, and that is awakening. In this way,
                        sister, the essential nature of the aggregates is the essential nature of
                        awakening, and the essential nature of awakening is the essential nature of
                        all phenomena. Sister, the essential nature of the five aggregates, and the
                        essential nature of awakening, is the essential nature of all beings.
                        Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-57"/>
                    <p tid="62">“Further, sister, the understanding of the aggregates is undoubtedly
                        awakening. There is no real understanding that does not include the
                        aggregates. There is no real understanding that does not include awakening.
                        Thus, understanding is awakening. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You
                        yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-58"/>
                    <p tid="63">“Sister, you should understand this teaching in this way: just as
                        all beings are included in awakening, that teaching that is not included in
                        anything is awakening. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are
                        awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-59"/>
                    <p tid="64">“Further, sister, in this body of yours, the four <term type="ignore">elements</term> are produced, namely, the element of
                        earth, the element of water, the element of fire, and the element of wind.
                        Moreover, sister, the element of earth is not a self, not a sentient being,
                        not a life principle, not a soul, and not an individual who is reborn;
                        awakening too is not a self, not a sentient being, not a life principle, not
                        a soul, and not an individual who is reborn. Thus, the element of water, the
                        element of fire, and the element of wind too are not a self, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.221.b"/> not a sentient being, not a life
                        principle, not a soul, and not an individual who is reborn. Awakening too is
                        not a self, not a sentient being, not a life principle, not a soul, and not
                        an individual who is reborn. The element of earth and awakening are the same
                        because of their absolute sameness with empty space. The element of water
                        and awakening are the same because of their absolute nonexistence. The
                        element of fire and awakening are the same because they are totally
                        unwavering. The element of wind and awakening are the same because they are
                        totally indefinable. The element of earth, sister, is known and understood
                        by the Tathāgata. The element of water, sister, is known and understood by
                        the Tathāgata. The element of fire, sister, is known and understood by the
                        Tathāgata. The element of wind, sister, is known and understood by the
                        Tathāgata. Further, sister, to understand the element of earth is awakening.
                        Thus, sister, to understand the element of water, the element of fire, and
                        the element of wind is awakening. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You
                        yourself are awakening.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-60"/>
                    <p tid="65">“Sister, the element of earth does not know the element of water.
                        The element of water does not know the element of fire. The element of fire
                        does not know the element of wind. In this way, sister, thorough knowledge
                        of the word <distinct>element</distinct> is called awakening. Therefore,
                        sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-61"/>
                    <p tid="66">“Further, sister, the eye is produced in this body of yours, and in
                        the same way the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body, and the mind are
                        produced. But sister, the eye is empty, and the essential nature of the eye,
                        being emptiness, is awakening. But sister, the ear is empty, and the
                        essential nature of the ear, being emptiness, is awakening. But sister, the
                        nose is empty, and the essential nature of the nose, being emptiness, is
                        awakening. But sister, the tongue is empty, and the essential nature of the
                        tongue, being emptiness, is awakening. But sister, the body is empty, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.222.a"/> and the essential nature of the body,
                        being emptiness, is awakening. But sister, the mind is empty, and the
                        essential nature of the mind, being emptiness, is awakening. Therefore,
                        sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-62"/>
                    <p tid="67">“Further, sister, the emptiness of the eye is not amenable to
                        conceptual imputation as ‘form,’ and the essential nature of empty form is
                        awakening. The emptiness of the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body, and the
                        mind is not amenable to conceptual imputation as ‘mental phenomena,’ and the
                        essential nature of empty mental phenomena is awakening. Therefore, sister,
                        I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ Thus, sister, the eye does not
                        grasp form, just as awakening does not grasp form; the ear does not grasp
                        sounds, just as awakening does not grasp sounds; the nose does not grasp
                        smells, just as awakening does not grasp smells; the tongue does not grasp
                        tastes, just as awakening does not grasp tastes; and the mind does not grasp
                        mental phenomena, just as awakening does not grasp mental phenomena.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-63"/>
                    <p tid="68">“What, sister, is the reason for this? The eye that is not connected
                        to form is awakening, and, similarly with the other senses, the mind that is
                        not connected to mental phenomena is awakening. Thus, sister, the sensory element
                        of eye consciousness is not connected to the sensory element of form, and the
                        sensory element of eye consciousness that is not connected to form is awakening. The
                        sensory element of ear consciousness is not connected to the sensory element of sound, and
                        the sensory element of ear consciousness that is not connected to sound is
                        awakening. The sensory element of nose consciousness is not connected to the sensory element
                        of smell, and the sensory element of nose consciousness that is not connected to
                        smell is awakening. The sensory element of tongue consciousness is not connected to
                        the sensory element of taste, and the sensory element of tongue consciousness that is not
                        connected to taste is awakening. The sensory element of body consciousness is not
                        connected to the sensory element of physical objects, and the sensory element of body
                        consciousness that is not connected to physical objects is awakening. The
                        sensory element of mind consciousness is not connected to the sensory element of mental
                        phenomena, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.222.b"/> and the sensory element of mind
                        consciousness that is not connected to mental phenomena is awakening.
                        Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-64"/>
                    <p tid="69">“Thus, sister, awakening and the sensory element of eye consciousness are
                        beyond duality and not distinguishable as two entities. Awakening and the
                        sensory element of form are beyond duality and not distinguishable as two entities.
                        As awakening and the sensory element of mind are beyond duality and not
                        distinguishable as two entities, awakening and the sensory element of mental
                        phenomena are beyond duality and not distinguishable as two entities.
                        Awakening and the sensory element of mind consciousness are beyond duality and not
                        distinguishable as two entities. Therefore, sister, I say to you: ‘You
                        yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-65"/>
                    <p tid="70">“Further, sister, understand that the eye is awakening. Similarly,
                        understand that the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body, and the mind are
                        awakening. The essential nature of the eye is empty, and this empty
                        essential nature is awakening. Similarly, the essential nature of the ear,
                        the nose, the tongue, the body, and the mind is empty, and this empty
                        essential nature is awakening. Sister, the essential nature of the eye is
                        beyond desire, aversion, and bewilderment, and that which is without desire,
                        aversion, and bewilderment is awakening. The essential nature of the ear,
                        the nose, the tongue, the body, and the mind is beyond desire, aversion, and
                        bewilderment, and that which is without desire, aversion, and bewilderment
                        is awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-66"/>
                    <p tid="71">“Sister, the eye has no owner, nothing that is owned, and no state
                        of ownership. Awakening too has no owner, nothing that is owned, and no
                        state of ownership. In the same way, the ear, the nose, the tongue, the
                        body, and the mind have no owner, nothing that is owned, and no state of
                        ownership.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-67"/>
                    <p tid="72">“Sister, the eye is not connected to the state of being a man, and
                        it is not connected to the state of a being a woman; <ref type="folio" cRef="F.223.a"/> nor, sister, is awakening connected to the
                        state of being a man, or connected to the state of a being a
                        woman. Similarly, sister, the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body, and
                        the mind are not connected to the state of being a man, and are not
                        connected to the state of a being a woman; nor, sister, is awakening
                        connected to the state of being a man, or connected to the
                        state of a being a woman. Sister, the eye is not a man, and it is not a
                        woman; nor, sister, is awakening a man, or a woman. In
                        the same way, sister, the mind is not a man, and it is not a woman, and,
                        sister, awakening is not a man, and it is not a woman. Sister, this is how
                        the Tathāgata understands the reality of the eye, and this understanding is
                        awakening. The Tathāgata understands the reality of the mind in the same
                        way, and this understanding is awakening. Therefore, sister, I say to you:
                        ‘You yourself are awakening.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-68"/>
                    <p tid="73">“Further, sister, this body of yours is not a self, not a sentient
                        being, not a life principle, not a soul, not a person, not a human being,
                        not a man, not a creator, not a subject of feeling, knowing, hearing,
                        smelling, tasting, or touching, nor is it a subject of consciousness.
                        Sister, awakening too is not a self, not a sentient being, not a life
                        principle, not a soul, not a personality, not a human being, not a man, not
                        a creator, not a subject of feeling, knowing, hearing, smelling, tasting, or
                        touching, nor is it a subject of consciousness. Thus, sister, the universal
                        sameness of all phenomena is awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-69"/>
                    <p tid="74">“Sister, this body of yours is without mobility, without a subject that
                        acts, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.223.b"/> and without permanence. It is not
                        distinct or different from grass, wood, trees, and building materials of
                        stone. Also, sister, the inner element of earth and the outer element of
                        earth are not two and are not distinguishable as two entities. As such, they
                        have the one characteristic of being without characteristics when they are
                        understood by the Tathāgata through his insight and knowledge. Therefore,
                        sister, I say to you: ‘You yourself are awakening.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-70"/>
                    <p tid="75">“Moreover, sister, the intention by which we have representations of
                        thought, mind, and consciousness, and these representations of thought,
                        mind, and consciousness themselves, are not found in the hair. They do not
                        abide in the hair of the body, nor in the cuticles, nor in the skin, nor in
                        the flesh, nor in the blood, nor in the bones, nor in the sinews, nor in the
                        marrow. They do not abide inside, nor outside, nor neither inside nor
                        outside. They do not abide in the eye, nor in the ear, nor in the nose, nor
                        in the tongue, nor in the body, nor in the mind. They do not abide, nor do
                        they not abide. They are not discontinuous, and do not abide in any location
                        or direction. They are without form, not demonstrable, beyond
                        representation, ungraspable, unmixed, without basis, pure, clean, and
                        brilliant. That representation of thought and mind is beyond the impurity of
                        afflicted mental states and also beyond purification. It is because it is
                        not embodied, in being essentially pure and brilliant, that it is beyond the
                        impurity of afflicted mental states and also beyond purification.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-71"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Thus, sister, the essential nature of the aggregates, the sensory elements,
                        and the sense sources is awakening, and the essential nature of awakening is
                        the aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense sources. Also, sister, the
                        aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense sources as developed in your body
                        are awakening. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.224.a"/> Awakening is nothing else.
                        Why is this? Awakening is nothing other than the aggregates, the sensory elements,
                        and the sense sources. These are indeed awakening, because to understand the
                        sameness of all phenomena is awakening. Therefore, sister, I say to you:
                        ‘You yourself are awakening.’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-72"/>
                    <p tid="77">When the princely Mañjuśrī had given this teaching, five hundred
                        gods in the heavens developed the mind of incomparable, perfect awakening.
                        Among the men, women, boys, and girls in Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī’s entourage,
                        two hundred developed the mind of incomparable, perfect awakening. Sixty
                        gods and humans too attained the stainless, impeccable, pure vision of
                        phenomena.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-73"/>
                    <p tid="78">The courtesan Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī was content and elated,
                        delighted and joyful. Joy and good temper arose in her, and having made
                        obeisance with all five parts of her body by falling down at the feet of the princely
                        Mañjuśrī, having gone to the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha for refuge,
                        having adopted a chaste life and the moral precepts, and having developed
                        the mind of incomparable, perfect awakening with determination, she uttered
                        the following words: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-545"/>
                    <p tid="6">“I too, Mañjuśrī, having heard what you have taught,
                        will develop the mind of incomparable, perfect awakening for the sake of
                        your teaching, for the sake of pity and compassion for all beings, for the
                        sake of not breaking the tradition of the Buddha, for the sake of not
                        breaking the tradition of the Dharma, and for the sake of not breaking the
                        tradition of the Saṅgha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-74"/>
                    <p tid="79">“In the same way, I will teach the Dharma to all beings to help them
                        understand it. To purify the hindrances that originate from negative
                        actions, I will confess each fault according to how it is committed. When
                        beings do not understand that all phenomena are peaceful and tranquil, they
                        do not understand the essential nature of phenomena, since they are
                        controlled by error that follows incorrect thinking <ref type="folio" cRef="F.224.b"/> and chained to desire by attachment to their bodies.
                        But, Mañjuśrī, though this is the case, even those beings who are chained to
                        desire are connected to exactly that essential nature of phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-75"/>
                    <p tid="80">“The bodhisatvas train themselves in this Dharma of connectedness
                        and develop the mind of incomparable, perfect awakening. Why is this?
                        Mañjuśrī, the afflicted mental states are not real but are born out of
                        concepts, and they disappear when the concepts are understood as being
                        empty. As I understand the meaning of what you have said, Mañjuśrī, the
                        afflicted mental states are without any essential nature and are unborn,
                        just like a mass of clouds. The afflicted mental states break up and
                        dissolve in an instant, just like bubbles. The afflicted mental states are
                        not produced, just like wind. The afflicted mental states are beyond all
                        spheres, just like a drawing in the air. The afflicted mental states are not
                        lasting, just like a drawing on water. The afflicted mental states originate
                        from indulging in superficial mental activity, just like yakṣas and bhūtas.
                        The afflicted mental states originate from mistakenly seeing things where
                        there is nothing, just like in a fever. The afflicted mental states
                        originate from concepts, and thus are nonexistent. The afflicted mental
                        states are connected to the inclinations of the ego. The afflicted mental
                        states grasp at objects because of the principle of greed for possessions.
                        The afflicted mental states are adventitious because they are produced by
                        misunderstanding. The afflicted mental states follow the distinguishing
                        marks as they are the results of concepts. The afflicted mental states are
                        not intellectual activity, as they do not investigate the different
                        elements. The afflicted mental states, which originate with the fluctuation
                        of thoughts, are the absence of introspection. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.225.a"/> The afflicted mental states, which originate in the
                        attachment to self and others, are the absence of faith. The afflicted
                        mental states are the grasping at the aggregates. The afflicted mental
                        states are the holding on to the sensory elements as material things. The afflicted
                        mental states are the amassing of the sense sources as material things. The
                        afflicted mental states are the making of distinctions between concepts and
                        forms. The afflicted mental states are the failure to understand
                        the mind’s incorrect thinking. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-76"/>
                    <p tid="81">“Despite that, Mañjuśrī, the afflicted mental states are the
                        supporting pillar of awakening. Why is that? It is because awakening is
                        immovable, and the afflicted mental states are the seeds of awakening.
                        Awakening is really the understanding of the afflicted mental states. The
                        afflicted mental states are also the adamantine basis of awakening. Why is
                        this? It is because awakening is indivisable from the afflicted mental
                        states, because of the principle of being inseparable from the totality of
                        reality.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-546" index="8">This topic, 
                            found in many Mahāyāna sūtras, is the specific theme of 
                            the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharma­dhātu­prakṛtyasambheda­nirdeśa</title> 
                            (“The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena,” Toh 52), see Dharmachakra Translation Committee (2018), especially 
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh52.html#UT22084-040-003-21">1.8</ref>.</note> 
                        To see the afflicted mental states, Mañjuśrī, is awakening.
                        Awakening is ever-present in all objects. Mañjuśrī, as awakening is not
                        established anywhere, so too the afflicted mental states are not
                        established—they do not remain, as they are broken up and melt away as soon
                        as they have arisen. Mañjuśrī, the afflicted mental states have thought as
                        their essential nature. Why is this? Mañjuśrī, it is not possible to point
                        out the essential nature of thought by expressions such as, ‘This thought is
                        full of desire, full of aversion, and full of bewilderment.’ But, Mañjuśrī,
                        since it is impossible to demonstrate what thought is, it is also not
                        possible to point out the essential nature of the afflicted mental states by
                        expressions such as, ‘The afflicted mental states are found in certain
                        places and regions.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-77"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Bodhisatvas, Mañjuśrī, great beings, to the extent that they
                        penetrate the afflicted mental states, do not get tired of bringing to maturity 
                        beings who behave in accord with their desire. Nor do they get tired of
                        bringing to maturity beings who behave in accord with their aversion, nor
                        those who behave in accord with their bewilderment, nor those who behave in
                        accord with the three afflicted mental states in equal combination. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-78"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Thus, Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.225.b"/> I will look upon
                        my own desire in the same way as I look upon the desire of all those who
                        behave in accord with their desire. Thus, Mañjuśrī, I will look upon my own
                        aversion in the same way as I look upon the aversion of all those who behave
                        in accord with their aversion. And, Mañjuśrī, I will look upon my own
                        bewilderment in the same way as I look upon the bewilderment of all those
                        who behave in accord with their bewilderment. I will, Mañjuśrī, look upon my
                        own afflicted mental states in the same way as I look upon the afflicted
                        mental states of all those who behave in accord with their afflicted mental
                        states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-79"/>
                    <p tid="84">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, fire is not frightened by grass and trees, in
                        the same way, Mañjuśrī, the fire of noble insight is not frightened by all
                        the grass and trees of the afflicted mental states. Just as, Mañjuśrī, the
                        disk of the sun does not remain in the company of darkness, in the same way,
                        Mañjuśrī, noble insight does not remain in the company of the afflicted
                        mental states.</p>

                    <p tid="85">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, the wind does not cling to trees and mountains,
                        in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts according to noble
                        insight does not cling to any region of the afflicted mental states.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-81"/>
                    <p tid="86">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, the element of space is not burned by the
                        world-consuming fire at the end of an eon, in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the
                        bodhisatva who acts according to noble insight is not burned by the
                        world-consuming fire that is the afflicted mental states.</p>

                    <p tid="87">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, space does not remain in the company of dust,
                        mist, or clouds, in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts
                        according to noble insight does not remain in the company of any of the
                        afflicted mental states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-83"/>
                    <p tid="88">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, space does not remain in the company of earth,
                        in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts according to noble
                        insight does not stay in the company of any of the afflicted mental states. </p>

                    <p tid="89">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, the lodestone does not remain in the company of
                        iron, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.226.a"/> in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the
                        bodhisatva who acts according to noble insight does not remain in the
                        company of any of the afflicted mental states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-85"/>
                    <p tid="90">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, the circle of mountains cannot be shaken by all
                        the winds, in the same way, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts according to
                        noble insight cannot be shaken by the afflicted mental states. </p>

                    <p tid="91">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, in the animal world the goose drinks the milk
                        and not the water from a mixture of milk and water, in the same way,
                        Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts according to noble insight draws out the
                        insight and not the afflicted mental states from a mixture of noble insight
                        and afflicted mental states.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-87"/>
                    <p tid="92">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, on the northern continent the tree branches will
                        not bow down to women who have sexual relations with their relatives, in the
                        same way, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatva who acts according to noble insight does
                        not bow down to those living beings whose faculties are immature.</p>

                    <p tid="93">“Thus, Mañjuśrī, I have no fear of the afflicted mental states. Why
                        not? Bodhisatvas, Mañjuśrī, are clad in the armor of fearlessness.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-89"/>
                    <p tid="94">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, one cannot call someone who fears the enemy a
                        hero, in the same way, Mañjuśrī, one cannot call someone who fears the
                        afflicted mental states a bodhisatva.</p>

                    <p tid="95">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, one cannot call someone who is conquered by the
                        enemy a hero, in the same way, Mañjuśrī, one cannot call someone who is
                        conquered by the afflicted mental states a bodhisatva.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-91"/>
                    <p tid="96">“Just as, Mañjuśrī, the jewel called <distinct>purifier of
                            water</distinct> purifies all the dirt of the water that it is thrown
                        into without getting soaked and sullied by the impurities of that water, in
                        the same way, Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.226.b"/> bodhisatvas who
                        act according to noble insight, even if they find themselves among the
                        afflicted mental states, purify all the impurities of the afflicted mental
                        states without getting soaked and sullied by the impurities of those
                        afflicted mental states.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-92"/>
                    <p tid="97">After the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī had
                        given this teaching, she again asked the princely Mañjuśrī, “How,
                        Mañjuśrī, does the bodhisatva become free from afflicted mental states?”</p>

                    <p tid="98">“Sister,” replied Mañjuśrī, “the bodhisatva who sees the afflicted
                        mental states in terms of origination and disappearance is not called
                            <distinct>one without afflicted mental states</distinct>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-94"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Sister, if only darkness appears in the midst of an oil lamp, it
                        cannot really be called an oil lamp. In the same way, sister, a bodhisatva
                        who sees the afflicted mental states in terms of origination and
                        disappearance is not called <distinct>a bodhisatva without afflicted mental
                            states</distinct>. Those without any afflicted mental states, sister, do
                        not see impurity or purity anywhere. They are beyond seeing, not seeing,
                        thought, mind, and consciousness, and they are without any afflicted mental
                        states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-95"/>
                    <p tid="100">“Anyone anywhere, sister, who fosters the activity of thought,
                        mind, and consciousness—even the thought of nirvāṇa—has afflicted mental
                        states. Why is this? For one without afflicted mental states there is
                        neither thought nor the activity of thought. For all of those who foster
                        thoughts that have good and bad as their objects, conditioning is active.
                        Conditioning is existence, and existence is conditioning. All conditioning
                        is existence. Such are the afflicted mental states, dear sister.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-96"/>
                    <p tid="101">“The afflicted mental states, sister, are attachment. Attachment to
                        the eye and to forms is an afflicted mental state, as is attachment to the
                        ear and to sounds, to the nose and to smells, to the tongue and to tastes,
                        to the body and to physical objects, and to the mind and to mental
                        phenomena. Attachment to morality is an afflicted mental state. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.227.a"/> Attachment to meditation is an afflicted
                        mental state. Attachment to insight, liberation, and the vision of the
                        knowledge of liberation is an afflicted mental state. Attachment to
                        isolation is an afflicted mental state.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-97"/>
                    <p tid="102">“The absence of afflicted mental states, sister, is a designation
                        for the absence of activity. The absence of afflicted mental states is a
                        designation for the absence of discursive thinking. The absence of afflicted
                        mental states is a designation for the absence of effort. The absence of
                        afflicted mental states is a designation for the absence of purpose. One who
                        is without calculation and non-calculation, sister, is without afflicted
                        mental states.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-98"/>
                    <p tid="103">“Further, sister, as the Tathāgata says, one who is
                        without afflicted mental states but strives to release others
                        from afflicted mental states is to be called <distinct>one without afflicted
                            mental states</distinct>, so freeing others from the afflicted mental
                        states is how the bodhisatva adopts vigor.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-99"/>
                    <p tid="104">“Mañjuśrī, how does the bodhisatva adopt vigor?” asked the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="105">Mañjuśrī replied, “To be in harmony with the discernment of
                        emptiness but still have compassion for beings who act according to
                        viewpoints; to be in harmony with the discernment of the absence of
                        distinguishing marks but still have compassion for beings who act according
                        to distinguishing marks; to be in harmony with the discernment of the absence
                        of wishes but still have compassion for beings who act according to wishes;
                        to be in harmony with the discernment of the absence of conditioning but
                        still have compassion for beings who act according to conditioning; to be in
                        harmony with the discernment of the absence of birth and death but still have
                        compassion for beings who entertain the concepts of old age and death; to be
                        in harmony with the discernment of the absence of birth but still have
                        compassion for beings who entertain the concepts of origination and
                        destruction; to be in harmony with the discernment of what is certain to a hearer but still give
                        up the attainment of the fruit of the hearer; to be in harmony with the
                        discernment of what is certain to a solitary buddha but still give up the
                        attainment of the fruit of the solitary buddha; <ref type="folio" cRef="F.227.b"/> and to be in 
                        harmony with the discernment of the untroubled state of a
                        bodhisatva but still have compassion for all beings—this, sister, is how the
                        bodhisatva adopts vigor. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-101"/>
                    <p tid="106">“Just as, sister, it is easy to enter the ocean but hard to get
                        hold of the great pearls and to return, in the same way, sister, reflecting
                        on emptiness is easy but returning from it is difficult for one who has no
                        expedient means. Reflecting on the absence of distinguishing marks, wishes,
                        and conditioning, the absence of birth and origination, and
                        the untroubled states of the hearers and the solitary
                        buddhas is easy, but returning from such reflections is difficult for one
                        who has no expedient means. Just as, sister, it is easy to enter a great
                        battle but hard to get out unscathed and without injuries, in the same way,
                        sister, entering the three gates of liberation is easy but returning is
                        difficult for one who has no expedient means.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-102"/>
                    <p tid="107">“What, Mañjuśrī, is expedient means like?” asked the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="108">Mañjuśrī replied, “Expedient means, sister, is not giving up the
                        two opposite sides, that is, the side of existence and the side of nirvāṇa.
                        Expedient means, sister, is demonstrating the dual gates, that is, the gate
                        of existence and the gate of nirvāṇa; the gate of emptiness and the gate of
                        freedom from viewpoints; the gate of the absence of distinguishing marks and
                        the gate of freedom from distinguishing marks; the gate of the absence of
                        wishes and the gate of being born intentionally; the gate of the absence of
                        conditioning and the gate of the conditioning of virtue; the gate of no
                        birth and the gate of demonstrating birth; the gate of no activity and the
                        gate of the aggregates, the sensory elements, and the sense sources; the gate of no
                        origination and destruction and the gate of birth and activity; the gate of
                        voidness and the gate of bringing beings to maturity; the gate of total
                        reality and the gate of caring for every single thing; the gate of the way
                        of the hearers and the gate of the determination of the bodhisatva; <ref type="folio" cRef="F.228.a"/> and the gate of isolated awakening and the
                        gate of never forgetting the qualities of the Buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-104"/>
                    <p tid="109">“Sister, the bodhisatva who demonstrates the dual gates but does
                        not become attached to any gate is said to be able in expedient means. The
                        same goes for the gate of desire and the gate of the absence of desire, the
                        gate of aversion and the gate of the absence of aversion, the gate of
                        bewilderment and the gate of the absence of bewilderment, the gate of the
                        afflicted mental states and the gate of the absence of the afflicted mental
                        states, and the gate of all movement and the gate of the absence of
                        movement. That, sister, is the bodhisatva’s ability in expedient means. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-105"/>
                    <p tid="110">“The gate of the behavior of ordinary, naive beings on the one hand, and the gate of
                        the behavior of one to be trained, one without need of further training,
                        the hearer, the solitary buddha, and the
                        bodhisatva on the other—knowledge of these two gates is the bodhisatva’s ability in
                        expedient means.” <ref cRef="B2" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-106"/>
                    <p tid="111">At that time, as the Blessed One was walking in the mountain forest
                        on the slopes of Vulture Peak with his attendant, the venerable monk Ānanda,
                        he sat down. Once he was seated, he commended the princely Mañjuśrī: “Mañjuśrī, you
                        taught how a bodhisatva adopts vigor and his ability in expedient means just
                        the way it is. This is very good! Very good!” This whole trichiliocosm was
                        filled with the melody of those words “very good,” and it shook six times.
                        Inspired by those words “very good,” the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas,
                        demigods, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, non-humans, Śakra, Brahmā,
                        and many protectors of the world went to the place where the Blessed One was
                        residing, greeted him by bowing their heads to the Blessed One’s feet, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.228.b"/> and sat down at one side. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-107"/>
                    <p tid="112">When they had seated themselves, the gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                        gandharvas, demigods, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, non-humans,
                        Śakra, Brahmā, and many protectors of the world asked the Blessed One, “To
                        whom did the Blessed One utter the words ‘very good’ that filled this whole
                        trichiliocosm with their melody?” </p>

                    <p tid="113">The Blessed One replied, “Gods, it was to the princely Mañjuśrī.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-109"/>
                    <p tid="114">The gods then asked, “Blessed One, where is the princely Mañjuśrī
                        now?” </p>

                    <p tid="115"> “Gods,” answered the Blessed One, “the princely Mañjuśrī is at the
                        eastern gate of the great city of Rājagṛha, and is engaged in conversation
                        on the Dharma with the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī. Those
                        gods who wish to hear the Dharma should go there.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-111"/>
                    <p tid="116">Then all of those gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, demigods,
                        garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, non-humans, Śakra, Brahmā, and many
                        protectors of the world gathered and went to the place where the princely
                        Mañjuśrī was residing. They manifested themselves in physical bodies and
                        showered a rain of flowers. That rain of flowers spread bouquets of flowers
                        all over Rājagṛha and the surrounding area. There, the gods could see the
                        humans, and the humans could see the gods, but they did not speak to each
                        other. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-112"/>
                    <p tid="117">Many hundreds of thousands of beings from the great city of
                        Rājagṛha who had been inspired by the flowers, and who had been inspired by
                        the visible bodies of the gods, went to the place where the princely
                        Mañjuśrī was staying. King Ajātaśatru, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.229.a"/>
                        surrounded by his retinue of women, with his armed forces of the four
                        branches, and with his great royal wealth and his great royal might, also
                        went to the place where the princely Mañjuśrī was staying. The retinue,
                        the king, the ministers, the sons of the ministers, the traders, and the
                        sons of the householders all saw that the courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī was free from the manifestation of the afflicted
                        mental state of desire. Her senses and her behavior were calm. Her senses
                        were undisturbed, full of modesty, and she was adorned with beauty. When
                        they saw her, none of them gave rise to lustful thoughts.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-113"/>
                    <p tid="118">When he saw that great crowd of people, the princely Mañjuśrī said
                        to the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī, “My child, this great
                        crowd of people is no longer filled with desire upon seeing you. Where have
                        you disposed of those afflicted mental states?” </p>

                    <p tid="119"> “The afflicted mental states of all beings, Mañjuśrī, are located
                        within knowledge and liberation,” answered the girl. “They are placed within
                        the totality of phenomena, and I have understood them thus as being without
                        origination, without destruction, and without change. This essential nature
                        of the afflicted mental states is what I have understood.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-115"/>
                    <p tid="120">Mañjuśrī then asked, “My child, what is the essential nature of the
                        afflicted mental states?” </p>

                    <p tid="121">The girl replied, “The essential nature of the afflicted mental
                        states, Mañjuśrī, is an essential nature beyond construction and concept.
                        The essential nature of the afflicted mental states is a fundamentally
                        unborn essential nature. The afflicted mental states are adventitious. They
                        do not remain when emptiness is understood. They do not remain when the
                        absence of distinguishing marks and the absence of wishes is known. They do
                        not remain when the originally pure light is present.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-117"/>
                    <p tid="122">“Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.229.b"/> people can be killed
                        by the poison of a highly venomous snake, but if they ingest the
                        antivenom called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">agada</foreign>,
                        which neutralizes and pacifies all poison, then, as soon as the drug is
                        administered, the poison of the venomous snake is made innocuous. Thus, boys
                        and girls who ingest it can lovingly play with the snake. When they play
                        with the snake, they may take it on their laps and wear it on one side as a
                        shoulder belt. But even though they adorn themselves with it, it will not
                        hurt, consume, or inflict harm on them.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-118"/>
                    <p tid="123">“In the same way, Mañjuśrī, I had not previously heard of the
                        discipline of the Dharma and was burned by the afflicted mental states that
                        were brought about by superficial mental activity and misunderstanding. I
                        was attached to my own body by desire, I was attached to my beauty, and I
                        did not reflect upon the fact that beauty is just as fragile as foam. I did
                        not understand that the body has the nature of an illusion. I did not
                        understand that playing with pleasures is like a dream. I did not understand
                        that the taste of the pleasure of desire is like a drop of honey. I did not
                        understand that the life principle is like dewdrops. I did not understand
                        that all composite things are impermanent. I did not understand that the
                        body is impure. I did not understand that all composite things are intense
                        suffering, and I did not reflect on the fact that all phenomena are without
                        any self. I was thus obscured by darkness myself and I also obscured others.
                        I was bound myself and I bound others as well.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-119"/>
                    <p tid="124">“I heard your teaching on the Dharma, Mañjuśrī, and when I heard
                        it, I had faith in it. When I had attained faith in it, I was freed, and so
                        I will not look upon anyone with desirous eyes, neither in the present nor
                        in the future. And why is this? Mañjuśrī, light does not coexist with
                        darkness. In the same way, Mañjuśrī, no one who is free of desires is
                        attached to the afflicted mental states.” <ref type="folio" cRef="F.230.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-120"/>
                    <p tid="125">Then the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī implored the
                        princely Mañjuśrī, “Please, Mañjuśrī, as these great assemblies of gods and
                        humans are gathered here, be eloquent in your speech on the Dharma so that
                        when they have understood the essential nature of the afflicted mental
                        states, these gods and these people will develop the mind of absolute,
                        incomparable awakening out of compassion for living beings.” </p>

                    <p tid="126"> “But sister,” replied Mañjuśrī, “the essential nature of the
                        afflicted mental states is very difficult to reach. And why is this? Because
                        the essential nature of the afflicted mental states is awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-122"/>
                    <p tid="127">“Sister, just as an unkindled fire does not have the nature of
                        burning, in the same way, sister, the afflicted mental states that are not
                        imagined do not have the nature of existence. Sister, just as a kindled fire
                        has the nature of burning, in the same way, sister, the afflicted mental
                        states that are imagined have the nature of existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-123"/>
                    <p tid="128">“Sister, just as a fire burns if it has a cause, in the same way,
                        sister, if the afflicted mental states have the cause of the manifestation
                        of viewpoints, they burn in the three spheres of existence. Sister, just as
                        a fire does not burn if it has no cause, in the same way, sister, if the
                        afflicted mental states do not have the cause of the manifestation of
                        viewpoints, they do not burn in the three spheres of existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-124"/>
                    <p tid="129">“Sister, just as there is no increase or decrease in a
                        thousand-year fire, in the same way, sister, there is no increase or
                        decrease in the afflicted mental states generated over a hundred thousand
                        eons. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-125"/>
                    <p tid="130">“Sister, just as a fire that has been extinguished cannot be called
                        a fire, in the same way, sister, afflicted mental states that have abated
                        cannot be called afflicted mental states. </p>

                    <p tid="131">“Sister, just as a fire that burns in an open space cannot burn the
                        space itself, in the same way, sister, the adventitious afflicted mental
                        states that arise in that which is originally luminous are not able to
                        pollute that which is originally luminous. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.230.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-127"/>
                    <p tid="132">“Even though this is the case, sister, how should the body of form
                        be regarded?” </p>

                    <p tid="133">“Mañjuśrī,” answered the girl, “just like the reflection of the
                        moon in a small lake.” </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-560"/>
                    <p tid="134">“How, girl, should the aggregates be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="135">“Just like the manifestation of the Tathāgata, Mañjuśrī,” answered
                        the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-131"/>
                    <p tid="136">“How, girl, should the sensory elements be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="137">“Just like the three spheres of existence when they are consumed by
                        the fire of the eon, Mañjuśrī,” answered the girl.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-553" index="9">This question and the girl’s answer are frequently cited in the commentarial literature to support the emptiness of the sensory elements as well as of the aggregates.</note>
                    </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-561"/>
                    <p tid="138">“How, girl, should the sense sources be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="139">“Just like formed actions, which are really unformed, Mañjuśrī,”
                        answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-135"/>
                    <p tid="140">“How, girl, should this assembly be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="141">“Just like the empty space above us, Mañjuśrī,” answered the
                        girl.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-562"/>
                    <p tid="142">“How, girl, should you be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="143">“Just like a meeting between my mother and father, Mañjuśrī,”
                        answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-139"/>
                    <p tid="144">“How, girl, should I be regarded?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="145">“Just like a blind man seeing form, Mañjuśrī,” answered the
                        girl.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-549"/>
                    <p tid="146">“Girl, have you heard these teachings?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="147">“I have heard them, Mañjuśrī, like information heard from a
                        magically conjured person,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-143"/>
                    <p tid="148">“Girl, do you wish to reach incomparable, perfect awakening?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="149">“As I myself am awakening, I do not need to wish for it anymore,
                        Mañjuśrī,” answered the girl.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-563"/>
                    <p tid="150">“Girl, have you practiced the perfection of giving?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="151">“I have practiced it, Mañjuśrī, by completely giving away my
                        afflicted mental states,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-147"/>
                    <p tid="152">“Girl, have you fulfilled the perfection of morality?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="153">“I have fulfilled it, Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.231.a"/>
                        in the manner of filling up empty space,” answered the girl. </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-564"/>
                    <p tid="154">“Girl, have you cultivated the perfection of patient acceptance?”
                        asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="155">“I have cultivated it, Mañjuśrī, by means of the absence of birth
                        and the absence of all beings,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-151"/>
                    <p tid="156">“Girl, have you undertaken the perfection of vigor?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="157">“I have undertaken it, Mañjuśrī, by means of the principle that all
                        phenomena are beyond reach,” answered the girl.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-565"/>
                    <p tid="158">“Girl, are you established in the perfection of meditation?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="159">“I am established in it, Mañjuśrī, by means of the principle that
                        the expanse of reality is unestablished,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-155"/>
                    <p tid="160">“Girl, have you fulfilled the perfection of insight?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="161"> “I have fulfilled it, Mañjuśrī, without adding or removing
                        anything,” answered the girl. </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-566"/>
                    <p tid="162">“Girl, have you cultivated friendliness?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="163">“I have cultivated it, Mañjuśrī, by means of the principle that all
                        beings are nonexistent,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-159"/>
                    <p tid="164">“Girl, from where is great compassion to be sought by the
                        bodhisatva?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="165">“Great compassion is to be sought by the bodhisatva from the
                        afflicted mental states of all beings, Mañjuśrī. Why is this? If the
                        afflicted mental states of all beings did not exist, the bodhisatva would
                        not develop the mind of awakening,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-161"/>
                    <p tid="166">“Girl, from where is joy to be sought by the bodhisatva?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="167">“Joy is to be sought by the bodhisatva from the mind of awakening,
                        Mañjuśrī, which is characterized by great determination,” answered the girl. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-163"/>
                    <p tid="168">“Girl, what is the use of the equanimity of the bodhisatva?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="169">“The equanimity of the bodhisatva brings about the complete absence
                        of any deceit toward all beings, Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.231.b"/> and 
                        brings that about without there being any opposition toward all phenomena,” answered the
                        girl. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-165"/>
                    <p tid="170">“Girl, what kind of ‘opposition,’ as you say, is that?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="171">“It is that of those who have entered awakening trying to get rid of the
                        afflicted mental states, Mañjuśrī, which are really nonexistent,” answered
                        the girl. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-167"/>
                    <p tid="172">“Girl, to what are they opposed?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="173">“To all who argue against them,” answered the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="174">“But girl, who are those who argue against them?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="175">“They are people conceited about their
                        patient acceptance who argue against others,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-171"/>
                    <p tid="176">“Girl, where does what you call ‘patient acceptance’ come from?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="177">“It comes from being hurt by all beings, Mañjuśrī. Why is this? If
                        one is not hurt, there is no patient acceptance. But those who, even though 
                        they have been hurt by all beings, are unperturbed
                        and do not harm anyone, they have
                        cultivated patient acceptance,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-173"/>
                    <p tid="178">“Girl, what is so-called ‘anger’ like?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="179">“Mañjuśrī, that which destroys the roots of virtue collected for a hundred eons
                        is called ‘anger,’ ” answered the girl.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-547" index="10">This 
                            sentence is very widely quoted in the commentarial literature, both Indian and Tibetan. The Sanskrit 
                            can be found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsammucaya</title> (Toh 3940), ch. 7 (Bendall 149.5), as well as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhicaryāvatārapañjikā</title> (Toh 3872), ch. 6 (Bcp 91): <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">pratighaḥ pratigha iti kalpaśatopacitaṃ kuśalamūlaṃ pratihanti tenocyate pratigha iti</foreign>. The etymological relationships are lost in translation: “anger / hostility (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratigha</foreign>) is called ‘anger / hostility’ because it destroys (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratihanti</foreign>) the roots of virtue collected for a hundred eons, and on that account it is called ‘anger / hostility.’ ” As well as being an important doctrinal point, this sentence also constitutes a canonical gloss for the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratigha</foreign>, which has the more general meaning of “hostility” or “aversion” compared to the standard Tibetan translation (specified in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> S.1945), <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">khong khro ba</foreign>, “anger.” </note>
                    </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-567"/>
                    <p tid="180">“Girl, what could be called ‘the absence of anger’?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="181">“Those who have no negative thoughts and do not cause any harm can
                        be known as those who are patient,” answered the girl. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-177"/>
                    <p tid="182">“Girl, how are bodhisatvas victorious in battle?” asked Mañjuśrī. </p>

                    <p tid="183">“They discern all phenomena, Mañjuśrī, but do not apprehend them,”
                        answered the girl.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-550" index="11">The Sanskrit of 
                            this question and response are found cited in Kamalaśīla’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanākrama</title> III Bhk 235 (Toh 3917): <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">mañjuśrīr uvāca kathaṃ dārike bodhisatvo vijitasaṃgrāmo bhavati | āha yo mañjuśrīr vicīya sarvadharmān nopalabhate</foreign>. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-179"/>
                    <p tid="184">“Girl, how do bodhisatvas become killers of demons?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="185">“They are not sullied even though they subdue demons, Mañjuśrī. Why
                        is this? Mañjuśrī, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.232.a"/> bodhisatvas display
                        the aggregates, but they do not abide with the afflicted mental states in
                        the aggregates. Moreover, Mañjuśrī, even though bodhisatvas demonstrate
                        afflicted mental states, they are essentially and by their nature not
                        attached to them. They demonstrate old age and death in order to bring
                        living beings to maturity, but they understand that all phenomena are beyond
                        death and movement. Even though, Mañjuśrī, bodhisatvas show such qualities
                        as a child of the gods, they are without any envy or conceit,” answered the
                        girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-181"/>
                    <p tid="186">“Girl, how do bodhisatvas bring living beings to maturity?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="187">“Bodhisatvas bring beings to maturity by cultivating insight and
                        expedient means, Mañjuśrī,” answered the girl.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-568"/>
                    <p tid="188">“Girl, how do bodhisatvas stay close to all beings?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="189">“They stay close to all beings by cultivating their own thoughts
                        and knowledge, Mañjuśrī,” answered the girl. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-185"/>
                    <p tid="190">“Girl, is there any wish to listen to your teachings in this
                        assembly?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="191">“Someone who is entrenched in the concept of ‘self and others’ has
                        no wish to listen, Mañjuśrī. Someone who has penetrated the knowledge
                        derived from hearing has no wish to listen,” answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-187"/>
                    <p tid="192">“So, girl, what is the wish to listen to the Dharma?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="193">“When one believes in one’s own body in the same way as one
                        believes in a person who appears in a dream, when one believes in the
                        teacher of the Dharma in the same way as one believes in a person who has
                        been created through magical deception, when one believes in a Dharma
                        teaching in the same way as one believes in an echo, and when there is no
                        duality of belief and liberation, that is the wish to listen, Mañjuśrī,”
                        answered the girl.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-189"/>
                    <p tid="194">“How then, girl, should Dharma teachings be listened to?” asked
                        Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="195">“Dharma teachings should be listened to in such a way that one
                        makes progress in relying on the Dharma teaching, Mañjuśrī,” answered the
                        girl. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.232.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-191"/>
                    <p tid="196">When the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī taught
                        the Dharma in that way, by means of the powerful presence of the princely
                        Mañjuśrī and the insight resulting from the roots of virtue that she herself had
                        collected, twelve thousand beings in that assembly developed the mind of
                        incomparable, perfect awakening, five hundred gods and humans who had
                        collected roots of virtue as followers of the bodhisatva’s way attained
                        patient acceptance of the fact that all things are unborn, and thirty-two
                        thousand beings attained impeccable pure vision of phenomena. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-192"/>
                    <p tid="197">By means of the joy and rapture resulting from hearing about the
                        Dharma, the girl herself attained the patient acceptance that is in accord with
                        all things. When she had attained it, she fell down before the feet of the
                        princely Mañjuśrī, and asked him for permission to go forth:
                        “Out of compassion, Mañjuśrī, allow me to go forth, and please
                        release me from this body, which is inappropriately produced and ignoble,
                        and which indeed makes us stray from the noble Dharma.”</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-569"/>
                    <p tid="198">Mañjuśrī replied, “It is like this, sister. Shaving the hair on
                        your head is not equivalent to going forth as it pertains to
                        the bodhisatva. Why not? Girl, bodhisatvas go forth by means
                        of the effort to eliminate the afflicted mental states of all beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-194"/>
                    <p tid="199">“Girl, wearing the yellow robe is not equivalent to going forth
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, girl, bodhisatvas
                        go forth by adopting the training and rules of morality
                        themselves while encouraging immoral beings to adopt the vows and practice
                        of morality.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-195"/>
                    <p tid="200">“Girl, practicing for oneself in isolation is not equivalent to
                        going forth as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, girl,
                        bodhisatvas go forth by establishing the beings dispersed
                        throughout the five destinies of existence in the knowledge of
                        disengagement.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-196"/>
                    <p tid="201">“The qualities of color and beauty, of behavior and appearance, are
                        not equivalent to going forth as it pertains to the
                        bodhisatva. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.233.a"/> Rather, bodhisatvas go forth
                        by generating thoughts of friendliness and compassion.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-197"/>
                    <p tid="202">“Planting one’s own roots of virtue is not equivalent to going forth
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas
                        go forth by planting the roots of virtue of all beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-198"/>
                    <p tid="203">“Honoring the determination to reach one’s own complete nirvāṇa is
                        not equivalent to going forth as it pertains to the
                        bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas go forth by honoring the
                        determination that others should reach complete nirvāṇa.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-199"/>
                    <p tid="204">“Pacifying one’s own afflicted mental states is not equivalent to
                        going forth as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather,
                        bodhisatvas go forth by appeasing the afflicted mental
                        states of others.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-200"/>
                    <p tid="205">“Protecting one’s own mind is not equivalent to going forth 
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas go forth 
                        by protecting the minds of all beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-201"/>
                    <p tid="206">“Striving for one’s own freedom is not equivalent to going forth 
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas go forth
                        by striving for the freedom of all beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-202"/>
                    <p tid="207">“Girl, disgust for existence is not equivalent to going forth
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas go forth
                        by means of the joy of freeing all beings from
                        existence.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-203"/>
                    <p tid="208">“Girl, the pleasure of nirvāṇa is not equivalent to going forth
                        as it pertains to the bodhisatva. Rather, bodhisatvas go forth 
                        by fully developing all the qualities of an awakened
                        one.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-204"/>
                    <p tid="209">“Girl, going forth is an expression of great
                        compassion for all beings. Girl, going forth is an expression
                        of not seeing others’ faults. Girl, going forth is an
                        expression of not being jealous of others’ gains. Girl, going forth
                        is an expression of harming neither oneself nor others. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.233.b"/> Girl, going forth is an
                        expression of not blaming others. Girl, going forth is an
                        expression of serving others. Girl, going forth is an
                        expression of not encouraging others’ faults. Girl, going forth
                        is an expression of lifting others out of all faults.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-205"/>
                    <p tid="210">“Girl, the bodhisatva’s going forth is dependent on
                        other things, but the bodhisatva is not dependent on other things.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-206"/>
                    <p tid="211">The girl asked, “How, Mañjuśrī, is the bodhisatva’s 
                        going forth dependent on other things?”</p>

                    <p tid="212">“Girl, going forth is dependent on morality,”
                        replied Mañjuśrī. “There is no going forth in immorality.
                        Girl, going forth is dependent on concentration. There is no
                        going forth in sustained forgetfulness. Girl, 
                        going forth is dependent on insight. There is no going forth
                        in false insight. Girl, going forth is dependent
                        on freedom. There is no going forth when the mind is not
                        free. Girl, going forth is dependent on insight into freedom.
                        There is no going forth in the absence of insight into
                        freedom.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-208"/>
                    <p tid="213">“How, Mañjuśrī, do bodhisatvas become independent in their 
                        going forth?” asked the girl.</p>

                    <p tid="214">“Girl,” replied Mañjuśrī, “bodhisatvas are independent as they do
                        not depend on anyone else. By means of their own comprehension and
                        knowledge, whatever they know, they know themselves. Whatever they say, they
                        say themselves. Thus they are independent because they are not compliant.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-210"/>
                    <p tid="215">When the princely Mañjuśrī had taught this exposition of the Dharma
                        consisting of this passage on going forth, because it was so
                        well formulated <ref type="folio" cRef="F.234.a"/> five hundred bodhisatvas
                        took the clothes and ornaments off their bodies and declared, “The going forth
                        of the bodhisatvas as you have taught it was so well
                        formulated that we also wish to attain that going forth.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-211"/>
                    <p tid="216">The princely Mañjuśrī then said to the courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī, “Girl, get into the carriage and, out of compassion,
                        bring the banker’s son Bhayadatta to maturation. By this, you will go forth
                        and attain full ordination.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-212"/>
                    <p tid="217">Then the great crowd of people thought, “How can it be right that
                        one without desire remains in the company of one who is not without desire?” </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-570"/>
                    <p tid="218">The girl knew the thoughts of the great crowd of people, and she
                        said to them, “Friends, even though bodhisatvas who are without desire
                        remain in the company of beings who are full of desire, they are without
                        blemish. They educate those beings who are full of desire. Friends, even
                        though bodhisatvas who are without aversion stay in the company of beings
                        who are full of aversion, they are without blemish. They educate those
                        beings who are full of aversion. Friends, even though bodhisatvas who are
                        without bewilderment stay in the company of beings who are full of
                        bewilderment, they are without blemish. They educate those beings who are
                        full of bewilderment. Friends, even though bodhisatvas who are without
                        afflicted mental states stay in the company of beings who are full of
                        afflicted mental states, they are without blemish. They educate those beings
                        who are full of afflicted mental states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-214"/>
                    <p tid="219">“Friends, just as a mother has no desire for her son even though
                        she dwells together with him, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.234.b"/> in the same
                        way, friends, bodhisatvas are not desirous of living beings, although they
                        dwell together with them. Friends, just as a man who is shut up in prison
                        does not act according to habits of desire, in the same way, friends,
                        bodhisatvas are not attached to concepts in the threefold world, which is
                        like a pit in a prison.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-215"/>
                    <p tid="220">Then the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī stood on the
                        Dharma dismounting step, attained the profound, and stepped down
                        on to the earth. Freed from the obscuration of ignorance, she had fully
                        realized the view of the fearfulness of the afflicted mental states that
                        result from the imperfections of existence. She bowed her head to the feet
                        of the princely Mañjuśrī, circumambulated him three times, and then
                        expressed herself in verse by the carriage steps:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-216"/>
                    <lg tid="461">
                        <l>“Being essentially pure, I am not impassioned. </l>
                        <l>Due to my constant friendliness, I am not affected by aversion. </l>
                        <l>Because of the light of my insight, I am not bewildered by delusion, </l>
                        <l>And I will mount this carriage.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-450"/>
                    <lg tid="462">
                        <l>“That which previously overpowered me </l>
                        <l>When I went to the park attached to riches, </l>
                        <l>Riding in a carriage with a banker’s son— </l>
                        <l>That concept of passion, where has it gone?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-451"/>
                    <lg tid="463">
                        <l>“The rays of the sun do not shine and do not burn </l>
                        <l>When thick clouds cover the earth. </l>
                        <l>Nevertheless, those rays do not go anywhere. </l>
                        <l>They simply do not shine while obscured by clouds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-452"/>
                    <lg tid="464">
                        <l>“In just the same way, all fools are obscured by the afflicted mental
                            states. </l>
                        <l>Though understanding via the light of insight has not arisen, </l>
                        <l>And the areas of insight are nowhere present, </l>
                        <l>By comprehending the afflictions, insight shines forth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-453"/>
                    <lg tid="465">
                        <l>“Afflicted mental states come from nowhere; </l>
                        <l>They do not depart to anywhere. </l>
                        <l>Afflicted mental states arise from the superficial;</l>
                        <l>They do not arise from the fundamental.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-454"/>
                    <lg tid="466">
                        <l>“There is no giving away and no grasping, </l>
                        <l>No arising and no destruction. </l>
                        <l>There is no giving to others or taking back, </l>
                        <l>And because of the sameness of all phenomena, I too am pure. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.235.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-455"/>
                    <lg tid="467">
                        <l>“When a sesame-oil lamp appears in the darkness, </l>
                        <l>The darkness does not disperse in different directions. </l>
                        <l>When darkness is dispelled by insight </l>
                        <l>There is no cessation of afflicted mental states and also no
                            origination.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-456"/>
                    <lg tid="468">
                        <l>“Doctors do not destroy the <term type="ignore">elements</term>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of their patients’ bodies when they cure them. </l>
                        <l>They pacify the adventitious disease, </l>
                        <l>And then other diseases do not arise.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-457"/>
                    <lg tid="469">
                        <l>“In just the same way, the best of physicians, Mañjughoṣa, </l>
                        <l>Who knows the appropriate methods, </l>
                        <l>Pacifies the afflicted mental states of beings by means of various
                            practices, </l>
                        <l>But he does not make the phenomena disappear.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-458"/>
                    <lg tid="470">
                        <l>“These aggregates, sensory elements, and sense sources </l>
                        <l>Do not change into something else. </l>
                        <l>The factors that earlier had the poison of negativity </l>
                        <l>Are now without poison and are unchanged.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-256"/>
                    <p tid="261">Then, when the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī had
                        spoken these verses, she again bowed her head to the feet of the princely
                        Mañjuśrī, and, after she had again circumambulated him, she ascended into
                        the carriage with the banker’s son Bhayadatta and proceeded to the park with
                        all those riches. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-257"/>
                    <p tid="262">The princely Mañjuśrī too taught the whole of that assembly by
                        means of conversation on the Dharma. He led them to take the conversation to
                        heart, gave them cause to rejoice, and made them happy. After he had taught
                        them, led them to take the conversation to heart, given them cause to
                        rejoice, and made them happy, he said to them, “Friends, those of you who
                        wish to listen to the Dharma should go to the Tathāgata in the evening.” </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-575"/>
                    <p tid="263">After he had said this, they left that place, and all went their
                        separate ways. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.235.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-259"/>
                    <p tid="264">Then the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī and the
                        banker’s son Bhayadatta went to the park together. There were bouquets of
                        flowers spread everywhere, giving off their fragrance. There were awnings
                        decorated with parasols, banners, and ensigns. They prepared riches of food
                        and drink and stayed in the park and gathered around them drums large and
                        small, cymbals, and songs for amusement. Because they had eaten and drunk so
                        much, they became quite intoxicated, and the courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī fell asleep on a pillow on the lap of Bhayadatta, the
                        banker’s son.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-260"/>
                    <p tid="265">Then that girl, by means of her power of supernormal knowledge,
                        made her body appear withered and gave the impression that she was dead. Her
                        whole body became impure and appeared to be a rotting corpse. Ill-smelling
                        impurities emerged from the two openings of her ears, from her eyes, and
                        from the inside of her nose, and spread all over her body. A foul odor
                        issued from the inside of her mouth and filled the whole park. Blood and pus
                        flowed from every pore. Her liver and all her intestines appeared from her
                        abdomen, with her navel in the center. Excrement and urine appeared and
                        flowed out from her anus and her vulva. Her brains oozed out from her head,
                        and blue flies began creeping over the nails of her feet and hands. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-261"/>
                    <p tid="266">Seeing what had happened to the girl's body, the banker's son
                        Bhayadatta was seized by panic and terror. Having no protection or support,
                        no one and nothing to turn to, he sought protection.. He was greatly
                        frightened, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.236.a"/> and he trembled and cried
                        bitterly. Such great fear arose in him for two reasons. He was an ordinary
                        person outside the religious life, and he was aware of the crimes that are
                        connected with such fear. “As punishment for this girl’s fate, King
                        Ajātaśatru will kill me,” he thought. He tried to move the girl off his lap and
                        escape, but he was unable to. All of his companions saw his great
                        and terrible fear and ran away.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-262"/>
                    <p tid="267">He sat there all alone and without friends, wondering, “Who is
                        going to free me from this great fear that afflicts me—a god, a nāga, a
                        yakṣa, a gandharva, a demigod, a garuḍa, a kiṃnara, a mahoraga, a human, a
                        non-human being, a monk, or a brahmin?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-263"/>
                    <p tid="268">As the banker’s son’s roots of virtue had not yet matured, he had
                        not heard the teaching that the princely Mañjuśrī had given to the girl, and
                        he did not know it. Because of the magical presence of the princely
                        Mañjuśrī, though, the following verses resounded from all the trees in the
                        park: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-264"/>
                    <lg tid="471">
                        <l>“All worlds are nonexistent. </l>
                        <l>It is like seeing an illusion, </l>
                        <l>But this boy sees phenomena </l>
                        <l>As having an essential nature.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-459"/>
                    <lg tid="472">
                        <l>“That which is clothed in flesh and blood </l>
                        <l>Deceives the foolish. </l>
                        <l>The unwise and the childish imagine </l>
                        <l>That the nonexistent is existent and become impassioned.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-460"/>
                    <lg tid="473">
                        <l>“One is like an unwise person </l>
                        <l>Walking with a vase </l>
                        <l>That has a nicely painted exterior </l>
                        <l>But is full of foul-smelling filth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-461"/>
                    <lg tid="474">
                        <l>“While one is walking, however, the jar falls, </l>
                        <l>And upon seeing the foul-smelling filth, </l>
                        <l>All passion ceases and one runs away, </l>
                        <l>Despite having been so impassioned before.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-462"/>
                    <lg tid="475">
                        <l>“In the same way, the unwise and the foolish <ref type="folio" cRef="F.236.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Become mentally impassioned— </l>
                        <l>They become impassioned by imagining </l>
                        <l>Color, beauty, and the appearance of women.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-463"/>
                    <lg tid="476">
                        <l>“But you, my boy, should understand </l>
                        <l>The essential nature of the body. </l>
                        <l>What wise man becomes impassioned </l>
                        <l>By the rotten smell from a cemetery?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-464"/>
                    <lg tid="477">
                        <l>“Do not be afraid; there is no reason </l>
                        <l>To be frightened by the nonexistent. </l>
                        <l>Look at the essential nature </l>
                        <l>Of the things that used to depress you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-465"/>
                    <lg tid="478">
                        <l>“A wonderful teacher of the Dharma </l>
                        <l>Clears away the fear of those who are afraid. </l>
                        <l>A teacher whose name is </l>
                        <l>The Lion of the Śākyas has appeared.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-466"/>
                    <lg tid="479">
                        <l>“Pleasure is impermanent and does not abide. </l>
                        <l>It is like a flash of lightning—</l>
                        <l>Though it blazes up, it is not real,</l>
                        <l>And the wise are not attached to it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-467"/>
                    <lg tid="480">
                        <l>“Bubbles and foam </l>
                        <l>Arise from turbulent waters, </l>
                        <l>Arising in dependence on causes and circumstances, </l>
                        <l>But with no agent to bring them about.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-468"/>
                    <lg tid="481">
                        <l>“In just the same way, </l>
                        <l>Names and forms arise from actions. </l>
                        <l>They stem only from causes, </l>
                        <l>But have no agent to bring them about.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-469"/>
                    <lg tid="482">
                        <l>“Where has the beautiful color gone? </l>
                        <l>And where do the impurities come from </l>
                        <l>That frightened you so much just now? </l>
                        <l>That, my boy, is what you should realize.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-470"/>
                    <lg tid="483">
                        <l>“Phenomena are not found in the outside world, </l>
                        <l>And they do not come from any direction. </l>
                        <l>They are beyond both coming and going, </l>
                        <l>And you should understand their essential nature.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-471"/>
                    <lg tid="484">
                        <l>“There is no subject that acts or feels, </l>
                        <l>And phenomena, </l>
                        <l>Which have no subject that acts or feels, </l>
                        <l>Are like illusions and not existent things.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-472"/>
                    <lg tid="485">
                        <l>“Understand your own body </l>
                        <l>In this way, and you </l>
                        <l>Should not be frightened </l>
                        <l>By the body of another.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-473"/>
                    <lg tid="486">
                        <l>“Just as one experiences amorous play </l>
                        <l>And pleasure when one dreams, </l>
                        <l>All amorous pleasure and play is like </l>
                        <l>That amorous play one experiences in a dream.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-474"/>
                    <lg tid="487">
                        <l>“So, my boy, go to </l>
                        <l>The Lion of the Śākyas, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.237.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And he will pull your fear and terror </l>
                        <l>Up by their roots.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-475"/>
                    <lg tid="488">
                        <l>“Your father and mother are no longer your protection, </l>
                        <l>Nor are your friends and relatives. </l>
                        <l>When they have left you, </l>
                        <l>How can you do what you wish?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-548" index="12">This stanza is widely quoted in the Tibetan commentarial literature.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-476"/>
                    <lg tid="489">
                        <l>“So go for protection to the one </l>
                        <l>Who clears away the fear of those who are afraid, </l>
                        <l>The Awakened One who is the protector of the unprotected, </l>
                        <l>To the Dharma, and to the Supreme Assembly.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-477"/>
                    <lg tid="490">
                        <l>“Those who go to him for protection— </l>
                        <l>Be they gods, gandharvas, or humans—</l>
                        <l>Are liberated from every fear, </l>
                        <l>And happiness is not hard for them to obtain.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-344"/>
                    <p tid="349">When the banker’s son had heard those verses, he felt happy
                        and rejoiced. He had gotten rid of his fear, and he felt joy. Overjoyed, he
                        cast the rotting corpse aside and left the park. Then the Blessed One
                        emitted a ray of light from his body in order to educate the banker’s son,
                        and the whole land of Magadha was filled with that light. The boy saw the
                        Tathāgata, the Worthy One, the Perfectly Awakened One, from a distance,
                        looking like the orb of the rising sun, burning with heat and beauty,
                        bringing glory and happiness, with his senses calmed, with his mind calmed,
                        well trained, incomparable, having obtained the highest truth, shining like
                        a sacrificial pillar of gold, with his senses guarded and controlled like
                        those of an elephant, clear and shining, not turbid like the sea, adorned
                        with the thirty-two characteristics of a great man, surrounded by his
                        disciples, and teaching the Dharma. The path upon which he was walking was
                        variegated and beautiful to behold, a railing of gems was set up, and
                        flowers were scattered all around.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-345"/>
                    <p tid="350">Then Śakra, the king of the gods, appeared before the boy <ref type="folio" cRef="F.237.b"/> and addressed him: “Boy, now that you have
                        seen the Tathāgata, your mind will be at ease, and that is truly a great
                        attainment. The Tathāgata is thinking of you, boy, so set out on this road
                        and go to the Tathāgata!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-346"/>
                    <p tid="351">So the boy went with Śakra, the king of the gods, to the Blessed
                        One, and Śakra, the king of the gods, gave the boy some mandārava flowers,
                        saying, “Boy, you should scatter these over the Tathāgata.” At this, the boy
                        scattered the flowers over the Blessed One. When he had done this, he bowed
                        his head to the Blessed One’s feet and circumambulated him three times. Then
                        he sat down before the Blessed One and addressed him with the following
                        words: “Blessed One, I take my refuge in the Blessed One, his Dharma, and
                        his Community, and I dedicate my root of virtue toward complete awakening.
                        Blessed One, I led this famously beautiful girl Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī, who
                        was approached even by kings, to the park to have fun and pleasure with her,
                        but suddenly she lost all of her color and her body started to rot. As all
                        my companions have left me, I have become very frightened. Blessed One, will
                        the king not execute me as punishment for this?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-347"/>
                    <p tid="352">The Blessed One replied, “My boy, have no doubt. Fear no longer
                        arises in those who have taken their refuge in the Buddha, so as I have
                        invited you here by means of the absence of fear, have no fear! Instead,
                        give up the cause from which fear and terror arise.” <ref type="folio" cRef="F.238.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-348"/>
                    <p tid="353">“Blessed One, what is the cause of fear and terror?” asked the
                        boy.</p>

                    <p tid="354">“Desire, aversion, and bewilderment are the cause of fear
                        and terror, my boy,” replied the Blessed One. “The arrogance of thinking ‘I am’ is
                        the cause. Being obsessed with doctrinal viewpoints is the cause. Attachment
                        caused by thirst is the cause. Egotism and self-centered ideas are the
                        cause. Attachment to things is the cause. Possessions and quarreling are the
                        cause. The fetter of viewing things as substantial and real is the cause.
                        Seeing the impermanent as permanent is the cause. Seeing suffering as
                        happiness is the cause. Seeing the ugly as beautiful is the cause. Seeing
                        no-self as self is the cause. The idea that there is something to hold on to
                        among the aggregates is the cause. Lack of insight into the sensory elements is the
                        cause. Absence of knowledge of the sense sources is the cause. Not seeing
                        the defects of the body is the cause. Enjoyment of life is the cause. Fear
                        and terror arise from these causes, and so they should be done away with. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-350"/>
                    <p tid="355">“My boy, do you see the perished body of this girl?”</p>

                    <p tid="356">“Blessed One, I see it,” replied the boy.</p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-572"/>
                    <p tid="357">“My boy,” said the Blessed One, “all composite things are like
                        this: impermanent, filled with suffering, and without self. They are always
                        changing and unstable, without permanence. They deceive foolish people. They
                        arise from falseness. They are without activity, and their establishment is
                        illusory. They are like an illusion because they are manifested from
                        nothing. They are like a dream because they provide a limited kind of
                        enjoyment. They are like a mirage because they manifest out of bewilderment.
                        They are like a visual distortion because they have never arisen in the
                        first place. They are like a reflection because actions culminate in their
                        effects. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.238.b"/> They are like the reflection of
                        the moon in water because there is no movement. They are like an echo
                        because sound is produced from the soundless. They are like shadow images because
                        they are the gate of the non-conditioned. They are like an empty fist because
                        they are empty of any essential nature. They are like the wind because they
                        cannot be held on to. They are false, without support, and without purpose.
                        They do not diminish or increase. In this way, my boy, all phenomena are
                        without a controlling self, and you should not be attached to them. What do
                        you think then, my boy? How do you view the thoughts and reflections
                        connected to your desire?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-353"/>
                    <p tid="358">“The desire of childish, ordinary people arises from imagining a
                        beautiful complexion and bodily form,” answered the boy. “It does not arise
                        when they contemplate impurity, and so on, as found in the discipline of the
                        noble Dharma. Blessed One, if one does not generate concepts of desire, its
                        origin does not arise.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-354"/>
                    <p tid="359">“Very good! Very good, my boy!” said the Blessed One. “This is how it
                        is: the essential nature of desire is to not generate concepts and thoughts.
                        So, my boy, you should strive to have the correct ideas concerning 
                        phenomena regarding not viewing them as self, not viewing them as other,
                        and not superimposing on them any other views.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-355"/>
                    <p tid="360">“But Blessed One, how does the bodhisatva strive 
                        to have the correct ideas concerning phenomena?” asked the boy.</p>

                    <p tid="361">“My boy,” replied the Blessed One, “the bodhisatva seeks awakening
                        by means of the essence of desire. My boy, the bodhisatva seeks awakening by
                        means of the essence of aversion, the essence of bewilderment, and the
                        essence of all the afflicted mental states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-357"/>
                    <p tid="362">“My boy, desire, aversion, and bewilderment are insubstantial, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.239.a"/> and the bodhisatva’s entrance into
                        knowledge is in accord with this.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-358"/>
                    <p tid="363">“My boy, desire, aversion, and bewilderment have no root, no
                        dwelling place, no foundation, and no subject that acts or feels. They are
                        beyond the dichotomy of inner and outer. They are empty, without a self,
                        being, life principle, soul, person, or personality. They have no
                        distinguishing marks, no construction of distinguishing marks, no wishes, no
                        pleasure, no passion, no thirst, and no conditioning. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-359"/>
                    <p tid="364">“My boy, desire, aversion, and bewilderment are unborn, and the
                        bodhisatva’s entrance into knowledge is in accord with this.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-360"/>
                    <p tid="365">“Further, my boy, all the thoughts of the bodhisatva who practices
                        genuinely are awakening. Why is this? The understanding of thought is beyond
                        demonstration, beyond wishes, beyond information. It is like an illusion—not
                        inside, nor outside, nor both. It is therefore formless, and that, my boy,
                        is exactly what the awakening of the bodhisatva is. Moreover, my boy, there
                        is nothing that bodhisatvas need to understand apart from their own
                        thoughts. To understand one’s own thoughts is indeed to understand the
                        thoughts of all beings. If one’s own thoughts stand aloof, the thoughts of
                        all beings stand aloof. By understanding the essence of one’s own thoughts,
                        one understands the essence of the thoughts of all beings. If one’s own
                        thoughts are pure, the thoughts of all beings are pure. If one’s own
                        thoughts are without desire, the thoughts of all beings are without desire.
                        If one’s own thoughts are without aversion, the thoughts of all beings are
                        without aversion. If one’s own thoughts are without bewilderment, <ref type="folio" cRef="F.239.b"/> the thoughts of all beings are without
                        bewilderment. If one’s own thoughts are without afflicted mental states, the
                        thoughts of all beings are without afflicted mental states. This
                        understanding is the understanding of omniscience. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-361"/>
                    <p tid="366">“Thus, my boy, the bodhisatva who practices genuinely has acquired
                        the insight that the thoughts of all beings are essentially without
                        afflicted mental states.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-362"/>
                    <p tid="367">“Moreover, because of their expanded vision that is in accord with
                        the true Dharma, there is no fervent desire in the trains of thought of
                        those who are not stained by afflicted mental states, even though they may
                        occasionally be sullied by adventitious afflicted mental states. Thus, those
                        bodhisatvas are not stained by afflicted mental states because they see that
                        afflicted mental states are adventitious.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-363"/>
                    <p tid="368">When this teaching had been given, the banker’s son Bhayadatta
                        attained patient acceptance that is in accord with all things.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-573"/>
                    <p tid="368"> 
                        The courtesan’s
                        daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī noticed that the banker’s son Bhayadatta had
                        been educated, and accompanied by about five hundred goddesses she caused
                        cymbals to sound, music to be heard, and songs to be sung. She went to the
                        Blessed One, bowed her head to his feet, and sat down before him.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-364"/>
                    <p tid="369">Then the princely Mañjuśrī addressed the banker’s son Bhayadatta:
                        “My boy, do you know this sister?”</p>

                    <p tid="370">“Yes, I do,” answered the boy.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-366"/>
                    <p tid="371">“What do you know her to be?” asked Mañjuśrī.</p>

                    <p tid="372">Then the boy spoke these verses to the princely Mañjuśrī:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-368"/>
                    <lg tid="491">
                        <l>“Beautiful forms are just like a mass of foam,</l>
                        <l>Feelings are just like bubbles, </l>
                        <l>Perceptions are like mirages,</l>
                        <l>Conditioning is like the soft plantain tree,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-478"/>
                    <lg tid="492">
                        <l>“And consciousness is just like an illusion. </l>
                        <l>Everything is produced from fantasies </l>
                        <l>And from the nonexistent imaginings of a fool. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.240.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Thus I know her to be the nonexistent concept of a child.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-479"/>
                    <lg tid="493">
                        <l>“Her body itself is inactive. </l>
                        <l>It is dead matter, like grass and stones. </l>
                        <l>Consciousness is impossible to display. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-480"/>
                    <lg tid="494">
                        <l>“There is no being, no self, no life principle, </l>
                        <l>No person in this body. </l>
                        <l>It is just a heap. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-481"/>
                    <lg tid="495">
                        <l>“There is no desire, aversion, or bewilderment, </l>
                        <l>No afflicted mental state </l>
                        <l>And no purification in it. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-482"/>
                    <lg tid="496">
                        <l>“The childish confusion of fools </l>
                        <l>Is to be found in superficial teachings. </l>
                        <l>The wise are not attached to this. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-483"/>
                    <lg tid="497">
                        <l>“This form has the same nature </l>
                        <l>As a foul-smelling corpse </l>
                        <l>Rotting away in the jungle. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-484"/>
                    <lg tid="498">
                        <l>“It is unborn in the beginning, </l>
                        <l>Does not perish in the end, </l>
                        <l>And is nonexistent in the present. </l>
                        <l>This is what I know her to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-485"/>
                    <lg tid="499">
                        <l>“As I have been liberated by impurity</l>
                        <l>After being stupefied by this young woman, </l>
                        <l>I am not really able to say, Mañjughoṣa, </l>
                        <l>What this is about.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-486"/>
                    <lg tid="500">
                        <l>“Although there is really no death and no transmigration, </l>
                        <l>I will still manifest my death for the sake </l>
                        <l>Of living beings who are coming to maturity, </l>
                        <l>So that no one will fail to seek awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-487"/>
                    <lg tid="501">
                        <l>“My desire, my aversion, </l>
                        <l>And all my afflicted mental states are superficial. </l>
                        <l>The character of all beings is the same. </l>
                        <l>This is the reality of all things.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-412"/>
                    <p tid="417">Then the Blessed One smiled. The nature of the Awakened One is such
                        that when he smiles, light of many colors appears from the opening of his
                        mouth: blue, yellow, red, white, rose, crystal, and silver. When it had
                        appeared, it reached all the way to the heaven of Brahmā <ref type="folio" cRef="F.240.b"/> and illuminated innumerable world spheres. When it
                        returned, it was absorbed into the crown of the Blessed One’s head.
                        Venerable Ānanda saw the Blessed One smile and approached his feet. He put
                        his robe over one shoulder and placed his right knee on the ground. He
                        joined his palms, bowed his head toward the Blessed One in veneration, and
                        addressed the Blessed One as follows:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-413"/>
                    <p tid="418">“The tathāgatas, the worthy ones, the perfectly awakened ones do
                        not smile without a specific reason and cause. So, Blessed One, what is the
                        reason, what is the cause, for your smile?”</p>

                    <p tid="419">Then Ānanda spoke the following verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-415"/>
                    <lg tid="502">
                        <l>“The Leader, the Knower of the World for whom there is no false doctrine, </l>
                        <l>The Teacher does not smile without a cause. </l>
                        <l>Thus, since you have smiled, we ask you sincerely: </l>
                        <l>What is the cause of your smile?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-488"/>
                    <lg tid="503">
                        <l>“Having seen the smile of the Victorious One, </l>
                        <l>Doubt has arisen in the world, even among the gods. </l>
                        <l>So we ask you to clear away the uncertainty of the doubtful. </l>
                        <l>Best among all human beings, please reveal to us the cause of your
                            smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-489"/>
                    <lg tid="504">
                        <l>“Who are those who have set their minds on the Dharma? </l>
                        <l>Who are the ones who in reality have been seen by the victorious ones? </l>
                        <l>Who are those who have made offerings to the Awakened One and praised him
                            today? </l>
                        <l>This is what we wish to hear.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-490"/>
                    <lg tid="505">
                        <l>“Who are those who have defeated Māra and his forces? </l>
                        <l>Who has satisfied the mind of our teacher today? </l>
                        <l>Who has understood the depth of conditioned things today? </l>
                        <l>We ask you to hear us. Please clear away our doubts.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-491"/>
                    <lg tid="506">
                        <l>“The whole world praises you with palms joined together </l>
                        <l>Because it wishes to hear why our leader has smiled. </l>
                        <l>Best among all human beings, </l>
                        <l>Please bring forth compassion and clear away the perplexity of
                            doubt.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-435"/>
                    <p tid="440">“Ānanda, do you see this courtesan’s daughter,
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī?” asked the Blessed One. <ref type="folio" cRef="F.241.a"/>
                    </p>

                    <p tid="441">“Yes, Blessed One, I see her,” Ānanda replied. “I see her, Sugata.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-437"/>
                    <p tid="442">“Ānanda,” said the Blessed One, “the princely Mañjuśrī has inspired
                        this courtesan’s daughter, Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī to fully embrace
                        incomparable, perfect awakening. When she had heard about the Dharma from
                        him, she developed the patient acceptance that is in accord with all
                        things.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-438"/>
                    <p tid="443">Then the Blessed One asked, “Ānanda, do you see this banker’s son
                        Bhayadatta?”</p>

                    <p tid="444">“Yes, Blessed One, I see him,” Ānanda replied. “I see him,
                        Sugata.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-440"/>
                    <p tid="445">“Ānanda,” said the Blessed One, “I inspired this banker’s son
                        Bhayadatta to fully embrace incomparable, perfect awakening. When he heard
                        about the Dharma from me, he developed the patient acceptance that is in
                        accord with all things. Ānanda, nine million two hundred thousand eons
                        from now, he will be called Ratnasaṃbhava, and this courtesan’s daughter
                        Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī will attain perfect awakening in a world sphere
                        called Ratna. She will be a tathāgata, a worthy one, a perfectly awakened
                        one called Ratnaprabha. Moreover, Ānanda, the pleasure and delight of the
                        beings in that world sphere will be like that of the gods of the Heaven of
                        the Thirty-Three. The only jewels there will be bodhisatva jewels, and the
                        lifespan of that tathāgata will be immeasurable. During the life of this
                        perfectly awakened one, the banker’s son Bhayadatta will be born as a
                        bodhisatva called Guṇaratnaprabha, and he will do the work of preserving the
                        collected teachings of the Tathāgata. When the tathāgata Ratnaprabha reaches
                        final nirvāṇa, he will pronounce the following prophecy for that bodhisatva
                        Guṇaprabha: <ref type="folio" cRef="F.241.b"/> ‘This bodhisatva Guṇaprabha
                        will reach complete awakening after me, and he will be a tathāgata, a worthy
                        one, a perfectly awakened one called Ratnārcis. His buddhafield will
                        resemble mine in appearance.’ ” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-441"/>
                    <p tid="446">As soon as this prophecy had been spoken for the two of them, for
                        the courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī and for the banker’s son
                        Bhayadatta, the six forms of existence in this trichiliocosm were shaken,
                        and all the worlds were illuminated by a great brightness. As that prophecy
                        was set forth, a hundred thousand beings developed the mind set on the
                        attainment of incomparable, perfect awakening.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-442"/>
                    <p tid="447">Then Venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One,
                        what is the name of this exposition of the Dharma? How should it be
                        adopted?” </p>

                    <p tid="448">The Blessed One said, “Ānanda, you should adopt this exposition of
                        the Dharma as <title xml:lang="en">The Chapter on the Gate to the Great Presentation</title>. You
                        should adopt it as <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī.</title> You should adopt it as
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Education of the Courtesan’s Daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī</title>.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-444"/>
                    <p tid="449">When the Blessed One had uttered these words, Venerable Ānanda, the
                        courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī, the banker’s son Bhayadatta,
                        the princely Mañjuśrī, the bodhisatvas, those great beings and all their
                        retinues, and the world with its gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas were
                        overjoyed and praised what the Blessed One had said.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="450">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-445"/>
                    <p tid="451">This was edited and finalized by the Indian scholar Surendrabodhi,
                        and by the chief editor and translator Venerable Yeshé Dé. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="452">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="454">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-492">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’jam dpal
                            rnam par rol pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 96, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 46 (mdo sde, kha), folios 217.a–241.b.</bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-541">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’jam dpal
                            rnam par rol pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa
                        zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                        Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
                        House), 2006–2009, vol. 46, pp. 588–654.</bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-494">Dharmarakṣa (tr). 佛說大淨法門經 (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Fo shuo da jing fa men jing</title>; Chinese translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title>), <ref target="http://tripitaka.cbeta.org/T17n0817">Taishō 817</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                                
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-495">Narendrayaśas (tr). 大莊嚴法門經 (<title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Da zhuang yan fa men jing</title>; Chinese translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title>), <ref target="http://tripitaka.cbeta.org/T17n0818">Taishō 818</ref>.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-578">Bhattacharya, Gouriswar. “How to Justify the
                        Spelling of the Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Term Bodhisatva?” In <title xml:lang="en">From Turfan to Ajanta: Festschrift for Dieter Schlingloff
                            on the Occasion of his Eightieth Birthday</title>, edited by Eli Franco
                        and Monika Zin, vol. II, 35–50. Rupandehi: Lumbini International Research
                        Institute, 2010.</bibl>

                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-493">Braarvig, Jens. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                            <ref target="https://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=volume&amp;vid=20">Mañjuśrī­vikrīḍita­sūtra</ref>
                        </title>. University of Oslo, Faculty of Humanities, Bibliotheca Polyglotta, <ref target="https://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=library&amp;bid=2">Thesaurus Literaturae Buddhicae</ref>, input 2010.</bibl>
                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-046-002-577">Dharmachakra Translation Committee. <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh52.html">The Teaching on the Indivisible Nature of the Realm of Phenomena</ref>
                        </title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadhātu­prakṛtyasambheda­nirdeśa</title>, Toh 52). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2018. </bibl>

                    
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-496">
                            <term>aggregates</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The fivefold basic grouping of the components
                                out of which the world and the personal self are formed.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-556">
                            <term>anger</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khong khro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁོང་ཁྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratigha</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Sanskrit, the term is almost synonymous with <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dveṣa</foreign> (see “aversion”), but in Tibetan is differentiated following <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> S. 1945. The present text contains this particular term’s widely quoted canonical gloss. See <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-173"/> and <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-547"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-557">
                            <term>aversion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhe sdang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞེ་སྡང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dveṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">See also “anger.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-497">
                            <term>bhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A generic term for “spirit” or “ghost.” They can
                                be malevolent or benevolent.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-535">
                            <term>conditioning</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par du ’byed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་དུ་འབྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhisamskāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-498">
                <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term><term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                <term type="definition">A magical formula invoking a particular deity for a
                    particular purpose; <term type="ignore">dhāraṇīs</term> are longer than most mantras, and their application
                    is more specialized.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-580">
                            <term>going forth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pravrajyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term used for renunciation and the taking of vows as a novice, 
                                monk, or nun at the vinaya or pratimokṣa level of Buddhist practice.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">go forth</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-499">
                            <term>sensory elements</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world
                                in terms of eighteen <term type="ignore">elements</term> (eye and
                                form, ear and sound, nose and odor, tongue and taste, body and
                                touch, and mind and mental objects, to which the six consciousnesses
                                are added).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-536">
                            <term>armed forces of the four branches</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpung gi tshogs yan lag bzhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡན་ལག་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturaṅgabala</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ancient Indian army was composed of <term type="ignore">four branches</term> (<term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturaṅga</term>)—infantry, cavalry, chariots, and
                                elephants.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-500">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings sometimes referred
                                to as “celestial musicians.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-501">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lower class of divine beings, described as
                                eagle-type birds with gigantic wing pans. They were traditionally
                                enemies of the nāgas. In the Vedas, they were thought to have
                                brought nectar from the heavens to earth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-502">
                            <term>great king</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahārāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A guardian of one of the four cardinal
                                directions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-503">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śravaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of the disciples of the Buddha who
                                follow the teachings of the Lesser Vehicle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-504">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings that resemble
                                humans to the degree that their very name—which means “Is that a
                                man?”—suggests some confusion as to their divine status.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-505">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of serpentine non-human beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-506">
                            <term>mandārava flowers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog man dA ra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་མན་དཱ་ར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mandārava</term>
                            <term type="definition">The flowers of the coral tree, <foreign xml:lang="la">Erythrina indica</foreign>, one of the five trees
                                of paradise, which has brilliant scarlet flowers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-507">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in
                                subterranean aquatic environments and who are known to hoard wealth
                                and esoteric teachings. They are associated with snakes and
                                serpents. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-508">
                            <term>protector of the world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten skyong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་སྐྱོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lokapāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">One category of Dharma protectors in
                                Buddhism.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-509">
                            <term>sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world
                                in terms of twelve <term type="ignore">sense sources</term> (eye and
                                form, ear and sound, nose and odor, tongue and taste, body and
                                touch, and mind and mental objects).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-510">
                            <term>solitary buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who obtains personal liberation through
                                very little or no instruction from others.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-511">
                            <term>expanse of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">Varyingly, “the sphere of dharmas,” “the base of
                                dharmas,” “the realm of dharmas”—a synonym for the nature of
                                phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-512">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten gyi
                                khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tri­sāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest universe spoken of in Buddhist
                                cosmology, consisting of one billion smaller world systems. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-513">
                            <term>worthy one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">A person who has accomplished the final fruition
                                of the path of the hearers and is liberated from saṃsāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-514">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of beings said to dwell in the north,
                                under the jurisdiction of the great king Vaiśravaṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-515">
                            <term>Ajātaśatru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma skyes dgra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་སྐྱེས་དགྲ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajātaśatru</term>
                            <term type="definition">King of Magadha and son of the king Bimbisāra.
                                While he was a prince, he became friends with Devadatta, who
                                convinced him to have his father killed and become the king instead.
                                After his father’s death, he became tormented with guilt and regret,
                                converted to Buddhism, and supported the compilation of the Buddha’s
                                teachings during the First Council.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-516">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s cousin and principal
                                attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-517">
                            <term>Bhayadatta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhayadatta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A banker’s son who purchases the favors of the
                                courtesan’s daughter Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī in <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title> sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-518">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the Sahā world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-519">
                            <term>Guṇaratnaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan rin chen ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་རིན་ཆེན་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇa­ratna­prabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of the banker’s son Bhayadatta when he
                                becomes a bodhisatva, according to a prophecy of the Buddha. </term>
                            <term type="alternative">Guṇaprabha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-520">
                            <term>Mañjughoṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dbyangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དབྱངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjughoṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">An alternate name for Mañjuśrī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-521">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The bodhisatva of wisdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-522">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The personification of negativity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-523">
                            <term>Ratnaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī when she reaches
                                perfect awakening, according to a prophecy of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-524">
                            <term>Ratnārcis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od ’phro </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འོད་འཕྲོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnārcis</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of the banker’s son Bhayadatta when he
                                reaches perfect awakening, according to a prophecy of the tathāgata
                                Ratnaprabha. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-525">
                            <term>Ratnasaṃbhava</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnasaṃbhava</term>
                            <term type="definition">Future name of the banker’s son Bhayadatta,
                                according to a prophecy of the Buddha. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-526">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-527">
                            <term>Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">su ren dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the Indian teachers invited to Tibet at
                                the time of the emperor Ralpacan (early ninth century). He was one
                                of the great Indian pandits who assisted the Tibetan translators
                                such as Yeshé Dé with the translation of Buddhist texts from
                                Sanskrit.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-528">
                            <term>Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser mchog ’od dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསེར་མཆོག་འོད་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Suvarṇottama­prabhāśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A courtesan’s daughter, central figure 
                                of <title xml:lang="en">The Miraculous Play of Mañjuśrī</title>
                                sūtra. Her name means “Glorious Light of Supreme Gold.” The 
                                Sanskrit name is reconstructed from the Tibetan and 
                                is not attested (see <ptr target="#UT22084-046-002-571"/>). </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-529">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam thos kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great guardian kings, he
                                presides over the northern direction and rules over the
                                yakṣas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-530">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator in the eighth and
                                ninth centuries. He was one of the twenty-five disciples of Guru
                                Rinpoche, and he assisted with the translation of more than three
                                hundred texts that now appear in the Kangyur and Tengyur.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-531">
                            <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six heavens of the desire
                                realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-532">
                            <term>Magadha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ga dha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ག་དྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Magadha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest kingdom of northern India during the
                                time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-533">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital of the ancient kingdom of
                                Magadha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-534">
                            <term>Vulture Peak</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod kyi phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mountain where many Great Vehicle teachings
                                were delivered by Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-046-002-537">
                            <term>Ratna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen can</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of a world sphere (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’jig rten gyi
                                khams</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>