<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yul la ’jug pa’i ye shes snang ba’i rgyan</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་ལ་འཇུག་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྣང་བའི་རྒྱན།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Ornament of the Light of Awareness that Enters the Domain of All
                    Buddhas</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­buddha­viṣayāvatāra­jñānālokālaṃkāra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་ཡུལ་ལ་འཇུག་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྣང་བའི་རྒྱན་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yul la ’jug pa’i ye shes snang ba’i
                    rgyan zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Ornament of the Light of Awareness that Enters
                    the Domain of All Buddhas”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sarva­buddha­viṣayāvatāra­jñānālokālaṃkāra­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">
                    Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-69">Mattia Salvini</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
                
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.3 <date>2015 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-047-002"/>
                <date>2015-02-17</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh100" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 100</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 47 (mdo sde, ga), folios 276.a–305.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bhande Yeshe De</author>
                    <location count-pages="59">
                        <start volume="47" page="553"/>
                        <end volume="47" page="611"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11655" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-26T08:37:12.819Z" user="mike">26/02/2019 08:37:12</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--Contents       
Summary
Acknowledgements
Introduction

The Translation
The Ornament of the Light of Awareness That Enters the Domain of All Buddhas

Bibliography
Notes-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="314">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-1"/>
                <p tid="1">The main topic of this sūtra is an explanation of how the Buddha and all things share the very same
                    empty nature. Through a set of similes, the sūtra shows how an illusion-like Buddha may dispense appropriate
                    teachings to sentient beings in accordance with their propensities. His activities are effortless since his
                    realization is free from concepts. Thus, the Tathāgata’s non-conceptual awareness results in great compassion
                    beyond any reference point.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="315">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. The
                    translation was produced from the Sanskrit by Mattia Salvini, who also wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor
                    compared the translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="316">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-3"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="4">
                            <l>“Space has no abode;</l>
                            <l> It is free from elaboration, and stainless.</l>
                            <l>Your mind is the same as space,</l>
                            <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                            <l> I bow to you!”<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-344"> Mañjuśrī praising the
                                    Buddha in The Ornament of the Light of Awareness. <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anālayaṃ yathākāśaṃ niḥprapañcaṃ nirañjanam | ākāśasama­citto 'si nirālamba namo 'stu
                                        te</foreign> || 13 ||</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The Ornament of the Light of Awareness (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānālokālaṃkāra</title>,
                        hereafter JAA) is of particular significance for its discussion of the nature of a buddha, his appearance
                        to sentient beings, and his beneficial activities. These themes are in turn related to the doctrine of
                        buddha nature (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgatagarbha</foreign>), important for both
                        general Mahāyāna Buddhism and Secret Mantra. The JAA has even been interpreted as propounding an explicit
                        Vajrayāna perspective of purity, and has been quoted by masters of secret mantra in India, Tibet, and
                        Japan. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">Although this sūtra is called “an ornament” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">alaṃkāra</foreign>), it is perhaps rather about an ornament. More literally, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">alaṃkāra</foreign> means “something that completes,” and according to the
                        conventions of ancient and medieval Indian literature, that is what an ornament should do. Therefore,
                        rather than being a dispensable decoration, the sūtra completes and adorns the light or appearance
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āloka</foreign>) of a special type of knowledge (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>). This knowledge is a meaningful awareness, not just the
                        awareness of an ordinary object. This awareness can engage with, or descend into (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avatāra</foreign>), the scope of all buddhas, which is their object or, more
                        precisely, their domain (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viṣaya</foreign>). If we follow the
                        interpretation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title>, the light of awareness is
                        itself the ornament that allows bodhisattvas to descend or enter into the domain of all buddhas.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-345">
                            <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">etacchrutamayodāra­jñānālokādyalaṃkṛtāḥ</foreign> | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhīmanto'vatarantyāśu sakalaṃ buddha­gocaram</foreign>
                            ||4.79||</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">Although texts preserved as sūtra or <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūtrānta</foreign> are
                        classified as “Word of the Buddha” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhavacana</foreign>), this
                        does not necessarily mean that the Buddha is the main speaker. For example, the bulk of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā­pāramitā­hṛdaya</title> (the “<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Heart Sūtra</title>”)
                        consists of a dialogue between the venerable Śāriputra and the bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara. In the present
                        sūtra, however, Buddha Śākyamuni is not only there to offer a seal of approval but is, in effect, the main
                        speaker. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">The sūtra locates its teaching in Rājgir, on the mountain of Vulture Peak. Although this is also
                        the place where many of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</title> teachings are set, the Buddha
                        is here dwelling in the Womb of the Dharmadhātu Palace. The symbolism is perhaps more attuned to the third
                        turning of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmacakra</foreign>, taking place in a variety of
                        locations and teaching a wide array of advanced topics. </p>
                    <p tid="9">The teaching does not take place within the ordinary appearance of our world sphere. Just before
                        the Buddha sits on his lion throne, the entire environment is transformed into the purest gold and jewels.
                        Such emphasis on the purified appearance of the environment of the sūtra may be significant in the light
                        of its more esoteric interpretations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-8"/>
                    <p tid="10">The audience is made up of two kinds of individual: hearers who have already become arhats, and
                        bodhisattvas who are close to buddhahood, i.e., on the tenth or last level (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūmi</foreign>), called “Cloud of Dharma.” The hearers are headed by
                        Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya; his name means “Kauṇḍinya who understood,” and he is described in other sūtras as the
                        first monk to have been praised by the Buddha for having understood his teaching. The bodhisattvas are
                        headed by Mañjuśrī, the embodiment of wisdom or higher knowledge, who is also the main interlocutor of
                        this sūtra. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-9"/>
                    <p tid="11">The Buddha signals that an exceptional teaching will take place through a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihārya</foreign>, an extraordinary display of light meant to attract audiences
                        from very far away. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prātihārya</foreign> is sometimes translated as
                        “miracle,” but rather than being an inexplicable testimony of divine intervention, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihāryas</foreign> are classified in Mahāyāna scholasticism as a means to draw
                        the listeners’ attention, and to instill reverence toward what is going to be taught. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">If we follow Buddhist cosmology and cosmogony, the appearance of a buddha may be understood as an
                        exceptional event, resulting from a myriad of positive causal concomitances. Each buddha conforms to
                        specific cosmic regularities, due to inner causal factors (his aspirations during countless previous
                        lives) and outer ones (the collective merit of sentient beings); and each buddha arises within a specific
                        area of the universe, called a “buddhafield” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhakṣetra</foreign>). This will be the field of activity of one, and only one, buddha—at least in
                        the sense that only one buddha will enact the specific set of activities that, just as the sun cannot
                        avoid shining, no buddha can avoid performing. Certain teachings will be taught by all the buddhas; the
                        jeweled throne that appears and invites Buddha Śākyamuni to sit and teach suggests that this is, indeed,
                        one of those recurrent teachings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">Infinite buddhafields may exist at the same time. Mahāyāna sūtras often specify that diligent and
                        wise bodhisattvas can perceive and even visit other buddhafields, paying their respects and obtaining
                        teachings from the buddhas residing there. In this sūtra, after Buddha Śākyamuni emits light that fills
                        the entire trichiliocosm, a very large number of bodhisattvas arrive from other buddhafields—suggesting
                        once more the importance of the teaching about to be given. </p>
                    <p tid="14"> Mañjuśrī is the bodhisattva associated with wisdom (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>).<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-346"><!--KB-->It is by now common to
                            translate <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign> as “wisdom,” and more precise
                            alternatives (such as “superior cognition”) may appear cumbersome or odd. However, it is useful to
                            keep in mind that <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign> is also a synonym for
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhidharma</foreign> (a higher understanding of the
                            dharmas), <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma­pravicaya</foreign> (the grouping or analysis
                            of the dharmas), and of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipaśyanā</foreign> (special insight
                            into the nature of things). This also helps explain the sūtra’s interest in discrete classifications,
                            especially in the last sections.</note> The JAA’s thematic focus on wisdom and the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñāpāramitā</foreign> is quite clear: Mañjuśrī begins by asking the
                        Buddha about the meaning of non-arising and non-cessation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-12"/>
                    <p tid="15">As the <title xml:lang="en">Heart Sūtra</title> puts it, all dharmas are “emptiness, without
                        characteristics, non-arisen, non-ceased.”<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-347"><!--KB-->[...]
                                <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūnyatālakṣaṇā anutpannā aniruddhā</foreign> [...] See
                            Vaidya (1961): 98. Note also that “non-cessation, non-arising” are the first words of Nāgārjuna’s
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūla­madhyamaka­kārikā</title>; the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānālokālaṃkāra</title> is quoted in Candrakīrti’s commentary to the “Examination of the
                            Tathāgata” section, where emptiness (hence, non-arising and non-cessation) is the logical ground to
                            prove the fundamental equality between the Tathāgata and all the dharmas. The same quote appears in
                            Kamalaśīla’s commentary to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajra­cchedikā</title>, and in Rongzom
                            Mahāpaṇḍita’s explanation of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmatā­yukti</foreign>
                            (reasoning in terms of the nature of the dharmas). See Köppl (2008): 117.</note> That all dharmas
                        neither arise nor cease seems to be a specifically Mahāyāna doctrine that sets the Mahāyāna sūtras, and
                        the treatises associated with them, apart from their non-Mahāyāna counterparts. While all Buddhist schools
                        agree that dharmas are dependently arisen, within a Mahāyāna perspective this also entails that in some
                        sense they do not arise and do not cease (in the Yogācāra scheme of three natures, this regards only their
                        “wrongly imagined nature,” the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parikalpita</foreign>). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-13"/>
                    <p tid="16">In response to Mañjuśrī, the Buddha answers that “non-arising and non-cessation […] designates the
                            Tathāgata.”<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-348">JAA, below</note> The Buddha is a
                        synonym for the non-arising of all dharmas, appearing in a certain way to sentient beings according to
                        their karma and their dispositions. In other words, in the landscape of the JAA, there is no ultimate
                        difference between the Tathāgata and the tathatā, the nature of things; nor, furthermore, between the
                        teacher and the place where the teaching occurs (the lion throne at the center of the Womb of Dharmadhātu
                        Palace), between the teacher and the assembly of listeners (bodhisattvas on the tenth <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūmi</foreign>), or between the teacher and the Dharma that he teaches (which is
                        the nature of a Buddha’s appearance as a teacher). All these differences appear within the close-knit
                        fabric of interdependence and its ultimate emptiness.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-349">A number of Indian and Tibetan masters have referred to the JAA to
                            highlight that, from the perspective of the non-arisen dharmatā, there is no difference between the
                            buddhas and anything else. </note> The JAA relates the teachings on dependent arising and emptiness to
                        a specific perspective regarding a type of awareness (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>), which, unlike ordinary consciousness, is free from a point of reference.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-350"><!--KB-->The question of the precise difference between
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign> is of course complex. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>
                            can be either a synonym of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign>, or a synonym of
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>, or—and this is the sense that we are
                            referring to in the present context—a non-referential, liberating “awareness.” The structure of the
                            Sanskrit words helps in remembering the intended sense: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign> is the cognition of a point of reference or object (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viṣaya-prativijñapti</foreign>). What is absent in <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> is the point of reference or object (the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vi</foreign>). Within the context of the JAA, when referring to an exalted or
                            desirable state, we always find <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> and never
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign>: “These bodhisattvas have come looking
                            for awareness” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāgateme bahu­bodhi­sattvā
                                jñānārthinaḥ</foreign>); “Mañjuśrī, you should rely on awareness” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna­pratisaraṇena ca te mañjuśrīr bhavitavyam</foreign>); “They wish for a
                            buddha’s awareness […]” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">te buddha­jñānābhilāṣiṇo</foreign>);
                            “They dedicate their roots of merit toward obtaining the tathāgata-awareness” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kuśala­mūlaṃ tathāgata­jñāna­prati­lambhāya pari­ṇāmayanti</foreign>);
                            “Awareness is explained as the entrance in the sameness of the three times” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñānam ucyate</foreign> | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tryadhva­samatāvatāraḥ sarva­dharmeṣu</foreign>); “For those endowed with attachment to form,
                            Mañjuśrī, the eye is attachment; the awareness of the nature of form and the eye is non-attachment”
                                (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa­saṅga­saṃyuktānāṃ mañjuśrīś cakṣuḥ saṅgaḥ</foreign>
                            | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa­cakṣuḥ­prakṛti­jñānam asaṅgaḥ</foreign>); “Awareness
                            precedes all your actions, and you are free of any point of reference: I bow to you!” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anābhoga­pravṛtto 'si sarva­doṣa­vivarjitaḥ</foreign> / <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna­pūrvaṅgamā ceṣtā nirālamba namo 'stu te</foreign>).
                            “Awareness” thus seemed the English term that (like <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>) best covers both the cognition of objects, as well as soteriologically more
                            crucial types such as the “non-conceptual awareness beyond the world” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lokottara­nir­vikalpa­jñāna</foreign>) and so forth. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-14"/>
                    <p tid="17">An analysis of the contents of the JAA should take into account its close relation to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title>, the principal treatise on buddha nature within Indian
                        Buddhist literature. Despite being a treatise rather than a sūtra, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> is invested with special authority, as it is considered to have been
                        revealed by Maitreya, the very next buddha in our specific universe. Within the Tibetan tradition, Asaṅga
                        (the recipient of Maitreya’s revealed texts) is believed to be the author of its main commentary, in which
                        the JAA is cited.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-351">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</title> on <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> 1.5.
                            Whether we consider the verses and commentary as the work of the same author or not, it does not seem
                            necessary to term the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</title> a commentary, since its terminological
                            choices make it clear that this is how it presents its own relationship to the root verses.</note>
                        Although the term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgatagarbha</foreign> never occurs in the
                        JAA, Maitreya and Asaṅga clearly interpret the text in the context of the teachings on buddha nature. </p>
                    <p tid="18"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> is composed of three sections (five
                        chapters), dealing with the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgatagarbha</foreign> in a
                        non-purified, partially purified, and completely purified state, respectively. The themes of the JAA are
                        mostly related to the completely purified state, i.e., a perfect and complete buddha and his activity. </p>
                    <p tid="19"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> makes use of the JAA in two different
                        sections. In chapter 1, the JAA is quoted in connection with one of the crucial verses that explain the
                        nature of buddhahood:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="20">“unproduced, effortless, not arisen by understanding from others, buddhahood is endowed with
                            the power of awareness and compassion, and has the two purposes.”<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-352">
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> 1.5: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asaṃskṛtam anābhogam apara­pratyayoditam</foreign> | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhatvaṃ jñāna­kāruṇyaśaktyupetaṃ dvayārthavat</foreign>. Strictly speaking, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</title> quoting the JAA in this section relates to the following
                                explanatory verses as well, and starts after verse 8.</note>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-15"/>
                    <p tid="21">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</title> (commentary) quotes from various sections of the
                        sūtra <note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-353">The quotations as found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</title> differ from the precise wording of the JAA as we have it, but
                            some differences are clearly due to textual corruptions, while others may indicate a different
                            manuscript tradition. It is clear, in any case, that the passages are meant as quotations and not mere
                            paraphrases. </note> and relates them to the first four qualifications found in the verse:</p>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="309">i. When the JAA states that “non-arising” and “non-cessation” are epithets of the
                                Tathāgata, it shows that the Buddha is <emph>unproduced</emph>.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="310">ii. The nine examples explain what it means for the Tathāgata to be non-arising and
                                non-cessation (given in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> as the reason for
                                his being unproduced).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="311">iii. The explanations of all that has been pacified show that, since all his elaborations
                                and concepts have been pacified, the Tathāgata is <emph>effortless</emph> with respect to his own
                                activities.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="312">iv. The next section shows that the Tathāgata realizes for himself the gates to the
                                realization of the nature of all dharmas, and goes on to explain the sixteen features of the
                                Tathāgata’s realization (this links to <emph>not arisen by understanding from others</emph>).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="313">v. One sentence describes the Tathāgata’s great compassion, showing that he is endowed
                                with unexcelled awareness and compassion.</p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-16"/>
                    <p tid="22">According to the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyākhyā</foreign>, therefore, the JAA is
                        an elaborate exposition of the nature of buddhahood—buddha nature in its fully purified form. Furthermore,
                        chapter 4 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> can be considered a commentary on
                        the section of the JAA presenting the nine examples of a buddha’s activity; this also regards buddha
                        nature in a fully purified state, and activity is in fact the final topic in the list of seven “crucial
                        terms” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajrapada</foreign>) through which Maitreya’s treatise, in
                        its opening stanza, parses its own contents. In the JAA the appearance of a Buddha is compared to (1)
                        Indra’s Palace reflected upon the emerald ground, (2) the Dharma drum that plays for the gods, (3) a rain
                        cloud, (4) the god Mahābrahmā, (5) the rays of the sun, (6) the wish-fulfilling jewel, (7) an echo, (8)
                        the earth, and (9) space.<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-354">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> inverts the order of the last two analogies.</note>
                        The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> elaborates on the significance of each example,
                        on their mutual relationship, and on the overall purpose of the whole set. A verse in chapter 4 (4.83)
                        interprets the initial sections of the JAA (including the nine analogies) as a syllogism, including a
                        thesis, an analogy, and a logical ground or proof (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratijñā</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dṛṣṭānta</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hetu</foreign>):</p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="23">
                            <l>“The thesis is that all effort has been pacified;</l>
                            <l>The logical ground is that wisdom is free from concepts;</l>
                            <l>The analogies starting with Śakra’s image</l>
                            <l> Are for the sake of establishing the subject matter.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="24">Thus the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> provides some keys for understanding
                        the sūtra according to a number of topical subdivisions and an overall rationale behind its structure.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-17"/>
                    <p tid="25">The activity of a buddha is a complex matter, and it is therefore understandable that the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title> gears its interpretation of the JAA toward the
                        illustrations that help make this difficult point easier to assimilate. Buddhas are free from delusion in
                        the form of conventions, yet appear to engage with conventions in order to benefit others. A buddha is
                        free from mental constructs and intentional mental elaborations, yet his teachings are attuned to each and
                        every mindset. This seeming paradox has been tackled through a number of divergent solutions, some of
                        which (as we shall see) are directly linked to the contents of the JAA. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-18"/>
                    <p tid="26">Following the nine analogies, the JAA discusses the nature of awakening. The topic is brought up
                        to explain why a buddha’s activity is as described in the nine analogies. The answer is that a buddha’s
                        activity could not be otherwise because of the nature of a buddha’s awakening. The JAA’s progression
                        follows the questions posed by Mañjuśrī, directly enunciating the first part of the syllogistic structure
                        discussed above (the relationship between thesis and logical ground). </p>
                    <p tid="27">This section offers several remarkable explanations of a buddha’s awakening, relying on
                        fundamental categories of Buddhist thought, such as the twelve entrances (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</foreign>) and the eighteen bases (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</foreign>). These categories subsume the entirety of existent things (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</foreign>s) within schemes that may highlight the dependent arising of
                        sentience, defined as the perception of objects. Mañjuśrī most consistently praises the Buddha for the
                        lack of that perception. The section on the nature of awakening concludes with several verses extolling
                        Śākyamuni Buddha as “you who are free of any point of reference” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirālamba</foreign>). Freedom from point of reference is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> rather than <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign>; it is not mind
                        or conventions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhi</foreign> or <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃvṛti</foreign>). Mañjuśrī is asked by the Buddha to rely on <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>, and he responds to the teachings with an extensive praise of its
                        nature. This section is therefore related to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra</title>’s explicit
                        discussion of the distinction between <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</foreign>; as also to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra</title>, and a number of other treatises wherein ultimate truth is described as
                        never within the range of consciousness. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-19"/>
                    <p tid="28">One of the first prominent authors to employ the JAA is probably the Madhyamaka philosopher
                        Bhāviveka (6th century), who inaugurates a long trend of quoting the JAA when discussing the nature of
                        buddhahood. More specifically, he cites the JAA in order to prove that a buddha is devoid of any
                        conceptuality or mind whatsoever.<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-355">See Almogi
                            (2009).</note> Candrakīrti and Kamalaśīla also quote the JAA in the context of establishing that all
                        dharmas share the same nature as the Buddha.<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-356">See
                            Prasannapadā on MMK (De la Vallée Poussin, 1913: 12.16) and also Kamala­śīla’s commentary on the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajra­cchedikā</title>, in the glosses preceding the sentence “all
                            dharmas are Buddha­dharmas” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarva­dharmā buddha­dharmā
                                iti</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-20"/>
                    <p tid="29">The JAA starts to be quoted in a Mantranaya context at least by the 8th century, in Buddhaguhya’s
                        commentary on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­vairocana­sūtra</title>. The latter text is of special
                        importance for East Asian Buddhism. Kūkai (Kobo Daishi, 8th–9th century), who founded the Shingon school
                        of Japan, brought the JAA back to Japan from his visit to China in 806. The JAA influenced his
                        visualization techniques relating to the dharmakāya. In this instance, the JAA had a direct bearing on
                        very practical aspects of tantric meditation.<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-357">See
                            Study Group on Buddhist Sanskrit Literature (2004b): 87.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-21"/>
                    <p tid="30">The Vajrayāna adept Naḍapāda (Nāropā, 10th–11th century), whose lineage became influential in
                        Tibet during the later translation period, quoted from the JAA in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sekoddeśa­ṭīkā</title>, a text primarily associated with the Kālacakra tradition and still extant in
                            Sanskrit.<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-358">See Sferra (2006).</note> In this
                        work Naḍapāda cites the following verse to corroborate his explanation of a buddha’s awareness in relation
                        to the four <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mudrās</foreign>: </p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="31">
                            <l>“With your unplaced awareness,</l>
                            <l>You see all the fields,</l>
                            <l>And the conduct of all beings.</l>
                            <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                            <l>I bow to you!”<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-359">The Tibetan translation of
                                    this verse in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sekoddeśa­ṭīkā</title> differs from the Degé
                                    Kangyur. Notably, the Degé version translates <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign> with <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mkhyen pa</foreign>, while
                                    the translators of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sekoddeśa­ṭīkā</title> used <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ye shes</foreign>. See also Sferra (2006): 173.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="32">Naḍapāda’s quote brings up the doctrine of “non-abiding” or “no ground to stand upon” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apratiṣṭhāna</foreign>), the idea, recurrent in some sūtras, that the
                        mind should not abide within any dharma whatsoever. This theme was also important for subsequent secret
                        mantra authors who made use of the JAA for scriptural support. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-22"/>
                    <p tid="33">According to Tibetan sources,<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-360">See Tatz
                            (1987).</note> Advayavajra (11th century, also known as Maitrīgupta and Maitrīpa) was a student of
                        Naropa, Ratnākaraśānti (10–11th century), Jñānaśrīmitra (10–11th century), and Śabarapāda (10–11th
                        century?). He is also considered one of the two main teachers of Marpa Chökyi Lodrö (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar pa chos kyi blo gros</foreign>, 1012–1097). The colophons to his works describe
                        Advayavajra as both a great scholar (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paṇḍita</foreign>) and a
                        realized Vajrayāna adept (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avadhūta</foreign>). Although his works
                        are short, they reflect this double characterization. His Madhyamaka interpretation is especially attuned
                        to Vajrayāna practice and to the context and terminology of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāmudrā</foreign>. In both regards, recurrent notions in the JAA play an important role within his
                        writings, and he cites the JAA in at least three texts.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-361">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Advaya­vajra­saṃgraha</title>: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcatathāgata­mudrā­vivaraṇa</title> (p. 25); <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caturmudrā</title> (p.
                            34); <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amanasikārādhāra</title> (p. 60).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="34">Furthermore, the relationship between non-arising and primordial purity has been linked in the
                        Tibetan tradition to the JAA, which thus becomes an important element in the exposition of secret mantra
                        within that fold.<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-362">This is particularly true of
                            the writings of Rongzom Mahāpaṇḍita (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rong zom mahāpaṇḍita</foreign>, 11th
                            century). See Köppl (2008) and Almogi (2009).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="35">Many scholars throughout the Mahāyāna Buddhist world have taken the JAA as an authoritative source
                        of inspiration; we hope that contemporary readers may also find some of its depth transmitted in this
                        English translation. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-23"/>
                    <p tid="36">The translation presented here is primarily based on the Sanskrit edition by the Study Group on
                        Buddhist Sanskrit Literature (2005). The Sanskrit was also compared to the Tibetan translation in the Degé
                        Kangyur. In several instances the Tibetan proved useful by offering more complete readings. Hence, we have
                        at times followed the Tibetan rather than the Sanskrit reading. On occasion, we have also consulted
                        Kimura’s transliteration of the Sanskrit manuscript (GRETIL version, 2004) and reverted to its readings.
                        For the most part, the Tibetan follows the Sanskrit closely, although in a few instances it appears to be
                        based on a different manuscript tradition. This is certainly plausible if the proposed date of the
                        Sanskrit manuscript (11th–13th century) is correct, since the Tibetan translation was produced centuries
                        earlier. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="317">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="318">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra </head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="319">The Ornament of the Light of Awareness that Enters the Domain of All Buddhas </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-24"/>
                    <p tid="37">
                        <ref cRef="F.276.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to the Buddha!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="38">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="thusDid">-->Thus have I heard, at one time, the Bhagavat was dwelling on the
                        Vulture Peak Mountain in Rājgir, on a summit of infinite gems, in the Womb of Dharmadhātu Palace, together
                        with a great assembly of twenty-five thousand monks. <!--</modularPassage>-->All of them were arhats who
                        had exhausted their outflows. They were without afflictions and controlled. Their minds were perfectly
                        liberated, and their wisdom was perfectly free. They were knowledgeable great elephants who had
                        accomplished what needed to be done. They had laid down their burden and fulfilled their own benefit. They
                        had destroyed the bonds of existence and, thanks to their correct knowledge, their minds were perfectly
                        liberated. They had obtained supreme perfection in mastering all mental states. The sixty-eight great
                        hearers, headed by Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya, were also there. <ref cRef="4" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-25"/>
                    <p tid="39">Moreover, present with the Bhagavat were seventy-two quintillion bodhisattvas, such as the
                        youthful Mañjuśrī, Dhanaśrī, Buddhiśrī, Bhaiṣajyarāja, and Bhaiṣajya­samudgata. All of them were turning
                        the Dharma wheel that does not turn back. They were skilled in inquiring about the vaipulya sūtras of the
                        Heap of Jewels<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-363">Vaipulya could refer to a category
                            of teachings, the Mahāyāna as a whole, the Ratnakūṭa as a whole, or specifically, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapa­parivarta</title>.</note> and had obtained the level called Cloud of
                        Dharma. In terms of wisdom, they were like Sumeru, and all of them had thoroughly cultivated the dharmas
                        of emptiness, no sign, no wish, no arising, no birth, and no existence. The greatly profound Dharma
                        appeared to them <ref cRef="F.276.b"/>, and they had the postures of the tathāgatas. In other world
                        spheres, they had been sent out by quintillions of tathāgatas. All of them were fully clairvoyant and well
                        settled in the essential nature of all dharmas. <ref cRef="6" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-26"/>
                    <p tid="40"> At that time, the Bhagavat thought, “To generate great swiftness, strength, impetus, and stamina
                        in the bodhisattva great beings, I shall give a Dharma discourse. From as many world spheres as there are
                        grains of sand in the river Ganges, I shall cause splendorous bodhisattva great beings to assemble. Hence,
                        I will display a sign to show that there is to be a great teaching of the Dharma. I shall cause a great
                        light, so that bodhisattva great beings shall come to me and ask for a great Dharma teaching.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-27"/>
                    <p tid="41">With that thought, the Bhagavat illuminated the ten directions with great clouds of light rays
                        that shone in as many worlds as there are atoms of dust in the great trichiliocosm—an uncountable and
                        inconceivable number. At that very time, as many bodhisattva great beings as there are atoms of dust in
                        ten ineffable quintillion buddhafields approached him from all the ten directions; each and every
                        bodhisattva great being arrived with exceptional feats beyond imagination. They first performed a fitting,
                        inconceivable worship of the Bhagavat, and then sat down in front of him on lotus seats that appeared
                        through the force of their aspirations. They stayed still, looking at the Bhagavat without blinking. <ref cRef="8" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-28"/>
                    <p tid="42">A lion throne within a great, jeweled lotus then appeared at the center of the Womb of Dharmadhātu
                        Palace. It was an uncountable number of leagues in width, and of unprecedented height. <ref cRef="F.277.a"/> It was made of gems and jewels sparkling in every way, with lightning for lamps, and a surrounding
                        railing made of gems and jewels. Its staffs were of gems and jewels of inconceivable brilliance, and
                        incomparable gems and jewels enclosed it. Jewel garlands splendid beyond comparison beautified the throne,
                        studded with many types of precious gems. It was hung about with raised parasols, standards, and flags. </p>
                    <p tid="43">From above the lion throne within the great lotus of gems and jewels, ten innumerable quintillions
                        of light rays now issued forth in all directions and illumined the very many world spheres in the ten
                        directions by their great brightness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-29"/>
                    <p tid="44">And at that very time, from each and every one of the ten directions, gods, nāgas, yakṣas,
                        gandharvas, demigods, garuḍa, kiṃnaras, great serpents, śakras, brahmās, and world protectors arrived, as
                        many as there are atoms of dust in the ineffable quintillion buddhafields. </p>
                    <p tid="45">Some of them arrived together with a quintillion apsaras, uncountable and beyond conception,
                        singing and playing musical instruments while they sat in jeweled palaces. Some arrived with palaces that
                        were made of flowers, others with palaces were made of heaps of uragasāra sandalwood. Some palaces were
                        made of pearls, others of diamonds, and others still of gems and jewels that shone like diamonds. <ref cRef="10" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="46">Some were made of gold from the river Jāmbū, and others were built with gems that shone in all
                        colors. Some were made of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaśirāja</foreign> gem and others of
                        wish-fulfilling jewels. Still other palaces <ref cRef="F.277.b"/> were made of those gems worn by Śakra. </p>
                    <p tid="47">Yet others arrived with uncountable, inconceivable quadrillions of apsaras, singing and playing
                        musical instruments while they sat in palaces of great jewels, gems beaming uninterruptedly from the array
                        of pure, ocean-ground jewels. </p>
                    <p tid="48">As they arrived, they first worshipped the Bhagavat in an inconceivable, matchless, immeasurable,
                        and limitless manner. Then they arranged themselves on one side, on seats that manifested through their
                        own aspirations. After having seated themselves, they stayed still, looking at the Bhagavat without
                        blinking. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-30"/>
                    <p tid="49">At that very moment this world sphere, a great trichiliocosm, turned into Jāmbū River gold. It was
                        adorned with trees of many great gems and jewels, divine flowering trees, trees of fine fabrics, and trees
                        of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uragasāra</foreign> sandalwood perfume. It was covered with a
                        net of precious moon gems, sun gems, and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyutpradīpa</foreign>
                        gems. Parasols, standards, and flags were hoisted. </p>
                    <p tid="50">Innumerable quintillions of apsaras with half their bodies in sight thronged all trees, which were
                        enveloped by strings of pearls and garlands of great precious jewels. <ref cRef="12" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-31"/>
                    <p tid="51"> At that time these verses rang out from the lion throne with its great, jeweled lotus inside:</p>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“Come, be seated, king of the best among men!</l>
                        <l>I came about by the force of your merit.</l>
                        <l>Fulfilling my wish, today I shall support you,</l>
                        <l>Victor, best among the two-footed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-32"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“My body is made of jewels.</l>
                        <l>Oh Guide, for your sake,</l>
                        <l>At my center is a beautiful jewel lotus; <ref cRef="F.278.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Protector, please fulfill my wish today! <ref cRef="14" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-33"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“Seated on this jewel lotus,</l>
                        <l>You shall beautify this entire world and me.</l>
                        <l> You shall teach the Dharma to many millions of living beings.</l>
                        <l>Hearing such Dharma, one obtains a lion throne like this!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-34"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l> “Thousands of light rays shining from your limbs</l>
                        <l>Illuminate many world spheres.</l>
                        <l>This is the sign of someone in whom joy is born.</l>
                        <l>Guide, ascend to me!<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-364">It appears that <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāyakāḥ</foreign> is here singular (the verses are not in
                                classical Sanskrit and plurals in <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āḥ</foreign> are attested
                                even by Edgerton). The Tibetan has only <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dren pa</foreign>;
                                hence, it does not force us to take it as plural.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-35"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Quickly, take your seat and grant your favor!</l>
                        <l>In the past, in this very place,</l>
                        <l> I have supported eighty million self-arisen sages.</l>
                        <l>May the Bhagavat also, today, bestow his favor!”<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-365">The manuscript transcription has <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavāṇ</foreign> rather than the edited text’s <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavat</foreign>. We prefer the first <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vibhakti</foreign> reading for syntactical reasons.</note>
                            <ref cRef="16" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-36"/>
                    <p tid="57">At this the Bhagavat arose from his previous seat and sat down on the lion throne with its great
                        jewel lotus inside. He sat with his legs crossed and observed the entire gathering of bodhisattvas. Then,
                        to those bodhisattva great beings, he signaled that he was about to deliver a distinguished Dharma
                        teaching. </p>
                    <p tid="58">At that very time, the entire assembly of bodhisattvas had the thought, “The youthful Mañjuśrī
                        should now inquire of the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha, about non-arising and
                        non-cessation. We have not heard that Dharma teaching for a long time.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-37"/>
                    <p tid="59">The youthful Mañjuśrī had understood the Bhagavat’s signal, and he also knew what the bodhisattva
                        great beings were thinking. So he arose and adjusted his upper robe so that one shoulder was uncovered. He
                        then knelt in front of the Bhagavat with his right knee placed in the center of a lotus.<note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-366">Translation based on the Tibetan.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="60"> With joined palms he then addressed this question to the Bhagavat:<note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-367">“With joined palms” according to the Tibetan.</note> “Bhagavat,
                        ‘non-arising’ and ‘non-cessation’ have been spoken of. Bhagavat, to what dharma do the terms ‘non-arising’
                        and ‘non-cessation’ refer?” <ref cRef="18" type="sanskrit"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.278.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-38"/>
                    <p tid="61">He also expressed his question in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“Guide, you speak </l>
                        <l> Of ‘non-cessation’ and ‘non-arising.’</l>
                        <l> Greatly wise one, </l>
                        <l>How do you explain those terms?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-39"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“ ‘Non-cessation’ and ‘non-arising,’</l>
                        <l>Why are they called so?</l>
                        <l>Great sage, please tell us</l>
                        <l>Through analogies and reasons!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-40"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“These many bodhisattvas have come here,</l>
                        <l>Wishing for awareness; </l>
                        <l>They were sent to salute you, Lord, by many guides of the world.</l>
                        <l>So please teach the lofty and excellent, good Dharma!” <ref cRef="20" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-41"/>
                    <p tid="65">In reply, the Bhagavat said to the youthful Mañjuśrī:</p>
                    <p tid="66"> “Good, Mañjuśrī, good! Mañjuśrī, it is good that you think to ask the Tathāgata about this
                        matter. You are striving for the benefit of many people, for the happiness of many people, and with
                        compassion for the world. You are doing so for the goodness, benefit, and happiness of a great group of
                        beings, both gods and men. You are also acting so that the bodhisattva great beings who have come here may
                        obtain the level of a buddha. Mañjuśrī, you should apply yourself to this point without alarm, without
                        fear, and without hesitation. And, Mañjuśrī, you must rely on awareness. Mañjuśrī, when the Tathāgata
                        teaches about ‘non-arising and non-cessation,’ this expression actually refers to the Tathāgata. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-42"/>
                    <p tid="67">“It is as follows. Mañjuśrī, imagine that this wide earth were made entirely of beryl, so that in
                        that beryl one could see reflections of the abode of the Thirty-Three; of Śakra, lord of the gods; and of
                        his Palace of Victory. <ref cRef="F.279.a"/> And imagine that Śakra, lord of the gods, could be seen
                        there, playing and enjoying himself with the five divine objects of pleasure. <ref cRef="22" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-43"/>
                    <p tid="68">“At that time, the gods might call out to all the men, women, boys, and girls of Jambūdvīpa, ‘Come
                        here, men and women! Look at Śakra, lord of the gods, as he is playing, enjoying, and amusing himself with
                        the five divine objects of pleasure in his Palace of Victory. Come, all men and women, offer gifts and
                        make merits. Take up discipline and abide by it. Then you shall also get to play, enjoy, and amuse
                        yourself in such Palaces of Victory. You will become like Śakra himself and will come to possess wealth
                        like his. The lord of the gods, Śakra, has all divine enjoyments, and so shall you.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-44"/>
                    <p tid="69">“Then, Mañjuśrī, all those men, women, girls, and boys, who could see the abode of the
                        Thirty-Three along with Śakra, lord of the gods, and his Palace of Victory reflected in the wide earth of
                        beryl, would fold their hands toward this reflection. They would scatter flowers and offer perfumes toward
                        it, saying, ‘May we also obtain such a body as that of Śakra, lord of the gods; may we also play, enjoy,
                        and amuse ourselves in the Palace of Victory, just like Śakra, lord of the gods.’ <ref cRef="24" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-45"/>
                    <p tid="70">“However, those beings would not understand that this would merely be a reflection in the wide
                        earth of beryl, a reflection occurring due to the complete purity of the beryl, wherein the abode of the
                        Thirty-Three, along with Śakra, lord of the gods, and his Palace of Victory, could be seen. <ref cRef="F.279.b"/> Wishing for the state of Śakra, they would then offer gifts and make merits. They
                        would take up discipline and abide by that. They would then dedicate the roots of what is wholesome toward
                        birth in that reflection of the abode of the Thirty-Three. </p>
                    <p tid="71">“Mañjuśrī, in that wide earth of beryl there would, of course, be no abode of the Thirty-Three,
                        and neither would there be a Palace of Victory, or Śakra, lord of the gods. However, due to the purity of
                        the great beryl, the abode of the Thirty-Three along with the Palace of Victory and Śakra, lord of the
                        gods would all be visible. Non-existent, non-arisen, and non-ceased, their reflections would be seen
                        because of the purity of the great beryl. <ref cRef="26" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-46"/>
                    <p tid="72">“In the same way, Mañjuśrī, it is due to the complete purity of the mind, as well as due to proper
                        cultivation, that sentient beings see the body of a tathāgata. Mañjuśrī, it is due to the power of the
                        Tathāgata that sentient beings see him. And still he remains non-existent, non-arisen, and non-ceased. He
                        is neither existence nor non-existence, neither visible nor invisible, neither worldly nor unworldly,
                        neither an object of thinking nor not an object of thinking, neither existent nor non-existent. </p>
                    <p tid="73">“It is so, Mañjuśrī, that sentient beings focus on the reflection of the Tathāgata and offer it
                        flowers, perfumes, garments, and jewels while making this aspiration: ‘May we also become like the
                        Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha.’ Wishing for a buddha’s awareness, <ref cRef="F.280.a"/> they offer gifts and make merit. They take up discipline and abide by it. Then they
                        dedicate that root of what is wholesome toward obtaining a tathāgata’s awareness. <ref cRef="28" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-47"/>
                    <p tid="74">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, the reflection of Śakra, ruler of the gods, on that wide earth made
                        of beryl does not move. Nor does it think, elaborate, construct, or conceptualize. It is not a construct,
                        not a concept, inconceivable, and not a mental placement. It is peaceful and cool, non-arising,
                        non-cessation, not seen, not heard, not smelt, not tasted, not touched, not a sign, not a cognition, and
                        not something that can be made known. </p>
                    <p tid="75"> “In the same way, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha does not
                        move. Nor does he think, elaborate, construct, or conceptualize. He is not a construct, not a concept,
                        inconceivable, not a mental placement. He is peaceful and cool, non-arising and non-cessation, not seen,
                        not heard, not smelt, not tasted, not touched, not a sign, not a cognition, and not something that can be
                        made known. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-48"/>
                    <p tid="76"> “Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata is in the realm of non-arising. On the other hand, he appears in the
                        world as a reflected image. According to the beliefs of sentient beings he displays diverse appearances
                        and diverse lifespans. He appears among sentient beings who have become fitting receptacles for awakening
                        thanks to their maturation and belief. These sentient beings then hear the Dharma according to their
                        dispositions and beliefs. According to their dispositions they understand the three vehicles <ref cRef="F.280.b"/>, and according to their dispositions they obtain belief.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-49"/>
                    <p tid="77"> “It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, a great Dharma drum for making sounds of Dharma, which come about
                        through the force of merit of the gods of the Thirty-Three, is placed in the atmosphere above the
                        Vaijayanta Palace, beyond visible range. The divine scions cannot see it or behold it. </p>
                    <p tid="78"> “However, Mañjuśrī, it is a great Dharma drum. Sometimes the gods in the heaven of the
                        Thirty-Three become so intensely and continuously oblivious from playing with, enjoying, and delighting
                        themselves with their divine pleasures that they fail to enter the divine hall called Sudharma to jointly
                        chant the Dharma. And, Mañjuśrī, Śakra, lord of the gods, becomes so intensely and continuously oblivious
                        from playing with, enjoying, and delighting himself with his divine pleasures that he fails to sit on his
                        Dharma seat to speak of the Dharma. <ref cRef="32" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-50"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Mañjuśrī, at such times, that great Dharma drum, not to be seen or beheld, hanging in the
                        atmosphere beyond visible range, plays a Dharma sound that addresses all the gods in the heaven of the
                        Thirty-Three, ‘Friends! Form, sound, smell, flavor, and touch are impermanent; do not be careless. Do not
                        quickly fall down from this abode! Friends, all co-producing factors are suffering! Friends, all
                        co-producing factors are without self! Friends, all co-producing factors are empty! Do not become
                        careless: for those who die and fall from here, to take birth here once again is difficult. So chant the
                        Dharma together, and delight in the pleasant joy of Dharma. Remain with Dharma as your essence, being
                        inclined toward the Dharma, with Dharma pouring like rain, recollecting and placing the Dharma in the
                        mind. <ref cRef="F.281.a"/> You shall not then have to part from these divine enjoyments and delights in
                        games of pleasure.’ <ref cRef="34" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-51"/>
                    <p tid="80"> “At that time, Mañjuśrī, due to the sound of that great Dharma drum—invisible, formless,
                        inconceivable, not a mental construct, out of sight, unborn, unceasing, beyond the way of words, and
                        devoid of mind, mentality, and consciousness—all the gods in the heaven of the Thirty-Three are roused,
                        scared, alarmed, and very distressed. They enter the divine hall called Sudharma and remain there,
                        delighting in the pleasant joy of Dharma. They make the Dharma their essence, they become inclined toward
                        the Dharma, with Dharma pouring like rain, recollecting and keeping the Dharma in mind. When they die and
                        fall from that abode, they will again reach excellent places. Śakra, the king of the gods, then enters
                        Sudharma, the divine hall, takes a seat on the Dharma throne, and teaches the Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-52"/>
                    <p tid="81">“Mañjuśrī, when the demigods battle against the gods, whenever the gods of the heaven of the
                        Thirty-Three are being defeated, the Dharma drum emits a sound that makes the demigods so frightened,
                        alarmed, agitated, and distressed that they flee. <ref cRef="36" type="sanskrit"/> Nevertheless, Mañjuśrī, that great
                        Dharma drum does not have a producer, nor does it have a body. Mañjuśrī, that Dharma drum is invisible,
                        not to be beheld, not true, not real, with no mind, without intention, sign-less, formless, voiceless,
                        immaterial, non-dual, and out of sight. </p>
                    <p tid="82">“Nevertheless, Mañjuśrī, for those gods in the heaven of the Thirty-Three who have previously
                        purified themselves, a sound comes forth from the great Dharma drum. <ref cRef="F.281.b"/> It occurs to
                        pacify all the misfortunes, troubles, and afflictions of the gods of the Thirty-Three. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-53"/>
                    <p tid="83"> “Mañjuśrī, in the same way that from that great Dharma drum, a sound issues forth—invisible,
                        bodiless, not to be beheld, not true, not real, with no mind, without intention, sign-less, formless,
                        voiceless, immaterial, non-dual, and out of sight—due to the maturation of previous karma of those gods in
                        the heaven of the Thirty-Three, to pacify all their misfortunes, troubles, and afflictions, and prompts
                        the careless gods, and in the same way as that sound of Dharma occurs to pacify all the misfortunes,
                        troubles, and afflictions of the gods of the Thirty-Three, <ref cRef="38" type="sanskrit"/> so, too, Mañjuśrī, although
                        the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is invisible, not to be beheld, bodiless, not
                        true, not real, with no mind, without intention, sign-less, formless, voiceless, non-dual, non-existent,
                        and out of sight, nevertheless, Mañjuśrī, sentient beings perceive the voice of Dharma due to the
                        maturation of previous karma, according to their individual aspirations and interests. And that sound of
                        Dharma occurs to pacify all misfortunes, troubles, and afflictions of all sentient beings. Being the voice
                        of Dharma, it is regarded in the world as the voice of the Tathāgata. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-54"/>
                    <p tid="84"> “Mañjuśrī, there is no Tathāgata. However, the designation ‘Tathāgata’ comes about in the world
                        because of the voice of Dharma. <ref cRef="F.282.a"/> It is exclusively due to the maturation of sentient
                        beings’ previous wholesome karma that they perceive the voice of the Tathāgata. That voice emerges in
                        order to produce happiness for all sentient beings and to prompt those who are careless. Mañjuśrī, as
                        those sentient beings hear that sound, they form the concept of a tathāgata, thinking, ‘This is the
                        Tathāgata’s body.’ </p>
                    <p tid="85"> “The speech of the Tathāgata is heard so that beginner bodhisattvas and all immature, ordinary
                        people may generate roots of what is wholesome by taking the Tathāgata as their reference point. However,
                        Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata should be known to be non-arisen and non-ceasing. <ref cRef="40" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-55"/>
                    <p tid="86">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, at the end of summertime, during the first month of rains, due to the
                        maturation of sentient beings’ previous karma, and to generate, out of the multitudes of seeds and
                        elements, all the grass, thickets, medicinal herbs, and trees on earth, winds begin to blow in the
                        atmosphere and the sky above; then water comes about due to that wind, and it falls on the great earth.
                        Thus, the great earth is satisfied, and all sentient beings in Jambūdvīpa are joyful and happy. Referring
                        to this, the notion of a ‘cloud’ comes about in the world. </p>
                    <p tid="87">“Mañjuśrī, whenever not much rain falls from the atmosphere and the sky above, all the sentient
                        beings in Jambūdvīpa think, ‘Here there is not a cloud.’ But when, Mañjuśrī, a lot of rain falls on the
                        great earth from the atmosphere and the sky above, they say: ‘Oh, a great cloud <ref cRef="F.282.b"/> is
                        pouring down water, satisfying the great earth.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-56"/>
                    <p tid="88">“However, Mañjuśrī, when this happens there is neither a cloud, nor anything that can be
                        designated as a cloud. Mañjuśrī, a large mass of water is generated by the wind, and then it falls from
                        the atmosphere above. Mañjuśrī, the mass of water disappears in the atmosphere itself, due to the ripening
                        of sentient beings’ previous karma. <ref cRef="42" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="89">“Mañjuśrī, that cumulus of water above in the atmosphere, stirred by the wind and releasing water,
                        is designated a cloud due to the maturation of sentient beings’ previous karma. However, Mañjuśrī, no
                        cloud can be found there, nor anything that could be designated a cloud. Mañjuśrī, the cloud is non-arisen
                        and non-ceasing; it does not enter the way of mind, and it is free from coming and going. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-57"/>
                    <p tid="90"> “In the same way, Mañjuśrī, for bodhisattva great beings who have accumulated previous roots of
                        what is wholesome; for other sentient beings who wish for the awareness of a hearer or a pratyekabuddha;
                        and for those sentient beings who have accumulated roots of what is wholesome and possess the causes to be
                        shown the path to nirvāṇa, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha with unobstructed
                        brilliance comes to be counted as arisen in the world. </p>
                    <p tid="91"> “Whatever he says is thus (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathā</foreign>), undistorted,
                        thus and not otherwise. Therefore, he was given the name Tathāgata among gods and men. <ref cRef="44" type="sanskrit"/>
                        Mañjuśrī, this word appears among gods and men: Tathāgata. However, Mañjuśrī, there is no Tathāgata to be
                        found. The Tathāgata, Mañjuśrī, is not a sign, and he is free from signs. <ref cRef="F.283.a"/> He is not
                        placed in any of the primary or intermediate directions. He is unreal, non-arisen, and non-ceasing. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-58"/>
                    <p tid="92">“On the other hand, Mañjuśrī, the appearance of the Tathāgata satisfies and entertains this world,
                        including the gods, through the Dharma. And then, due to the ripening of previous karma of beginner
                        bodhisattvas and immature, ordinary people who are guided by means of nirvāṇa, it appears that the
                        Tathāgata is no more to be seen. They think, ‘The Tathāgata has passed into complete nirvāṇa.’ However,
                        Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata neither arises nor ceases. The Tathāgata, Mañjuśrī, is non-arisen and non-ceasing.
                        Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is primordially in complete nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-59"/>
                    <p tid="93">“Mañjuśrī, when some water is taken as a point of reference for an unreal cloud that has not
                        arisen nor ceased, and is non-existent, the designation ‘cloud’ is established in the world. In the very
                        same way, Mañjuśrī, when the teaching of the Dharma is taken as a point of reference for an unreal
                        tathāgata who has not arisen nor ceased, and who is non-existent and primordially unborn, the designation
                        ‘the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha’ becomes established in the world. <ref cRef="46" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-60"/>
                    <p tid="94">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, every day the great and unsurpassed Brahmā, who controls ten
                        trichiliocosms, looks upon all the classes of gods, as far as the class of the gods of the Four Great
                        Kings. At that time, Mañjuśrī, while the great Brahmā, who controls ten trichiliocosms, looks upon all the
                        classes of gods, they all abandon their games of pleasure, delights, and enjoyments. <ref cRef="F.283.b"/>
                        They stop playing their percussion instruments and halt their singing. Shifting their attention from their
                        games of pleasure and delights, they respectfully fold their hands and look toward the great Brahmā
                        without blinking. For a moment, the great Brahmā offers sight of himself to all the classes of gods. At
                        that time, the gods all long to be born in the world of the great Brahmā, and they dedicate their roots of
                        what is wholesome toward taking birth in the world of the great Brahmā. <ref cRef="48" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-61"/>
                    <p tid="95">“Moreover, Mañjuśrī, that great Brahmā, without falling down from that Brahmā Palace, empowers
                        another great Brahmā as the controller of ten trichiliocosms, thanks to the power of his previous
                        aspirations and due to the prior accumulation of virtue on the part of the gods. </p>
                    <p tid="96">“Mañjuśrī, that emanated great Brahmā looks upon all the classes of gods, as far as the class of
                        the gods of the Four Great Kings. At that time, Mañjuśrī, among all the classes of gods, all the scions of
                        the gods abandon their games of pleasure, delights, and enjoyments. They stop playing their percussion
                        instruments and halt their singing. Shifting their attention from their games of pleasure and delights,
                        they respectfully fold their hands and look toward the great Brahmā without blinking. For a moment, the
                        great Brahmā offers sight of himself to all the classes of gods. At that time, the gods all long to be
                        born in the world of the great Brahmā, and they dedicate their roots of what is wholesome toward taking
                        birth in the world of the great Brahmā. <ref cRef="50" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-62"/>
                    <p tid="97">“Still, Mañjuśrī, no Brahmā is there to be found. Mañjuśrī, Brahmā is empty, dependent, unreal,
                        without syllables, without voice, <ref cRef="F.284.a"/> without place, and also not an existent thing. He
                        is inconceivable, without signs, and free from mentality, mind, and consciousness. He is non-arisen and
                        unceasing. And yet, Mañjuśrī, a semblance of him offering sight of himself appears among all the classes
                        of gods, by the power of his own previous roots of what is wholesome and aspirations, and due to the
                        previous accumulations of roots of what is wholesome on the part of those gods. </p>
                    <p tid="98">“Yet, Mañjuśrī, those gods do not think, ‘This Brahmā is an emanation. He is empty, dependent,
                        unreal, without syllables, without voice, without place, and also not an existent thing. He is
                        inconceivable, without signs, and free from mentality, mind, and consciousness. He is non-arisen and
                        unceasing.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-63"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Mañjuśrī, in the same manner the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is empty,
                        dependent, unreal, without syllables, without voice, without place, and also not an existent thing. He is
                        inconceivable, without signs, and free from mentality, mind, and consciousness. He is non-arisen and
                        unceasing. </p>
                    <p tid="100"> “Still, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is seen in the
                        world. This is due to the power of his previous aspirations during his practice as a bodhisattva, and also
                        due to the power of all the roots of what is wholesome of the beginner bodhisattvas, of those who set out
                        on the vehicles of the hearers and the pratyekabuddhas, as well as of all the immature, ordinary people.
                        He is seen in the world as a tathāgata adorned with hundreds of thousands of marks, like a reflected
                        image; and he does not move from his place. <ref cRef="52" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-64"/>
                    <p tid="101">“However, Mañjuśrī, the beginner bodhisattvas and all those who set out on the vehicles of the
                        hearers and the pratyekabuddhas, as well as all immature, ordinary people, do not think, ‘The Tathāgata,
                        the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is empty, dependent, unreal, without syllables, without voice,
                        without place, and also not an existent thing. He is inconceivable, without signs, and free from
                        mentality, mind, <ref cRef="F.284.b"/> and consciousness. He is non-arisen and unceasing.’ </p>
                    <p tid="102">“Yet, Mañjuśrī, from the body of the Tathāgata, adorned with hundreds of thousands of marks,
                        during all the empty postures of a tathāgata, a great Dharma teaching emanates for the sake of varied
                        sentient beings with diverse beliefs. </p>
                    <p tid="103">“That Dharma teaching occurs to pacify all the troubles, harms, and afflictions of all sentient
                        beings. In that regard, the Tathāgata is the same, neutral, without concepts, and does not make any
                        distinctions. Thus, Mañjuśrī, through this explanation you should understand that ‘non-arising and
                        non-cessation’ is an appellation of the Tathāgata.” <ref cRef="54" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-65"/>
                    <p tid="104">Then, at that time, the Bhagavat spoke the following two stanzas:</p>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“The Tathāgata always has the quality of non-arising,</l>
                        <l>And all dharmas resemble the Sugata.</l>
                        <l>Yet immature minds, by their grasping at signs,</l>
                        <l> Roam the world among non-existent dharmas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-66"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>“The Tathāgata is a reflected image</l>
                        <l>Of the wholesome Dharma without .</l>
                        <l>Yet here there is no tathatā and no Tathāgata,</l>
                        <l>While an image is seen in the entire world. <ref cRef="56" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-67"/>
                    <p tid="107"> “It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, here in Jambūdvīpa the rays of the sun only shine at first on the
                        great king of mighty mountains. After that, they shine on the Cakravāḍa and Mahācakravāḍa ranges. After
                        that, they shine on the elevated regions of the earth. After that, they shine on the low-lying regions of
                        the earth here in Jambūdvīpa. </p>
                    <p tid="108">“Yet those sun rays, Mañjuśrī, do not form mental constructs or concepts. They do not think or
                        ponder. The rays of the sun, Mañjuśrī, are free from mentality, mind, and consciousness; they are unborn
                        and unceasing, without characteristics, free from characteristics; <ref cRef="F.285.a"/> without mental
                        placement, free from mental placement, without elaboration, free from elaboration; without torment, free
                        from torment; not abiding hither, not abiding thither; not high, not low; not bound, not liberated; not
                        knowing, not ignorant; not afflictions, not free from afflictions; not speaking the truth, not speaking
                        falsely; not over there, not here; not on dry land, not in the stream; not the domain of reasoning, not
                        the domain of non-reasoning; neither with form, nor formless. Yet, Mañjuśrī, due to the distinction of
                        higher, middling, and lower places on the earth, the light shines differently, at higher, middling, and
                        lower degrees causing varied shades. <ref cRef="58" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-68"/>
                    <p tid="109">“In the same way, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha does not
                        form mental constructs or concepts. He does not think or ponder. Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata is free from
                        mind, mentality, and consciousness. He is unborn and unceasing. He is without characteristics, free from
                        characteristics; without mental placement, free from mental placement, without elaboration, free from
                        elaboration; without torment, free from torment; not abiding hither, not abiding thither; not high, not
                        low; not bound, not liberated; not knowing, not ignorant; not afflictions, not free from afflictions; not
                        speaking the truth, not speaking falsely; not over there, not here; not on the shore, nor on the
                        non-shore; not on low land, nor on non-low land; not on dry land, nor on non-dry land; not in the stream,
                        nor in the non-stream; not on the plains. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-69"/>
                    <p tid="110"> “He is not omniscient, not non-omniscient; <ref cRef="F.285.b"/> not reasoning, not
                        non-reasoning; not acting, not non-acting; neither behavior nor non-behavior; neither mindful nor
                        unmindful, neither with intention nor free from intention; neither mind nor without mind; neither
                        originated nor unoriginated;<note place="end" index="25" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-368">Translation based on
                            the Tibetan.</note> neither name nor no name; neither form nor no form; neither verbal expression nor
                        non-verbal expression; neither a possible object of imputation, nor not a possible object of imputation;
                        neither visible nor invisible; neither a conducive way nor not a conducive way; neither leading along the
                        way, nor not leading along the way; neither having obtained the result, nor not having obtained the
                        result; neither a concept, nor not a concept; neither free from concepts, nor not free from concepts. <ref cRef="60" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-70"/>
                    <p tid="111">“Similarly, Mañjuśrī, the rays of awareness from the round sun of the Tathāgata shine brilliantly
                        in the three realms, unimpeded throughout the dharmadhātu with neither edge nor center. Once they shine,
                        they first descend upon the bodies of bodhisattvas, whose aspirations are like the great lord of
                        mountains. After that, they descend upon the bodies of those who set forth on the Vehicle of
                        Pratyekabuddhas. Then they descend upon the bodies of those who have set forth on the Hearers’ Vehicle.
                        After that, they descend upon the body of sentient beings with wholesome aspirations, according to their
                        specific inclinations. After that, the rays of awareness from the round sun of the Tathāgata even descend
                        upon the body of those sentient beings with mental continua that are stuck in what is wrong.<note place="end" index="26" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-369">Translation based on the Tibetan, which suggests
                            the Sanskrit could have been <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mityātvaniyata­santānānāṃ
                                satvānāṃ kāye</foreign>.</note> The rays assist all these beings by producing causes for what will
                        come later, and increase their wholesome dharmas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-71"/>
                    <p tid="112">“In that respect, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata <ref cRef="F.286.a"/> is everywhere the same, neutral,
                        without concepts, and does not make any distinctions. Moreover, Mañjuśrī, the round sun of the Tathāgata’s
                        awareness does not think, ‘I will teach this person the vast Dharma, but I will not teach that one.’
                        Neither do they have the concept, ‘This person has vast beliefs, that one has middling beliefs. This one
                        has belief in the Hearers’ Vehicle. This one has wholesome aspirations while that one is low, with wrong
                        aspirations.’ <ref cRef="62" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="113">“Mañjuśrī, the round sun of the Tathāgata’s awareness does not think, ‘This sentient being has
                        vast beliefs, so I will teach him the Great Vehicle. This one has middling beliefs, so I will teach him
                        the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle. This one has belief in the Hearers’ Vehicle, so I will teach him the Hearers’
                        Vehicle. I shall come to understand the aspirations of sentient beings with either wholesome or
                        unwholesome aspirations, then purify them and straighten up their view. Even for sentient beings stuck in
                        what is wrong, I shall teach a fitting dharma.’ </p>
                    <p tid="114">“The light of the rays of awareness from the round sun of the Tathāgata does not have any such
                        concepts. And why? Because the light of the rays of awareness from the round sun of the Tathāgata has cut
                        off all constructs, concepts, and elaborations. On the other hand, Mañjuśrī, because of variations in
                        sentient beings’ inclinations to wholesome intent, the light of the rays of awareness from the round sun
                        of the Tathāgata is varied too. <ref cRef="64" type="sanskrit"/>
                        <ref cRef="B2" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-72"/>
                    <p tid="115"> “It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, in the great ocean there is a great, precious jewel called
                            <distinct>Fulfilling All Wishes</distinct>. When it is attached to the top of a banner and a sentient
                        being makes a wish,<ref cRef="F.286.b"/> sentient beings will perceive corresponding words coming forth
                        from the jewel. However, that great, precious jewel does not form mental constructs or concepts. It does
                        not think or ponder. It is inconceivable, free from what can be conceived, and free from mind, mentality,
                        and consciousness. </p>
                    <p tid="116">“In the very same way, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha does
                        not form mental constructs or concepts. He does not think or ponder. He is inconceivable, free from what
                        can be conceived, and free from mind, mentality, and consciousness. He is non-grasping, the act of not
                        holding on. He is not obtained, not obtainable. He has eliminated arbitrary truths as well as attachment,
                        aversion, and delusion. He is neither true nor false, neither permanent nor impermanent, neither shining
                        nor not shining, neither worldly nor non-worldly. He is without deliberation or analysis. He is non-arisen
                        and unceasing. <ref cRef="66" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-73"/>
                    <p tid="117">“He is inconceivable, imponderable, essence-less, and not possibly an essence. He is empty of
                        non-existence; he is free from striving or giving anything up. He cannot be clung to. He is not a
                        conventional expression; he is the cutting off of conventional expressions. He is not bliss, he is free
                        from bliss; he is the destruction of bliss. </p>
                    <p tid="118">“He cannot be counted; he is free from counting. He is not movement, he has reached non-movement;
                        he has cut off all movement and has cut off all conventional expressions. </p>
                    <p tid="119">“He cannot be seen or beholden, he is ungraspable. He is not space, not lack of space. He is not
                        visible, not to be described, not an assemblage, and not a non-assemblage. He is neither mentally
                        constructed nor not mentally constructed. He is not established, shown, <ref cRef="F.287.a"/> afflicted,
                        or purified. He is not name, not form, not sign; not karma, not the maturation of karma. He is not past,
                        not future, not present. He is nothing whatsoever. He is without impurity, without syllables, without
                        voice, beyond a voice, not speech. He is not a characteristic, he is free from all characteristics; not
                        perceived inside, outside, or in between. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-74"/>
                    <p tid="120">“And Mañjuśrī, the awareness jewel of the Tathāgata is completely pure in its intent, and is
                        fixed at the top of the banner of great compassion. According to his or her inclinations and beliefs, a
                        sentient being perceives a Dharma teaching issuing forth from that jewel.<note place="end" index="27" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-370">It seems that <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tataḥ</foreign> here
                            means “from that,” which the gender indicates as referring to “that jewel.”</note> And in this
                        respect, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata is the same, neutral, without concepts, and does not make any
                        distinctions. <ref cRef="68" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-75"/>
                    <p tid="121">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, sentient beings perceive an echo issuing forth as the intimation of
                        someone else’s speech.<note place="end" index="28" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-371">We have here translated
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñapti</foreign> as “intimation,” as it seemed the only
                            possible term to capture both possible senses of coming to know an object (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viṣaya­prati­vijñapti</foreign>) and vocal or bodily information (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vāg­vijñapti</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāya­vijñapti</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="122">“But that echo is not past, future, or present. It cannot be perceived inside, outside, or in
                        between. It is non-arisen and unceasing. It is not cut off, not permanent; it is not endowed with
                        awareness, nor is it without awareness. It is neither wisdom nor not wisdom, neither knowledge nor
                        ignorance, and neither liberation nor not liberation. </p>
                    <p tid="123">“It is neither blameworthy nor free from blame, neither recollection nor non-recollection,
                        neither placed nor unplaced, neither sitting nor not sitting. It is not the earth element, not the water
                        element, not the fire element, and not the wind element. <ref cRef="F.287.b"/> It is neither co-produced
                        nor unproduced, neither free from elaboration nor with elaboration, neither speech nor not speech, and
                        neither visible nor invisible. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-76"/>
                    <p tid="124"> “It is without syllables, free from non-syllables, without voice, beyond voice, without
                        comparison, beyond comparison, not a characteristic, free from characteristics. It is neither peace nor
                        not peace, neither long nor short, neither sentient nor insentient, and neither mental nor not mental. It
                        is neither to be beheld, nor not to be beheld. It is empty of the nature of seeing. It is
                        non-recollection, and non-mental-placement. It is not deliberation, not analysis, and free from mind,
                        mentality, and consciousness. In all regards it is the same, neutral, without concepts, and does not make
                        any distinctions. It is beyond the three times. However, Mañjuśrī, the echo, the voice of many sounds,
                        comes forth for sentient beings with varied inclinations, as the intimation of the voice of many sounds,
                        and sentient beings perceive it to be just that way. <ref cRef="70" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-77"/>
                    <p tid="125">“In the very same way, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is not
                        past, future, or present. He cannot be perceived inside, outside, or in between. He is non-arisen and
                        unceasing. He is not cut off, not permanent; he is not endowed with awareness, nor is he without
                        awareness. He is neither with wisdom nor without wisdom. He is neither knowledge nor ignorance, neither
                        liberation nor not liberation. </p>
                    <p tid="126"> “He is neither blameworthy nor free from blame, neither with recollection nor without
                        recollection, neither placed nor unplaced, neither sitting nor not sitting. He is not the earth element,
                            <ref cRef="F.288.a"/> not the water element, not the fire element, and not the wind element. He is
                        neither co-produced nor unproduced, neither elaboration nor non-elaboration, neither speech nor not
                        speech, and neither visible nor invisible. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-78"/>
                    <p tid="127">“He is without syllables, without voice, beyond voice, without comparison, beyond comparison, not
                        a characteristic, free from characteristics. He is neither peaceful nor not peaceful, neither long nor
                        short, neither sentient nor insentient, and neither mental nor not mental. He is neither to be beheld, nor
                        not to be beheld. He is empty of the nature of seeing. He is non-recollection and non-mental-placement. He
                        is not deliberation, not analysis, and free from mind, mentality, and consciousness. In all regards he is
                        the same, neutral, without concepts, and does not make any distinctions. He is beyond the three times.
                        Yet, Mañjuśrī, sentient beings with varied beliefs perceive the speech of the Tathāgata, issuing forth in
                        accordance with their manifold inclinations. <ref cRef="72" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-79"/>
                    <p tid="128">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, it is through having the earth as their basis and support that all
                        grass, thickets, herbs, and trees grow to become sizeable. But, Mañjuśrī, the earth does not form mental
                        constructs or concepts. With respect to everything it is the same, free from concepts, free from
                        distinctions. It is free from speculations and free from mind, mentality, and consciousness. </p>
                    <p tid="129">“In the same way, Mañjuśrī, it is through having the Tathāgata as their basis and support that
                        all the roots of what is wholesome of all sentient beings grow and become sizeable. <ref cRef="F.288.b"/>
                        Whether it is the roots of what is wholesome of those on the Vehicle of the Hearers, on the Pratyekabuddha
                        Vehicle, or on the Great Vehicle; or of all tīrthikas such as the Carakas, Parivrājakas, and Nirgranthas,
                        and so forth; or of any others, down to the roots of what is wholesome of those stuck in what is wrong; it
                        is through having the Tathāgata as their basis and support that they grow and become sizeable. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-80"/>
                    <p tid="130"> “However, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata does not form mental constructs or concepts. Mañjuśrī, the
                        Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha has cut off all mental constructs, concepts, points
                        of reference, and mental engagement. He is free from mind, mentality, and consciousness; he is neither
                        speculation nor the domain of speculation. He is invisible, not to be beheld, not an object of thought or
                        deliberation. He is without mental engagement, free from thought, and free from mind, mentality, and
                        consciousness. With respect to all, he is the same, neutral, without concepts, and he does not make any
                        distinctions. <ref cRef="74" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-81"/>
                    <p tid="131">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, space is everywhere the same, free from concepts and distinctions.
                        It is non-arisen and unceasing; it is not past, future, or present. It is indefinable, non-elaborate, and
                        formless; it cannot be shown or made known. It is without contact, without dwelling, not comparable, and
                        beyond compare. It has no simile and is beyond all similes. It has no basis; it is ungraspable and beyond
                        visible range. It is free from mind, mentality, and consciousness. It has no characteristic; it is without
                        syllables, voice, and mental engagement. It has no striving or giving up; no removal, no addition. It is
                        beyond the realm of words. It reaches and enters everywhere. And still, Mañjuśrī, sentient beings
                        experience space as being low or high, according to whether the place is low, middling, or high. <ref cRef="76" type="sanskrit"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.289.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-82"/>
                    <p tid="132">“In the same way, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete Buddha is
                        everywhere the same, free from concepts and distinctions. He is non-arisen and unceasing, he is not past,
                        future, or present. He is indefinable, non-elaborate, and formless; he cannot be shown or made known. He
                        is without contact, without dwelling, not comparable, and beyond compare. He has no simile and is beyond
                        all similes. He has no basis, he is ungraspable and beyond visible range. He is free from mind, mentality,
                        and consciousness. He has no characteristic; he is without syllables, voice, and mental engagement. He has
                        no striving or giving up; no removal, no addition. He is beyond the realm of words. He reaches and enters
                        everywhere. And still, Mañjuśrī, according to whether sentient beings are low, middling, or high, they see
                        the Tathāgata as low, middling, or high. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-83"/>
                    <p tid="133">“Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata does not think, ‘This sentient being has low inclinations and beliefs,
                        so I will show him a low perfection of the form body. This sentient being has middling inclinations and
                        beliefs, so I will show him a middling perfection of the form body. This sentient being has vast
                        inclinations and beliefs, so I will show him a vast perfection of the form body.’ <ref cRef="78" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="134">“Mañjuśrī, this is also what you should understand regarding how the Dharma is taught. Mañjuśrī,
                        the Tathāgata does not think, ‘This sentient being has low beliefs, so for him I shall make a speech
                        relating to the Hearers’ Vehicle. This sentient being has middling beliefs, <ref cRef="F.289.b"/> so for
                        him I shall make a speech relating to the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle. This sentient being has vast beliefs, so
                        for him I shall make a speech relating to the Great Vehicle.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-84"/>
                    <p tid="135">“Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata does not think, ‘This sentient being has belief in giving, so for him I
                        shall make a speech related to giving.’ Nor does he think so for discipline, forbearance, diligence, or
                        concentration. </p>
                    <p tid="136"> “Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata does not think, ‘This sentient being has belief in the perfection of
                        wisdom, so for him I shall make a speech related to the perfection of wisdom.’ Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata
                        does not think in that way. And why is that? Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata is the dharmakāya. Mañjuśrī, the
                        Tathāgata is utterly non-arisen.<note place="end" index="29" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-372">The Tibetan adds
                            “and non-ceasing” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ’gags pa</foreign>).</note>
                        <ref cRef="80" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-85"/>
                    <p tid="137">“Mañjuśrī, for the Tathāgata, a consciousness chasing after names, forms, and etymological
                        explanations does not occur. Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata does not form mental constructs or concepts.
                        Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata is momentary, and his characteristic is to be inexhaustible. He is fixed at the
                        pinnacle of non-exhaustion, the pinnacle of reality. Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and
                        Complete Buddha is the pinnacle of the sameness of all dharmas, the pinnacle of their non-duality, and the
                        pinnacle of their utter non-arising.<note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-373">Translation
                            based on the Tibetan.</note> In all regards he is the same, free from concepts, and free from
                        distinctions. He is not low, nor middling, nor high. </p>
                    <p tid="138">“Mañjuśrī, just in the same way, all dharmas are same free from concepts, and free from
                        distinctions. They are not low, nor middling, nor high. And why? It is because no dharmas are perceived.
                        Mañjuśrī, <ref cRef="F.290.a"/> this non-perception of all dharmas is their sameness. Their sameness is
                        their remaining fixed. Remaining fixed means that they do not move; not moving means being without any
                            abode.<note place="end" index="31" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-374">Compare this passage to chapter 2 of
                            the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūla­madhyamaka­kārikā</title>; the force of the passage is precisely in
                            its elliptic reference to taking movement and abiding as an empty, interdependent pair.</note>
                        <ref cRef="82" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-86"/>
                    <p tid="139"> “For someone with no abode in any dharma, the mind has no place to stand. For a mind that stands
                        nowhere, there will be non-arising. And for someone who sees in this way, no distorted mind and mental
                        states come about; someone whose mind is undistorted will have authentic attainment. </p>
                    <p tid="140">“Whoever has authentic attainment will not form elaborations. Someone who does not form
                        elaborations does not move about. When one does not move about, one does not wander. When one does not
                        wander, one does not become distracted. One who does not become distracted does not oppose the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmatā</foreign>. One who does not oppose the dharmatā is in
                        conformity with everything. One who is in conformity with everything does not move from the nature of the
                        dharmas. One who does not move from the nature of the dharmas obtains the nature of the dharmas. One who
                        obtains the nature of the dharmas does not form any elaboration. Why is that? Because he is born due to
                        conditions and causes. <ref cRef="84" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-87"/>
                    <p tid="141">“Whoever is born from conditions and causes is utterly unborn. Someone utterly unborn has gained
                        certainty. Whoever has gained certainty does not dwell with any mental engagement in the dharmas. When one
                        does not dwell with any mental engagement in the dharmas, one does not dwell with the dharmas. When one
                        does not dwell with the dharmas, one does not come into existence or go out of existence. When one does
                        not come into existence or go out of existence, one becomes fixed and has obtained the Dharma. </p>
                    <p tid="142">“When one becomes fixed and has obtained the Dharma, one applies oneself to the proper dharma.
                        When one applies oneself to the proper dharma, no dharma whatsoever is not a buddhadharma. And why? Due to
                        the realization of emptiness. The realization of emptiness is awakening. </p>
                    <p tid="143">“It is awakening, because in this way one realizes emptiness, no-sign, no-wish; <ref cRef="F.290.b"/> no-effort, no-dwelling, no coming about; no object of apprehension and no-abode.
                        Awakening is proper application. <ref cRef="86" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-88"/>
                    <p tid="144">“What is called proper application is to neither remove nor add. It is the application of not
                        doing and not changing, and it is not connected. It is the non-liberated application, the application of
                        neither oneness nor plurality, and the application of what has yet to come. This is proper application. </p>
                    <p tid="145"> “In that respect, there is no application, no measure, and no direct realization of a result.
                        And why? Because mind is by nature luminous. It is afflicted by adventitious afflictions, but its nature
                        is not afflicted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-89"/>
                    <p tid="146"> “Luminosity by nature is non-affliction. With respect to non-affliction there is no
                        counteragent—a counteragent by which the destruction of the afflictions may occur. And why? Because what
                        is pure does not become pure; it just is pure. </p>
                    <p tid="147">“That which is pure is non-arising. Non-arising is faultless. What is faultless is the
                        destruction of joys, whereby all attachments cease. Where all attachments cease, that is non-arising. And
                        non-arising is awakening. <ref cRef="88" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-90"/>
                    <p tid="148">“Awakening is sameness. Sameness is the tathatā. All dharmas, co-produced and unproduced, abide
                        in the tathatā. With respect to the tathatā there is neither something co-produced nor something
                        unproduced; there is no designation of duality. Where there is nothing co-produced or unproduced, and no
                        designation of duality, that is the tathatā. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-91"/>
                    <p tid="149">“The tathatā is nothing else but the tathatā. Nothing else but the tathatā is the unchanging
                        tathatā. The unchanging tathatā <ref cRef="F.291.a"/> is the non-coming tathatā. The non-coming tathatā is
                        the tathatā that does not go. The tathatā that does not go is the authentic tathatā. The authentic tathatā
                        is the not-at-all-tathatā. The not-at-all-tathatā is not afflicted and is not purified. That which is
                        neither afflicted nor purified neither arises nor ceases. That which neither arises nor ceases is the same
                        as nirvāṇa. That which is the same as nirvāṇa neither roams within saṃsāra nor passes into complete
                        nirvāṇa. That which neither roams within saṃsāra nor passes into complete nirvāṇa is not past, future, or
                        present. That which is not past, future, or present is not low, middling, or high. That which is not low,
                        middling, or high is the tathatā. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-92"/>
                    <p tid="150">“What we call tathathā is an expression meaning tattva. What we call tattva is tathatā itself.
                        Tathatā being the same as tattva is called tathatva.<note place="end" index="32" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-375"><!--KB-->We are here following the Tibetan, that would plausibly correspond the
                            following Sanskrit sentences: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā nāmocyate</foreign> |
                                <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattvārthādhi­vacanam etat</foreign> | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattvam nāmocyate tathataiva</foreign> | | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā­tattvam tathatvam ucyate</foreign> | This is an explanation of synonyms
                            and etymology. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathatā</foreign> could be rendered as
                            ‘thus-ness’; <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattva</foreign> as ‘that-ness’ (both the suffix
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">–tā</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">–tva</foreign> have a
                            similar value in Sanskrit). <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathatva</foreign> would again be
                            ‘thus-ness’, but here the Sūtra explains that it is rather a phonetic abbreviation of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā</foreign> + <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattva</foreign>. The difficulty of this passage is that the available Sanskrit text needs to be
                            emended following the Tibetan, while the Tibetan translation does not distinguish phonetically between
                            the suffix <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">–tā</foreign> and the suffix <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">–tva</foreign> (making the implied etymological abbreviation difficult to perceive). Hence, this
                            is a good example of a passage where we need both the Sanskrit and Tibetan texts to offer a plausible
                            reading. </note> Thus, the tathatā and the self are not two, they are non-dual. The meaning of
                        non-duality is awakening, in the sense of becoming awake. <ref cRef="90" type="sanskrit"/> The meaning is explained as the
                        awareness that enters the three gates of liberation with respect to all the Dharma teachings. The
                        awareness is explained as engaging in the sameness of the three times with respect to all dharmas. The
                        meaning of the inseparability of all dharmas is what is explained as the meaning. It is voiceless,
                        ineffable, inexpressible, and cut off from any expressions. Awareness is explained as the awareness that
                        understands the meaning and understands consciousness; this is explained as awareness. The meaning is
                        explained as the meaning that is established by the awareness that understands the meaning of tattva, and
                        by the awareness that understands consciousness. <ref cRef="F.291.b"/> That itself is the dharmatā. And
                        the dharmatā is the meaning. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-93"/>
                    <p tid="151">“The dharmatā is the fixity of the dharmas, the regularity of the dharmas; it does not occur
                        within a dharma. The non-occurrence of the dharma and the sameness of meaning and expression are the same
                        with respect to the non-dual meaning. Sameness is the meaning. It is sameness according to the
                        understanding of the meaning; it is the sameness of awareness, entering the gate of non-duality. </p>
                    <p tid="152"> “The sameness of the interpretable meaning and the definitive meaning is their common meaning,
                        which is emptiness. The sameness of the person is the same as the common meaning. The sameness of the
                        dharmas is the same as the sameness of persons. The sameness of liberation is the same as the sameness of
                        the dharmas. Realization according to the sameness of liberation is awakening. <ref cRef="92" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-94"/>
                    <p tid="153">“Mañjuśrī, for those who have attachment to form, the eye is attachment. Knowing the nature of
                        form and of the eye is non-attachment. </p>
                    <p tid="154">“For those who have attachment to views, one’s own body is attachment. For those who have done
                        away with all views, the awareness of one’s body’s natural emptiness is non-attachment. </p>
                    <p tid="155">“For those who are stuck in their attachment to improper mental placement, the appearance of
                        dharmas is attachment. Discerning the dharmas through proper mental placement, the awareness of emptiness
                        by nature and emptiness of essence is non-attachment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-95"/>
                    <p tid="156">“For those who are stuck in their attachment to the stain of doubt, liberation is attachment. The
                        authentic awareness of belief and liberation is non-attachment. </p>
                    <p tid="157"> “For those who are stuck in their attachment to the stain of laziness, having present diligence
                        toward realization is attachment. <ref cRef="F.292.a"/> The realization of dharmas as they are is
                        non-attachment. </p>
                    <p tid="158"> “For those who are stuck in their attachment to the hindrances, the limbs of awakening are
                        attachment. Liberation through unobstructed awareness is non-attachment. </p>
                    <p tid="159"> “Being by nature completely pure, all dharmas occur due to an assemblage of causes and
                        conditions. With respect to that, a bodhisattva should understand well the cause of affliction and the
                        cause of purification. He should neither abide with the purity of the cause of affliction, nor with the
                        purity of the cause of purification. <ref cRef="94" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-96"/>
                    <p tid="160">“Elevating self is a cause of affliction. Forbearance in one’s engagement with the selflessness
                        of dharmas is a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="161">“The view of ‘I’ and ‘mine’ is a cause of affliction. Inner pacification and outer non-movement
                        is a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="162">“Thoughts of desire, ill will, and harm are a cause of affliction. Forbearance in one’s dealings
                        with impure things, in one’s practice of friendliness, compassion, rejoicing, equanimity, and with
                        dependent dharmas, is a cause of purification. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-97"/>
                    <p tid="163">“The four distortions are a cause of affliction. The four placements of mindfulness are a cause
                        of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="164"> “The five hindrances are a cause of affliction. The five faculties are a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="165">“The six entrances are a cause of affliction. The six remembrances are a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="166">“The <term>seven false dharmas</term> are a cause of affliction. The seven limbs of awakening are
                        a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="167">“The eight wrong modes are a cause of affliction. The eight right modes are a cause of
                        purification. </p>
                    <p tid="168">“The nine causes of antagonism are a cause of affliction. The absorptions into nine successive
                        abodes are a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="169">“The ten unwholesome courses of karma are a cause of affliction. <ref cRef="F.292.b"/> The ten
                        wholesome courses of karma are a cause of purification. </p>
                    <p tid="170">“In brief, all unwholesome mental engagements are a cause of affliction; all wholesome mental
                        engagements are a cause of purification. <ref cRef="96" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-98"/>
                    <p tid="171">“In that respect, whether causes of affliction or of purification, all dharmas are by nature
                        empty, without a sentient being, without a living being, without one who nourishes, without a soul or a
                        person, without a master, without appropriation, without activity, comparable to an illusion, without
                        characteristics, pacified from within. </p>
                    <p tid="172"> “Moreover, pacified from within they are utterly pacified. Utterly pacified, they are their
                        intrinsic nature. Their intrinsic nature is not being perceived. Not being perceived is to have no abode.
                        That which has no abode is thatness.<note place="end" index="33" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-376">This reading
                            follows the Tibetan, which has <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de kho na nyid</foreign>,
                            probably translating the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattvam</foreign>. The
                            transcribed manuscript has <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kham</foreign>.</note> Thatness is
                        space. One cognizes all dharmas as the same as space. One engages conventionally in the purification of
                        afflictions, yet does not abandon the dharmatā of space. And why? Mañjuśrī, no dharma whatsoever can be
                        found for which there may be arising or cessation.” <ref cRef="98" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="173"> Mañjuśrī inquired, “How then, Bhagavat, did the Tathāgata obtain awakening?”</p>
                    <p tid="174">The Bhagavat answered, “Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata obtained an awakening that has no root and no
                        ground to stand upon.” </p>
                    <p tid="175"> Mañjuśrī asked, “Bhagavat, what root would that be, and what ground to stand upon?” </p>
                    <p tid="176">The Bhagavat replied, “Mañjuśrī, that root would be the transitory collection, and that ground to
                        stand upon the imagination of what is not there.<note place="end" index="34" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-377">In Yogācāra texts, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhūta­parikalpa</foreign> is taken as a
                            sixth <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vibhakti tatpuruṣa</foreign>, rather than a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karma­dhāraya</foreign>. “What is not there” is the pair of
                            perceiver/perceived (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">grāhya</foreign>/<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">grāhaka</foreign>); hence it is not “false imagination,” as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhūta</foreign> does not function as a qualifier for <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parikalpa</foreign>. See the first chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyānta­vibhāga­bhāṣya</title> for a representative instance.</note> Then, Mañjuśrī, the
                        Tathāgata knows the sameness of all dharmas through the sameness of awakening. Therefore it is said,
                        Mañjuśrī, that ‘the Tathāgata realized an awakening that has no root and no ground to stand upon.’ <ref cRef="100" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-99"/>
                    <p tid="177">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is to be at peace, utterly at peace. <ref cRef="F.293.a"/> In that respect,
                        what is peace, and what is utter peace? Inside there is peace; outside there is utter peace. Why is that? </p>
                    <p tid="178">“The eye, Mañjuśrī, is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature. This is
                        called <distinct type="term">peace</distinct>. Thoroughly understanding that the eye is empty, one does
                        not run toward forms. Thus it is called <distinct type="term">utter peace</distinct>. </p>
                    <p tid="179"> “In the same way, the ear is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature.
                        This is called <distinct type="term">peace</distinct>. Thoroughly understanding that the ear is empty, one
                        does not run toward sounds. Thus it is called <distinct type="term">utter peace</distinct>. </p>
                    <p tid="180">“The nose is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature. This is called
                            <distinct type="term">peace</distinct>. Thoroughly understanding that the nose is empty, one does not
                        run toward smells. Thus it is called <distinct type="term">utter peace</distinct>. </p>
                    <p tid="181"> “The tongue is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature. This is called
                        peace. Thoroughly understanding that the tongue is empty, one does not run toward flavors. Thus it is
                        called utter peace. </p>
                    <p tid="182">“The body is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature. This is called
                            <distinct type="term">peace</distinct>. Thoroughly understanding that the body is empty, one does not
                        run toward touchable things. Thus it is called <distinct type="term">utter peace</distinct>. </p>
                    <p tid="183"> “The mind, Mañjuśrī, is empty of a self and what belongs to a self; such is its nature. This is
                        called <distinct type="term">peace</distinct>. Thoroughly understanding that the mind is empty, one does
                        not run toward dharmas. Thus it is called <distinct type="term">utter peace</distinct>. <ref cRef="102" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-100"/>
                    <p tid="184"> “Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is by nature luminous, because the mind is by nature luminous; that is why
                        it is said to be luminous by nature. The nature is not afflicted; it is the same as space, it has the
                        nature of space, it goes together with space, it is comparable to space. The nature is utterly luminous. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="185">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is without striving or giving anything up. In that respect, how is it
                        without striving, and how is it without giving anything up? Without striving <ref cRef="F.293.b"/> means
                        not to grasp at any dharma. Without giving anything up means not to abandon any dharma. In that respect,
                        Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata, without striving or giving anything up, crossed the stream. He crossed it in such
                        a way that he does not see this shore or the other shore of tathatā. Therefore, the Tathāgata realized all
                        dharmas to be free from this shore or the other shore. Thus he is called the Tathāgata. <ref cRef="104" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-101"/>
                    <p tid="186">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is without sign or reference point. In that respect, what is signlessness,
                        and what is the lack of reference point? </p>
                    <p tid="187">“That the eye-consciousness does not perceive, Mañjuśrī, is signlessness. That form is not seen
                        is the lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="188">“That the ear-consciousness does not perceive is signlessness. That sounds are not heard is the
                        lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="189">“That the nose-consciousness does not perceive is signlessness. That smells are not smelt is the
                        lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="190"> “That the tongue-consciousness does not perceive is signlessness. That flavors are not tasted is
                        the lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="191">“That the body-consciousness does not perceive is signlessness. That touchable things are not
                        touched is the lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="192">“That the mind-consciousness does not perceive is signlessness. That dharmas are not cognized is
                        the lack of reference point. </p>
                    <p tid="193">“This, Mañjuśrī, is the scope of the noble ones. That which is not the scope of the three realms,
                        Mañjuśrī, is the scope of the noble ones. <ref cRef="106" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-102"/>
                    <p tid="194">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is not past, not future, not present. It is the same in the three times,
                        and is cut off from the three spheres. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, what does it mean to be cut off from the
                        three spheres? The mind in the past is not perceived. Consciousness does not run toward the future. <ref cRef="F.294.a"/> Mental placement does not occur in the present. One who does not abide in mind,
                        mentality, and consciousness does not form mental constructs or concepts. Not forming mental constructs or
                        concepts, one does not create the past and does not think of the future; one does not elaborate about the
                        present. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-103"/>
                    <p tid="195">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is bodiless and unproduced. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, bodilessness is what
                        cannot be cognized by the eye consciousness, what cannot be cognized by the ear, nose, tongue, body, or
                        mind consciousness. Mañjuśrī, that which cannot be cognized by mind, mentality, and consciousness is
                        unproduced. The unproduced is explained this way: where there is no arising, no abiding, no passing away,
                        that is called the <distinct type="term">unproduced purified of the three spheres</distinct>. The
                        co-produced should be understood just like the unproduced. And why? The essence of all dharmas is
                        no-essence; in that respect, there is no duality. <ref cRef="108" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-104"/>
                    <p tid="196">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is a basis of non-division. In that respect, what is non-division, and what
                        is the basis? No-notion is non-division. The tathatā is the basis. No-ground-to-stand-upon is
                        non-division. The dharmadhātu is the basis. Non-multiplicity<note place="end" index="35" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-378">The Sanskrit here is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nanatvam</foreign> but the Tibetan reading, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tha dad pa
                                nyid med pa</foreign>, clearly makes more sense.</note> is non-division. The true limit is the
                        basis. Non-apprehension is non-division. Non-movement is the basis. Emptiness is non-division. No-sign is
                        the basis. Non-deliberation is non-division. No-wish is the basis. Non-solicitation is non-division. Being
                        without a sentient being is the basis. Non-essence of a sentient being is non-division. Space is the
                        basis. Non-perception is non-division. Non-arising is the basis. Non-cessation is non-division. The
                        unproduced <ref cRef="F.294.b"/> is the basis. No moving about is non-division. Awakening is the basis.
                        Pacification is non-division. Nirvāṇa is the basis. Non-development is non-division; non-birth is the
                        basis. <ref cRef="110" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-105"/>
                    <p tid="197">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is not realized by the body nor by the mind. And why? The body, Mañjuśrī,
                        is inert, motionless, and insentient. It is similar and comparable to grass, logs of wood, walls, or
                            clay.<note place="end" index="36" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-379">We believe that here <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratibhāsopama</foreign> does not mean “comparable to the appearance
                            of” but rather it is both <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratibhāsa</foreign> and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upamā</foreign>—a “similitude” and a “comparison”; it is an emphatic
                            restatement through synonym, not uncommon in sūtras.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="198">“The mind, on the other hand, can be compared to an illusion. It is hollow, void, unreal, and
                        unproduced. Mañjuśrī, to realize the body and mind in this manner is explained as awakening. This is based
                        on conventional usage, but it is not in the ultimate sense. And why? Mañjuśrī, awakening cannot be
                        explained in terms of the body, the mind, or dharma, non-dharma, real, unreal, truth, or falsity. <ref cRef="112" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-106"/>
                    <p tid="199">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, cannot be expressed through any dharma. And why? Mañjuśrī, awakening does
                        not have the slightest location that allows it to enter conventional usage. Mañjuśrī, space has no
                        location; it is unproduced, non-arisen, unceasing, and cannot be expressed. In the same way, Mañjuśrī,
                        awakening has no location; it is unproduced, non-arisen, unceasing, and cannot be expressed. Mañjuśrī,
                        when searching for the real space, it cannot be explained through any dharma. In the same way, Mañjuśrī,
                        when searching for the real awakening, it cannot be explained through any dharma. And why? Mañjuśrī, with
                        respect to what is real, no words can be found, because it is non-arisen and unceasing. <ref cRef="114" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="200">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, means to be ungraspable and to have no abode. In that respect, Mañjuśrī,
                        what is it to be ungraspable, <ref cRef="F.295.a"/> and what is it to have no abode? The thorough
                        cognition of the eye, Mañjuśrī, is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of form is to have no abode. The
                        thorough cognition of the ear is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of sound is to have no abode. The
                        thorough cognition of the nose is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of smell is to have no abode. The
                        thorough cognition of the tongue is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of flavor is to have no abode.
                        The thorough cognition of the body is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of touchable things is to have
                        no abode. The thorough cognition of the mind is to be ungraspable. The non-perception of dharmas is to
                        have no abode. In this way, the Tathāgata has realized awakening, ungraspable and without abode. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-107"/>
                    <p tid="201">“Once that has been realized, by not grasping at the eye and not perceiving form, the
                        eye-consciousness has no ground to stand upon.<note place="end" index="37" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-380">This section might appear counterintuitive. However it becomes more comprehensible when we keep in
                            mind that the eye is the basis (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āśraya</foreign>) and visible
                            form is the point of reference (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālambana</foreign>) that make
                            the arising of visual consciousness possible.</note> Not grasping at the ear and not perceiving
                        sounds, the ear-consciousness has no ground to stand upon. Not grasping at the nose and not perceiving
                        smells, the nose-consciousness has no ground to stand upon. Not grasping at the body and not perceiving
                        touchable things, the body-consciousness has no ground to stand upon. Not grasping at the mind and not
                        perceiving dharmas, the mind-consciousness has no ground to stand upon. Therefore, as his consciousness
                        has no ground to stand upon, he comes to be counted as the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the Perfect and Complete
                        Buddha. <ref cRef="116" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="202">“Mañjuśrī, there are four grounds for the minds of sentient beings to stand upon. Which four?
                        Form is a ground for the mind of sentient beings to stand upon. Similarly, Mañjuśrī, feeling, notion, and
                        co-producing factors are grounds for the minds of sentient beings to stand upon. Moreover, Mañjuśrī, these
                        four grounds for the mind to stand upon are known by the Tathāgata <ref cRef="F.295.b"/> to be non-arisen
                        and unceasing. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-108"/>
                    <p tid="203">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is an appellation for emptiness. Mañjuśrī, the emptiness by which awakening
                        is empty is also the emptiness by which all dharmas are empty. And the Tathāgata realized them, precisely
                        in the way in which they are empty. Mañjuśrī, it is not that emptiness is realized through emptiness. On
                        the other hand, Mañjuśrī, there is one single method: emptiness, or awakening. Mañjuśrī, where there is no
                        emptiness, there is no awakening. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, there is no duality by which emptiness and
                        awakening could be made into two. And why? Mañjuśrī, all dharmas are non-dual, without characteristics,
                        not made into two, without names, without signs, free from mind, mentality, and consciousness, non-arisen
                        and unceasing, not acting, not moving forth, not occurring, without syllables, and without speech. <ref cRef="118" type="sanskrit"/>
                        <ref cRef="B3" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-109"/>
                    <p tid="204">“Moreover, Mañjuśrī, that which is called empty is an appellation for no attachment and no
                        grasping. On the other hand, Mañjuśrī, in the ultimate sense, no dharma called empty is there to be
                        perceived. Mañjuśrī, the sky is called sky, yet the sky cannot be expressed. In the same way, Mañjuśrī, we
                        say ‘empty, empty’ as an entrance to inexpressible, empty things. </p>
                    <p tid="205">“All dharmas are nameless, Mañjuśrī; yet all dharmas are described through names. Mañjuśrī, a
                        name is not placed in either a primary or an intermediate location. The Tathāgata realized the dharmas to
                        be precisely that way. As for the Dharma expressed through a name, that dharma too is not placed in either
                        a primary or a secondary location. <ref cRef="F.296.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="206">“Thus, Mañjuśrī, all the dharmas are known by the Tathāgata to be, from the very beginning,
                        unborn, non-arisen, unceasing, without characteristics, free from mind, mentality, and consciousness,
                        without syllables, and without voice. They are known to be just free. Mañjuśrī, it is not that they are
                        first bound and then freed. <ref cRef="120" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-110"/>
                    <p tid="207">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is the same as the sky. The sky is neither even nor uneven. Awakening, too,
                        is neither even nor uneven. And why? Mañjuśrī, a dharma with no real perfection cannot be spoken of as
                        either even or uneven. Therefore, Mañjuśrī, all dharmas are realized by the Tathāgata as neither even nor
                        uneven. They are realized in such a way that not even an atom is made even or uneven. Dharmas are cognized
                        just as they are. </p>
                    <p tid="208">“And how does that accord with the awareness of reality? Mañjuśrī, all dharmas, non-arisen and
                        unceasing, come into being after having not existed. Then, having existed, they disperse. They come into
                        existence without a master and without being owned; and, Mañjuśrī, without a master and without being
                        owned, they disperse. In this way, Mañjuśrī, they come into existence and go out of existence. They come
                        about within the dharma of dependence, and there is no one here that causes them to come about. Thus it is
                        said that the Tathāgata teaches the Dharma for the sake of cutting off the dharmas. <ref cRef="122" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-111"/>
                    <p tid="209">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is a consistent basis. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, what is a consistent
                        basis? Mañjuśrī, just like awakening, so also form does not swerve from the tathatā. Just like awakening,
                        so also feeling, notion, co-producing factors, and consciousness <ref cRef="F.296.b"/> do not swerve from
                        the tathatā. Just like awakening, so also the earth element does not swerve from the tathatā. Just like
                        awakening, so also the water element, the heat element, and the wind element do not swerve from the
                        tathatā. </p>
                    <p tid="210">“Just like awakening, so also the eye-base, the form-base, and the eye-consciousness-base do not
                        swerve from the tathatā. Just like awakening, Mañjuśrī, the ear-base, the sound-base, the
                        ear-consciousness-base, the nose-base, the smell-base, the nose-consciousness-base, the tongue-base, the
                        flavor-base, the tongue-consciousness-base, the body-base, the touchable-base, the
                        body-consciousness-base, the mind-base, the dharma-base, and the mind-consciousness-base do not swerve
                        from the tathatā. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-112"/>
                    <p tid="211">“And dharmas can be designated just as this: the aggregates, the bases, and the entrances. And
                        this entire set has been realized by the Tathāgata as consistent: as it is before, so also is it later,
                        and in between. It is unborn in the prior limit, not transferred at the later limit, and isolated in the
                        middle. In this way, for all those things there is a ‘consistent basis.’ Just as one is, so are all; just
                        as all are, so is one. And in this respect, Mañjuśrī, neither oneness nor plurality is perceived. <ref cRef="124" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-113"/>
                    <p tid="212">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, enters the aspect-less by entering an aspect. In that respect, Mañjuśrī,
                        what is an aspect, and what is the aspect-less? The aspect, Mañjuśrī, is explained as taking up all
                        wholesome dharmas. The aspect-less is explained as the non-perception of any dharmas. The aspect is
                        explained as the stabilization of an unstable mind. The aspect-less is explained as the gate to liberation
                        of the samādhi of no-sign. <ref cRef="F.297.a"/> The aspect is explained as thinking, comparing, counting,
                        and thorough consideration of all dharmas. The aspect-less is explained as transcending comparison. What
                        is transcending comparison? It is that with respect to which there is no function of consciousness. The
                        aspect is explained as the thorough consideration of the co-produced. The aspect-less is explained as the
                        thorough consideration of the unproduced. <ref cRef="126" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-114"/>
                    <p tid="213">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is without outflows and without clinging. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, how is
                        it without outflows, and how is it without clinging? Being without outflows, Mañjuśrī, is explained as the
                        absence of the four outflows. Which four? They are: the outflow of desire, the outflow of existence, the
                        outflow of ignorance, and the outflow of views. These are the four outflows. </p>
                    <p tid="214"> “Being without clinging is explained as the absence of four types of clinging. Which four? They
                        are: clinging to desire, clinging to views, clinging to one’s attachment to discipline and vows, and
                        clinging to positing a self. These are the four types of clinging. </p>
                    <p tid="215">“Beings are blinded by ignorance. Craving disturbs them. They develop mutual attachment and cling
                        to each other. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, the Tathāgata thoroughly understands that the root of clinging
                        is the position of a self. Through self-purity, he understands the purity of all sentient beings. The
                        purity of self is the purity of all sentient beings. The purity of all sentient beings is non-dual, not
                        divided into two. And the meaning of non-duality is non-arising and non-cessation. <ref cRef="128" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-115"/>
                    <p tid="216">“With respect to non-arising and non-cessation, Mañjuśrī, mind, mentality, and consciousness do
                        not come about. In that respect there is no mental construct by which one may place the mind
                            improperly.<note place="end" index="38" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-381">The reading of the transcribed
                            manuscript is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manasi</foreign> rather than <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">'manasi</foreign> and is consistent with the Tibetan.</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.297.b"/> Whosoever engages in proper mental placement does not give rise to ignorance. Not
                        giving rise to ignorance means not giving rise to the twelve limbs of existence. Not giving rise to the
                        twelve limbs of existence means no birth. No birth is the fixed rule. The fixed rule is the definitive
                        meaning. The definitive meaning is the ultimate meaning. The ultimate meaning means to be devoid of a
                        person. The meaning of being devoid of a person is the ineffable meaning. The ineffable meaning is the
                        meaning of dependent arising. The meaning of dependent arising is the meaning of the Dharma. The meaning
                        of the Dharma is the meaning of the Tathāgata. Hence it is said, ‘One who sees dependent arising sees the
                        Dharma; one who sees the Dharma sees the Tathāgata.’ And he sees in such a way that, when he searches, he
                        does not see anything whatsoever. In that respect, Mañjuśrī, what is anything whatsoever? It is the mind
                        and the point of reference. When one does not see the mind and the point of reference, one then sees
                        reality. In this way, the Tathāgata has realized, through their very sameness, that all these dharmas are
                        equal. <ref cRef="130" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-116"/>
                    <p tid="217">“Awakening, Mañjuśrī, is pure, stainless, and without disturbance. In that respect, Mañjuśrī,
                        what is purity, what is meant by stainless, and what is non-disturbance? Emptiness, Mañjuśrī, is purity;
                        no-sign is stainless; no-wish is non-disturbance. Non-birth is purity; non-effort is stainless;
                        non-arising is non-disturbance. The nature is purity; complete purity is stainless; luminosity is
                        non-disturbance. No elaboration is purity; freedom from elaboration is stainless; the pacification of
                        elaborations <ref cRef="F.298.a"/> is non-disturbance. The tathatā is purity; the dharmadhātu is
                        stainless; the pinnacle of reality is non-disturbance. Space is purity; the sky is stainless; the
                        atmosphere is non-disturbance. </p>
                    <p tid="218">“To thoroughly cognize inside is purity;<note place="end" index="39" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-382">The Tibetan <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang yongs su shes pa ni dag pa o</foreign>
                            suggests that the Sanskrit should be <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhyātma­parijñā
                                śuddhiḥ</foreign>. The edited text has <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhyātmaḥ
                                pari­śuddhiḥ</foreign>, and the manuscript transcription has <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhyātma pari­śuddhiḥ</foreign>.</note> not to move forth on the outside is
                        stainless; non-perception inside and outside is non-disturbance. To thoroughly cognize the aggregates is
                        purity; the essencelessness<note place="end" index="40" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-383">The Sanskrit has
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svabhāva</foreign> but the following phrases suggest that
                            the Tibetan reading (implying <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asvabhāvo</foreign>) is
                            preferable.</note> of the bases is stainless; putting away the entrances is non-disturbance. To
                        cognize past destruction is purity; to cognize future non-arising is stainless; to cognize the present
                        abiding of the dharmadhātu is non-disturbance. <ref cRef="132" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-117"/>
                    <p tid="219">“In this way, Mañjuśrī, purity, the stainless, and non-disturbance are collected within a single
                        basis: the peaceful basis. That which is peaceful is very peaceful. That which is very peaceful is utterly
                        peaceful. That which is utterly peaceful is utter pacification; utter pacification is called the sage.
                        Thus, Mañjuśrī, just like space, so is awakening. Just like awakening, so are the dharmas. Just like the
                        dharmas, so are sentient beings. Just like sentient beings, so are the fields. Just like the fields, so is
                        nirvāṇa. Therefore, Mañjuśrī, it is said that all dharmas are the same as nirvāṇa. Since this is their
                        ultimate mode, there is no counteragent. Because there is no counteragent, they are primordially pure,
                        primordially stainless, and primordially without disturbances. It is thus, Mañjuśrī, that the Tathāgata
                        realized all dharmas to be; as he observes the sphere of sentient beings, a pure, great compassion that is
                        free from disturbances, called play, comes about toward those sentient beings. <ref cRef="134" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-118"/>
                    <p tid="220">“Mañjuśrī, how does a bodhisattva practice within the conduct of a bodhisattva? <ref cRef="F.298.b"/> Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva does not think of destruction, arising, non-destruction,
                        non-arising, and the utter destruction of destruction; nor is he disturbed by utter non-arising. It is in
                        this way, Mañjuśrī, that he practices within the conduct of a bodhisattva. Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a
                        bodhisattva does not practice by thinking, ‘The past mind is destroyed;’ he does not practice by thinking,
                        ‘The future mind has yet to be obtained;’ he does not practice by thinking, ‘The present mind abides.’ He
                        is not stuck in the past, future, or present mind. As he practices in this way, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva
                        practices within the conduct of a bodhisattva. <ref cRef="136" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-119"/>
                    <p tid="221">“Mañjuśrī, giving, awakening, and sentient beings and, on the other hand, the Tathāgata: these
                        are non-dual, they are not divided into two.<note place="end" index="41" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-384">The
                            Tibetan suggests <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">punar aparaṃ mañjuśrī bodhisattvo dānaṃ ca
                                bodhiś ca sattvāś ca tathāgataś cādvayam etad advaidhīkāram</foreign>. The Tibetan also contains
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’</foreign> before <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa</foreign> and all the other pāramitās; however, the Sanskrit text does
                            not contain bodhisattva in any of those instances. It seems that in this case, the Tibetan translators
                            may have been using a different text.</note> Practicing in this way, a bodhisattva practices within
                        the conduct of a bodhisattva. Mañjuśrī, discipline, awakening, and sentient beings and, on the other hand,
                        the Tathāgata: these are non-dual, they are not divided into two. Practicing in this way, a bodhisattva
                        practices within the conduct of a bodhisattva. </p>
                    <p tid="222">“It is the same way with forbearance, awakening, and sentient beings, and, on the other hand, the
                        Tathāgata; diligence, awakening, and sentient beings, and, on the other hand, the Tathāgata;
                        concentration, awakening, and sentient beings, and, on the other hand, the Tathāgata; and similarly,
                        wisdom, awakening, and sentient beings, and, on the other hand, the Tathāgata. These are non-dual, they
                        are not divided into two. Practicing in this way, a bodhisattva practices within the conduct of a
                        bodhisattva. </p>
                    <p tid="223">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva may practice thinking that ‘form is not empty’ and also ‘not non-empty.’
                        Practicing in this way, Mañjuśrī, that bodhisattva practices within the conduct of a bodhisattva. And why?
                        He thinks, ‘Form itself is empty of the essence of form. In the same way, <ref cRef="F.299.a"/> feeling,
                        notion, co-producing factors, and consciousness are empty.’ He practices thinking in this way and also
                        thinking that ‘they are not non-empty.’ Practicing in this way, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva practices within
                        the conduct of a bodhisattva. And why? Because mind, mentality, and consciousness are not perceived. <ref cRef="138" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-120"/>
                    <p tid="224">“Mañjuśrī, there is no dharma whatsoever that could be thoroughly cognized, dispelled,
                        cultivated, or directly realized. Mañjuśrī, that which is understood as destruction is simply the
                        destruction of extremes. And that which is completely destroyed is not something one should cause to be
                        destroyed. As it is indestructible and not destroyed, it is without destruction. And why? It conforms to
                        destruction; and conforming to destruction is the destruction of nothing whatsoever. And that, wherein
                        there is no destruction of anything whatsoever, is unproduced. With respect to the unproduced, there is no
                        arising and no cessation. </p>
                    <p tid="225">“Therefore it is said, ‘Whether the tathāgatas arise or not, this dharmatā is invariable; it is
                        the invariability of the dharmas, the dharmadhātu.’ Just like the invariability of the dharmadhātu, the
                        Tathāgata’s awareness is neither occurring nor ceasing. Entering the Dharma method in this way, the
                        outflows do not arise and do not cease. The destruction of the outflows, Mañjuśrī, is a conventional
                        expression, speech, syllables, sign, and designation. Here no dharma whatsoever arises or ceases.” <ref cRef="140" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-121"/>
                    <p tid="226">Then the youthful Mañjuśrī rose from his seat, folded his upper robe, and placed his right knee
                        on the ground. Folding his hands in the direction of the Bhagavat, he praised him with these verses: </p>
                    <lg tid="227">
                        <l>“You have no color, sign, or shape, </l>
                        <l>No cessation or origination,</l>
                        <l>No root and no ground to stand upon,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="F.299.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-122"/>
                    <lg tid="228">
                        <l>“You have no ground to stand upon,</l>
                        <l> No striving or giving up; </l>
                        <l>You are unplaced and free from the six entrances,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-123"/>
                    <lg tid="229">
                        <l>“You are not situated in any dharma,</l>
                        <l>Bereft of existence or non-existence.</l>
                        <l>You obtained the sameness of co-producing factors,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="142" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-124"/>
                    <lg tid="230">
                        <l>“Free from the three world spheres, </l>
                        <l> You have attained the sky’s own sameness.</l>
                        <l>You are not defiled by desires,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-125"/>
                    <lg tid="231">
                        <l>“You always remain in samādhi,</l>
                        <l>As you move, stand, or lie down—</l>
                        <l>Whichever your posture may be.</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-126"/>
                    <lg tid="232">
                        <l>“You arrive evenly and go evenly,</l>
                        <l> Remaining well placed in sameness.</l>
                        <l>You are not disturbed at sameness,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-127"/>
                    <lg tid="233">
                        <l>“You are absorbed in sameness,</l>
                        <l>In samādhi within all dharmas.</l>
                        <l>Absorbed in the sign-less,</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="144" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-128"/>
                    <lg tid="234">
                        <l>“Unplaced, without point of reference,</l>
                        <l>Your samādhi is the peak of wisdom.</l>
                        <l>You have become the lord of Dharma,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-129"/>
                    <lg tid="235">
                        <l>“In one instant, you see</l>
                        <l>The forms, voices, and postures </l>
                        <l>Of all sentient beings.</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-130"/>
                    <lg tid="236">
                        <l>“Free from name and form,</l>
                        <l>You cut off all causes and aggregates.</l>
                        <l>You are the entrance into the aspect-less,</l>
                        <l> And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-131"/>
                    <lg tid="237">
                        <l>“You are free from signs</l>
                        <l>And bereft of their aspects.</l>
                        <l>You are the entrance into the sign-less,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="146" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-132"/>
                    <lg tid="238">
                        <l>“You do not form concepts,</l>
                        <l>And your mind has no ground to stand upon.</l>
                        <l>You have no recollection or mental placement,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-133"/>
                    <lg tid="239">
                        <l>“Space is without abode;</l>
                        <l>It is free from elaboration and stainless.</l>
                        <l>Your mind is the same as space,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-134"/>
                    <lg tid="240">
                        <l>“Space is without edge or center,</l>
                        <l>And so, too, is the dharmatā of the buddhas.</l>
                        <l>You have gone beyond the three times, <ref cRef="F.300.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-135"/>
                    <lg tid="241">
                        <l>“The buddhas have the characteristic of space,</l>
                        <l>And space has no characteristics.</l>
                        <l>You are free from effect and cause,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="148" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-136"/>
                    <lg tid="242">
                        <l>“Like the moon in the water, you cannot be grasped:</l>
                        <l>You are not placed in any dharma.</l>
                        <l>You have no sense of ‘I’ and no voice,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-137"/>
                    <lg tid="243">
                        <l>“You are not dwelling in the aggregates,</l>
                        <l>The bases, or the entrances.</l>
                        <l>You are free from distortions,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-138"/>
                    <lg tid="244">
                        <l>“Free from the two extremes,</l>
                        <l>You cut off the view of ‘self.’</l>
                        <l>You obtained sameness with the dharmadhātu,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-139"/>
                    <lg tid="245">
                        <l>“You are free from form and number,</l>
                        <l>And bereft of any false dharmas.</l>
                        <l>You neither cling to, nor abandon,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="150" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-140"/>
                    <lg tid="246">
                        <l>“You have gone beyond the faults of Māra </l>
                        <l>And reached the path of the dharmadhātu.<note place="end" index="42" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-385">Here
                                the Tibetan differs, suggesting perhaps <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māra­nāma­samati­krāntaḥ</foreign> and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma­saṁkalpaṁ viditvā</foreign>. The expression <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma­dhātu­gatiṁgataḥ</foreign> appears in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­nāma­saṁgīti</title>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>You have the feature of non-obscuration,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-141"/>
                    <lg tid="247">
                        <l>“Those who understand the meaning, </l>
                        <l>Do not say ‘he exists’ or ‘he does not.’</l>
                        <l>You are not in the realm of words,</l>
                        <l>And you do not take up anything.</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-142"/>
                    <lg tid="248">
                        <l>“Not relying on duality,</l>
                        <l>You cut down the banner of pride.<note place="end" index="43" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-386">Here the
                                Tibetan differs. It reads <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">theg pa’i rgyal mtshan kun tu
                                    btsugs</foreign>, which would correspond to something like <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yāna­dhvaja­samucchritaḥ</foreign>, or “having well raised the banner of the
                                vehicle.”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>You are free from duality and non-duality,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="152" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-143"/>
                    <lg tid="249">
                        <l>“You have subdued all mental flaws,</l>
                        <l>And the four flaws of the body.</l>
                        <l> You are inconceivable, without compare,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-144"/>
                    <lg tid="250">
                        <l>“You conduct yourself effortlessly,</l>
                        <l>And you are bereft of any flaws.</l>
                        <l>Awareness precedes all your actions,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-145"/>
                    <lg tid="251">
                        <l>Your recollection has no outflows:</l>
                        <l> It is subtle and conforms to what is real and unreal.</l>
                        <l>You have no abode and no thoughts,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-146"/>
                    <lg tid="252">
                        <l>“With your mind free of a point of reference,</l>
                        <l>You understand well the mind of all,</l>
                        <l>While having no notion of ‘self’ and ‘others.’</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-147"/>
                    <lg tid="253">
                        <l>“Taking up points of reference</l>
                        <l> Makes everyone’s mind bewildered.</l>
                        <l>You remain unobscured,</l>
                        <l>As you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!<note place="end" index="44" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-387">Here the Tibetan differs. It
                                would perhaps suggest: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avāraṃbanaṃ avālamba sarva­cittāna
                                    mohana</foreign> | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāvaraṇa­dharmo’si nirālamba
                                    namo’stu te</foreign>. The verse may appear odd, but it becomes perhaps more comprehensible
                                when we recollect that a mind (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">citta</foreign>) needs a
                                point of reference (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālambana</foreign>) in order to exist
                                in the first place (a point of significant importance for the whole sūtra). </note>
                            <ref cRef="F.300.b"/>
                            <ref cRef="154" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-148"/>
                    <lg tid="254">
                        <l>“And a mind without point of reference</l>
                        <l>Cannot essentially be found.</l>
                        <l>You obtained inconceivable sameness,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-149"/>
                    <lg tid="255">
                        <l>“With your unplaced awareness,</l>
                        <l>You see all the fields,</l>
                        <l>And the conduct of all beings.</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-150"/>
                    <lg tid="256">
                        <l>“The buddhas do not apprehend the mind,</l>
                        <l>In any way, ever;</l>
                        <l>Yet, you know everything about all dharmas.</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-151"/>
                    <lg tid="257">
                        <l>“Illusion-like are all dharmas,</l>
                        <l>Yet the illusion itself cannot be found.</l>
                        <l>You are free from the dharma of illusion,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="156" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-152"/>
                    <lg tid="258">
                        <l>“Perfect Buddha, you act in the world,</l>
                        <l>Not dwelling upon worldly dharmas,</l>
                        <l>And you do not form concepts about the ‘world.’</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-153"/>
                    <lg tid="259">
                        <l>“In what is empty, you move in accordance with emptiness;</l>
                        <l>In accordance with emptiness, your domain is what is empty.</l>
                        <l>You declare what is empty as empty,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l> I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-154"/>
                    <lg tid="260">
                        <l>“Through great powers and illusory samādhi,</l>
                        <l>You perform miracles. </l>
                        <l>You are absorbed into freedom from multiplicity,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-155"/>
                    <lg tid="261">
                        <l>“You are neither one, nor many,</l>
                        <l>You are neither far, nor near.</l>
                        <l>You neither remove, nor add,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l> I bow to you! <ref cRef="158" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-156"/>
                    <lg tid="262">
                        <l>“Through the diamond-like samādhi,</l>
                        <l>You obtained supreme awakening in one instant.</l>
                        <l>You are absorbed into non-appearance,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-157"/>
                    <lg tid="263">
                        <l>“You know nirvāṇa to be unmoving in the three times.</l>
                        <l>You are a guide endowed with many methods,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-158"/>
                    <lg tid="264">
                        <l>“You are expert in understanding which methods,</l>
                        <l>Even indirect, are appropriate for sentient beings.</l>
                        <l>You know nirvāṇa to be unmoving,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-159"/>
                    <lg tid="265">
                        <l>“You are free from signs, effortless, </l>
                        <l>Free from elaboration, and untainted.</l>
                        <l>Free from appearance, free from a ‘self,’</l>
                        <l>You are free of any point of reference: </l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="160" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-160"/>
                    <lg tid="266">
                        <l>“Free from concepts, free from what belongs to a self,</l>
                        <l>You yourself know the self as it is.</l>
                        <l>You are omniscient with respect to everything,</l>
                        <l>And you are free of any point of reference:</l>
                        <l>I bow to you! <ref cRef="162" type="sanskrit"/>
                            <ref cRef="F.301.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-161"/>
                    <lg tid="267">
                        <l>“I salute you, who have ten powers and have crossed the stream.</l>
                        <l>I salute you, the fearless one who bestows fearlessness.</l>
                        <l>You obtained certainty in the unshared dharmas:</l>
                        <l>Guide for the entire world, I salute you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-162"/>
                    <lg tid="268">
                        <l>“I salute you, who break the bondage of fetters,</l>
                        <l>I salute you, who reached the other shore and remain on dry ground.</l>
                        <l>I salute you, guide for the exhausted world.</l>
                        <l>I salute you, who go to saṃsāra and remain unplaced.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-163"/>
                    <lg tid="269">
                        <l>“I salute you, who even when dwelling with sentient beings,</l>
                        <l>Keep your mind aloof, in all realms of rebirth.<note place="end" index="45" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-388">Here the Sanskrit text seems rather corrupt. Following the Tibetan,
                                we would propose <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vandāmi satva­samāvāsa pi gatam</foreign>
                                | <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvāsu gatīṣu vivikta­mānasam</foreign>. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>You are untainted, like a lotus by the waters it grows in;</l>
                        <l>Sage, Buddha, you practiced emptiness! <ref cRef="164" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-164"/>
                    <lg tid="270">
                        <l>“Isolation is the unexcelled state of the Teacher;</l>
                        <l>I salute you, who are free from a point of reference and crossed the great stream.</l>
                        <l>You have thoroughly eliminated all signs,</l>
                        <l>And you wish for nothing whatsoever.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-165"/>
                    <lg tid="271">
                        <l>“I salute the inconceivable Buddha of great power,</l>
                        <l>Who is the same as space and without abode.</l>
                        <l>I salute you, supreme holder of all good qualities.</l>
                        <l>I salute you, whose glory rises up like Meru.” <ref cRef="166" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-166"/>
                    <p tid="272">Then the Bhagavat praised the youthful Mañjuśrī:</p>
                    <p tid="273">“Good, Mañjuśrī, that is good! You have spoken well, Mañjuśrī. It is just as you said. Mañjuśrī,
                        the buddhas should not be seen through form, through dharmas, through characteristics, or through the
                        dharmadhātu. The buddhas do not stay by themselves nor do they reside among many people. The buddhas have
                        not been seen by anyone, nor heard, nor worshipped, nor are they being worshipped now. The buddhas do not
                        make oneness or plurality out of any dharma. </p>
                    <p tid="274">“The buddhas did not obtain awakening. The buddhas are not increased by any dharma. No dharma has
                        been seen by the buddhas, nor has it been heard, recollected, <ref cRef="F.301.b"/> cognized, or known.
                        The buddhas have not spoken or expressed anything. They do not speak or express anything. They will not
                        speak or express anything. The buddhas do not gain supreme realization. The buddhas do not supremely
                        realize any dharma. The buddhas’ afflictions have not been destroyed. Buddhas have not directly realized
                        purification. Buddhas have not seen any dharma, nor heard it, smelt it, tasted it, touched it, or cognized
                        it. And why? Because of the primordial purity of all dharmas. <ref cRef="168" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-167"/>
                    <p tid="275"> “Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva may establish as many sentient beings as there are atomic particles in
                        a great trichiliocosm into the state of a pratyekabuddha, but he may still have no belief in this Dharma
                        teaching. Another bodhisattva, Mañjuśrī, who believes in this Dharma teaching engenders much more merit
                        than the first. All the more so for one who writes down this Dharma teaching or makes others write it—such
                        a person engenders even more merit. <ref cRef="170" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-168"/>
                    <p tid="276">“Mañjuśrī, there are many sentient beings to be found in the great trichiliocosm, whether born
                        from an egg, born from a womb, born from moisture, or born suddenly; some with form, others formless; some
                        with notions, others without notions; some without feet, others with two feet, and some with four feet, or
                        with many feet. Now, imagine that all of them obtain a human body, without precedent, but not their last.
                        Once they obtain a human body, they give rise to bodhicitta. Having given rise to bodhicitta, each and
                        every one of those bodhisattvas attends as many buddhas, together with bodhisattvas and hearers, <ref cRef="F.302.a"/> as there are atomic particles in buddhafields as numerous as the grains of sand in
                        the Ganges. Each bodhisattva offers robes, alms-food, bedding, seats, herbs that counteract illness, and
                        provisions, and he collects all the necessities for their happiness. Furthermore, he builds stūpas for
                        those buddhas who have already reached complete nirvāṇa, for as many eons as the number of grains of sand
                        in the Ganges. He constructs them out of precious substances, one hundred yojanas high, encircled by
                        jeweled vedikās, beautified with festoons of gems, pearls, and jewels, with raised umbrellas, standards,
                        and flags, and covered in nets of the precious vaśirāja gem. <ref cRef="172" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-169"/>
                    <p tid="277">“Now imagine another bodhisattva, with the right inclination, who listens to this Dharma
                        teaching, <title xml:lang="en">The Ornament of the Light of Awareness That Enters the Domain of All
                            Buddhas</title>, and then believes in it, engages with it, trusts it, realizes it, or teaches at least
                        one of its stanzas. Compared to the bodhisattvas first mentioned, he would engender even more uncountable
                        merit that would lead him to follow the awareness of a buddha. Compared to the merit he would produce, the
                        production of merit in the first instance, consisting of the bodhisattvas’ acts of giving, would not even
                        amount to a hundredth part. It would not even count for one thousandth or one-billionth of it. It would
                        not even count as any part, any number worthy of consideration, simile or approximation of any kind. <ref cRef="174" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-170"/>
                    <p tid="278">“Mañjuśrī, imagine a householder bodhisattva who attends as many buddhas and bodhisattvas,
                        together with their saṅgha of hearers, as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, for eons as numerous as
                        the grains of sand in the Ganges. He would offer them robes, alms-food, bedding, seats, remedies for
                        exhaustion, medicinal herbs, and provisions. But another ordained bodhisattva, disciplined and with the
                        right inclination, <ref cRef="F.302.b"/> may give a morsel of food to a single sentient being born as an
                        animal. Compared to the merit he would produce, the production of merit in the first instance would not
                        even amount to a hundredth part. It would not even count for one thousandth or one-billionth of it, up to,
                        as before, any approximation of any kind. <ref cRef="176" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-171"/>
                    <p tid="279">“Mañjuśrī, imagine as many bodhisattvas as there are atomic particles in the great trichiliocosm,
                        all of them ordained, disciplined, and pure in their inclinations. Each bodhisattva would attend as many
                        buddhas and bodhisattvas, together with their saṅgha of hearers, as there are grains of sand in the
                        Ganges. He would offer robes, alms-food, bedding, seats, remedies for exhaustion, medicinal herbs, and
                        provisions, for eons as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges. All those bodhisattvas would thus
                        produce merit through their acts of giving. But another bodhisattva, pure in his inclinations and
                        disciplined, whether householder or ordained, may listen to this Dharma teaching and believe in it, trust
                        it, write it down, or make others write it down. Compared to the merit he would produce, the production of
                        merit in the first instance, consisting of the bodhisattvas’ acts of giving, would not even amount to a
                        hundredth part. It would not even count for one thousandth or one-billionth of it. It would not even bear
                        approximation of any kind. <ref cRef="178" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-172"/>
                    <p tid="280">“Mañjuśrī, imagine that a bodhisattva great being were to fill the great trichiliocosm with seven
                        precious substances and offer it as a gift to the buddhas, the bhagavats. Offering in this way, he would
                        give this gift for as many eons as there are atomic particles of dust in a great trichiliocosm. But
                        another bodhisattva may teach just a four-line stanza from this Dharma method <ref cRef="F.303.a"/> to
                        another bodhisattva. Compared to the merit he would produce, the production of merit in the first instance
                        would not even amount to a hundredth part. It would not even count for one thousandth or one-billionth of
                        it. It would not even bear approximation of any kind. <ref cRef="180" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-173"/>
                    <p tid="281">“Mañjuśrī, consider that the production of merit of someone giving offerings were to continue for
                        as many eons as there are atomic particles in a great trichiliocosm. Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas as numerous as
                        the grains of sand in the Ganges would be there; each bodhisattva would cover as many golden buddhafields
                        as the number of grains of sand in the Ganges, and also all their trees, with divine clothes, and then
                        cover them in nets of gems and jewels shining in all possible ways. He would then fill them with high
                        palaces made of precious vaśirāja gems and surrounded with vedikās of the precious vidyutpradīpa gems.
                        Once filled, he would give them as a gift, with raised parasols, standards, and flags, to as many buddhas
                        as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, each and every day. In this way, he would offer such gifts for
                        eons as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges. But another bodhisattva may believe in this Dharma
                        teaching and teach just a single four-foot stanza from it to another bodhisattva. Compared to the merit he
                        would produce, the production of merit in the first instance, consisting of the bodhisattvas’ acts of
                        giving, would not even amount to a hundredth part. It would not even count for one thousandth or
                        one-billionth of it. It would not even count as any part, any number worthy of consideration, simile or
                        approximation of any kind. <ref cRef="182" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-174"/>
                    <p tid="282">“It is as follows: Mañjuśrī, if all sentient beings included in the three world spheres were to
                        be born in the hells, or as animals, <ref cRef="F.303.b"/> or as pretas in the world of Yama, a
                        householder bodhisattva may pull all of them out from those hells, the animal realm, and the preta world
                        of Yama and establish them in the state of a pratyekabuddha. But another ordained bodhisattva may just
                        give a morsel of food to one sentient being born as an animal. Compared to the first, the second would
                        engender a greater merit, an uncountably greater merit. <ref cRef="184" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-175"/>
                    <p tid="283">“Mañjuśrī, imagine that there were as many ordained bodhisattvas in the ten directions as there
                        are atomic particles in inexpressibly numerous, tens of quintillions of buddhafields. Each bodhisattva,
                        everywhere within the ten directions, would then see as many buddhas, as many bhagavats, as there are
                        atomic particles in inexpressibly numerous, tens of quintillions of buddhafields. He would then attend
                        upon each tathāgata, and the corresponding bodhisattvas and hearers, for as many eons as there are atomic
                        particles in inexpressibly numerous, tens of quintillions of buddhafields. He would offer robes,
                        alms-food, bedding, seats, remedies for exhaustion, medicinal herbs, and provisions. To each tathāgata,
                        each and every day, he would offer as many world spheres as there are atomic particles in inexpressibly
                        numerous, tens of trillions of buddhafields, after filling them with the precious vaśirāja gems. But
                        another bodhisattva, believing in this Dharma teaching, may give just one morsel of food to a sentient
                        being born as an animal. Compared to the merit he would produce, the production of merit in the first
                        instance, consisting of the bodhisattvas’ acts of giving, would not even amount to a hundredth part. It
                        would not even count for one thousandth or one-billionth of it. It would not even count as any part, any
                        number worthy of consideration, simile or approximation of any kind. And why? <ref cRef="F.304.a"/> The
                        seal of non-returning bodhisattvas is to hear this Dharma teaching. <ref cRef="186" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-176"/>
                    <p tid="284">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the state of one who follows out of conviction. But another bodhisattva might establish a
                        single sentient being in the state of one who follows the meaning. In that case, the latter would engender
                        incalculably greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-177"/>
                    <p tid="285">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the state of one who follows the meaning. But another bodhisattva might establish a single
                        sentient being in the state of one who follows the Dharma. In that case, the latter would engender
                        incalculably greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-178"/>
                    <p tid="286">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the state of one who follows the Dharma. But another bodhisattva might establish a single
                        sentient being in the result of attaining the stream. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably
                        greater merit. <ref cRef="188" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-179"/>
                    <p tid="287">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the result of attaining the stream. But another bodhisattva might establish a single
                        sentient being in the result of a once-returner. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably
                        greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-180"/>
                    <p tid="288"> “Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the result of a once-returner. But another bodhisattva might establish a single sentient
                        being in the result of a non-returner. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-181"/>
                    <p tid="289">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the result of a non-returner. But another bodhisattva might establish a single sentient
                        being in the result of an arhat. <ref cRef="F.304.b"/> In that case, the latter would engender
                        incalculably greater merit. <ref cRef="190" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-182"/>
                    <p tid="290">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the result of an arhat. But another bodhisattva might establish a single sentient being in
                        the result of a pratyekabuddha. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-183"/>
                    <p tid="291">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the result of a pratyekabuddha. But another bodhisattva might establish a single sentient
                        being in bodhicitta. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably greater merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-184"/>
                    <p tid="292">“Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in bodhicitta. But another bodhisattva might establish a single sentient being in the state of
                        irreversibility. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably greater merit. <ref cRef="192" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-185"/>
                    <p tid="293"> “Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva might establish the sentient beings of all the world spheres in the ten
                        directions in the state of irreversibility. But another bodhisattva, believing in this Dharma teaching,
                        might make others write it down, might shed light on it, or at least cause a single sentient being to
                        engage with this Dharma teaching. In that case, the latter would engender incalculably greater merit.”
                            <ref cRef="194" type="sanskrit"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-186"/>
                    <p tid="294">Then, at that time, the Bhagavat spoke the following verses:</p>
                    <lg tid="295">
                        <l>“In the final times of decay, a bodhisattva </l>
                        <l>May uphold the good Dharma of a hundred million buddhas.</l>
                        <l>Yet, if another listens with reverence to this sūtra,</l>
                        <l>His merit will be great, and exceed the former.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-187"/>
                    <lg tid="296">
                        <l>“By using one’s own special powers,</l>
                        <l>Someone may travel through the ten directions,</l>
                        <l>And worship a hundred million buddhas.</l>
                        <l>Eliciting compassion, not craving for any pleasure,</l>
                        <l>He may then salute all of those sacred persons. <ref cRef="F.305.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-188"/>
                    <lg tid="297">
                        <l>“Yet if for just a brief moment,</l>
                        <l>Another teaches others this sūtra,</l>
                        <l>That points to the Dharma of the victorious ones,</l>
                        <l>And keeps his mind well disposed toward the Sugata’s teaching,</l>
                        <l>The fruit of his merit will exceed the former. <ref cRef="196" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-189"/>
                    <lg tid="298">
                        <l>“The Sugata taught this sūtra, a lamp for gods and men:</l>
                        <l>Whoever makes this visible to others</l>
                        <l>Will have sharp wisdom and great strength</l>
                        <l>And quickly reach the level of the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-190"/>
                    <lg tid="299">
                        <l>“A person might hear and then tell someone else</l>
                        <l>The news that the buddhas, the best among men,</l>
                        <l>Have attained complete nirvāṇa,</l>
                        <l>Without any remainder.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-191"/>
                    <lg tid="300">
                        <l>“He may establish tall and beautiful stūpas,</l>
                        <l>Beautified with fine gems to the summit of existence;</l>
                        <l>With parasols, standards, and the sound of bells,</l>
                        <l>They would rise to the summit of existence. <ref cRef="198" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-192"/>
                    <lg tid="301">
                        <l>“Yet, when hearing this very sūtra, a bodhisattva </l>
                        <l>May form the wish to establish it well,</l>
                        <l>Either within his body or within a book.</l>
                        <l>Then the fruit of his merit exceeds the former.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-193"/>
                    <lg tid="302">
                        <l>“If a bodhisattva upholds this Dharma,</l>
                        <l>Removing all stains of miserliness and being without fear,</l>
                        <l>His merit will indeed be immeasurable,</l>
                        <l>And he shall obtain awakening, in accordance with his wish.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-194"/>
                    <lg tid="303">
                        <l>“This sūtra is extolled by the sugatas,</l>
                        <l>And upheld by many bodhisattvas.</l>
                        <l>Here the body of the tathāgatas,</l>
                        <l>Like the space-element, is shown to all.” <ref cRef="200" type="sanskrit"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-195"/>
                    <p tid="304">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="finalPraise">-->Thus spoke the Bhagavat joyfully. The bodhisattva Ārya Mañjuśrī
                        and the bodhisattva great beings, who had assembled from all the infinite, limitless world spheres of the
                        ten directions, along with the great hearers and the world with its gods, humans, demigods, and
                        gandharvas, rejoiced at the Bhagavat’s teachings.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="320">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-196"/>
                    <p tid="305">This completes the Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra <title xml:lang="en">The Ornament of the Light of
                            Awareness That Enters the Domain of All Buddhas</title>. </p>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="321">Sanskrit Colophon </head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-197"/>
                        <lg tid="306">
                            <l>The Tathāgata spoke of the cause and cessation,</l>
                            <l>Of those dharmas that come about through causes.</l>
                            <l>That is how the Great Śramaṇa speaks.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <p tid="307">This is an offering on the part of the monk Śīladhvaja, who takes the excellent Great Vehicle
                            as his vehicle. May the merit produced hereby go toward the obtainment of the fruit of supreme wisdom,
                            for all sentient beings, with the ācārya, the upādhyāya, and my mother and father going in front. This
                            was written down by the servant Cāṇḍoka in the kingdom of the supreme king of great kings, the
                            glorious Gopāladeva, in the 12th year of the Samvat, on the 30th day of Śrāmaṇa. May there be
                            splendor! </p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="322">Tibetan Colophon</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-198"/>
                        <p tid="308">This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholar Surendrabodhi, the
                            translator-editor Bhande Yeshe De, and others.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="323">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="324">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="325">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-199">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yul la ’jug pa’i ye shes snang ba’i rgyan
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sarva­buddha­viṣayāvatāra­jñānālokālaṃkāra­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 100, Degé Kangyur,
                        vol. 47 (mdo sde, ga), folios 276a1–305a7. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-200">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas thams cad kyi yul la ’jug pa’i ye shes snang ba’i rgyan
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sarva­buddha­viṣayāvatāra­jñānālokālaṃkāra­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur
                        ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur
                        khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 47,
                        pp. 727–799. </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="326">Sanskrit Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-201">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānālokālaṃkāra</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-202">The Study Group on Buddhist Sanskrit Literature (eds.). (2005). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānālokālaṃkāra</title>, Kyoto: Taisho University Press. </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-203">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryasarvabuddha­viṣayāvatārajñānālokālaṃkāra­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-204">GRETIL version. (2004). Based on the edition by Takayasu Kimura, Nobuo
                        Otsuka, Hideaki Kimura, and Hisao Takahashi, “Bonbun kotei ’Chikomyoshogon-kyo’ -
                        Sarvabuddhaviṣayāvatāra­jñānālokālaṃkāra­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra.” In <title xml:lang="en">Kūkai no shiso to
                            bunka [*A Felicitation Volume Presented to Prof. Kicho Onozuka on his Seventieth Birthday]</title>,
                        Tokyo: 1 (596) – 89 (508). </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-205">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­yāna­sūtrālaṃkāra</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-206">Bagchi, S. (ed.). (1970). <title xml:lang="en">Mahāyāna­sūtrālaṃkāra of
                            Asaṅga</title>. Darbhanga: The Mithila Institute.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-207">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-208">de la Vallée Poussin, L. (ed.). (1902). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title>. Calcutta: Asiatic Society of Bengal.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-209">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-210">———. (1903–1913). <title xml:lang="fr">Mūlamadhyamaka­kārikās
                            (Mādhyamikasūtras) de Nāgārjuna, avec la Prasannapadā commentaire de Candrakīrti</title>. St.
                        Petersburg: Bibliotheca Buddhica. Reprint, Osnabruck: Biblio, 1970. </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-211">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattvasaṃgraha</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-212">Dwarikadass, S. (ed.). (1968). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tattva­saṃgraha</title>. Varanasi: Bauddha Bharati.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-213">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharma­kośa­bhāṣya</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-214">———. (1981). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharma­kośa</title>. Varanasi:
                        Bauddha Bharati.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-215">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapa­parivarta</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-216">Staël-Holstein, Baron A. von (ed.). (1926). <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Kāśyaparivarta: A Mahāyānasūtra of the Ratnakūṭa Class in the Original Sanskrit, in Tibetan and in
                            Chinese</title>. Shanghai: The Commercial Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-217">Pāsādika, Bhikkhu (ed., transl.). (2015). <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Kāśyaparivarta</title>. New Delhi: Aditya Prakashan.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-218">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­gotra­vibhāga</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-219">Prasad, H.S. (ed.). (1991). <title xml:lang="en">The Uttaratantra of
                            Maitreya</title>, Bibliotheca Indo-Buddhica No. 79 (contains E.H. Johnston's Sanskrit text and E.
                        Obermiller's English translation). Delhi: Sri Satguru Publications. </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-220">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Advaya­vajra­saṃgraha</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-221">Shastri, H.P. (ed.). (1927). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Advaya­vajra­saṃgraha</title>. Baroda: Oriental Institute.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-222">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­prajñā­pāramitā­vajracchedikā­ṭīkā</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-223">Tenzin, P. (ed. and trans.). (1994). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­prajñā­pāramitā­vajra­cchedikā­sūtram evaṃ Ācārya­kamalaśīla­viracitā
                            Ārya­prajñā­pāramitā­vajracchedikā­ṭīkā</title>. Sarnath: CIHTS. </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-224">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sekoddeśaṭīkā</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-225">Sferra, F. and Merzagora, S. (eds.). (2006). <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Sekoddeśaṭīkā by Nāropā Paramārtha­saṃgraha</title>. Rome: Istituto Italiano per l’Africa e l’Oriente. </bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-226">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­parivarta</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-227">Vaidya, P.L. (ed.). (1961). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­yāna­sūtra­saṃgrahaḥ</title>, Darbhanga: Mithila Institute.</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-228">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra</title>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-229">———. (1963). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharma­laṅkāvatāra­sūtram</title>.
                        Darbhanga: The Mithila Institute.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="327">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-230">Almogi, O. (2009). <title xml:lang="en">A Study of Various Conceptions of
                            Buddhahood in Indian Sources with Special Reference to the Controversy Surrounding the Existence of
                            Awareness (jñāna: ye shes) as Presented by the Eleventh-Century Tibetan Scholar Rong-zom
                            Chos-kyi-bzang-po</title>. Tokyo: The International Institute for Buddhist Studies. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-231">Edgerton, F. (1953). <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar
                            and Dictionary</title>. Vol. I, Grammar. New Haven: Yale University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-232">Köppl, H. (2008). <title xml:lang="en">Establishing Appearances as
                            Divine</title>. Ithaca: Snow Lion. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-233">De la Vallée Poussin, L. (Ed.). (1913). <title xml:lang="fr">Mūlamadhyama­kakārikās de Nāgārjuna avec la Prasanna­padā commentaire de Candrakīrti</title>. St.
                        Petersbourg: Académie Impériale des Sciences. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-234">Prasad, H.S. (1991). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Uttara­tantra­śāstra</title>.
                        Delhi: Sri Satguru Publications. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-235">Skilling, P. (2004). “Jambūdvīpepracaramāṇaḥ: The Circulation of Mahāyāna
                        Sūtras in India,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International College for Advanced Buddhist
                            Studies</title>, VII, 73–87. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-236">Study Group on Buddhist Sanskrit Literature (2004). <title xml:lang="en">Introduction to the Vimalakīrti­nirdeśa and Jñānālokālaṃkāra</title>. Tokyo: Taisho University Press. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-237"> Takasaki, J. (1966). <title xml:lang="en">A Study on the
                            Ratnagotra­vibhāga (Uttara­tantra): Being a Treatise on the Tathāgata­garbha Theory of Mahāyāna
                            Buddhism</title>. Rome: Is. M.E.O. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-238">Tatz, M. (1987). “The Life of the Siddha-Philosopher Maitrīgupta,” in
                            <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the American Oriental Society</title> 107(4): 695–711. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-047-002-239">Wayman, A. (1955). “Notes on the Sanskrit Term Jñāna,” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the American Oriental Society</title> 75(4): 253–268. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-240">
                            <term>absorptions into nine successive abodes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthar gyis gnas pa’i snyoms par ’jug pa dgu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐར་གྱིས་གནས་པའི་སྙོམས་པར་འཇུག་པ་དགུ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">navānupūrva­vihāra­samāpattayaḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four dhyānas, the four formless absorptions, and the absorption of
                                cessation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-241">
                            <term>ācārya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">slob dpon </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སློབ་དཔོན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ācārya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Teacher (sometimes more specifically the deputy or substitute of the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādhyāya</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-242">
                            <term>affliction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of mental imperfection. The most basic afflictions are attachment,
                                aversion, and confusion.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-243">
                            <term>aggregate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Five collections of similar dharmas, under which all compounded dharmas may be
                                included; form, feeling, notions, factors, and consciousness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-244">
                            <term>apsaras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha’i bu mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་བུ་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apsaras</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine girl.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-245">
                            <term>arhat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Worthy one” or “someone who has killed his foes” (i.e., mental afflictions);
                                a Buddhist saint who has obtained liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-246">
                            <term>Bhagavat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha, meaning “one who has fortune” (explained as having six
                                features); or “one who has vanquished (Māra).”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-247">
                            <term>bodhicitta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The intent to obtain buddhahood to benefit all sentient beings; the practices
                                towards buddhahood; the realization of emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-248">
                            <term>bodhisattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the Vehicle of the Bodhisattvas; one who
                                aims for complete buddhahood; “awakening hero;” “one who has a wish for awakening;” “one who
                                awakens sentient beings.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-249">
                            <term>buddhafield</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi zhing </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཞིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhakṣetra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The field of activity of a specific buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-250">
                            <term>Cloud of Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi sprin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྤྲིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmameghā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The tenth and highest of the levels in the bodhisattva path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-251">
                            <term>Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Among many of its meanings, this term can refer to: the teachings of the
                                Buddha; positive actions that accord with those teachings; or a minimal element of existence,
                                which bears certain features through which it may be cognized.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-252">
                            <term>Dharma wheel</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’khor lo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmacakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">When a buddha gives his first teaching he “sets in motion the Wheel of
                                Dharma;” just like a monarch with exceptional merit sets in motion a magical wheel that easily
                                subdues all his enemies.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-253">
                            <term>dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">“The sphere of dharmas,” “the base of dharmas,” “the ore of dharmas”—a synonym
                                for the nature of things.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-254">
                            <term>dharmakāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the subdivisions in the collection of dharmas that constitutes a
                                buddha, variously explained but usually more closely related to the aspect of ultimate
                                truth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-255">
                            <term>dharmatā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The nature of the dharmas, or their state.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-256">
                            <term>diamond-like samādhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje lta bu’i ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajropama­samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A very high level of samādhi obtained during the last stages of the Buddhist
                                path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-257">
                            <term>eight right modes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa nyid brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པ་ཉིད་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭau samyaktvāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">eight right modes</term> are: right view, right thought, right speech, right
                                actions, right livelihood, right effort, right recollection, and right samādhi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-258">
                            <term>eight wrong modes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">log pa nyid brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལོག་པ་ཉིད་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭa­mithyātvāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">eight wrong modes</term> are: wrong view, wrong thought, wrong speech, wrong
                                actions, wrong livelihood, wrong effort, wrong recollection, and wrong samādhi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-259">
                            <term>eighteen bases</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eighteen collections of similar dharmas, under which all compounded and
                                uncompounded dharmas may be included: eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind, plus their objects:
                                visible forms, sounds, smells, flavors, touchables, and dharmas, plus the consciousnesses
                                corresponding to each of the first six.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-260">
                            <term>attaining the stream</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyun du zhugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">srota-āpatti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first level of noble ones when practicing the path of the hearers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-261">
                            <term>five faculties</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po lnga’i ming la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ་ལྔའི་མིང་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcendriyāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, diligence, recollection, samādhi, and wisdom (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śraddhā</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛti</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-262">
                            <term>five hindrances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañca nīvaraṇāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Longing for desires (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāmacchanda</foreign>), malice (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyāpāda</foreign>),
                                sloth and torpor (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">styānamiddha</foreign>), excitement and
                                remorse (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">auddhatya­kaukṛtya</foreign>) and doubt (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vicikitsā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-263">
                            <term>four distortions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyin ci log bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catvāro viparyāsāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Taking what is impure as pure; what is impermanent as permanent; what is
                                suffering as happiness; and what is non-self as a self.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-264">
                            <term>four placements of mindfulness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i dran pa nye bar bzhag pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་བཞག་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catvāri samyak­smṛtyupasthānāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mindfulness of the body; feelings; the mind; and dharmas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-265">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semi-divine being “feeding on smell” and musically skilled.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-266">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semi-divine bird.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-267">
                            <term>gods of the Four Great Kings</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal chen bzhi’i lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་ཆེན་བཞིའི་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cātur­mahārājika­deva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-268">
                            <term>Great Vehicle</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The same as the Bodhisattva Vehicle, whose practitioners aim at complete
                                buddhahood.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-269">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the Vehicle of the <term type="ignore">Hearers</term> (those who hear
                                the teachings from others); or, someone who heard the Dharma from the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-270">
                            <term>hindrances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nīvaraṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “five hindrances.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-271">
                            <term>irreversibility</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyir mi ldog pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིར་མི་ལྡོག་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avaivartikatva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A stage in the bodhisattva path where the practitioner will never turn
                                back.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-272">
                            <term>karma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karman</term>
                            <term type="definition">Intention or what follows an intention. Intention is mental <term type="ignore">karma</term>; what
                                follows an intention is verbal and bodily <term type="ignore">karma</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-273">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semi-divine being who is partly human and musically skilled.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-274">
                            <term>vaipulya sūtras of the Heap of Jewels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rgyas pa’i sde kon mchog brtsegs pa’i mdo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པའི་སྡེ་ཀོན་མཆོག་བརྩེགས་པའི་མདོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ratna­kūṭa­vaipulya­sūtra</term>
                            <term type="definition">This could refer to the Ratnakūṭa collection of sūtras as it is known in the
                                Kangyur and Chinese canons; however, as the collection is not known to have existed, as such, in
                                earlier times, this could also be either a general term covering Mahāyāna sūtras as a category, or
                                a synonym for the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapa­parivarta</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-275">
                            <term>limbs of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyanggāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “seven limbs of awakening.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-276">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semi-divine being similar to a large snake.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-277">
                            <term>nine causes of antagonism</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas mnar sems kyi dngos po dgu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་མནར་སེམས་ཀྱི་དངོས་པོ་དགུ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">navā­ghātavastūni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Thinking that someone harms oneself, harms someone dear to oneself, or
                                benefits someone dear to oneself, each in the present, past, or future.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-278">
                            <term>Nirgrantha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gcer bu pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཅེར་བུ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirgrantha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of non-Buddhist religious practitioner.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-279">
                            <term>nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The “blowing off” of suffering; the state of freedom from the suffering of
                                saṃsāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-280">
                            <term>noble one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who has entered the “path of seeing,” i.e., who has a direct and
                                stable realization of selflessness, ceases to be an “ordinary person” and becomes a <term type="ignore">noble
                                one</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-281">
                            <term>non-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyir mi ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">The third level of noble ones when practicing the path of the hearers (bound
                                to never be reborn).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-282">
                            <term>once-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lan cig phyir ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sakṛdāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second level of noble ones when practicing the path of the hearers (bound
                                to be born again no more than once).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-283">
                            <term>one who follows out of conviction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dad pas rjes su ’brang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དད་པས་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śraddhānusārin</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who follows his or her goal out of trust in someone else.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-284">
                            <term>one who follows the Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi rjes su ’brang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmānusārin</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who follows his or her goal according to the teaching of the sūtras
                                and so forth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-285">
                            <term>one who follows the meaning</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">don gyi rjes su ’brang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོན་གྱི་རྗེས་སུ་འབྲང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arthānusārin</term>
                            <term type="definition">According to the Abhi­dharma­kośa­bhāṣya, both those who “follow out of
                                conviction” and those who “follow due to the Dharma” are actually “following the meaning/goal.” On
                                the other hand, the JAA seems to take this as a separate subdivision.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-286">
                            <term>ordinary people</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so so’i skye bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོའི་སྐྱེ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pṛthagjana</term>
                            <term type="definition">Anyone who has not entered the “Path of Seeing” (i.e., has no stable direct
                                realization of selflessness) is an ordinary person as opposed to a noble one.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-287">
                            <term>outflow</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsrava</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mental afflictions can be called <term type="ignore">outflows</term> since they “flow out,” i.e., they
                                are caused by certain dharmas (said to be “with <term type="ignore">outflows</term>”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-288">
                            <term>Parivrājakas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu rgyu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་རྒྱུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pari­vrājaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A non-Buddhist religious practitioner who “roams around.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-289">
                            <term>perfection</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A set of practices to be completely mastered (until one reaches their “other
                                shore”) for those on the bodhisattva path. They are listed as either six or ten.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-290">
                            <term>postures</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱོད་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">īryapatha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Sitting, standing, lying down, walking.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-291">
                            <term>pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyeka­buddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who obtains personal liberation through very little or no instruction
                                from others; “solitary buddha” in some interpretations.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-292">
                            <term>preta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dwags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དྭགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of sentient beings constantly suffering from hunger and thirst, one of
                                the six (or five) possible realms of rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-293">
                            <term>samādhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Placing the mind on an object of attention, or sometimes more generally, a
                                meditative state.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-294">
                            <term>saṃsāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continuum of repeated birth and death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-295" mode="marked">
                            <term>seven false dharmas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam pa ma yin pa’i chos bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམ་པ་མ་ཡིན་པའི་ཆོས་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saptāsaddharmāḥ</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-296">
                            <term>seven limbs of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta bodhyanggāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Recollection, analysis of the dharmas, diligence, joy, pliancy, samādhi,
                                equanimity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-297">
                            <term>six entrances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaḍ-āyatanāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, and mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-298">
                            <term>six remembrances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rjes su dran pa drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྗེས་སུ་དྲན་པ་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaḍ-anusmṛtayaḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Remembrance of the Buddha, the Dharma, the Saṅgha, relinquishing, discipline,
                                and the gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-299">
                            <term>stūpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A Buddhist sacred monument usually holding the relics of a buddha or some
                                highly revered Buddhist master.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-300">
                            <term>sugata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sugata</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the Buddha meaning “well-gone one,” “gone to bliss,” “easily
                                understood.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-301">
                            <term>sūtra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མདོ་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūtra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Usually referring to a discourse by the Buddha; sometimes to just a few
                                sentences by the Buddha; or also, when not referring to the words of the Buddha, any concise
                                doctrinal statement.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-302">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the Buddha, meaning “one who has gone, reached, or had realized
                                in that way.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-303">
                            <term>tathatā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bshin nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཤིན་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The state in which things are; “thusness.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-304">
                            <term>tattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de kho na nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་ཁོ་ན་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">The nature of things; their actual state; “thatness.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-305">
                            <term>ten unwholesome courses of karma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dge ba bcu’i las kyi lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśākuśalāḥ karma­pathāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">Killing, taking what is not given, sexual misconduct, speaking what is false,
                                divisive speech, harsh speech, scattered speech, covetousness, wish to harm, and wrong view (three
                                of the body, four of speech, and three of the mind).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-306">
                            <term>ten wholesome courses of karma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba bcu’i las kyi lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བ་བཅུའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśakuśalāḥ karma­pathāḥ</term>
                            <term type="definition">The opposite of the ten unwholesome courses of karma.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-307">
                            <term>Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rsta gsum pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རསྟ་གསུམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trayastriṃśat</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-308">
                            <term>three vehicles</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐེག་པ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">triyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Hearers’ Vehicle, the Pratyekabuddha Vehicle, and the Bodhisattva
                                Vehicle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-309">
                            <term>three world spheres</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">traidhātuka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The realm of desire, the realm of form, and the formless realm (under which
                                the whole universe is subsumed).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-310">
                            <term>tīrthika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu stegs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthika</term>
                            <term type="definition">A non-Buddhist religious practitioner who relies on sacred “fords” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrtha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-311">
                            <term>transitory collection</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig tshogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་ཚོགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">satkāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">transitory collection</term> of the five aggregates, the basis for the view of a
                                self or that which belongs to a self.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-312">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten gyi khams stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས་སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tri­sāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A very large universe.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-313">
                            <term>twelve entrances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">Twelve collections of similar dharmas, under which all compounded and
                                uncompounded dharmas may be included: eye, ear, nose, tongue, body, mind, and their objects:
                                visible forms, sounds, smells, flavors, touchables, and dharmas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-314">
                            <term>twelve limbs of existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srid pa’i yan lag bcu gnyis </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིད་པའི་ཡན་ལག་བཅུ་གཉིས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvādaśa bhavānggāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Twelve successive parts in which to subdivide the longest possible process of
                                dependent arising for one sentient being: ignorance, formations, consciousness, name and form, six
                                entrances, contact, feeling, craving, clinging, becoming, birth, old age, and death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-315">
                            <term>two extremes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ gnyis </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་གཉིས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">antadvaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The extreme of permanence (of a self through many lives) and the extreme of
                                cutting off (i.e., the cessation of consciousness after one life).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-316">
                            <term>upādhyāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mkhan po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཁན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādhyāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Teacher, (monastic) preceptor; “having approached him, one studies from him”
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upetyādhīyate asmāt</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-317">
                            <term>uragasāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbrul gyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྲུལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uragasāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-318">
                            <term>vedikā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kha khyer </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁ་ཁྱེར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vedikā</term>
                            <term type="definition">An architectural element similar to a pedestal.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-319">
                            <term>vidyutpradīpa gem</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor bu rin po che glog gi sgron ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་བུ་རིན་པོ་ཆེ་གློག་གི་སྒྲོན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyutpradīpa­maṇi­ratna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-320">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semi-divine being.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-321">
                            <term>Caraka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod pa ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱོད་པ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caraka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A non-Buddhist wanderer, often grouped with the Parivrājakas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-322">
                            <term>Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun shes kauN+Din+ya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎྜིནྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ājñāta­kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Kauṇḍinya Who Understood.” Name of the first monk that Śākyamuni Buddha
                                recognized as having understood his teachings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-323">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhaiṣajya­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “King of Medicine.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-324">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajya­samudgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman yang dag ’phags la sogs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་ཡང་དག་འཕགས་ལ་སོགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhaiṣajya­samudgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Medicine-Risen Up.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-325">
                            <term>Bhande Yeshe De</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ban de ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-326">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahman</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity who presides over a divine world where other beings
                                consider him the creator; he is also considered to be the Lord of the Sahā-world (our
                                universe).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-327">
                            <term>Buddhiśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhiśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Intellect-Splendor.” However, the Tibetan suggests
                                “Buddha-” rather than “Buddhi-,” which would then mean “Buddha-Splendor.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-328">
                            <term>Dhanaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhanaśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Wealth-Splendor.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-329">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Beautiful Glory, Lovely Splendor.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-330">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The personification of negativity. In the Sanskrit tradition, four <term type="ignore">Māras</term> are
                                usually listed: the aggregates, the afflictions, the god <term type="ignore">Māra</term> (the god of infatuation), and
                                death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-331">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the gods of the Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-332">
                            <term>Śīladhvaja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims rgyal mtshan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྒྱལ་མཚན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīladhvaja</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Banner of Discipline;” the name of the person who sponsored the writing of
                                the manuscript of the JAA.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-333">
                            <term>Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">su ren dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">surendrabodhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-334">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The king of the preta realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-335">
                            <term>Cakravāḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor yug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ཡུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravāḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a mountain range in Buddhist cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-336">
                            <term>Jāmbū</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jāmbū</term>
                            <term type="definition">A river whose gold is believed to be especially good.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-337">
                            <term>Jambūdvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambūdvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvīpa</foreign>) on
                                which we live which, according to ancient South-Asian cosmology, is shaped like a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambū</foreign> fruit (probably <foreign xml:lang="la">Syzygium
                                    cumini</foreign>, the jambolan, Malabar plum, or Java plum; or possibly <foreign xml:lang="la">S. amarangense</foreign>, the Java apple, rose-apple, or wax jambu).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-338">
                            <term>Mahācakravāḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor yug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ཡུག་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā­cakra­vāḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a mountain range in Buddhist cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-339">
                            <term>Meru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhun po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷུན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">meru</term>
                            <term type="definition">The highest mountain at the center of our world according to traditional
                                Buddhist cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-340">
                            <term>Rājgir</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">“King’s House;” name of a town in modern-day Bihar, North India.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-341">
                            <term>Sudharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sudharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of hall where the gods of the thirty-three assemble to listen to the
                                Dharma.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-342">
                            <term>Sumeru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sumeru</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “Meru.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-047-002-343">
                            <term>Vulture Peak</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gṛdhrakūṭa parvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a mountain in Rājgir.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>