<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye shes kyi mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">འདའ་ཀ་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on Wisdom at the Hour of Death</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyaya­jñāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་འདའ་ཀ་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Wisdom at the Hour of Death”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryātyaya­jñāna­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-44">Translated by Tom Tillemans’ class in the University of Vienna’s program of Buddhist
                    Translation Studies<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
                    Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-31">Casey Kemp</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Tom Tillemans</author>
                <!-- 
                <author role="translatorEng">Tom Tillemans</author> -->
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.24 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-054-003"/>
                <date>2016-12-01</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh122" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 122</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur vol. 54 (mdo sde, tha), folios 153.a–153.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Unknown</author>
                    <location count-pages="2">
                        <start volume="54" page="307"/>
                        <end volume="54" page="308"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11695" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-18T16:07:40.028Z" user="admin">18/06/2019 16:07:40</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.24" date-time="2019-06-18T16:07:37.289Z" user="celso">v 1.24 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--Contents    
    Summary
    Acknowledgments
    Introduction
    The Translation
    The Sūtra on Wisdom at the Hour of Death
    Bibliography 
    Notes-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="29">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-1"/>
                <p tid="1">While the Buddha is residing in the Akaniṣṭha realm, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha asks him
                    how to consider the mind of a bodhisattva who is about to die. The Buddha replies that when death comes a
                    bodhisattva should develop the wisdom of the hour of death. He explains that a bodhisattva should cultivate a
                    clear understanding of the non-existence of entities, great compassion, non-apprehension, non-attachment, and
                    a clear understanding that, since wisdom is the realization of one’s own mind, the Buddha should not be sought
                    elsewhere. After these points have been repeated in verse form, the assembly praises the Buddha’s words,
                    concluding the sūtra.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="30">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated into English by Tom Tillemans’ class in the University of Vienna’s program of Buddhist
                    Translation Studies in 2014. The introduction was written by Casey Kemp and Tom Tillemans.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="31">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">This sūtra, brief though it is, addresses central Mahāyāna concepts in relation to practices to be
                        carried out at the hour of death. When the Buddha is asked how one is to consider the mind (or mindset) of
                        a bodhisattva who is about to die, he replies by giving pith instructions on the nature of phenomena and
                        the mind, and instructs that a bodhisattva should accordingly engender specific clear understandings. The
                        Buddha points out that all phenomena are pure, subsumed within the mind of enlightenment, and naturally
                        luminous. Entities are impermanent, and the realization of mind is wisdom. Consequently, a bodhisattva
                        should arouse a clear understanding that no entities truly exist, a clear understanding of great
                        compassion, a clear understanding of non-apprehension, a clear understanding of non-attachment, and a
                        clear understanding that the Buddha should not be sought elsewhere than in one’s own mind. Although he
                        refers to these instructions as the wisdom of the hour of death, the implication is that these teachings
                        can be cultivated and realized throughout a bodhisattva’s lifetime in order to prepare for death and
                        attain liberation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The Sanskrit title of the sūtra is found transcribed in all Kangyurs as <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-ātajñāna-nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-59">In
                            all Kangyurs, both printed and manuscript, the only minor variation being that the initial
                                <emph>a</emph> of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-āta-</foreign> is shortened in the Peking and Yongle
                            Kangyurs. The Tōhoku Catalogue entry for the sūtra (but not the commentaries) also has this
                            title.</note> This transcription, however, appears to have been truncated; as Sanskrit, it is not
                        readily comprehensible, and certainly not equivalent to the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye
                            shes.</foreign> Another version of the Sanskrit title occasionally given is <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atijñānasūtra</title>,<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-60">See Rhaldri (2010) and
                            Jackson (2011).</note> which, although certainly understandable, yields a meaning quite different from
                        that of the Tibetan. The more likely Sanskrit phrase that would capture <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka
                            ye shes </foreign>is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atyayajñāna</foreign> (“wisdom at the time of passing
                        away”), and this has been proposed as a revision of the Sanskrit title in several modern catalogues.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-61"> Including the Tōhoku Catalogue’s (1934) Sanskrit
                            transliteration of the titles of the associated commentaries (though not of the sūtra itself); the
                            catalogue of the Nyingma Edition of the Degé Kangyur published by Dharma Publishing (1977-1983); and
                            Tadeusz Skorupski’s <title xml:lang="en">Catalogue of the Stog Palace Kanjur</title> (1985).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">There is no extant Sanskrit text to our knowledge, although it is clear that there was such an
                        original at one time—the Tibetan colophon to Śāntideva’s commentary mentions that the Indian abbot
                        Dharmarāja collaborated with Pakpa Sherab (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa shes rab</foreign>) in the
                        translation of the commentarial text. The sūtra translation preserved in the Kangyur, however, has no
                        colophon with the usual mention of the Tibetan translators and Indian paṇḍits, and was most likely made
                        not from the Sanskrit but from an earlier Chinese translation, as the early 9th century Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</foreign>) catalogue explicitly includes the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title> in a list of sūtras translated into Tibetan from Chinese. Its inclusion in the
                        Denkarma allows it to be dated to the first decades of the ninth century at the latest, and possibly earlier
                        if it was indeed known to King Trisong Detsen (see below). The putative Chinese version, however, does not
                        seem to have survived and the sūtra does not seem to figure in the Chinese canon.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">There are two commentaries on this text written by Indian authors in the Degé Tengyur, one
                        attributed to Śāntideva (c. eighth century) and the other to Prajñāsamudra (dates unknown).<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-62"> See bibliography.</note> There are also six known Tibetan
                        commentaries, four of which were written by seventeenth to nineteenth century Gelukpa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge lugs
                            pa</foreign>) scholars, the longest and most detailed being one by the seventh Dalai Lama, Kelsang
                            Gyatso.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-63"> See bibliography for some of these.                            Also Khomthar Jamlö (2014), vol. 1, p. 4, and vol. 6, pp. 1-2 for comments and a partial list; vol. 4
                            contains the two Indian commentaries and five of the six known Tibetan ones. See also Jackson (2009),
                            p. 7, n. 17.</note> Our translation mainly follows the commentary of Prajñāsamudra and, to a lesser
                        degree, that of Choné Drakpa Shedrub (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne grags pa bshad sgrub</foreign>,
                        1675-1748). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title> is included in lists of sūtras known as the Five
                        Royal Sūtras and Ten Royal Sūtras, two sets of profound, relatively short, and pithy works<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-64"> See Khomthar Jamlö (2014), vol. 1 pp. 2-3, and
                            Jackson (2009), p. 3. Lists of both sets can also be found in <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod rgya tshig
                                mdzod chen mo </title>(ed. Zhang Yisun) and <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dung dkar tshig mdzod chen
                                mo</title>, s.v. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo lnga </title>and <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo bcu.</title>
                        </note> traditionally said to have been translated on Padmasambhava’s recommendation and used for daily
                        practice by the eighth century Tibetan king Trisong Detsen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khri srong lde
                            btsan</foreign>). Their use is said to have contributed (along with other practices) to the king’s
                        life being prolonged by thirteen years beyond the limit predicted by astrological reckoning. The texts
                        recounting this incident list the applications or uses of each of these texts; in the case of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title>, this is meditation or cultivation (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgom pa</foreign>). In the same accounts the sūtra is described as being of definitive meaning.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-65"> The accounts are found in the longer biographies of
                            Guru Padmasambhava, e.g. in the twelfth century <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Zanglingma</title> (chapter 18)
                            and fourteenth century <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Padma Kathang</foreign> (chapter 70). For these, see
                            bibliography under Nyangrel Nyima Özer and Orgyen Lingpa, respectively.</note> Another Tibetan
                        tradition explains that the Five Royal Sūtras each present the condensed, essentialized meaning of five of
                        the major canonical texts, all much longer, known as the Five Sets of One Hundred Thousand.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-66">See Khomthar Jamlö (2014), vol. 1, p. 3; Jackson
                            (2009), pp. 5-6; and Jackson’s source, Lopez (1988), pp. 29-30 and 143. Lopez, in turn, is quoting (and
                            translates at length) an eighteenth to nineteenth century Gelukpa author, Tendar Lharampa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan dar lha ram pa</foreign>). The term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’bum [chen] sde
                                lnga</foreign>—although it does not seem to have been particularly widespread—was used at least as
                            early as the tenth century.</note> From this viewpoint, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title> represents the essence of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­pari­nirvāṇa­sūtra</title> (Toh 119-120). Yet another, more prosaic explanation sometimes found
                        for the epithet “royal” being applied to these works is simply that each of them, compared to other works
                        on similar themes, is of paramount importance. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title> is considered particularly important in several
                        Tibetan Buddhist traditions, including Dzogchen (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rdzogs
                            chen</foreign>) and Mahāmudrā. Roger Jackson points out that it seems to be the only sūtra from the
                        Kangyur that is included in indigenous Tibetan lists of Indian canonical texts on Mahāmudrā. As a search
                        of the Buddhist Digital Resource Center (www.tbrc.org) data reveals, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyayajñāna</title> is quoted by well-known Tibetan authors of all schools—including Gampopa
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgam po pa</foreign>, 1079-1153), Sakya Paṇḍita (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa skya paN+Di ta</foreign>, 1182-1251), Karmapa Rangjung Dorje (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang byung rdo rje</foreign>, 1284-1339), Longchen Rabjampa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klong chen rab ’byams pa</foreign>, 1308-1364), Shākya Chogden (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya mchog ldan</foreign>, 1428-1507), Drukpa Padma Karpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’brug pa pad+ma dkar po</foreign>, 1527-1592), Tāranātha (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tA ra nA tha</foreign>, 1575-1634), and the Fifth Dalai Lama, Ngawang Lobzang Gyatso (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngag dbang blo bzang rgya mtsho</foreign>, 1617-1682). The most frequent excerpt
                        quoted is from the final verses on the mind (1.14):</p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="10">
                            <l>Since the mind is the cause for the arising of wisdom,</l>
                            <l>Do not look for the Buddha elsewhere.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-9"/>
                    <p tid="11">Unsurprisingly, this brief yet well-known sūtra has been translated into English a number of
                        times. Several translations can be found on the internet, including translations by Ruth Sonam, Erik
                        Tsiknopoulos, and at least one anonymous version. Published translations include those by Roger Jackson
                        (2009), Sherab Raldri (2010), and Tony Duff (2011). A translation of the sūtra together with translations
                        of Prajñāsamudra’s and Śāntideva’s commentaries has been published online by Lhasey Lotsawa Translations
                        (2015). We hope that our translation will contribute to readers’ appreciation of this remarkable and
                        justly celebrated work.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="32">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="33">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra on</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="34">Wisdom at the Hour of Death</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">
                        <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas! </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">Thus did I hear at one time. While the Blessed One was residing in the palace of the king of the
                        gods in the Akaniṣṭha realm,<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-67">This appears to be the
                            only Kangyur sūtra to be set in Akaniṣṭha (although a number of tantras are, too). As well as
                            referring to the highest level of the Realm of Form, Akaniṣṭha here, according to the Indian and
                            Tibetan commentaries, is also to be equated with the Ghana­vyūha (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stug po
                                bkod pa</foreign>) buddhafield and indicates that the Buddha is present here in his saṃbhoga­kāya
                            form, perceptible only to bodhisattvas on the highest levels.</note> he taught the Dharma to the
                        entire assembly. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha then paid homage to the Blessed One and asked, “Blessed
                        One, how should we think about the mind of a bodhisattva who is about to die?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">The Blessed One replied, “Ākāśagarbha, when a bodhisattva is about to die, he should cultivate the
                        wisdom of the hour of death. The wisdom of the hour of death is as follows: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">“All phenomena are naturally pure. So, one should cultivate the clear understanding that there are
                        no entities. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-15"/>
                <p tid="17">“All phenomena are subsumed within the mind of enlightenment. So, one should cultivate the clear
                        understanding of great compassion.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-68"><!-- KB -->
                            Prajñāsamudra’s commentary here explains that all phenomena of saṃsāra and nirvāṇa indeed have no true
                            “outer” existence but are one’s own very mind of enlightenment, and that “great compassion” means
                            applying all three levels of compassion, namely, (1) compassion that perceives sentient beings
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can la dmigs pa’i snying rje</foreign>) regarding their
                            suffering; (2) compassion that perceives phenomena (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos la dmigs pa’i
                                snying rje</foreign>) regarding the impermanent, suffering, empty, and selfless nature of all
                            phenomena; and (3) compassion that does not apprehend anything (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa
                                med pa’i snying rje</foreign>), and thus cultivating emptiness. The three together include all of
                            the Buddha’s teaching. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-16"/>
                    <p tid="18">“All phenomena are naturally luminous. So, one should cultivate the clear understanding of
                        non-apprehension.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-17"/>
                    <p tid="19">“All entities are impermanent. So, one should cultivate the clear understanding of non-attachment
                        to anything whatsoever.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-18"/>
                    <p tid="20">“When one realizes mind, this is wisdom. So, one should cultivate the clear understanding of not
                        seeking the Buddha elsewhere.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="21">The Blessed One then spoke the following verses:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-19"/>
                    <lg tid="22">
                        <l>“Since all phenomena are naturally pure,</l>
                        <l>One should cultivate the clear understanding that there are no entities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-20"/>
                    <lg tid="23">
                        <l>“Since all phenomena<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-69"> Although the subject “all
                                phenomena” is omitted in this verse, it is implicit, as can be seen in the parallel construction
                                in the preceding and following verses, each beginning with <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos
                                    rnams</foreign>. Significantly too, the earlier prose passage expressing this idea had
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos thams cad</foreign> (“all phenomena”) as the subject.</note>
                            are connected with the enlightened mind,</l>
                        <l>One should cultivate the clear understanding of great compassion.<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-70"><!-- KB --> Prajñāsamudra, commenting on this verse, first cites a passage from
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra­sūtra </title>to the effect that the nature of phenomena
                                is like illusions that are nonexistent, and then with reference to what he has said regarding the
                                equivalent passage in prose (see note 11), comments: “When one has cultivated in this way [i.e.,
                                with an understanding of the illusory nature of phenomena], one gives rise to compassion which
                                does not apprehend anything; this is the best type of compassion.” Degé F.173b.2-3:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> de ltar bsgoms na dmigs pa med pa’i snying rje skye ste / snying rje’i
                                    mchog yin no</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-21"/>
                    <lg tid="24">
                        <l>“Since all phenomena are naturally luminous,</l>
                        <l>One should cultivate the clear understanding of non-apprehension.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-22"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>“Since all entities are impermanent,</l>
                        <l>One should cultivate the clear understanding of non-attachment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-23"/>
                    <lg tid="26">
                        <l>“Since the mind is the cause for the arising of wisdom,</l>
                        <l>Do not look for the Buddha elsewhere.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">After the Blessed One had spoken, <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> the whole assembly, including the
                        bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha and others, were overjoyed and full of praise for the Buddha’s words. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-25"/>
                    <p tid="28">This concludes the Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra on Wisdom at the Hour of Death. </p>
                </div>
                <!--<div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="35">Colophon</head>
                    
                </div>-->
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="36">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="37">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="38">Works in Tibetan</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-26">’<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phags pa ’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba theg pa chen
                            po’i mdo.</title> Toh 122, Degé Kangyur, vol. 54 (mdo sde, tha), folios 153a–153b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-27">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo.</title> bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
                        bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009,
                        vol. 54, pp. 23–24.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-28">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo.</title> Also in
                        Khomthar Jamlö (2014, see below), vol. 6, pp. 23-24. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-30">Prajñāsamudra. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye shes kyi mdo’i rnam par
                        bshad pa. </title>Toh 4003, Degé Tengyur, vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios 171a–174a. Also in Khomthar
                        Jamlö (2014, see below), vol. 6, pp. 25-32. English translation in Lhasey Lotsawa Translations (2015, see
                        below).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-29">Śāntideva. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba chen po’i
                            mdo’i ’grel pa. </title>Toh 4004, Degé Tengyur, vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios 174a–178a. Also in
                        Khomthar Jamlö (2014, see below), vol. 6, pp. 33-42. English translation in Lhasey Lotsawa Translations
                        (2015, see below).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-32">Choné Drakpa Shedrub (co ne grags pa bshad sgrub). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ’da’ ka ye shes dang ’du shes bcu gcig bstan pa’i mdo gnyis kyi ’grel pa.</title> rJe btsun
                        grags pa bshad sgrub kyi gsung ’bum (computer input, Taipei: The Corporate Body of the Buddha Educational
                        Foundation, 2010) Vol. 8, pp. 452–456. Also in Khomthar Jamlö (2014, see below), vol. 6, pp. 118-125.</bibl>                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-31">Kalsang Gyatso (bskal bzang rgya mtsho), Dalai Lama XII. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye shes zhes bya ba’i theg pa chen po’i mdo’i ’grel kun mkhyen ye shes snang
                            ba’i nyi ma.</title> In his <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Collected Works </title>[bskal bzang rgya mtsho
                        gsung ’bum]. Gangtok: Dodrup Sangye (1975-1983). Vol. 1, pp. 341–406. Also in Khomthar Jamlö (2014, see
                        below), vol. 6, pp. 51-105.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-34">Kawa Peltsek (ska ba dpal brtsegs). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod
                        thang ldan dkar gyi chos kyi ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag. </title>Toh. 4364, Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna
                        tshogs, jo), folios 294b-310a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-33">Khomthar Jamlö (khoṁ thar ’jam los) (ed.) for si khron pod yig dpe rnying
                        bsdu sgrig khang. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo bcu’i rtsa ’grel phyogs bsgrigs</title> [<title xml:lang="en">The Ten Sūtras of the King, collected texts and commentaries</title>]. Sichuan: si khron
                        mi rigs dpe skrun khang [Sichuan Minorities Publishing House], 2014. 10 volumes.</bibl>             
                    
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-36">Nyangrel Nyima Özer (nyang ral nyi ma ’od zer). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">“Zanglingma”</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">slob dpon pad+ma ’byung gnas kyi skyes rabs chos
                            ’byung nor bu’i phreng ba / rnam thar zangs gling ma.</title> In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen
                            gter mdzod chen mo</title>. New Delhi: Shechen Publications (2007-8), vol. 1, pp. 1-190. English
                        translation in Tsogyal (1993, see below).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-37">Orgyen Lingpa (o rgyan gling pa). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Padma
                            Kathang</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">o rgyan gu ru pad+ma ’byung gnas kyi skyes rabs rnam par
                            thar pa rgyas pa bkod pa pad+ma bka’i thang yig.</title> sku ’bum byams pa ling par khang (2001).
                        Translations: in French, Toussaint (1933); in English, Douglas and Bays (1978, see entries below).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-35">Shākya Chogden (shAkya mchog ldan). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo mchog pa’i
                        dri lan sogs</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Shākya mchog ldan gyi gsung ’bum</title>, vol. 17
                        (tsa). Kathmandu: Sachen International, 2006, pp. 619-636.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="39">Works in Western languages</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-38">Douglas, K. and Bays, G. (trs.). <title xml:lang="en">The Life and
                            Liberation of Padmasambhava: Padma Bka’i Thang</title> (see above under Orgyen Lingpa). Emeryville,
                        CA: Dharma Publishing, 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-39">Duff, Tony (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Noble One Called “Point of
                            Passage Wisdom,” A Great Vehicle Sutra</title>. Kathmandu: PKTC, 2011. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-40">Jackson, Roger. “Two <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Bka’ ’gyur</foreign> Works
                        in Mahāmudrā Canons: The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya-ātajñāna-nāma-mahā­yāna­sūtra</title> and the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāvila-tantra-rāja</title>.” In <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the
                            International Association of Tibetan Studies</title> no. 5, <ref target="http://www.jiats.org">www.jiats.org</ref>, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-41">Jackson, Roger. “The Study of Mahāmudrā in the West: A Brief Historical
                        Overview.” In Jackson, R. and Kapstein, M. (eds.).<title xml:lang="en"> Mahāmudrā and the Bka’-brgyud
                            Tradition: Proceedings of the Eleventh Seminar of the International Association for Tibetan Studies,
                            Königswinter 2006</title>. Andiast: IITBS, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-42">Lhasey Lotsawa Translations (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Wisdom of
                            the Time of Death Sūtra: and Commentaries by Prajñāsamudra and Śāntideva</title>. Kathmandu: Lhasey
                        Lotsawa Translations and Publications, 2015. <ref target="https://lhaseylotsawa.org/assets/texts/The-Noble-Wisdom-of-the-Time-of-Death-Sūtra-and-Commentaries.pdf">https://lhaseylotsawa.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-43">Lopez, Donald S. <title xml:lang="en">The Heart Sūtra Explained: Indian and
                            Tibetan Commentaries</title>. Albany: State University of New York, 1988. Reprinted, Delhi: Sri
                        Satguru Publications, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-44">Rhaldri, Sherab. “A Brief Introduction to the ’Da’-Ka Ye-Shes (Atijñāna)
                        Sūtra.” In <title xml:lang="en">Universal Message of Buddhist Tradition (With Special Reference to Pāli
                            Literature</title>). Radhavallabh Tripathi (ed.). New Delhi: Rāshṭriya Saṃskṛta Saṃsthāna, 2010,
                        pp. 339-346. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-45">Toussaint, Gustave-Charles (tr.). <title xml:lang="fr">Le Dict de Padma:
                            Padma Thang Yig, Ms. de Lithang</title> (see above under Orgyen Lingpa). Paris: Librairie Ernest
                        Leroux, 1933. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-054-003-46">Tsogyal, Yeshe (Kunsang, Erik P. and Schmidt, Marcia B., trs.). <title xml:lang="en">The Lotus-Born: The Life Story of Padmasambhava</title>. Boston: Shambhala,
                        1993.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-47">
                            <term>Five Royal Sūtras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོ་མདོ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">(1) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadra­caryā­praṇidhāna</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang spyod smon lam</title>, in chapter 44 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avataṃsaka</title>); for aspiration (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon lam</foreign>), and
                                described as vast (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya chen</foreign>). (2) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajra­vidāraṇā­dhāraṇī</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje rnam ’joms</title>, Toh
                                750); for ablution (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khrus</foreign>). (3) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā­pāramitā­hṛdaya</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab snying po</title>, Toh 21
                                and 531); for the view (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lta ba</foreign>), and described as profound
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zab mo</foreign>). (4) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atyaya­jñāna</title> (’<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">da’ ka ye shes</title>, Toh 122); for
                                cultivation (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgom pa</foreign>) and described as of definitive meaning
                                    (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nges don</title>). (5) <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ba ltung
                                    bshags</title> (part of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya­viniścayopāli­paripṛcchā,</title> Toh
                                68); for purification of karmic obscurations (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las sgrib dag
                                    pa</foreign>). </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-48">
                            <term>Ten Royal Sūtras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po mdo bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོ་མདོ་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">In addition to the Five Royal Sūtras: (6) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aparimitāyur­jñāna</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe dang ye shes dpag tu med pa’i
                                    mdo</title>, Toh 674); for extending longevity (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe
                                    bsring</foreign>). (7) <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gos sngon can gyi gzungs</title>, perhaps
                                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavān­nīlāmbara­dhara­vajrapāṇi­tantra</title> (Toh 498) but
                                possibly another of the several texts on this form of Vajrapāṇi; for protection (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srung ba</foreign>). (8) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Uṣṇīṣa­sitāta­patrā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug tor gdugs dkar</title>, Toh
                                590-592); for averting (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zlog pa</foreign>). (9) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasu­dhāra</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor rgyun ma</title>, Toh
                                663-664); for increasing resources (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">longs spyod spel ba</foreign>).
                                (10) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ekākṣarīmātā­prajñā­pāramitā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sher
                                    phyin yi ge gcig ma</title>, Toh 23); for the essence (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snying
                                    po</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-49">
                            <term>Five Sets of One Hundred Thousand</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bum sde lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབུམ་སྡེ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bum chen sde lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབུམ་ཆེན་སྡེ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">(1) The long <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā­pāramitā </title>(Toh 8), which
                                contains 100,000 ślokas; (2) the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­pari­nirvāṇa</title> (Toh 119-120),
                                which contains 100,000 testaments given by the Buddha at the time of his <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pari­nirvāṇa</foreign>; (3) the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­kūṭa</title>
                                (Toh 45-93), which contains 100,000 distinct names of the Buddha; (4) the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avataṃsaka</title> (Toh 44), which contains 100,000 aspirations; and (5) the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra</title> (Toh 107-108), which contains 100,000 discourses that
                                are ways of subjugating the rākṣasas. These five sets of 100,000 features are also said to
                                correspond to the Buddha’s body, speech, mind, qualities, and activities, respectively.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-50">
                            <term>definitive meaning</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nges don </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངེས་དོན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nitārtha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-51">
                            <term>clear understanding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃjñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term is used in an ordinary sense in Sanskrit to mean “notion,” “sign,”
                                “conception,” “<term type="ignore">clear understanding</term>.” It is also used more specifically in Buddhist scholastic
                                contexts in the phrase “the aggregate of perceptions” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃjñāskandha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-52">
                            <term>cultivate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhāvanā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-53">
                            <term>luminous</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od gsal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་གསལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prabhāsvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-54">
                            <term>wisdom of the hour of death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’da’ ka ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདའ་ཀ་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atyayajñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-55">
                            <term>subsumed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dus pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-56">
                            <term>non-apprehension</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dmigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དམིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-57">
                            <term>Ākāśagarbha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśagarbha </term>
                            <term type="definition">An important bodhisattva, his name means “essence of space.” He is one of the
                                “eight great close sons” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭa­mahopa­putra</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye ba’i sras chen brgyad</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-054-003-58">
                            <term>Akaniṣṭha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’og min </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོག་མིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akaniṣṭha </term>
                            <term type="definition">The eighth and highest level of the Realm of Form (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs khams</foreign>), and thus part of the
                                world of the Brahmā gods (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmaloka</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsang ris</foreign>); it is only accessible as the result of specific
                                states of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</foreign>. According to some texts this is where
                                non-returners (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāgāmin</foreign>) dwell in their last lives. In other
                                texts it is the realm of the enjoyment body (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃbhoga­kāya</foreign>,
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">longs spyod rdzogs pa’i sku</foreign>) and is a buddhafield
                                associated with the Buddha Vairocana; it is accessible only to bodhisattvas on the tenth
                                level.</term>
                            <term type="definition">(See also <ptr target="#UT22084-054-003-67"/>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>