<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa'i ye shes kyi phyag
                    rgya'i ting nge 'dzin gyi mdo/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་རྒྱའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་གྱི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgatajñānamudrāsamādhisūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom
                    Seal</title>

                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa de bzhin gshegs pa’i ye shes kyi
                    phyag rgya’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryatathāgatajñānamudrāsamādhināmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra: The Absorption
                    of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom Seal</title>

                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-9" role="translatorMain">Translated by the
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>

            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.00 <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-055-005"/>
                <date>2019-01-18</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh131" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 131</ref>
                    <biblScope>Toh 131, Degé Kangyur, vol. 55 (da), folios 230b–253b</biblScope>
                    <location count-pages="47">
                        <start volume="55" page="462"/>
                        <end volume="55" page="508"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11712" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 18/01/2019 at 16:55:27 by andre</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-1"/>
                <p tid="2">In <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom
                        Seal</title>, a vast number of bodhisattvas request Buddha Śākyamuni to
                    teach them about his state of meditative absorption. In his responses to various
                    interlocutors, including the bodhisattvas Mañjuśrī and Maitreya, the Buddha
                    expounds on this profound state, exhorting them to accomplish it themselves. The
                    sūtra also describes the qualities of bodhisattvas and their stages of
                    development.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-2"/>
                <p tid="4">This sūtra was translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under
                    the supervision of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. Joseph McClellan produced the
                    translation and wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the draft
                    translation with the Tibetan, and edited the text. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtra of <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone
                            One’s Wisdom Seal</title> is a significant scripture in the canon of the
                        Great Vehicle due to its rich description of the highest levels of Buddhist
                        absorption, as well as for its unique discussion of the stages of a
                        bodhisattva’s journey and the qualities that pertain to them.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-4"/>
                    <p tid="8">This scripture appears to have enjoyed some measure of sustained
                        popularity in Asia. The earliest Chinese translation (out of three: T 632, T
                        633, and T 634) was completed by the translator Chih-ch’ien sometime between
                        223 and 253 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, while the Tibetan translation was
                        commissioned almost six centuries later during the dynastic translation
                        efforts of the early ninth century. In between these two notable efforts to
                        propagate the sūtra outside of India, we also know of at least one citation
                        of this text in the works of an Indian scholar: that of Bhāviveka (sixth
                        century) in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tarkajvālā</title>.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-5"> See Eckel 1994:
                            166.</note> As such, we have evidence of a continued relevance of this
                        sūtra during the formative centuries of the Great Vehicle tradition in
                        India. To our knowledge, this scripture has until now remained unexplored by
                        modern scholars, and no translation of the text has been made since the
                        Tibetan translation was produced in the early ninth century. This English
                        rendering was based on the Tibetan Degé block print with reference to the
                        Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the
                        Stok Palace manuscript. Since no extant Sanskrit manuscript remains, we have
                        based our translation exclusively on these Tibetan source texts.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-6"/>
                    <p tid="9">The sūtra’s title contains the Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhi</foreign> (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ting nge ’dzin</foreign>), which is a
                        feature shared by several sūtra titles in the Kangyur. The redactors of the
                        Degé Kangyur grouped them together, suggesting that they construed these
                        sūtras to form an unofficial subgenre of sūtra literature.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-7"> In the Degé Kangyur, this group
                            consists of eleven sūtras (Toh 127–37). This grouping is not unique to
                            the Degé, as it is also found in the Choné, Lhasa, and Narthang
                            Kangyurs, which means it is probably typical of all <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Tshalpa </foreign>recensions. The
                            Thempangma recension Kangyurs locate it differently, and seemingly
                            without any similar classificatory principle.</note> However, the term’s
                        significance clearly varies from sūtra to sūtra within this group of texts.
                        For example, in the famous <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samādhirājasūtra</title>
                        (Toh 127), <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samādhi</foreign> does not
                        appear to refer to an altered state of mind, or to meditative absorption.
                        Instead, the term is used to encapsulate a list of affects, qualities, or
                        concepts that the sūtra presents, with no explicit mention of states of deep
                        meditative concentration.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-8"> See Peter Alan Roberts, trans. <title xml:lang="en">The King of Samādhis Sūtra</title> . 84000 :
                            Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2018.
                            http://read.84000.co/translation/toh127.html. </note> Nevertheless, in
                        most other sūtras within this group of texts,<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-9"> Such as, for example, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Praśāntaviniścayaprātihāryasamādhi</title> (Toh
                            129), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyopamasamādhi</title> (Toh 130), and
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvapuṇyasamuccayasamādhi</title> (Toh
                            134).</note> the term clearly refers to a specific kind of meditative
                        state to be accessed and accomplished.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-10"> For further reading, see Skilton
                            2002.</note> It is to this latter group that the current sūtra belongs,
                        as it explicitly describes a meditative absorption, which the rest of the
                        title qualifies as “the thus-gone one’s wisdom seal.” Here,
                            <distinct>thus-gone one</distinct> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tathāgatha)</foreign> is a common epithet of a fully
                        awakened being. We have translated this term from the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de bzhin gshegs pa</foreign>, “one who has
                        thus gone,” whereas the Chinese equivalent, <foreign xml:lang="Zh-Ltn" type="term">ru lai</foreign>, reads closer to “thus-come one.” The final
                        term, <distinct>wisdom seal</distinct> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jñānamudrā</foreign>), qualifies the absorption in which the
                        thus-gone one dwells. <distinct>Seal</distinct> (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mudrā</foreign>) has a rich and varied
                        usage in Buddhist literature. Generally, it refers to a stamp or brand, like
                        a royal seal that is used to mark property. Since the thus-gone one’s
                        absorption is infinite and unimpeded, all of reality falls into its domain.
                        Thus, all of reality is subsumed in, or sealed by, the wisdom actualized in
                        this absorption.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-11"/>
                    <p tid="10">Like many Great Vehicle sūtras, <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption
                            of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom Seal</title> situates ancient India and
                        Buddha Śākyamuni in a much larger, cosmic context. The opening scene takes
                        place in the famous Veṇuvana (Bamboo Grove) monastic compound near Rājagṛha,
                        the capital of the former kingdom of Magadha (present-day Bihar). Located
                        nearby is the famed Vulture Peak Mountain, where Buddha Śākyamuni is said to
                        have delivered many Great Vehicle discourses. Here the Buddha is dwelling
                        with a vast retinue of monks and bodhisattvas when he enters into an exalted
                        state of absorption called <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom
                            seal</distinct>, describable only in ways that suggest its sheer
                        ineffability: it is “formless, indefinable, ungraspable, unimpeded, and not
                        apparent.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-12"/>
                    <p tid="11">The power of this state of absorption affects the entire
                        trichiliocosm, inspiring buddhas and bodhisattvas dwelling in faraway realms
                        to intensify their spiritual activity. Cosmic buddhas exhort their
                        innumerable bodhisattva disciples to seize the opportunity to go to Veṇuvana
                        and learn about this absorption, which will be the culmination of their
                        training. Accordingly, the bodhisattvas magically travel there, eager to
                        receive teachings about this exalted state. Countless gods and nonhuman
                        beings, hearers, and monks join them in their quest. When they arrive,
                        however, the Buddha is nowhere to be seen, as their perceptions are not
                        attuned to the level of absorption in which he abides. In dismay, the
                        assembly, led by a group of close disciples including Mahāmaudgalyāyana and
                        Subhūti, turns to the great bodhisattva Mañjuśrī for advice on how to
                        communicate with the Buddha. He simply tells them to look inward: they will
                        find the Buddha within their own absorptions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-13"/>
                    <p tid="12">Thus, a line of communication is established with the Buddha, who
                        now begins to teach them about this absorption, which is the hallmark of all
                        thus-gone ones. The teaching follows an extensive apophatic methodology, in
                        which the Buddha negates any proposition that may be made about this most
                        profound state of absorption: “This absorption is formless, indefinable,
                        ungraspable, unimpeded, and not apparent. It is beyond knowledge and not an
                        object of knowledge.” Upon concluding his teaching about
                            the<distinct> </distinct>absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s
                            wisdom seal</distinct>, all those in attendance purify negative karma
                        accumulated over innumerable eons and no longer regress from unsurpassed and
                        perfect awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-14"/>
                    <p tid="13">The discourse then shifts, and the Buddha addresses Maitreya,
                        explaining seven ways in which bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening. He
                        also lists two sets of five qualities that characterize a nonregressing
                        bodhisattva, as well as five that mark an incorrigible, flawed individual on
                        the bodhisattva path. To illustrate the exemplary bodhisattva, the Buddha
                        recounts a past-life memory of the deeds of a great king named Puṇyodgata,
                        who was a devotee of the buddha Śaśiketu.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-15"/>
                    <p tid="14">Following this discourse, countless female devotees, led by the
                        queens of King Bimbisāra, promise their service to the Dharma in all
                        subsequent lives. This delights the Buddha, who beams a smile at them. The
                        women, captivated, eloquently enjoin the Buddha to give them a teaching
                        about the causes, qualities, and implications of his smile. In response, the
                        Buddha recounts more past-life memories, this time about the noble deeds of
                        an ancient ruler named Puṇyaraśmi, who was an exemplary guardian of the
                        Dharma. The Buddha also describes the degenerate age, in which the influence
                        of the Dharma will wane. During this time, he explains, it will be
                        especially important for Buddhists to train in the sūtra of <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom Seal</title>,
                        and to master the absorption it describes. The Buddha then highlights
                        differences between bodhisattvas based on whether they have aroused the mind
                        of awakening and the roots of virtue in the presence of hundreds, thousands,
                        or millions of buddhas. In short, the latter have the greatest resolve to
                        traverse the path and are least susceptible to any kind of regression.
                        However, they will still suffer. The sūtra explains that whatever negative
                        karma remains for these bodhisattvas will be purified through instances of
                        ordinary human misfortune: they will be criticized, they will suffer bouts
                        of depression, they will be born into dysfunctional families, they will face
                        adverse economic conditions, and so forth. Bodhisattvas of the highest order
                        will bear these pains and persevere on the path; others will falter.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-16"/>
                    <p tid="15">Toward the end of the sūtra, the Buddha addresses Mañjuśrī,
                        Maitreya, and an assembly of distinguished disciples who ask him to explain
                        the meaning of the term <distinct>Dharma</distinct> itself. Thus begins a
                        long synonymic chain of significant Buddhist terms: inexhaustible, unborn,
                        uninterrupted, uncollected, ungraspable, nonabiding, and groundless, until
                        the final term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirvāṇa</foreign>.
                        This list echoes the terms used earlier in the sūtra to describe
                            the<distinct> </distinct>absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s
                            wisdom seal</distinct>. Given this definition of the Dharma, the
                        disciples wonder how they should act as its protectors. The Buddha explains
                        that if they indeed realize the meaning of what he has taught them,
                        “ultimately we find nothing at all—no Dharma and no conflict with the
                        Dharma.” Then, with philosophically rich verses he instructs them further on
                        the ultimate truth, beyond concepts and characteristics. The sūtra concludes
                        with another exhortation to the gathered assembly to accomplish
                            the<distinct> </distinct>absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s
                            wisdom seal</distinct>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="16"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="17">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra entitled:</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="18">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom
                    Seal</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-19"/>
                    <p tid="22">[B.1] <ref cRef="F.230.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and
                        bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-21"/>
                    <p tid="24">Thus did I hear at one time: The Blessed One was dwelling in
                        Veṇuvana, at Kalandakanivāpa, near Rājagṛha. He was staying there together
                        with a great saṅgha of twelve hundred fifty monks, and with three hundred
                        million bodhisattvas, all of whom had attained retention, unobstructed
                        eloquence, and mastery over absorption. They abided in the absorption of
                        emptiness, their domain was free of marks, their aspiration was uncontrived,
                        they abided in the absence of wishes, and their conduct was natural. They
                        had attained the retention that accomplishes limitless methods. They had
                        attained acceptance regarding sameness, they had attained sameness, and they
                        had attained unobstructed retention. They knew the higher or lower
                        capacities of all beings <ref cRef="F.231.a"/> and had precise knowledge of
                        beings’ thoughts and actions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-22"/>
                    <p tid="25">At that time, the Blessed One settled into the absorption that is
                        the blessing of the thus-gone one, that enters the domain of all the
                        buddhas. This absorption is formless, indefinable, ungraspable, unimpeded,
                        and not apparent. It is beyond knowledge and not an object of knowledge. It
                        is free from mentation, mind, and consciousness. It is rootless,
                        unsupported, and beyond observation. It is an incomparable, unequaled, and
                        matchless state. It has no notion of “mine,” is free from grasping, is free
                        from anything to avoid, and is uncreated. It never went and never came. It
                        does not go and does not stay. It is without interruption, baseless, and
                        without marks. It is free of all marks. It is beyond accepting and
                        rejecting. It is uncompounded and beyond any accumulation. It is beyond
                        assembling and beyond separating. It is without mind and free from mind. It
                        is unoriginated, beginningless, unestablished, nonarising, and totally
                        nonoccurring. It is utterly beyond movement, perfectly without movement,
                        totally empty, beyond association, and without superimpositions regarding
                        any phenomenon. It is a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇī</foreign> gateway to enter the domain of all buddhas. It is
                        known as <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom seal</distinct>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-23"/>
                    <p tid="26">As soon as he settled into that absorption, neither the Blessed
                        One’s body nor the characteristics of his body appeared; neither his mind
                        nor the characteristics of his mind appeared; neither his robes nor the
                        characteristics of his robes appeared; neither his cushion nor the
                        characteristics of his cushion appeared; neither his sleeping nor the
                        characteristics of his sleeping appeared; neither his walking nor the
                        characteristics of his walking appeared; neither his rising nor the
                        characteristics of his rising appeared; neither his abiding nor the
                        characteristics of his abiding appeared; neither his shadow nor the
                        characteristics of his shadow appeared; neither his sitting nor the
                        characteristics of his sitting appeared; and neither his sounds nor the
                        characteristics of his sounds appeared.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">At that point, through the power of this absorption, <ref cRef="F.231.b"/> and through the blessings of the Buddha, a bright light
                        filled the entire trichiliocosm. With this illumination, the moon was
                        outshone everywhere in the trichiliocosm, as were the sun, stars, fire,
                        jewels, and lightning. Gandharvas, kiṃnaras, gods of the realms of desire
                        and form, constellations, and divine palaces were outshone. Śakra, Brahmā,
                        and the world’s protectors were, too.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-25"/>
                    <p tid="28">Through the Buddha’s blessings and the power of his absorption, the
                        gods could no longer smell their divine fragrances. Throughout the
                        trichiliocosm, scents were rendered even sweeter by an aroma that completely
                        transcended the fragrances of the gods. Every part of the Lokāntarika Hell
                        was brought into light, as were the major and minor mountain ranges that
                        surround the world. Mount Meru and other great peaks like it were
                        illuminated, including the Black Peaks. Subsequently, however, they did not
                        appear to the eye faculties of sentient beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-26"/>
                    <p tid="29">The entire trichiliocosm was encompassed in a net of jewels. The
                        entire Sahā buddha realm was decorated with silk hangings, suffused with
                        frankincense, and strewn with a variety of flowers. Through the power of the
                        Buddha, Kalandakanivāpa in Veṇuvana, along with Vulture Peak Mountain,
                        became as level as the palm of the hand and they were saturated with the
                        delicious and captivating scent of a giant hundred-thousand-petaled lotus
                        flower composed of various jewels the size of chariot-wheels. From the sky,
                        a lattice-like jeweled canopy appeared, which covered and adorned
                        everything. All of Magadha became soft to the touch, like kācilindika
                        cloth.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-27"/>
                    <p tid="30">Then in the east, in as many buddha realms as there are grains of
                        sand in the Ganges, the individual blessed buddhas exhorted a limitless,
                        innumerable, and immeasurable number of hundreds of thousands of bodhisattva
                        great beings who were just one life away from unexcelled and perfect
                        awakening, <ref cRef="F.232.a"/> “Sons of noble family, you should go into
                        the Sahā world. There, the blessed one, the thus-gone one, the worthy one,
                        the perfect buddha Śākyamuni presently resides. He lives there and teaches
                        the Dharma. Now he has settled into the absorption that is a dhāraṇī gateway
                        to enter the domain of all buddhas known as the <distinct>thus-gone one’s
                            wisdom seal</distinct>. Sons of noble family, merely hearing about this
                        absorption, bodhisattvas are struck with reverence. This is better than
                        someone who, lacking skillful means, engages in the six perfections for a
                        hundred thousand eons. Therefore, go and hear about this absorption.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-28"/>
                    <p tid="31">The bodhisattva great beings listened accordingly to the respective
                        thus-gone ones and paid these blessed ones homage. Then, in an instant, they
                        all disappeared from those buddha realms and, by giving rise to their
                        magical powers of superknowledge, they came to the Sahā world, to the four
                        central continents, to the continent of Jambudvīpa, to the town of Rājagṛha,
                        to Veṇuvana, and to Kalandakanivāpa, where the blessed one, the thus-gone
                        one, the worthy one, the perfect buddha Śākyamuni was abiding. Upon
                        arriving, they bowed their heads to the feet of the blessed one, the
                        thus-gone one, the worthy one, the perfect buddha Śākyamuni. They then
                        circled the Blessed One three times and stood to one side. The Blessed One
                        welcomed them and they arranged themselves cross-legged upon a giant lotus
                        composed of various jewels.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-29"/>
                    <p tid="32">The same thing happened in the south, west, north, below, above,
                            <ref cRef="F.232.b"/>—throughout the cardinal and intermediate
                        directions, and everywhere in between. In all the ten directions, in as many
                        buddha realms as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, individual blessed
                        buddhas exhorted a limitless, innumerable, and immeasurable number of
                        hundreds of thousands of bodhisattva great beings who were just one life
                        away from unexcelled and perfect awakening, “Sons of noble family, you
                        should go into the Sahā world. There, the blessed one, the thus-gone one,
                        the worthy one, the perfect buddha Śākyamuni presently resides. He lives
                        there and teaches the Dharma. Now he has settled into the absorption that is
                        a dhāraṇī gateway to enter the domain of all buddhas, known as the<distinct>
                            thus-gone one’s wisdom seal</distinct>. Sons of noble family, merely
                        hearing the name of this absorption, bodhisattvas are struck with reverence.
                        This is better than someone who, lacking skillful means, engages in the six
                        perfections for a hundred thousand eons. Therefore, go and hear about this
                        absorption.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-30"/>
                    <p tid="33">The bodhisattva great beings listened accordingly to the respective
                        thus-gone ones and paid these blessed ones homage. Then, in an instant, they
                        all disappeared from those buddha realms and, by giving rise to their
                        magical powers of superknowledge, they came to the Sahā world, to the four
                        central continents, to the continent of Jambudvīpa, to the town of Rājagṛha,
                        to Veṇuvana, and to Kalandakanivāpa, where the blessed one, the thus-gone
                        one, the worthy one, the perfect buddha Śākyamuni was. Upon arriving, they
                        bowed their heads to the feet of the blessed one, the thus-gone one, the
                        worthy one, the perfect buddha Śākyamuni. They then circled the Blessed One
                        three times and stood to one side. The Blessed One welcomed them and they
                        arranged themselves cross-legged upon a great jewel lotus. <ref cRef="F.233.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-31"/>
                    <p tid="34">Throughout this great trichiliocosm, all the monks—whether engaged
                        with the vehicle of the hearers, the vehicle of the solitary buddhas, or the
                        bodhisattva vehicle—each in their own individual realms, stirred and,
                        through the blessings and power of the Buddha, they all came to Vulture Peak
                        Mountain, where the Blessed One resided. Upon arriving, they could not see
                        the Blessed One anywhere. Not seeing him, they joined their palms and paid
                        homage to him.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-32"/>
                    <p tid="35">Through the radiance of the absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone
                            one’s wisdom seal</distinct>, instantly, in that very moment, eight
                        hundred million bodhisattvas gathered in Veṇuvana, at Kalandakanivāpa, where
                        they sat down in the Blessed One’s retinue. Three hundred thousand hearers
                        also gathered together and took seats. Within this great trichiliocosm, many
                        other beings arrived in Veṇuvana, at Kalandakanivāpa, where the Blessed One
                        resided. They included Śakra, Brahmā, the guardians of the world, Maheśvara,
                        the gods of the pure realms, all gods including their lords, all nāgas and
                        their lords, all yakṣas and their lords, all gandharvas and their lords, all
                        asuras and their lords, all garuḍas and their lords, all kiṃnaras and their
                        lords, all mahoragas and their lords, as well as all suparṇis and their
                        lords. Each of these groups also brought with them many quadrillions of
                        servants. As they arrived in Veṇuvana, at Kalandakanivāpa, where the Blessed
                        One resided, no one could see the Blessed One anywhere. Not seeing him, they
                        joined their palms and paid homage to him. <ref cRef="F.233.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-33"/>
                    <p tid="36">At that time assembled the powerful and eminent bodhisattva great
                        beings, hearers, gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kiṃnaras,
                        mahoragas, humans, nonhumans, monks, nuns, and male and female lay
                        practitioners. No place was left unfilled, from the peak of existence in
                        this great trichiliocosm on down. Not even the space for the tip of a hair
                        was left unfilled.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-34"/>
                    <p tid="37">Then the elder Śāradvatīputra, Mahāmaudgalyāyana, the elder
                        Kauṣṭhila, Mahākātyāyana, Mahākāśyapa, the venerable Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra,
                        and the elder Subhūti—all those great hearers—turned to the youthful
                        Mañjuśrī and asked, “Mañjuśrī, where is the Thus-Gone One right now? What
                        does his body look like? How does he abide?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-35"/>
                    <p tid="38">The youthful Mañjuśrī replied to the great hearers, “Venerable ones,
                        you are great hearers, and you possess insight and miraculous abilities. You
                        are powerful and mighty, you have mastered the absorptions of the erudite,
                        and you have long observed pure conduct. Venerable ones, you should enter
                        your own absorptions and search for the Thus-Gone One’s body and abode. You
                        should strive to discover the location of the Thus-Gone One’s body, what his
                        body is like, and how he abides.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-36"/>
                    <p tid="39">Thereupon the hearers settled into their own absorptions and
                        investigated this entire trichiliocosm. They looked, but they still could
                        not see the Thus-Gone One’s body, <ref cRef="F.234.a"/> nor could they see
                        his abode. Then, when the great hearers did not see the Thus-Gone One’s body
                        nor his abode upon completely investigating the trichiliocosm, they arose
                        from their respective absorptions and addressed the youthful Mañjuśrī as
                        follows: “Mañjuśrī, we fail to see the Thus-Gone One’s body or his
                        abode.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-37"/>
                    <p tid="40">Mañjuśrī replied to the great hearers, “Then all you venerable great
                        hearers must silently join your palms and one-pointedly hold the Thus-Gone
                        One in your mind for a moment. Do this, and you will see his body and
                        witness his presence.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-38"/>
                    <p tid="41">Just then, the Blessed One, who was aware and cognizant of this,
                        emerged from his absorption. As soon as the Blessed One emerged from his
                        absorption, the entire trichiliocosm shook in six ways, with eighteen signs:
                        it quivered, trembled, and quaked; it wobbled, rocked, and swayed; it
                        vibrated, shuddered, and reeled; it rattled, shook, and convulsed; it
                        clattered, rattled, and clanged; and it boomed, thundered, and roared. The
                        world became exceedingly brilliant, open, and vivid.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-39"/>
                    <p tid="42">As an offering to the Blessed One, a rain of divine flowers fell to
                        the accompaniment of divine cymbals and song. At that point venerable
                        Śāradvatīputra arose from his seat, draped his shawl over one shoulder, and
                        knelt on his right knee. Joining his palms, he bowed toward the Blessed One
                        and asked, <ref cRef="F.234.b"/> “Blessed One, in what kind of absorption
                        did you abide so that even the eye of insight of the great hearers was
                        unable to see the Thus-Gone One’s body? Blessed One, how does the Thus-Gone
                        One abide?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-40"/>
                    <p tid="43">The Blessed One replied to venerable Śāradvatīputra,
                        “Śāradvatīputra, this absorption is not a stage of the hearers or solitary
                        buddhas. Śāradvatīputra, it is on the level of the thus-gone ones. This
                        magical display and miracle of the buddhas is inconceivable. Nevertheless,
                        Śāradvatīputra, listen well and keep this in mind. I will now teach you a
                        little bit about the body of the Thus-Gone One.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-41"/>
                    <p tid="44">“Very well, Blessed One!” Venerable Śāradvatīputra replied, and he
                        listened as the Blessed One had instructed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-42"/>
                    <p tid="45">Then the Blessed One explained to him, “Śāradvatīputra, the true
                        body of the Thus-Gone One transcends any view, like the sky. It is
                        incorporeal, uncreated, unborn, and unceasing. It is nonoccurring, truly
                        nonoccurring, and utterly nonoccurring. It is unobtained, unimputed,
                        nonengaging, unestablished, boundless, and limitless. It is peaceful,
                        placid, and absolutely serene. It is nonabiding, nonarising, ineffable,
                        beyond mind, and beyond origination. It is unmoving, utterly unmoving, and
                        free of movement. It is totally pure. It is nothing whatsoever and exists in
                        no way. It is beyond appropriation and acceptance. It is without motion,
                        without activity, and without support. It is unborn, unarisen, without
                        action, and without ripening. It is unseen, unheard, uncognized, detached,
                        not bound, and not released. It does not exist. It is not recalled, not
                        held, not experienced, and not seen. <ref cRef="F.235.a"/> It is beyond
                        cognition, is not an object of cognition, and is characterized by absence of
                        cognition.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-43"/>
                    <p tid="46">“It is without mind. It is unfathomable and unimaginable. It is not
                        mind. It is devoid of mind. It possesses the mind of sameness. It is
                        unequaled and cannot be comprehended by any act of mind. It has not gone
                        anywhere, does not go anywhere, is without going, and has eliminated any
                        going. It is uninterrupted, immeasurable, uninterruptible, boundless,
                        unobservable, and marvelous. It has no substance and is no substance. It is
                        insubstantial. It is not a distinction and has no distinctions. It is
                        nonarising, truly nonarising, unshakable, nondiscursive, nonconceptual,
                        beginningless, unestablished, and wholly unestablished. It is not
                        accomplished, without pervasion, and motionless. It is not clear, not
                        touchable, and not a thing to be desired. It has no light and does not
                        appear. It is not apprehended and has no appearance. It is without darkness,
                        is not darkness, and is free of darkness. It is not lucidity. It is without
                        abode and free of abode. It is not pacified, by no means pacified, without
                        peace, and free from peace. It is equal to peace. It is pure, totally pure,
                        and wholly pure.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-44"/>
                    <p tid="47">“It is nothing whatsoever, beyond appropriation, and without
                        perpetuation. It is without friendship, without strife, and free from
                        strife. It abides in a mode of nonabiding. It is without ties, free from
                        ties, limpid, and unsullied. It does not die or take rebirth. It will not
                        die or take rebirth. It is without Dharma and without non-Dharma. It is
                        without a field, and also without anything other than a field. It is
                        inexhaustible, not something that can be exhausted, and free from
                        exhaustion. It is without dust, instantaneous, and unshakable. It is beyond
                        letters, sounds, tones, explanations, trainings, and mind. It is without
                        logic and not illogical, and it is not separate from logic. It does not
                        possess anything and is without possession. It is also not destitute. It is
                        inexhaustible, <ref cRef="F.235.b"/> not inexhaustible, immortal, and not
                        immortal.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-45"/>
                    <p tid="48">“It is not something to be pacified. It is without marks, not
                        something without marks, not limited, not unlimited, and not something to be
                        measured. It has not gone and has not come. It is nondual and not nondual.
                        It is not perceived, not here, and not there. It is baseless, without abode,
                        nonemerging, indestructible, nontransferable, and nothing to be heard. It
                        does not conquer enemies. It accepts nothing and rejects nothing. It is
                        without characteristics, free of characteristics, not a characteristic
                        itself, and it has abandoned characteristics. It is without action and not
                        without action. It is without marks, not without marks, and adorned with
                        marks. It is gateless, unattached, and free from attachments. It inspires
                        faith. It is without connections and free from connections. It causes
                        delight and it causes bliss. It is freed from the six sense sources and
                        invisible.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-46"/>
                    <p tid="49">“It is reality—thoroughly distinguished by suchness. It is suchness,
                        which liberates beings by not liberating. It liberates by not liberating
                        sentient beings. It purifies sentient beings by way of not purifying. It
                        protects sentient beings by way of not protecting. It teaches the Dharma to
                        sentient beings by way of nonduality. It is unequaled, incomparable, without
                        likeness, and unrivaled. It is equal to that which is not present, equal to
                        the sky, and equal to that which does not remain. It is exceedingly even,
                        unborn, and the same as unborn. It does not apprehend and is the same as
                        nonapprehension. It is unpacified, free from peace, and its peace has waned.
                        It is peaceful, very peaceful, and thoroughly peaceful. It is gentle,
                        supple, utterly stainless, utterly controlled, not permanent, and not
                        interrupted. It has withdrawn from activities. It is irreversibly brave. It
                        has vanquished fear. It is beyond return. <ref cRef="F.236.a"/> It has
                        severed all grasping and cut through all ties.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-47"/>
                    <p tid="50">“It is clear, without distinctions, nondual, free from duality, and
                        taught to be without any duality. Its essence being unproduced, its nature
                        is luminosity that is utterly beyond occurring. Without any liberation, it
                        is liberated from activity. It is without meeting, without separating, not
                        long, not short, not round, not square, not spherical, and not substantial.
                        It is not perceived as the aggregates, elements, or sense sources. It cannot
                        be established as something conditioned, nor does it emerge from the
                        unconditioned. It is nonwaxing, nonwaning, nonaccumulating, and unborn. No
                        one can see it, hear it, or be conscious of it. It is neither real nor
                        unreal. It is unborn. It does not die or transmigrate. It does not coexist
                        with the world, nor does it not coexist with the world.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-48"/>
                    <p tid="51">“That body is unwavering, unmistaken, unexcited, motionless, and
                        undeviating. It is without cultivation and free from cultivation. It is
                        nonoccurring, not destroyed, not an essence, and not without essence. It is
                        without mind and indescribable. It is without connection and does not
                        connect, nor does it not connect. It has no attachment to desires, nor is it
                        without attachment to desires. It is nothing and it is not nothing. It is
                        without characteristics and is not without characteristics. It does not
                        transcend suffering and has not fully transcended suffering. It does not
                        abide, but it is not nonabiding, either. Śāradvatīputra, can sentient beings
                        who fixate on characteristics and who have fallen into dualistic perception
                        possibly understand the way in which the body of the Thus-Gone One
                        abides?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-49"/>
                    <p tid="52">“No, Blessed One, they cannot at all,” replied Śāradvatīputra. “That
                        is impossible. <ref cRef="F.236.b"/> And why? Because, Blessed One, the
                        Thus-Gone One’s body is free of any and all marks.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-50"/>
                    <p tid="53">“Śāradvatīputra, yes, that is correct. That is how it is,” the
                        Blessed One agreed. “The Thus-Gone One’s body is free from any and all
                        marks.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-51"/>
                    <p tid="54">Then the Blessed One proceeded to teach extensively about the
                        absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom seal</distinct>. In order
                        to be comprehensive and thorough, he spoke these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-52"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“This body is not a body, and it is completely free from a body.</l>
                        <l>Nobody has created it, nobody destroys it, and no one obtains it.</l>
                        <l>It is absolutely bereft of properties, yet it is not bereft.</l>
                        <l>Such are the terms applied to the body of the blissful ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-53"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“It is without meeting, parting, abode, or substance.</l>
                        <l>It is neither grasped, nor freed, nor even, nor is it long.</l>
                        <l>It has no beginning, no impediment, nor does it abide anywhere at
                            all.</l>
                        <l>This is how the body of the blissful ones is explained.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-54"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“It is not grasped, is not made, has no place, and is nothing at all.</l>
                        <l>It has no form and no mind, and it is neither two nor one.</l>
                        <l>It is unreal, not unreal, and not nonoccurring.</l>
                        <l>The body of the victorious ones is like this in its true state.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-55"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“It is without a core, not weak, and not interrupted.</l>
                        <l>It is not disrupted, nonoccurring, unoriginated, and without
                            destruction.</l>
                        <l>It is without obtainment, purified of dust, and not destroyed.</l>
                        <l>The body of the stainless ones should be understood like this.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-56"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“It is not seen, heard, held, or touched.</l>
                        <l>It is not perceived and not analyzed; rather, it is like a
                            hallucination.</l>
                        <l>When beings see it, they are delighted to apprehend it.</l>
                        <l>This is how the body of the buddhas is taught to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-57"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“It is not an aggregate, not an element, not false, and not true.</l>
                        <l>It is not pure, utterly not pure, and not encountered by the senses.</l>
                        <l>It is without concepts, utterly nonconceptual, and like the moon in
                            water.</l>
                        <l>This is how we should hold the body of the blissful ones to be.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-58"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“Since this body comes from causes and conditions, it has no intrinsic
                            nature.</l>
                        <l>It is unborn, unceasing, not going, and unmoving.</l>
                        <l>Under analysis, the three worlds appear like an illusion. <ref cRef="F.237.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>The body of the victorious ones must be seen nonconceptually like
                            this.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-59"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“It is without peace, not peaceful, free from peace, and unconnected.</l>
                        <l>It is without desire, without reason, and like an empty hand.</l>
                        <l>Moreover, it is naturally spacious.</l>
                        <l>Seeing it as such, one honors the Buddha day and night.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-60"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“You might fill billions of realms with jewels,</l>
                        <l>All the way up to the peak of existence,</l>
                        <l>And offer it to the buddhas until the end of time.</l>
                        <l>Yet that generosity cannot compare to copying this sūtra.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-61"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“You might cultivate loving kindness with equanimity toward all
                            beings</l>
                        <l>For as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                        <l>Yet that discipline cannot match the patience of someone</l>
                        <l>Who feels confidence in the supreme absorption of the wisdom seal.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-62"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“You might have forbearance toward every being for as many eons</l>
                        <l>As have passed in the infinity of cyclic existence.</l>
                        <l>Yet if you develop a single moment of trust in this seal of the
                            victorious ones,</l>
                        <l>The former merit, compared to this, will seem like a mustard seed next to
                            Mount Meru.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-63"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“You might honor as many beings as there are in the three worlds,</l>
                        <l>By carrying them over your head for many eons,</l>
                        <l>Without ever feeling tired or bothered.</l>
                        <l>Still, such diligence cannot compare to this patience.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-64"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“You might practice concentration for more eons</l>
                        <l>Than there are dust motes in a hundred buddha realms.</l>
                        <l>Still, compared to applying yourself to this sūtra for a single day,</l>
                        <l>That merit is no match for this patience.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-65"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“You might persevere in the insight that abandons the two extremes</l>
                        <l>For as many countless eons as there are particles in the world.</l>
                        <l>Still, if anyone realizes this wisdom, just as I have taught,</l>
                        <l>The former merit, compared to this, will seem like a drop of water next
                            to the ocean.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-66"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“When it comes to the Victorious One, do not look for forms or
                            features.</l>
                        <l>Do not regard the Blissful One as would a child.</l>
                        <l>Whoever sees me as Subhūti sees me</l>
                        <l>Trains in every kind of generosity found anywhere in the
                            trichiliocosm.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-67"/>
                    <p tid="70">Then, after the Blessed One had spoken these words, he continued,
                        addressing the elder Śāradvatīputra: <ref cRef="F.237.b"/> “Śāradvatīputra,
                        this absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom seal</distinct> is
                        the perfection of the stainless wisdom vision of all bodhisattvas in the
                        worlds throughout the ten directions. Śāradvatīputra, whoever wants to see
                        the blessed buddhas should train in this absorption with an altruistic
                        intention. Such bodhisattvas, practicing with altruistic intention, are able
                        to see the Thus-Gone One within the course of just a single day.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-68"/>
                    <p tid="71">“Moreover, Śāradvatīputra, bodhisattvas who desire to see the
                        blessed buddhas in all the buddha realms of the ten directions should train
                        day and night in this absorption. When bodhisattvas apply themselves with
                        altruistic intention, they come to see the blessed buddhas in all the buddha
                        realms of the ten directions. Śāradvatīputra, this absorption of
                            <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom seal</distinct> accomplishes the
                        dhāraṇī Dharma method that brings about infinite gateways for bodhisattvas.
                        It is the basis for all dhāraṇī gateways. From it the dhāraṇī gateways
                        emerge. This absorption will accomplish the bodhisattva’s thirty-two marks
                        and complete the eighty excellent signs of a great being. Whoever trains in
                        this absorption of the bodhisattvas will purify all karmic obscurations,
                        overcome all kinds of demonic activity, and will neither honor nor
                        experience the Thus-Gone One as a regular being. Whoever trains in this
                        absorption of the bodhisattvas will not be confused, no matter what is said.
                        All bodily activity will be faultless. All verbal activity will be free from
                        origin. All mental activity will be free of afflictions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-69"/>
                    <p tid="72">“Śāradvatīputra, bodhisattvas who wish to understand the hidden
                        teaching of the thus-gone ones should train in this absorption. <ref cRef="F.238.a"/> Wanting to understand Dharma teachings, they should
                        train in this absorption. Wanting to teach Dharma discourses, they should
                        train in this absorption. Wanting to understand the way of truth, they
                        should train in this absorption. Wanting to actualize the limit of reality,
                        they should train in this absorption. Wanting to understand dependent
                        origination, they should train in this absorption. Wanting to know the
                        inclinations of sentient beings, they should train in this absorption.
                        Wanting to apprehend the excellent display of qualities in the buddha realms
                        at will, they should train in this absorption. Wanting to attain excellent
                        luminosity, they should train in this absorption. Wanting to perfect an
                        excellent retinue, they should train in this absorption. Wanting to perfect
                        an excellent lifespan, they should train in this absorption. Wanting to
                        perfect an excellent arrangement, they should train in this absorption.
                        Wanting to perfect the excellent teaching, they should train in this
                        absorption. Wanting to fulfill the wishes of bodhisattva great beings and
                        others, they should train in this absorption. They should train in this
                        absorption in order to investigate, trust, write, read, remember, retain,
                        and meditate.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-70"/>
                    <p tid="73">“Why is this? Because within this absorption, none of that is
                        difficult. Śāradvatīputra, this absorption is like a precious
                        wish-fulfilling jewel that provides for all your wants. It is a
                        wish-granting tree that fulfills all beings’ wishes. Śāradvatīputra, thus
                        this absorption completely fulfills all the intentions of bodhisattva great
                        beings.” <ref cRef="F.238.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="74">Then the Blessed One spoke these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-72"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>“This sūtra of the seal of infinite wisdom</l>
                        <l>Is a mass of wisdom, a distinguished and sublime wisdom,</l>
                        <l>A wisdom light, a wisdom treasury,</l>
                        <l>A wisdom source, and an entrance to the gateway to wisdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-73"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>“It is powerful insight, the source of insight, the site of insight,</l>
                        <l>The lamp of insight, the light of insight that dispels darkness,</l>
                        <l>The inexhaustible insight, and the way of insight.</l>
                        <l>Like the sun, it accompanies the three worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-74"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>“It is sameness, abides in sameness,</l>
                        <l>Cuts through all grasping, and is the way of truth,</l>
                        <l>The gateway to all absorptions, and the seal of wisdom.</l>
                        <l>It is the vision of the buddhas’ discriminating awareness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-75"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>“It is an inexhaustible treasury that takes you to the other side.</l>
                        <l>It is miraculous insight, the source of insight, and a treasure.</l>
                        <l>It is the root of the happiness of having one’s wishes fulfilled.</l>
                        <l>This absorption seal is the blissful ones’ wealth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-76"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>“It is the luxurious kingdom enjoyed by the king.</l>
                        <l>It is the source of excellent, supreme jewels.</l>
                        <l>It clears away the dust of passion and the stain of aggression.</l>
                        <l>This sūtra teaching is the root of precious things.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-77"/>
                    <lg tid="80">
                        <l>“It is peaceful and sets your mind at ease.</l>
                        <l>It makes you beautiful and purifies the belief in a self.</l>
                        <l>When you discover this dhāraṇī seal of the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>You destroy Māra with this heroic weapon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-78"/>
                    <lg tid="81">
                        <l>“Its wisdom knows all beings in existence.</l>
                        <l>This insight is the source of wisdom, a wisdom fortune.</l>
                        <l>It is the light of wisdom, an infinite transcendence.</l>
                        <l>This sūtra is the source of the gateway to wisdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-79"/>
                    <lg tid="82">
                        <l>“It cuts through the two knots of discipline and training.</l>
                        <l>It purifies the sixty-two conceptual views.</l>
                        <l>It is the conqueror’s gateway; it obtains ambrosia.</l>
                        <l>It is the source of the thirty-two marks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-80"/>
                    <lg tid="83">
                        <l>“It is awakening; it agrees with full awakening.</l>
                        <l>It reveals extremist positions and the cause of awakening.</l>
                        <l>This awakening rouses you from sleep.</l>
                        <l>This way of awakening is infinite and inexhaustible.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-81"/>
                    <lg tid="84">
                        <l>“It is the way of Dharma, which cultivates reason.</l>
                        <l>It accomplishes infinite dhāraṇīs.</l>
                        <l>It engages in the Dharma of the ten powers.</l>
                        <l>This dhāraṇī is like the ocean. <ref cRef="F.239.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-82"/>
                    <lg tid="85">
                        <l>“This is the accomplishment of the perfection of generosity.</l>
                        <l>This is the perfection of discipline and patience.</l>
                        <l>It is inexhaustible diligence, concentration, and insight.</l>
                        <l>To rest in it is the completion of all the perfections.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-83"/>
                    <lg tid="86">
                        <l>“Do not be afraid of karma and disturbing emotions.</l>
                        <l>Do not be afraid of the demon of wrong understanding.</l>
                        <l>For those who connect with this, there are no obstacles.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-84"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’di la sbyor la bar du
                                    gcod med de</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’di la sbyor la rab tu mchod med de</foreign>.
                                Narthang has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod</foreign>
                                instead of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sbyor</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Just as you wish, you will manifest awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-85"/>
                    <lg tid="87">
                        <l>“Those who have traveled throughout the ten directions</l>
                        <l>To receive this discourse are certain vessels for awakening.</l>
                        <l>The offspring dwelling during this fortunate eon</l>
                        <l>Are all witnesses<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-86">
                                Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpang</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbang</foreign>.</note> to this.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-87"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>“This is the mother of the buddhas of the past.</l>
                        <l>This sūtra is the mother of those not yet come.</l>
                        <l>And all the present buddhas are born from it.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, kinsmen of the conqueror, apply yourselves to this!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-88"/>
                    <lg tid="89">
                        <l>“Those who live according to this sūtra</l>
                        <l>Attain the Thus-Gone One’s wealth.</l>
                        <l>They purify karma and perfect their conduct.</l>
                        <l>They become nonregressing and go beyond the swamp.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-89"/>
                    <p tid="90">When the Blessed One delivered this Dharma teaching, many hundreds
                        of billions of bodhisattvas, as numerous as the grains of sand in thirty
                        Ganges rivers, attained this absorption. Six trillion eight hundred billion
                        bodhisattvas purified the karmic obscurations accumulated over a hundred
                        thousand eons and became nonregressing from unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening. All of them attained the dhāraṇī called <distinct>accomplishing
                            the inexhaustible moment</distinct>. Six quintillion gods and humans who
                        previously had failed to arouse the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening now aroused this mind and rejoiced in this absorption. Due to the
                        roots of virtue resulting from rejoicing in this absorption, they became
                        nonregressing from unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Then the Blessed One
                        prophesied that after three million eons, all of them would become thus-gone
                        ones, worthy ones, perfect buddhas known as Fearless One. <ref cRef="F.239.b"/> Some among them would, after having made aspirations
                        for a long time, accomplish patience. For others among them, their
                        aspirations would quickly bring them to various buddha realms, where they
                        will fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood. However, all of
                        them will share the name Fearless One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-90"/>
                    <p tid="91">Then the Blessed One gazed out over this entire retinue and
                        addressed Mañjuśrī, saying, “Mañjuśrī, therefore, you must abide without
                        reifying, and delight in the absence of conceptual thinking. Thereby, you
                        must arrive at the practice of nonabiding. Not fixated on any phenomenon,
                        you must guard this accomplishment of unsurpassed and perfect awakening over
                        many countless quadrillions of eons. You must embrace it, hold it, and teach
                        it elaborately to others. You must delight in the absence of conceptual
                        thinking. You must practice nonabiding. You must not abide upon anything and
                        be free from envy.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-91"/>
                    <p tid="92">Then Mañjuśrī rose from his seat, draped his shawl over one
                        shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. Joining his palms, he bowed toward
                        the Blessed One and said, “Blessed One, since there are no graspable
                        phenomena, I am happy to guard and protect this unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening. Blessed One, as for awakening, it is nothing at all. It comes
                        from nowhere. It is found nowhere. It does not come about through anything.
                        It is nothing whatsoever. It does not appear. It is ungraspable,
                        unattainable, and inexhaustible.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-92"/>
                    <p tid="93">Then the three billion bodhisattvas in the retinue rose from their
                        seats. They joined their palms and addressed the Blessed One: <ref cRef="F.240.a"/> “Blessed One, as for this accomplishment of the
                        unsurpassed and perfect awakening of the thus-gone ones that spans countless
                        quadrillions of eons, we are happy to guard it, hold it, explain it, and
                        teach it elaborately to others.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-93"/>
                    <p tid="94">Then all of those bodhisattvas offered their own robes for the body
                        of the Blessed One, and they made aspirations. The Blessed One then
                        addressed the bodhisattva great being Maitreya: “Maitreya, remember your
                        intention to uphold the Dharma in a future life, in the future, during the
                        final five hundred years! This will be your task!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-94"/>
                    <p tid="95">Then the bodhisattva great being Maitreya rose from his seat, draped
                        his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. Joining his palms,
                        he bowed toward the Blessed One and said, “Blessed One, I remember my
                        intention to uphold the sacred Dharma!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-95"/>
                    <p tid="96">The Blessed One then spoke to the bodhisattva great being Maitreya:
                        “Maitreya, among the three billion bodhisattvas, eight thousand of them
                        uphold the holy Dharma and will continue to do so. As for the other
                        bodhisattvas, they are incorrigibly attached to grasping at reference
                        points. They will not uphold the holy Dharma. In the future, during the
                        final five hundred years, they will abandon my unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening, which I have accomplished over countless quadrillions of eons.
                        They will go against it. They will not teach it. They will not uphold it.
                        They will not uphold it at all.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-96"/>
                    <p tid="97">“Why is this? Maitreya, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening in
                        seven ways. <ref cRef="F.240.b"/> What are these seven? Inspired by the
                        blessed buddhas, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening. When the holy
                        Dharma is perishing, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening, in order to
                        protect the holy Dharma. Seeing the realms of beings afflicted by so many
                        pains, bodhisattvas feel great compassion and arouse the mind of awakening.
                        Inspired by other bodhisattvas, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening.
                        Having respectfully given beautiful gifts to bodhisattvas who have aroused
                        the mind of awakening, they arouse the mind of awakening themselves. Seeing
                        others arouse the mind of awakening, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of
                        awakening. Hearing perfect praises sung about the qualities of the various
                        ornaments of the thus-gone ones’ body, such as the excellent marks and
                        signs, bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening. Maitreya, these are the
                        seven ways in which bodhisattvas arouse the mind of awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-97"/>
                    <p tid="98">“Maitreya, as was just mentioned, there are those bodhisattvas who
                        arouse the mind of awakening because of the blessed buddhas, and those
                        bodhisattvas who arouse the mind of awakening in order to preserve the holy
                        Dharma at a time when it is perishing, and those bodhisattvas who arouse the
                        mind of awakening due to feelings of great compassion caused by witnessing
                        the realms of sentient beings afflicted with all kinds of suffering.
                        Maitreya, those bodhisattvas who arouse the mind of awakening in these three
                        ways are guarding the blessed buddhas’ awakening. They quickly become
                        nonregressing from unsurpassed and perfect awakening. The four other ways of
                        arousing the mind of awakening are for incorrigible bodhisattvas who do not
                        uphold the holy Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-98"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Maitreya, if bodhisattvas have five qualities, they become
                            <distinct>nonregressing</distinct>. <ref cRef="F.241.a"/> What are the
                        five? Their minds are equanimous toward all sentient beings. They do not
                        envy the success and prestige of others. Even at the threat of their lives,
                        they do not speak unflatteringly of those monks who uphold the sacred
                        Dharma. They are not attached to worldly success sought through knowledge of
                        the Dharma, nor to property, prestige, or praise. They are devoted to the
                        profound Dharma, have no interest in any kind of mundane activity, and carry
                        the profound Dharma with them in all situations. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas
                        possess these five qualities, know that they will not regress.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-99"/>
                    <p tid="100">“Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess the following five qualities,
                        know them to be <distinct>incorrigible</distinct>. What are the five? They
                        have little charisma and do not follow any advice. They are interested in
                        base things and give degraded teachings to others. They are attached to
                        worldly success sought through knowledge of the Dharma, property, and
                        prestige, and behave enviously in the patron’s household. They are
                        fraudulent and deceitful. Their verbal professions do not lead toward
                        emptiness. Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess these five qualities, know them
                        to be incorrigible.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-100"/>
                    <p tid="101">“Maitreya, if bodhisattvas possess the following five qualities,
                        know them to be <distinct>nonregressing</distinct>. What are they? They are
                        not self-referential, and they are not self-extolling. They do not observe
                        any sentient beings, and they do not use concepts to teach about the realm
                        of reality. They do not observe awakening, and they do not regard the
                        Thus-Gone One’s body as having the characteristics of form. Maitreya, if
                        bodhisattvas possess these five qualities, know that they will not regress
                        from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                    <p tid="102">Then the Blessed One spoke the following verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-102"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“Those who are envious, who covet worldly success through knowledge,</l>
                        <l>Who harm, who are fraudulent and insulting, and</l>
                        <l>Those who are all talk and whose conduct is petty</l>
                        <l>Are not able to guard the awakening of the blissful ones. <ref cRef="F.241.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-103"/>
                    <lg tid="104">
                        <l>“Yet those who delight in solitude and live in desolate wildernesses,</l>
                        <l>Paying more than lip service and persevering in what is profound,</l>
                        <l>Are like the rhinoceros, shun the pleasure of worldly success through
                            knowledge,</l>
                        <l>And guard against awakening’s destruction.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-104"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“Far away from crowds, they are intent on absolute peace.</l>
                        <l>Like antelopes, they are skittish and wander homelessly.</l>
                        <l>Like the wind in the sky, they are not attached to property.</l>
                        <l>Such are those who uphold the teachings of the victorious ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-105"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>“As they have no regard for their bodies, and make no efforts to
                            survive,</l>
                        <l>Surely they have also renounced worldly success.</l>
                        <l>Their efforts are not for themselves in any way.</l>
                        <l>In the future, they will be vessels of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-106"/>
                    <lg tid="107">
                        <l>“In the future, there will appear beings,</l>
                        <l>Who proclaim, ‘We are awakened.’</l>
                        <l>Their haughty and pretentious ways will be marred by afflictions.</l>
                        <l>Such people will be unable to uphold this teaching.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-107"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>“Billions of eons before</l>
                        <l>The teacher Dīpaṃkara,</l>
                        <l>I remember that the buddha called Śaśiketu appeared.</l>
                        <l>He taught this absorption to beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-108"/>
                    <lg tid="109">
                        <l>“That victorious one’s first retinue</l>
                        <l>Consisted of eighty trillion nonregressing beings.</l>
                        <l>The second, seven trillion.</l>
                        <l>The third, seven trillion three hundred billion.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-109"/>
                    <lg tid="110">
                        <l>“That victorious one’s lifespan lasted many millions of eons,</l>
                        <l>And his light shone over sixty-three leagues.</l>
                        <l>His saṅgha was ninety-nine million strong,</l>
                        <l>And all of them were powerful worthy ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-110"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“At that time there was a king,</l>
                        <l>A wheel-turning sovereign named Puṇyodgata.</l>
                        <l>His realm was as vast as Jambudvīpa,</l>
                        <l>Some twenty thousand leagues.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-111"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“It was as large as the four continents.</l>
                        <l>The king had six hundred million queens</l>
                        <l>And at least one thousand sons.</l>
                        <l>The name of his palace was Pleasing Light.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-112"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“His realm contained eight hundred million towns,</l>
                        <l>Each situated within lush and beautiful parks.</l>
                        <l>With bountiful harvests, this realm was delightful and enjoyable.</l>
                        <l>It was like the Vaijayanta Palace in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-113"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“In a dream, the king heard</l>
                        <l>That the buddha Śaśiketu had come.</l>
                        <l>With six hundred million servants and attendants,</l>
                        <l>He sought him out.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-114"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“The king prayed, ‘After hearing the teaching of this sūtra</l>
                        <l>On the profound absorption that is the body of the Victorious One,</l>
                        <l>May I experience emptiness, precisely as intended.’<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-115"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stong pa</foreign>. Degé
                                reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ston
                                pa</foreign>.</note>
                            <ref cRef="F.242.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Then he offered his entire kingdom to that buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-116"/>
                    <lg tid="116">
                        <l>“In all the cities, he commissioned</l>
                        <l>Temples to<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-117">
                                Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yi</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yis</foreign>.</note> the Thus-Gone One made of
                            sandalwood.</l>
                        <l>He offered them with joy and delight,</l>
                        <l>And covered the ground he tread upon with gold leaf.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-118"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“For a full eighty thousand years</l>
                        <l>The king did nothing but make offerings,</l>
                        <l>Never wearying or sleeping.</l>
                        <l>Without succumbing to<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-119"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi mthun</foreign>. Degé reads:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ’dun</foreign>.</note>
                            desire, he did not crave<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-120"> Translated based on Stok, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Yongle</foreign>,<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term"> Kangxi, and Lhasa</foreign>:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sred ma yin</foreign>.
                                Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid ma
                                    yin</foreign>.</note> his kingdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-121"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“All the arrays of things he offered</l>
                        <l>To the Thus-Gone One each day,</l>
                        <l>In order that this absorption would be disclosed,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-122"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’don pa</foreign>. Degé
                                reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’dod
                                pa</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Cannot be described in words.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-123"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>“Still, since it remained hidden, the king began to think,</l>
                        <l>‘Since this absorption is extremely profound,</l>
                        <l>It is impossible to accomplish this absorption, the wisdom seal,</l>
                        <l>While clinging to worldly goods.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-124"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“Thus, he took monastic ordination and renounced his kingdom.</l>
                        <l>He dressed in hemp robes and collected alms.</l>
                        <l>For a full eighty thousand years,</l>
                        <l>He did not succumb to sleep and trained in absorption.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-125"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“During that time, he retained whatever</l>
                        <l>Teachings that buddha gave.</l>
                        <l>When the Blissful One passed into the space of nirvāṇa,</l>
                        <l>He built six hundred forty million stūpas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-126"/>
                    <lg tid="122">
                        <l>“To each, he offered five hundred parasols</l>
                        <l>Adorned and beautified with the seven precious substances.</l>
                        <l>To each, a hundred cymbals were rung,</l>
                        <l>And a hundred thousand lamps were offered.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-127"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“For seven hundred thirty billion years</l>
                        <l>He lived his life with few possessions.</l>
                        <l>Having thus abided, free from worldly distractions,</l>
                        <l>He taught this absorption to his retinue.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-128"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>“He did not desire even praise,</l>
                        <l>Let alone any success gained through knowledge.</l>
                        <l>Wishing to preserve the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>He renounced all invitations to meals for the monastics.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-129"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>“He then pleased thus-gone ones </l>
                        <l>Numbering seven trillion eight hundred million.</l>
                        <l>He offered such arrays to them all,</l>
                        <l>And he obtained this absorption from each of them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-131"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“Whoever wishes to preserve this awakening</l>
                        <l>Should meditate devotedly, without desire,</l>
                        <l>And with unwavering altruistic motivation,</l>
                        <l>Just like that king trained. <ref cRef="F.242.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-132"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“Yet there are others who strive for wealth, without concern for the
                            Dharma;</l>
                        <l>Such undisciplined beings may claim to train in awakening.</l>
                        <l>In the future, people with such claims will appear.</l>
                        <l>They will delight in chattering and say that everything is empty.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-133"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l>“Yet they will not know things to be empty according to emptiness.</l>
                        <l>Their lives will be full of desire, harshness, and afflictions.</l>
                        <l>Encouraging emptiness to be grasped through words,</l>
                        <l>They will say, ‘I am awakened—beyond the shadow of a doubt.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-134"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“At that time, the supreme king’s lifespan will become infinite.</l>
                        <l>His thousand children of this fortunate eon</l>
                        <l>And the many in the retinue seated in front of him</l>
                        <l>Will all take monastic vows.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-135"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>“Recollecting the myriad victorious ones,</l>
                        <l>I received ordination from them.</l>
                        <l>All the words I have taught are only what they taught.</l>
                        <l>As I abided, I also cultivated emptiness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-136"/>
                    <lg tid="132">
                        <l>“While adhering for infinite eons to such a method,</l>
                        <l>I made offerings to all the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Yet I did not attain awakening thereby.</l>
                        <l>However, the Guide prophesied this:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-137"/>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>“ ‘If you continue to practice this,</l>
                        <l>Then, as soon as you behold Dīpaṃkara,</l>
                        <l>You will cast away uncertainties and gain insight into sameness.</l>
                        <l>Then you will become the buddha named Śākyasiṃha.’ ” [B.2]</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-138"/>
                    <p tid="134">At that point two of King Bimbisāra’s queens, Śrībhadrā,<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-139"> The name of
                            Ajātaśatru’s mother is more typically given as Vaidehī (See Edgerton,
                            vol. II, 510) or Kośaladevī, given that she was from the region of
                            Kośala/Kosala.</note> who was the mother of Ajātaśatru, and
                        Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā, who was the daughter of Kṣemavatī,<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-140"> The Tibetan for this name,
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye ba ldan</foreign>, has no variants in
                            the Kangyur collections consulted and appears nowhere else in the Degé
                            Kangyur. However, other sources (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣemavatīvyākaraṇa-sūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde sdan
                                ma lung bstan pa’i mdo</title>, Toh 192) give <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ldan ma</foreign> (*Kṣemavatī) as an attested
                            name for one of Bimbisāra’s wives. In <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dbu med</foreign> manuscripts <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde</foreign> might be easily confused for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bye</foreign>, with the following
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ba</foreign> subsequently
                            added to make some sense of the peculiar name resulting from the initial
                            scribal error. We have thus chosen to render this name accordingly. This
                            wife is also sometimes known as Kṣemā. </note> were seated as members of
                        that very assembly. The two queens rose from their seats and approached the
                        Blessed One. They draped their shawls over their left shoulders and knelt on
                        their right knees. Joining their palms, they bowed toward the Blessed One.
                        With reverence and respect, they each offered to the Blessed One’s body a
                        gift of priceless woven fabrics. Then, setting forth five hundred bowls of
                        the flowers of the seven precious substances, <ref cRef="F.243.a"/> they
                        said this:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-141"/>
                    <p tid="135">“Blessed One, in the future, during the final five hundred years,
                        we two shall be devoted to this precious absorption. We shall ensure that
                        others trust it, appreciate it, remember it, study it, understand it, and
                        teach it extensively to others, by serving and venerating those Dharma
                        teachers who uphold discourses such as this, with offerings of clothing,
                        food, bedding, healing medicines, and other necessities. We shall work to
                        mature sentient beings into unsurpassed and perfect awakening. We shall not
                        abandon emptiness. We shall not be occupied with words but practice
                        sincerely. Blessed One, since we shall not even be concerned with our bodies
                        and lives, what need is there to mention external objects?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-142"/>
                    <p tid="136">Following the two queens’ example, the retinue of King Bimbisāra’s
                        queens, which consisted of a hundred thousand girls, rose from their seats
                        and joined their palms. Those who had embarked on the path to unsurpassed
                        and perfect awakening rejoiced in this absorption and said, “Blessed One, in
                        the future, during the final five hundred years, we shall also gladly
                        embrace the sacred Dharma.” Of the sixty thousand female lay practitioners
                        of Magadha, those who had embarked for unsurpassed and perfect awakening
                        rejoiced in this absorption. Rejoicing, they said, “In the future, during
                        the final five hundred years, we shall also gladly embrace the sacred
                        Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-143"/>
                    <p tid="137">Then the Blessed One smiled. As is the nature of the blessed
                        buddhas, when he smiled, light radiated from the Blessed One’s mouth in
                        hundreds of thousands of distinct, manifold colors—blue, <ref cRef="F.243.b"/> yellow, red, white, violet, crystalline, and silver. This light beamed
                        from his mouth and illuminated boundless, infinite world-systems. It subdued
                        all demonic abodes and extended even up to the world of Brahmā. Its
                        brilliance outshone the light of the sun and the moon and pacified the
                        painful feelings of all beings born in hell, the animal realm, and the world
                        of the Lord of Death. Returning back, it swirled around the Blessed One
                        hundreds of thousands of times and disappeared back into the crown of his
                        head.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-144"/>
                    <p tid="138">At this point Śrībhadrā and Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā, who was the
                        daughter of Possessor of Millions, rose from their seats, draped their
                        shawls over their left shoulders, and knelt on their right knees. Joining
                        their palms, they bowed toward the Blessed One. Then they praised him with
                        these melodious verses and asked him about the purpose behind his smile:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-145"/>
                    <lg tid="139">
                        <l>“Supreme being with so many qualities, unlike anyone in the three
                            existences,</l>
                        <l>Your hundreds of qualities radiate like the moon in the sky.</l>
                        <l>Your smile is so beautiful and your speech so sweet!</l>
                        <l>With your ten powers, please tell us why you smiled.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-146"/>
                    <lg tid="140">
                        <l>“Foremost being, please survey the world with your smiling face, which is
                            like the moon.</l>
                        <l>Your voice is so gentle—the beautiful and clear voice of Brahmā.</l>
                        <l>It soothes the mind and pleases the body, fully satisfying our minds.</l>
                        <l>O Teacher, best of men, please reveal the cause of your lion-like
                            smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-147"/>
                    <lg tid="141">
                        <l>“Your speech is untroubled, unsullied, and not lacking in any way.</l>
                        <l>It is exceedingly rich, even-toned, and beautifully sweet.</l>
                        <l>Differentiating between the trillions of differing attitudes among
                            people,</l>
                        <l>You who possess every kind of precious quality, please explain your
                            smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-148"/>
                    <lg tid="142">
                        <l>“Your speech possesses the eight factors and sixty branches;</l>
                        <l>Your voice contains seven hundred languages and six hundred million
                                syllables.<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-149">
                                Translation tentative. The Tibetan reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">skad ni bdun brgya dag dang yi ge bye ba drug cu
                                    ldan</foreign>.</note>
                            <ref cRef="F.244.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Buddha’s voice has one hundred eighty billion applications.</l>
                        <l>Please declare the true and boundless causes<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-150">Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gleng gzhi</foreign>. Degé reads:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gling
                                bzhi</foreign>.</note> behind your smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-151"/>
                    <lg tid="143">
                        <l>“Like the supreme mountain, others do not sway you.</l>
                        <l>You discern a hundred differing attitudes and totally dismantle
                            ambivalence.</l>
                        <l>You pacify the suffering of existence and grant beings happiness.</l>
                        <l>Please explain in detail about your lovely smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-152"/>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“Your body is like a mountain of gold—delightful—like a jeweled
                            shrine.</l>
                        <l>Your face has the appearance of a hundred-petaled lotus in full
                            bloom.</l>
                        <l>You have the overwhelming power of a lion, the roar of the lord of
                            beasts.</l>
                        <l>Please reveal the meaning of your laughing smile.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-153"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“In the three worlds, you are unequaled and have none of the three
                            stains.</l>
                        <l>Acting beautifully, you thoroughly pacify and delight the hundreds of
                            existences.</l>
                        <l>Your smile illuminates all within the ten directions.</l>
                        <l>Tell us swiftly and in detail about the nectar that clears away
                            darkness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-154"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“The lute, clay drum, one-string, three-string, conch, and flute;</l>
                        <l>Kiṃnaras, nightingales, and cuckoos;</l>
                        <l>Swans, cranes, large drums, and tabors—</l>
                        <l>Even if resounding together, they would not equal a fraction of the
                            Buddha’s speech.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-155"/>
                    <lg tid="147">
                        <l>“In these vast assemblies, which have come here from the ten
                            directions,</l>
                        <l>Are a great number of intelligent beings, as well as some with poor
                            intelligence.</l>
                        <l>They have come from many places, having gained results and accomplished
                            their training.<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-156"> Translation tentative. The Tibetan reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ci nas ’bras bcas brtul zhugs
                                    grub nas phyogs phyogs mchi ’gyur pa</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Please explain how these beings will eliminate<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-157"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsal ba</foreign>. Degé
                                reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btsal
                                ba</foreign>.</note> the vine of craving.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-158"/>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“This boundless and sacred assembly comes from millions of realms.</l>
                        <l>The best of men from the ten directions sent forth these beings who
                            desire the Dharma.</l>
                        <l>Surely, having heard of this accomplishment, they will be delighted.<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-159"> Translated
                                based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de nas ci nas
                                    dngos grub thos nas dga’ ste mchi ’gyur bar</foreign>. Degé
                                reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de dag ci nas dngos
                                    grub thob nas rga ste ’chi ’gyur bar</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>So please bring down a rain of Dharma that explains the reasons for your
                            smile.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-160"/>
                    <p tid="149">In reply, the Blessed One spoke these verses to the queens
                        Śrībhadrā and Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-161"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“I remember, innumerable eons ago, as many as the grains of sand in the
                            Ganges,</l>
                        <l>There was a guide of the world called Puṇyaraśmi.</l>
                        <l>That teacher’s life spanned seven hundred million years.</l>
                        <l>That Dharma king’s saṅgha of hearers was infinite. <ref cRef="F.244.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l/>
                        <l>“Then appeared a wheel-turning king, Prajñāsārathi.</l>
                        <l>His two wives, Keturājñī and Arcī, were utterly free from attachment.</l>
                        <l>Desiring the Dharma, they took ordination,</l>
                        <l>And they kept their precepts for millions of years.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-162"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“During those days, they maintained the precepts</l>
                        <l>Of six hundred three million guides.</l>
                        <l>In the future, when the precepts of the world protectors—as many as there
                            are grains of sand</l>
                        <l>In thirty Ganges rivers—weaken, they will preserve them together.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-163"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“Throughout those lives, you two were together as those beings,</l>
                        <l>And eventually, you became the wives of the king Prajñāsārathi.</l>
                        <l>Through having preserved the Dharma, in the future you will cast off your
                            female forms</l>
                        <l>And behold the thus-gone one Amitābha in Sukhāvatī.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-164"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“Moreover, during the end times, all other followers</l>
                        <l>Will set out with the intent to safeguard awakening.</l>
                        <l>They will become the victors’ sons, adorned with the thirty signs,</l>
                        <l>Seated upon blooming lotus flowers in Sukhāvatī.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-165"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“In that realm they will devotedly pay homage to the teacher,</l>
                        <l>And in the eon without enemies called Vyūharāja,</l>
                        <l>All of them will attain the highest awakening of buddhahood.</l>
                        <l>They will remain, so that all gods and humans can practice the
                            Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-166"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“In that buddha realm there will be no demonic activity,</l>
                        <l>And at that time, hearers will be unheard of.</l>
                        <l>Their actions will be flawless; there will be no lower realms, and no one
                            will enter the womb.</l>
                        <l>Infinite numbers of bodhisattvas will always congregate there.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-167"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l>“Those who give up their lives to guard the awakening of the victorious
                            ones,</l>
                        <l>Who desire no profit and have no regard for their own lives,</l>
                        <l>Will soon abide in the highest awakening of buddhahood.</l>
                        <l>Just as they desire, they will travel to the buddha realms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-168"/>
                    <lg tid="157">
                        <l>“In this way, during the time of great quarrels, you must get along,</l>
                        <l>Delight in the buddhas, and, respectfully and without envy, preserve my
                            awakening!</l>
                        <l>In that future time of divisions, <ref cRef="F.245.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Do not follow those who long for wealth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-169"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>“As I pursued the meaningful qualities of buddhahood for millions of
                            eons,</l>
                        <l>I relinquished my wives, sons, daughters, kingdoms, heads, and eyes.</l>
                        <l>Those senseless ones will destroy my Dharma with a lust for wealth.</l>
                        <l>For the sake of profit and gain, they will be hostile to one another.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-170"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“During the end times, you will guard awakening with your sincere
                            intention.</l>
                        <l>To that end you will act, impelled by the tears of eight hundred million
                            beings.</l>
                        <l>The trichiliocosm will stir, and the gods will rain down flowers.</l>
                        <l>Whoever delights in this sūtra will discover a treasure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-171"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“All the guides in the ten directions will be delighted.</l>
                        <l>The gods will praise them in wonderful garlands of song.</l>
                        <l>In the future, whoever hears and trains in this sūtra of the wisdom
                            seal</l>
                        <l>Will receive the offerings of the gods and the protection of the
                            yakṣas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-172"/>
                    <lg tid="161">
                        <l>“One may fill with gold as many buddha realms as there are grains of sand
                            in the Ganges,</l>
                        <l>And offer it all to the guides for as many eons as there are grains of
                            sand in the Ganges.</l>
                        <l>Yet this would not approach the accumulation of merit</l>
                        <l>Of those who accept this discourse of the wisdom seal and apply it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-173"/>
                    <lg tid="162">
                        <l>“Awakening should not be forced upon those who do not want it.</l>
                        <l>Instead, let them arouse the mind of awakening by hearing of the Buddha’s
                            splendor.</l>
                        <l>When this teaching is applied just as it is explained in the
                            discourse,</l>
                        <l>They will soon become protectors of the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-174"/>
                    <lg tid="163">
                        <l>“Those who want to reach the vast and sacred awakening of buddhahood</l>
                        <l>Should stay in hermitages and devotedly take the vows of individual
                            liberation.</l>
                        <l>Because of the three vows, they will see all beings like a mother sees
                            her son.</l>
                        <l>They joyfully honor<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-175"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mdun du byas pa</foreign>. Degé
                                reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mdun du byas
                                    dpa’</foreign>.</note> them and see them as teachers.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-176"/>
                    <lg tid="164">
                        <l>“Those who record this absorption of the wisdom seal,</l>
                        <l>Who hold it, show it, read it, and teach it to others,</l>
                        <l>Will accrue limitless and unfathomable merit.</l>
                        <l>Such children of the victorious ones will travel to the world of
                            Sukhāvatī.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-177"/>
                    <p tid="165">Then the bodhisattva great being Maitreya asked the Blessed One,
                        “Venerable Blessed One, in the future, during the final five hundred years,
                            <ref cRef="F.245.b"/> what will happen to those who receive and hold
                        this absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom
                        seal</distinct>?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-178"/>
                    <p tid="166">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva great being Maitreya,
                        “Maitreya, in future times, they will suffer, suffer immensely. They will be
                        false, totally false. They will have little patience or interest, and they
                        will destroy their roots of virtue. Maitreya, even if I were to explain to
                        you how bodhisattvas will be destroyed in the future, Maitreya, you could
                        not comprehend it.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-179"/>
                    <p tid="167">The bodhisattva great being Maitreya beseeched the Blessed One,
                        “Please consider us all compassionately! Blessed One, please teach us!
                        Blissful One, please teach us! Blessed One, those bodhisattvas who endeavor
                        to learn, once they hear your teaching, will train in suchness. Once they
                        train in suchness, they will gain accomplishment in suchness. From then on,
                        they will not regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening. This will be
                        their accomplishment.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-180"/>
                    <p tid="168">The Blessed One responded to the bodhisattva great being Maitreya,
                        “Maitreya, beings who previously aroused the mind of awakening and
                        engendered roots of virtue in the presence of a hundred buddhas will, in
                        future times, allow the mind of awakening to deteriorate. They will no
                        longer have any interest in the extremely vast, but renounce it.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-181"/>
                    <p tid="169">“Maitreya, even beings who have previously aroused the mind of
                        awakening and produced roots of virtue in the presence of a thousand buddhas
                        will, in future times, no longer have any interest in the extremely vast,
                        but renounce it, even though they aroused the mind of awakening. They will
                        not commit it to writing, <ref cRef="F.246.a"/> receive it, hold it, teach
                        it, or trust it.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-182"/>
                    <p tid="170">“Maitreya, beings who have previously aroused the mind of awakening
                        and produced roots of virtue in the presence of a hundred thousand buddhas
                        will, in future times, arouse the mind of awakening, feel interest in the
                        extremely vast, and not renounce it. However, they will not proclaim it, and
                        they will not understand its meaning.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-183"/>
                    <p tid="171">“Maitreya, beings who have previously aroused the mind of awakening
                        and produced roots of virtue in the presence of ten million buddhas will, in
                        future times, arouse the mind of awakening, hear about the extremely vast,
                        commit it to writing, retain it, stay interested, proclaim it, and
                        understand its meaning. However, they will not gain acceptance of awakening,
                        will not attain this absorption, and will not gain eloquence.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-184"/>
                    <p tid="172">“Maitreya, beings who have previously aroused the mind of awakening
                        and produced roots of virtue in the presence of a hundred million buddhas
                        will, in future times, arouse the mind of awakening, hear about the
                        extremely vast, feel interested in it, commit it to writing, retain it,
                        proclaim it, and gain acceptance of it. Yet, they will not attain this
                        absorption and will not gain eloquence.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-185"/>
                    <p tid="173">“Maitreya, beings who have previously aroused the mind of awakening
                        and produced roots of virtue in the presence of three hundred million
                        buddhas will, in future times, arouse the mind of awakening, hear about the
                        extremely vast, feel interested in it, not renounce it, trust it, recite it,
                        commit it to writing, read it, and chant it. They will master it, retain it,
                        retain it thoroughly, realize its meaning, and teach it extensively to
                        others. They will train in it, gaining acceptance of awakening. However,
                        they will not attain this absorption of <distinct>the thus-gone one’s wisdom
                            seal,</distinct>
                        <ref cRef="F.246.b"/> and they will not gain eloquence.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-186"/>
                    <p tid="174">“Maitreya, beings who have previously aroused the mind of awakening
                        and produced roots of virtue in the presence of eight hundred million
                        buddhas and heard from these buddhas about this absorption that is
                            <distinct>the wisdom seal of the thus-gone ones</distinct>, and who
                        grasp it and understand it will, in future times, arouse the mind of
                        awakening, hear about the extremely vast, feel interested in it, trust it,
                        and not renounce it. They will recite it, trust it, chant it, commit it to
                        writing, read it, and master it. They will retain it, retain it thoroughly,
                        realize its meaning, and teach it extensively to others. They will train in
                        it, gaining acceptance of awakening. Furthermore, they will also attain this
                        absorption that is <distinct>the wisdom seal of the thus-gone
                            ones</distinct>. They will reveal the awakening of the buddhas by means
                        of the indivisibility and nonapprehension of all phenomena. They will not be
                        swept away by demonic activity. They will not be swept away by the
                        obscurations of phenomena. Whatever negative karma they have accumulated
                        over countless prior lifetimes, in future times, it will all be purified
                        merely by a headache. It will all be purified merely by a moment of worry.
                        It will all be purified merely by criticism. It will all be purified merely
                        by scorn. It will all be purified merely by disparagement. It will all be
                        purified merely by belittlement. It will all be purified merely by their
                        having few possessions. In just one life, everything will be purified.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-187"/>
                    <p tid="175">“Maitreya, in future times, those bodhisattvas who are not
                        discouraged from the mind of awakening, who teach the resolve, and who have
                        resolutely set out for awakening will have thereby venerated countless
                        buddhas. <ref cRef="F.247.a"/> Maitreya, the negativity accumulated by those
                        bodhisattvas that otherwise leads to the lower realms will, in future times,
                        be purified by ugliness of appearance. It will be purified by lack of
                        refinement. It will be purified by sickness. It will be purified by lack of
                        charisma. It will be purified by birth into a lowly family. It will be
                        purified by birth into an obscure family. It will be purified by birth into
                        a disrespected family. It will be purified by birth into a poor family. It
                        will be purified by being born into a family on the borderlands. It will be
                        purified by birth into a wretched family. It will be purified by birth into
                        a ruined family. It will be purified by birth into a family with wrong view.
                        It will be purified by birth into a family of slaves or barbarians. It will
                        be purified by encounters with unfortunate beings. It will be purified by
                        meetings with ignoble beings. It will be purified by depression. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-188"/>
                    <p tid="176">“Their karmic obscurations will be purified by experiences of
                        troubles in the kingdom, regions, provinces, towns, cities, villages,
                        countryside, royal palace, and their homes. Their karmic obscurations will
                        be purified by experiences of separation from loved ones, famine, not
                        encountering a teacher, and not being able to continuously listen to the
                        Dharma, as well as by long durations without clothing, food, bedding,
                        medicine, or possessions. They will also be purified by receiving only
                        things of poor quality, or too few things. They will also be purified by
                        admiration of the mediocre, and through lack of interest in those who are
                        excellent. Their karmic obscurations will also be purified by obstacles to
                        persevering in the roots of virtue, meager comprehension, straying
                        concentration, the inability to settle the mind, not achieving the factors
                        of awakening, and failing to comprehend the true meaning of the Dharma.
                        Their obscurations will even be purified by witnessing negative actions in
                        dreams.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-189"/>
                    <p tid="177">“If karmic obscurations afflict them, they will be overcome by the
                        evil Māra. <ref cRef="F.247.b"/> If the evil Māra overcomes them, they will
                        not understand Māra’s faults. Because they do not fully understand Māra’s
                        faults, those who have possessions will despise those who are without. Those
                        who are handsome will despise those who are not handsome. Those who are
                        lovely will despise those who are not lovely. Those who are delightful to
                        behold will despise those who are not so. The learned will despise the
                        ignorant. Those who are eloquent will despise those who are not so. Those
                        who like giving will despise the stingy. The disciplined will despise those
                        with no restraint. Those with a mere modicum of patience will despise those
                        who are malicious. The diligent will despise the lazy. Those with
                        concentration will despise those who are distracted. Those with insight will
                        despise those with erroneous insight. The skillful will despise the
                        unskillful. No matter what beautiful quality they obtain, they will distort
                        it to despise others. Maitreya, when even those who previously have created
                        roots of virtue in the presence of a hundred buddhas—and who now agree,
                        stand together, and are united—become divided in future times, then how
                        could it not be so for other irresolute beings with wild minds who have not
                        produced any such roots of virtue? Maitreya, in that way, the world will one
                        day become a terrifying place.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-190"/>
                    <p tid="178">“Thus, Maitreya, a bodhisattva such as you must don great and solid
                        armor. You must practice selflessly with the power of patience. You must
                        master the wisdom that engages in the profound Dharma. You must have a view
                        free of reference points. <ref cRef="F.248.a"/> Your mind must be firm, as
                        must your diligence. Your resolve and endeavor must be firm. In future
                        times, you must take up the sacred Dharma. You must uphold the sacred
                        Dharma. You must guard the sacred Dharma. You must delight in making the
                        sacred Dharma endure for a long time. You must engender diligence, remain
                        diligent, and keep others in mind.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-191"/>
                    <p tid="179">When Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the rest of the sixty incomparable
                        beings, as well as Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other bodhisattva
                        great beings of the fortunate eon, had listened to the teaching on upholding
                        the sacred Dharma delivered by the Blessed One, they were delighted by the
                        prospect of upholding the sacred Dharma, so they promised the Blessed One,
                        “Blessed One, all of us agree to renounce all deceit and artifice. We
                        renounce all pride, conceit, and arrogance. We eliminate all likes,
                        dislikes, and cravings.<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-192"> Translated based on <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Yongle</foreign> and Kangxi: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sred.</foreign> Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srid</foreign>.</note> We are
                        dedicated to the profound state beyond reference points, and we will guard
                        this awakening of the buddhas—the thus-gone ones—accomplished over the
                        course of countless quintillions of eons. We will protect it. We will teach
                        it extensively to others. Paying no heed to our bodies or lives, we will
                        guard this awakening of the buddhas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-193"/>
                    <p tid="180">Then, in order to instruct them, the Blessed One spoke these verses
                        to Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other sixty incomparable beings, and to
                        Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other bodhisattva great beings of the
                        fortunate eon:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-194"/>
                    <lg tid="181">
                        <l>“Be without deceit, artifice, ego, or rigidity.</l>
                        <l>Remain mindful, intelligent, and without a home.</l>
                        <l>Accept the profound and rest without distraction,</l>
                        <l>And guard the wealth of the ten powers! <ref cRef="F.248.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-195"/>
                    <lg tid="182">
                        <l>“Be honest, artless, without desire, and free from ego;</l>
                        <l>Delight in absence of grasping, and be totally free from clinging.</l>
                        <l>Be completely equanimous, like a path in the open sky.</l>
                        <l>Practicing like this, you will accomplish this absorption.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-196"/>
                    <lg tid="183">
                        <l>“Make your constant aspiration for awakening firm,</l>
                        <l>And meditate on the profound, as the victorious ones did.</l>
                        <l>If you disregard all loved ones and acquaintances,</l>
                        <l>That is the way you attain this precious absorption.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-197"/>
                    <lg tid="184">
                        <l>“By equalizing the mind that always likes or dislikes,</l>
                        <l>By perceiving supreme beings as teachers,</l>
                        <l>And by delighting in what is delightful,</l>
                        <l>You will quickly realize this absorption.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-198"/>
                    <lg tid="185">
                        <l>“Here are presented a billion paths to the seal of eloquence:</l>
                        <l>A treasure trove of inexhaustible light.</l>
                        <l>This is the way to enter wisdom,</l>
                        <l>As sunlight clears away darkness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-199"/>
                    <lg tid="186">
                        <l>“You must uphold this sūtra,</l>
                        <l>For it is like the sun, the moon, the stars,</l>
                        <l>The earth, the snowy mountains,</l>
                        <l>The lords of the four continents, Śakra, Brahmā, and a healer.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-200"/>
                    <lg tid="187">
                        <l>“It purifies the mind and exhausts karma.</l>
                        <l>It is nectar and it tames the demons.</l>
                        <l>It is a magical eye that sees the minds of others.</l>
                        <l>It is a roar that causes realization in all beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-201"/>
                    <lg tid="188">
                        <l>“It makes you remember billions of eons.</l>
                        <l>It entirely exhausts all entrapments.</l>
                        <l>This seal of the buddhas is praised by the blissful ones.</l>
                        <l>Awakening is in the hand of the one who holds it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-202"/>
                    <lg tid="189">
                        <l>“One realizes emptiness</l>
                        <l>According to how one abides in this empty nature.</l>
                        <l>By abandoning the conceptual thinking</l>
                        <l>Of both thoughts and concepts, you uphold the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-204"/>
                    <lg tid="191">
                        <l>“After I pass into nirvāṇa, some people will say</l>
                        <l>That this teaching should be seen as a dream.</l>
                        <l>The Dharma that is unarisen and uncreated</l>
                        <l>Is conceptualized by some according to their own understanding.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-205"/>
                    <lg tid="192">
                        <l>“Emptiness is unborn and not created by anyone.</l>
                        <l>It is not seen, does not come, and does not transfer.</l>
                        <l>So to say ‘We who cognize reference points train well in emptiness’</l>
                        <l>Is a statement made by thieves of the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-206"/>
                    <lg tid="193">
                        <l>“Those for whom receiving this teaching</l>
                        <l>Causes tears to well up and goosebumps to form</l>
                        <l>Will be called ‘nonregressing from awakening,’</l>
                        <l>But they will later be spoken of with multiple insults.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-207"/>
                    <lg tid="194">
                        <l>“Those from humble households will take ordination for well-being</l>
                        <l>After their family wealth has run out, <ref cRef="F.249.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And find every kind of happiness in this teaching,</l>
                        <l>And yet they will become hostile toward my offspring.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-208"/>
                    <lg tid="195">
                        <l>“Some who long for awakening will take ordination in this.</l>
                        <l>They will speak of awakening, yet not abide in it.</l>
                        <l>For those not secured in awakening,</l>
                        <l>It is as distant as the far shore of an ocean.<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-209"> Translated based on
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Yongle</foreign>,
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Lithang</foreign>,
                                Kangxi, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Narthang</foreign>,
                                and Choné: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgya mtsho tshur
                                    mtha’ pha mtha’</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgya mtsho chu mtha’ phyi
                                    mtha’</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-210"/>
                    <lg tid="196">
                        <l>“They will say, ‘To rely on the houses with wealth and friends,</l>
                        <l>We take authentic ordination.</l>
                        <l>We are pure in terms of our conduct and hermitage,</l>
                        <l>And with respect to our preceptor and friends.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-211"/>
                    <lg tid="197">
                        <l>“Whoever takes ordination within my teaching</l>
                        <l>Abides in worldly life like a lotus abides in water.</l>
                        <l>Those who persevere in this sūtra in this way</l>
                        <l>Will guard my awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-212"/>
                    <lg tid="198">
                        <l>“Prāmodyarāja, now that I have taught you this,</l>
                        <l>Do not train like those with low intelligence!</l>
                        <l>Attain the qualities of buddhahood in earnest!</l>
                        <l>Apply yourself to it without concepts!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-213"/>
                    <lg tid="199">
                        <l>“Imagine that every person in billions of buddha realms</l>
                        <l>Were to sow as many seeds</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in the Ganges,</l>
                        <l>And that each seed were to grow fruits.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-214"/>
                    <lg tid="200">
                        <l>“Imagine next that by skillful means,</l>
                        <l>All the grains were multiplied by a thousand,</l>
                        <l>Thus filling up all the infinite realms,</l>
                        <l>And that the ensuing set were counted as one.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-215"/>
                    <lg tid="201">
                        <l>“Imagine then that each such collection</l>
                        <l>Were multiplied by the previous number of sand grains,</l>
                        <l>And that all the ten directions</l>
                        <l>Were filled with that many victorious ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-216"/>
                    <lg tid="202">
                        <l>“Imagine further that each of those buddhas had that many heads,</l>
                        <l>And each head had that many tongues,</l>
                        <l>And each tongue called out praises of this sūtra</l>
                        <l>For as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-217"/>
                    <lg tid="203">
                        <l>“Such descriptions of this sūtra’s qualities</l>
                        <l>Would be like a mustard seed compare to Mount Meru,</l>
                        <l>Like a blade of grass compared to the sky, or like a single drop from the
                            ocean.</l>
                        <l>Thus, it must be approached in a way that transcends concepts.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-218"/>
                    <p tid="204">Then Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other sixty incomparable
                        beings, as well as Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other bodhisattva
                        great beings of the fortunate eon, asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, when
                        we say <distinct>Dharma</distinct>, to what does that term refer?” <ref cRef="F.249.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-219"/>
                    <p tid="205">The Blessed One replied to Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other
                        sixty incomparable beings, and to Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other
                        bodhisattva great beings of the fortunate eon, “Noble sons,
                            <distinct>Dharma</distinct> refers to that which is unchanging and
                        nonconceptual.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-220"/>
                    <p tid="206">“Blessed One, to what do the terms <distinct>unchanging</distinct>
                        and <distinct>nonconceptual</distinct> refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="207">“Noble sons, <distinct>unchanging</distinct> and
                            <distinct>nonconceptual</distinct> refer to
                            <distinct>nonreferential</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-222"/>
                    <p tid="208">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>nonreferential</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="209">“Noble sons, <distinct>nonreferential</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>inexhaustible</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-224"/>
                    <p tid="210">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>inexhaustible</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="211">“Noble sons, <distinct>inexhaustible</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>unborn</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-226"/>
                    <p tid="212">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>unborn</distinct> refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="213">“Noble sons, <distinct>unborn</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>uninterrupted</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-228"/>
                    <p tid="214">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>uninterrupted</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="215">“Noble sons, <distinct>uninterrupted</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>uncollected</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-230"/>
                    <p tid="216">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>uncollected</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="217">“Noble sons, <distinct>uncollected</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>ungraspable</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-232"/>
                    <p tid="218">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>ungraspable</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="219">“Noble sons, <distinct>ungraspable</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>nonabiding</distinct>.” <ref cRef="F.250.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-234"/>
                    <p tid="220">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>nonabiding</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="221">“Noble sons, <distinct>nonabiding</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>unchanging</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-236"/>
                    <p tid="222">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>unchanging</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="223">“Noble sons, <distinct>unchanging</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>uncompounded</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-238"/>
                    <p tid="224">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>uncompounded</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="225">“Noble sons, <distinct>uncompounded</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>unquantifiable</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-240"/>
                    <p tid="226">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>unquantifiable</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="227">“Noble sons, <distinct>unquantifiable</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>free from thought</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-242"/>
                    <p tid="228">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>free from thought</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="229">“Noble sons, <distinct>free from thought</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>unknowable</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-244"/>
                    <p tid="230">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>unknowable</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="231">“Noble sons, <distinct>unknowable</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>unassembled</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-246"/>
                    <p tid="232">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>unassembled</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="233">“Noble sons, <distinct>unassembled</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>without separation</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-248"/>
                    <p tid="234">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>without separation</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="235">“Noble sons, <distinct>without separation</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>sameness</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-250"/>
                    <p tid="236">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>sameness</distinct> refer?”
                            <ref cRef="F.250.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="237">“Noble sons, <distinct>sameness</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>without difference</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-252"/>
                    <p tid="238">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>without difference</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="239">“Noble sons, <distinct>without difference</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>nonabiding</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-254"/>
                    <p tid="240">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>nonabiding</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="241">“Noble sons, <distinct>nonabiding</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>immaterial</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-256"/>
                    <p tid="242">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>immaterial</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="243">“Noble sons, <distinct>immaterial</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>essenceless</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-258"/>
                    <p tid="244">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>essenceless</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="245">“Noble sons, <distinct>essenceless</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>groundless</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-260"/>
                    <p tid="246">“Blessed One, to what does <distinct>groundless</distinct>
                        refer?”</p>
                    <p tid="247">“Noble sons, <distinct>groundless</distinct> refers to
                            <distinct>nirvāṇa</distinct>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-262"/>
                    <p tid="248">Then Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other sixty incomparable
                        beings, as well as Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other bodhisattva
                        great beings of the fortunate eon, inquired of the Blessed One, “Blessed
                        One, if the Dharma has such characteristics, how can it be that the Dharma
                        ever vanishes? What is it that we should protect?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-263"/>
                    <p tid="249">The Blessed One replied to Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other
                        sixty incomparable beings, and to Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other
                        bodhisattva great beings of the fortunate eon, <ref cRef="F.251.a"/> “Noble
                        sons, what childish ordinary beings perceive to be the Dharma and understand
                        to be the Dharma are conceptual elaborations of the Dharma. Because they
                        conceptually impute and elaborate on the Dharma, they teach it
                        dualistically. Those who teach it dualistically are in conflict with the
                        Dharma. However, noble sons, ultimately we find nothing at all—no Dharma and
                        no conflict with the Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-264"/>
                    <p tid="250">When the Blessed One had explained the meaning to them, he spoke
                        these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-265"/>
                    <lg tid="251">
                        <l>“Some say that what is created is compounded,</l>
                        <l>While others say that it is uncompounded.</l>
                        <l>However, as both apprehend phenomena, both are concepts.</l>
                        <l>Such conceptual elaborations are called impure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-266"/>
                    <lg tid="252">
                        <l>“Phenomena are not created by anyone, nor does anything destroy them.</l>
                        <l>No one sees them, knows them, or is close to them.</l>
                        <l>Such untenable domains of imputed thought—</l>
                        <l>All are designated empty.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-267"/>
                    <lg tid="253">
                        <l>“The thought that something is empty is untenable,</l>
                        <l>Because the unarisen is imputed through such concepts.</l>
                        <l>All concepts are demonic nooses,</l>
                        <l>And immutability is called the<distinct> seal of Dharma</distinct>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-268"/>
                    <lg tid="254">
                        <l>“When they imagine nonexistent things,</l>
                        <l>The childish are bound by those movements of thought.</l>
                        <l>All concepts are like echoes,</l>
                        <l>Yet the childish conceptualize about them dualistically.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-269"/>
                    <lg tid="255">
                        <l>“The wise never discover knowledge,</l>
                        <l>And from the wise no knowledge arises.</l>
                        <l>It is taught in dependence on the relative;</l>
                        <l>Yet here, no knowledge or knower is observed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-270"/>
                    <lg tid="256">
                        <l>“If phenomena had essences,</l>
                        <l>Then, because they perish, their cessation would be nirvāṇa.</l>
                        <l>If phenomena did abide,</l>
                        <l>Then nirvāṇa would be completely permanent.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-271"/>
                    <lg tid="257">
                        <l>“Childish beings engage in abandonment and attainment.</l>
                        <l>Childish beings create nirvāṇa, though it has no characteristics.</l>
                        <l>Those who perceive a self attain the compounded,</l>
                        <l>While the wise are free from notions of existence and absence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-272"/>
                    <lg tid="258">
                        <l>“Knowing and not knowing are not different.</l>
                        <l>They are mere conventions and have no core.</l>
                        <l>Those who engage with constructs and marks</l>
                        <l>Declare nirvāṇa to be a destruction of entities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-273"/>
                    <lg tid="259">
                        <l>“The mind does not know the essence of mind. <ref cRef="F.251.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Neither does the essence know the mind.</l>
                        <l>All phenomena are essentially dreams.</l>
                        <l>This is what some call the two truths.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-274"/>
                    <lg tid="260">
                        <l>“Birth is not real,</l>
                        <l>Nor does cessation have any reality.</l>
                        <l>None of the buddhas are subject to birth.</l>
                        <l>They become real through skillful means.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-275"/>
                    <lg tid="261">
                        <l>“The buddhas have not attained any wisdom,</l>
                        <l>And the Dharma that has been taught—they did not teach at all.</l>
                        <l>Nobody liberates any beings whatsoever.</l>
                        <l>In this way the buddhas are unborn buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-276"/>
                    <lg tid="262">
                        <l>“If they had an essence that passed beyond suffering,</l>
                        <l>The victorious ones would go there together with the hearers.</l>
                        <l>But solid phenomena do not pass beyond suffering,</l>
                        <l>And the nonconceptual will never be known.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-277"/>
                    <lg tid="263">
                        <l>“Those who do not see beings for what they actually are</l>
                        <l>Teach beings according to the relative world;</l>
                        <l>But those who see beings as they actually are</l>
                        <l>Rest in groundless nirvāṇa.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-278"/>
                    <lg tid="264">
                        <l>“Some say that the aggregates are true.</l>
                        <l>Some say that existence, cessation, and the path are true.</l>
                        <l>Although the unborn is a single truth,</l>
                        <l>Some speak of four truths.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-279"/>
                    <lg tid="265">
                        <l>“At the seat of awakening I did not accomplish or see<note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-280"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ma grub ma
                                    mthong</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grub par ma mthong</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Even a single truth, so how could there be four?</l>
                        <l>Thus, many of low intelligence take ordination</l>
                        <l>And destroy my teaching.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-281"/>
                    <lg tid="266">
                        <l>“Spiritual practitioners who want to pursue positive qualities</l>
                        <l>In order to practice this absorption</l>
                        <l>Should not associate with such wild beings;</l>
                        <l>Instead, like the rhinoceros, they should stay in solitude.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-282"/>
                    <lg tid="267">
                        <l>“This was intended to be practiced</l>
                        <l>By eight hundred million excellent humans.</l>
                        <l>The many gods who behold this truth</l>
                        <l>Guard it day and night.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-283"/>
                    <lg tid="268">
                        <l>“Whoever meditates on this absorption, so hard to see,</l>
                        <l>In that person’s dream the Buddha will appear—</l>
                        <l>Clear, limitless, and inexhaustible—</l>
                        <l>And grant them entrance into the gateway of attainment.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-284"/>
                    <p tid="269">Then the Blessed One said to youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī,
                        bodhisattva great beings who wish to realize the buddhas’ awakening should
                        strive in this absorption. <ref cRef="F.252.a"/> Bodhisattvas who wish to
                        accomplish the excellent marks and signs should strive in this absorption.
                        Bodhisattvas who wish to attain the eighteen unique qualities of a buddha
                        should strive in this absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish to attain the
                        powers, the fearlessnesses, great love, and great compassion should strive
                        in this absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish to attain the buddha eye, the
                        self-arisen state, the excellent buddha realm, the excellent lifespan, and
                        the excellent array should strive in this absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish
                        to attain the excellent retinue, the excellent form, the excellent
                        bodhisattva name, as well as the excellent hearers should strive in this
                        absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish to attain illumination, wisdom, retention,
                        the conventions of beings’ languages, reason, methods, and gateways should
                        strive in this absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish to attain skill in entering
                        the path, the perfection of light, the generation of the power of correct
                        understanding, and the generation of the power of conviction should strive
                        in this absorption. Bodhisattvas who wish to attain excellent eloquence,
                        unmistaken view, and the realization of sameness should strive in this
                        absorption.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-285"/>
                    <p tid="270">“Why is that? Because when bodhisattvas strive in this absorption,
                        they attain all these advantageous qualities. And when bodhisattvas have
                        these advantageous qualities, they are called buddhas. They are called
                        guides, leaders, great leaders, teachers, omniscient ones, victorious ones,
                        protectors of the world, self-arisen ones, thus-gone ones, those who
                        practice what they preach, <ref cRef="F.252.b"/> peerless ones, unequaled
                        ones, and incomparable ones. They are called those who speak supremely,
                        those who speak correctly, those who speak the truth, those who speak at the
                        right time, and those who propound the vinaya. They are called unsurpassed,
                        and they are called the most excellent persons. Why is this? Mañjuśrī, as I
                        rested in this absorption and beheld the thus-gone one Dīpaṃkara, I
                        immediately attained awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-286"/>
                    <p tid="271">Mañjuśrī then asked, “If you discovered awakening upon seeing the
                        blessed thus-gone one Dīpaṃkara, then, Blessed One, why did you continue to
                        circle in saṃsāra for countless eons?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-287"/>
                    <p tid="272">“Mañjuśrī,” replied the Blessed One, “I was circling in saṃsāra for
                        countless eons in order to perform buddha activities, ripen beings, and
                        accomplish excellent former aspirations. However, Mañjuśrī, all the while I
                        sustained awakening and nirvāṇa.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-288"/>
                    <p tid="273">Then, in order to explain this meaning more extensively, the
                        Blessed One spoke these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-289"/>
                    <lg tid="274">
                        <l>“With this, you become a leader with boundless and supreme
                            intelligence,</l>
                        <l>Esteemed by billions of buddhas in the ten directions.</l>
                        <l>It discloses the methods of a hundred sūtras, beyond imagination and
                            limit.</l>
                        <l>Applying this sūtra, you will accomplish inexhaustible retention.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-290"/>
                    <lg tid="275">
                        <l>“This wisdom absorption is surely the gateway to all languages.</l>
                        <l>It brings realization, liberation, nonattachment, and an end to all
                            clinging.</l>
                        <l>It is beyond birth, interruption, or basis; it is nirvāṇa, free of
                            afflictions.</l>
                        <l>It brings power, noble marks and signs, and all the victors’
                            qualities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-291"/>
                    <lg tid="276">
                        <l>“It purifies all melodious speech and any form of language.</l>
                        <l>It brings realization, satisfaction, purification,<note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-292"> Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yongs sbyong</foreign>.
                                Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod
                                    dang</foreign>.</note> and freedom from clinging.</l>
                        <l>It knows very well, is beyond any doubt, and exhausts all
                            afflictions.</l>
                        <l>To practice this discourse is to stand before awakening. <ref cRef="F.253.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-293"/>
                    <lg tid="277">
                        <l>“Apply yourself to this—one-pointedly, directly, and properly.</l>
                        <l>Do not sleep or be lazy; do not obsess over profit or happiness.</l>
                        <l>Always be disciplined and free from jealousy, and have a loving mind.</l>
                        <l>In a state of delight, full of devotion, you will attain this supreme
                            absorption.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-294"/>
                    <lg tid="278">
                        <l>“Keep an unbiased, disciplined, honest, and joyous mind.</l>
                        <l>Have no dwelling or relations; concerning profit and pleasure, be like a
                            lotus in a pond.</l>
                        <l>Whatever you do, be egoless and dedicated, without craving or deceit.</l>
                        <l>Then, in the future you will attain this king of supreme dhāraṇīs.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-295"/>
                    <lg tid="279">
                        <l>“The trichiliocosm will tremble, and the cymbals of a hundred gods will
                            sound.</l>
                        <l>From the sky will appear hundreds of ointments, clothing, powders, and
                            victory banners.</l>
                        <l>Lovely garlands, chokers, earrings, capes, conch shells, anklets,
                            necklaces,</l>
                        <l>Jewels, pearls, armbands, crowns, and rings will be scattered all
                            around.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-296"/>
                    <lg tid="280">
                        <l>“Hosts of gods, goddesses, nāgas, gandharvas, and garuḍas;</l>
                        <l>Several hundred garuḍa lords, asura lords, male lay practitioners, and
                            monks;</l>
                        <l>Along with many nuns and female lay practitioners, will all be
                            delighted.</l>
                        <l>Offering their own clothing and jewelry, they will arouse the mind of
                            awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-297"/>
                    <lg tid="281">
                        <l>“When this Dharma is taught, many beings will embark for awakening.</l>
                        <l>It is impossible to show or calculate how many will become
                            nonregressing.</l>
                        <l>Those who become tamed as worthy ones will be as infinite as the grains
                            of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                        <l>To behold the Guide, they will joyfully assemble from hundreds of
                            realms.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-298"/>
                    <p tid="282">When the Blessed One gave this Dharma teaching, countless beings
                        set out for unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Eight trillion bodhisattvas
                        became nonregressing from unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Six hundred
                        million three hundred thousand bodhisattvas attained this absorption that is
                            <distinct>the wisdom seal of the thus-gone ones</distinct>. Innumerable
                        monks, nuns, male and female lay practitioners, and countless other beings
                        attained the state of a worthy one. <ref cRef="F.253.b"/> All bodhisattvas
                        in all the worlds in the ten directions attained this absorption that is
                            <distinct>the wisdom seal of the thus-gone ones</distinct>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-299"/>
                    <p tid="283">When the Blessed One had taught this, the great hearers;
                        Prāmodyarāja, Mañjuśrī, and the other sixty incomparable beings; as well as
                        Maitreya, Siṃhapradyota, and all the other bodhisattva great beings of the
                        fortunate eon up until Avabhāsakara, as well as all the bodhisattva great
                        beings who had gathered from the worlds in the ten directions, the royal
                        queens Śrībhadrā and Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā, the entire retinue, and the whole
                        world with its gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised
                        what the Blessed One had said.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-300"/>
                    <p tid="284">This completes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Absorption of the Thus-Gone One’s Wisdom
                        Seal</title>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="285">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-005-301"/>
                    <p tid="286">This was translated, edited, and finalized, with revisions made
                        according to the new terminology, by the Indian scholars Jinamitra,
                        Munivarman, and Dānaśīla, along with the chief editor and translator
                        venerable Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="287">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="289">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="290">Main Section</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-302">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa de bzhin gshegs pa’i ye shes kyi phyag
                            rgya’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba thegs pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh
                        131, Degé Kangyur vol. 55 (mdo sde, da), folios 230b4–253b5.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-303">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa de bzhin gshegs pa’i ye shes kyi phyag
                            rgya’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba thegs pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’
                        ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod
                        rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 55, pp. 606–63.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-304">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa de bzhin gshegs pa’i ye shes kyi phyag
                            rgya’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba thegs pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok
                        no. 214, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</title>, vol. 73
                        (mdo sde, za), folios 43a5–74b2.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-305">Eckel, Malcolm David. <title xml:lang="en">To
                            See the Buddha: A Philosopher’s Quest for the Meaning of
                            Emptiness</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-306">Edgerton, Franklin. Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit
                        Grammar and Dictionary – Volume II: Dictionary. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-307">New Haven: Yale University Press,
                        1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-308">Roberts, Peter Alan. <title xml:lang="en">The
                            King of Samādhis Sūtra</title>. 84000: Translating the Words of the
                        Buddha, 2018. http://read.84000.co/translation/toh127.html.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-005-309">Skilton, Andrew. “State or Statement?
                        ‘Samādhi’ in Some Early Mahāyāna Sutras.” <title xml:lang="en">The Eastern
                            Buddhist</title>, NEW SERIES, 34, no. 2 (2002): 51–93.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the devas (gods)
                                who are frequently portrayed in the Brahmanical mythology as having
                                a disruptive effect on cosmological and social harmony.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>correct understanding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so sor yang dag par rig pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvid </term>
                            <term type="definition">Correct understanding of meaning, Dharma,
                                language, and eloquence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “retention,” or “that which retains,
                                contains, or encapsulates,” this term refers to mnemonic formulas,
                                or codes possessed by advanced bodhisattvas that contain a
                                quintessence of their attainments, as well as the Dharma teachings
                                that express them and guide beings toward their realization. As
                                such, they are often described in terms of “gateways” for entering
                                the Dharma and training in its realization, or “seals” that contain
                                condensations of truths and their expression. The term can also
                                refer to a statement, or incantation meant to protect or bring about
                                a particular result.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical beings known as “scent-eaters” who
                                subsist on the subtle nourishment of aromas and who inhabit
                                fantastic cities in the clouds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of divine creatures with the bodies of
                                giant birds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the vehicle
                                of the hearers (those who hear the teachings from others); or,
                                someone who heard the Dharma from the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>kācilindika cloth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gos ka tsa lin di ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kācilindika</term>
                            <term type="definition">A very soft substance. The Tibetan translators
                                added “cloth” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gos</title>) to the term.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical beings with a human body and the head
                                of a horse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>limit of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for ultimate reality and a way of
                                describing the attainment of perfection as the culmination of the
                                spiritual path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of serpentine nonhuman beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in
                                subterranean aquatic environments and who are known to hoard wealth
                                and esoteric teachings. They are associated with snakes and
                                serpents.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>perfections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The trainings of the bodhisattva path:
                                generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and
                                insight.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>realm of phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for the nature of things, ultimate
                                reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world
                                in terms of twelve sense sources (eye and form, ear and sound, nose
                                and odor, tongue and taste, body and touch, mind and mental
                                objects).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>suparṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dab bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">suparṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of garuḍa: a divine creature with the
                                body of a giant bird.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>three worlds</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srid gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trailokya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The desire realm, the form realm, and the
                                formless realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>Vyūharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkod pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyūharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of a previous eon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snod byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings said to dwell in
                                the north, under the jurisdiction of the Great King Vaiśravaṇa,
                                otherwise known as Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Ajātaśatru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma skyes dgra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajātaśatru</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha who resides in Sukhāvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Arcī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ’phro </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Arcī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wife of the ancient king Prajñāsārathi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Bimbisāra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs can snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bimbisāra </term>
                            <term type="definition">A king of Magadha at the time of the Buddha, the
                                father of Ajātaśatru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity, presiding over a divine
                                world where other beings consider him the creator; he is also
                                considered to be the “Lord of the Sahā World” (our universe).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dA na shI la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet
                                during the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient buddha who prophied Buddha
                                Śākyamuni’s awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Jinamitra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian Kashmiri paṇḍita who was resident in
                                Tibet during the late eighth and early ninth centuries. He worked
                                with several Tibetan translators on the translation of several
                                sūtras. He is also the author of the<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyāyabindupiṇḍārtha</title>(Toh 4233), which is contained in
                                the Tibetan Tengyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</title>)
                                collection.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Kauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsus po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term type="definition">A senior student of Buddha Śākyamuni, famous for
                                his analytical knowledge.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Keturājñī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tog gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Keturājñī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wife of the ancient king Prajñāsārathi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Kṣemavatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye ba ldan, bde ldan ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Kṣemavatī, *Kṣemā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mother of Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā, who was
                                married to King Bimbisāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Lord of Death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">Usually the Lord of Death who directs the
                                departed into the next realm of rebirth, but here refers to the Lord
                                of the hungry ghost realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A senior student of Buddha Śākyamuni, famous for
                                his austere lifestyle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahākātyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kA tyA’i bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākātyāyana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the hearers present during the delivery
                                of the sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his miraculous abilities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Maheśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maheśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of Śiva; sometimes refers
                                specifically to one of the forms of Śiva or to Rudra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha
                                to follow Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Beautiful Glory,” or
                                “Lovely Splendor.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The demon opposing the Buddha’s teaching; in the
                                plural (māras) it denotes all such nonhuman beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Munivarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu ni war+ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Munivarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet
                                during the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Prajñāsārathi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kha lo sgyur ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Prajñāsārathi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Avabhāsakara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Avabhāsakara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in attendance as the Buddha
                                delivers this teaching.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog tu dga’ ba’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in attendance as the Buddha
                                delivers his teaching.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ’od zer </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Puṇyodgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ’phags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Puṇyodgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams ma’i bu gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the Heaven of the
                                Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha of this age; the historical
                                buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Lion of the S̄ākyas,” this is the
                                name under which Buddha Śākyamuni was prophesied for awakening by
                                Buddha Dīpaṃkara.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ra twa ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his pure observance of discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śaśiketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Śaśiketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Siṃhapradyota</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge rab snang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Siṃhapradyota</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva who is attending the Buddha’s
                                teaching in this sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śrībhadrā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Śrībhadrā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of King Bimbisāra’s queens.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his profound understanding of emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser mchog snang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of King Bimbisāra’s queens.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Not available </term>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the
                                late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                    
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Black Peaks</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri nag po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālaparvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Nine Black Mountains found on the northern
                                edge of the continent of Jambudvīpa. There are three sets of three
                                of these peaks, and behind them lies the great snow mountain that is
                                the source of the Ganges River. A description of this cosmology can
                                be found in chapter three of the<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośabhāṣya</title>of Vasubandhu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second heaven of the desire realm located
                                above Mount Meru and reigned over by Indra, otherwise known as
                                Śakra, and thirty-two other gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent to the south of Mt. Sumeru, where
                                according to Buddhist cosomology “the world as we know it” is
                                located.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Kalandanivāpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ka la da ka’i gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalandakanivāpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The Squirrel Feeding Ground.” A
                                location within the Veṇuvana where the Buddha stayed. The place
                                received its name from the many squirrels living there, being fed by
                                humans. It should be noted that Tibetan translations misunderstand
                                the Sanskrit term<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalandaka</title>to be a kind of
                                bird (Tib.<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya</title>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Lokāntarika Hell</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten gyi bar </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lokāntarika</term>
                            <term type="definition">According to abhidharma cosmology, when
                                different world systems form, they drift into each other, but remain
                                divided by massive rings of stone. Thus, a space remains between two
                                world-systems’ stone walls—one that is completely dark, untouched by
                                any light. These frigid and desolate spaces are populated by beings
                                with very negative karma. They cling to the cliffs, climbing around
                                in darkness searching for sustenance. When they encounter fellow
                                sufferers, they try to push each other, tumbling into the icy waters
                                below.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Magadha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ga dhA</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Magadha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest kingdom of Northern India during the
                                time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Meru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Meru</term>
                            <term type="definition">The great mountain at the center of the universe
                                according to ancient Indian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Pleasing Light </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The palace of a king known as Puṇyodgata.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i bab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important city in ancient India in the state
                                of present day Bihar.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm in which Buddha Amitābha
                                lives.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Vaijayanta Palace </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam rgyal khang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaijayanta </term>
                            <term type="definition">The palace of Śakra, an epithet for the god
                                Indra, in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Veṇuvana </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ma’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Veṇuvana </term>
                            <term type="definition">The famous bamboo grove near Rājagṛha where the
                                Buddha regularly stayed and gave teachings. It was situated on land
                                donated by King Bimbisāra of Magadha and, as such, was the first of
                                several landholdings donated to the Buddhist comunity during the
                                time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūṭaparvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mountain where many Great Vehicle teachings
                                were delivered by Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Sahā World</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahāloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A name for the world as we know it, where Buddha
                                Śakyamuni has appeared and taught.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the devas (gods)
                                who are frequently portrayed in the Brahmanical mythology as having
                                a disruptive effect on cosmological and social harmony.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>correct understanding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so sor yang dag par rig pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaṃvid </term>
                            <term type="definition">Correct understanding of meaning, Dharma,
                                language, and eloquence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “retention,” or “that which retains,
                                contains, or encapsulates,” this term refers to mnemonic formulas,
                                or codes possessed by advanced bodhisattvas that contain a
                                quintessence of their attainments, as well as the Dharma teachings
                                that express them and guide beings toward their realization. As
                                such, they are often described in terms of “gateways” for entering
                                the Dharma and training in its realization, or “seals” that contain
                                condensations of truths and their expression. The term can also
                                refer to a statement, or incantation meant to protect or bring about
                                a particular result.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical beings known as “scent-eaters” who
                                subsist on the subtle nourishment of aromas and who inhabit
                                fantastic cities in the clouds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of divine creatures with the bodies of
                                giant birds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the vehicle
                                of the hearers (those who hear the teachings from others); or,
                                someone who heard the Dharma from the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>kācilindika cloth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gos ka tsa lin di ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kācilindika</term>
                            <term type="definition">A very soft substance. The Tibetan translators
                                added “cloth” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gos</title>) to the term.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical beings with a human body and the head
                                of a horse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>limit of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for ultimate reality and a way of
                                describing the attainment of perfection as the culmination of the
                                spiritual path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of serpentine nonhuman beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in
                                subterranean aquatic environments and who are known to hoard wealth
                                and esoteric teachings. They are associated with snakes and
                                serpents.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>perfections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The trainings of the bodhisattva path:
                                generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, concentration, and
                                insight.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>realm of phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for the nature of things, ultimate
                                reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world
                                in terms of twelve sense sources (eye and form, ear and sound, nose
                                and odor, tongue and taste, body and touch, mind and mental
                                objects).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>suparṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dab bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">suparṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of garuḍa: a divine creature with the
                                body of a giant bird.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>three worlds</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srid gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trailokya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The desire realm, the form realm, and the
                                formless realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>Vyūharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkod pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vyūharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of a previous eon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snod byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings said to dwell in
                                the north, under the jurisdiction of the Great King Vaiśravaṇa,
                                otherwise known as Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha who resides in Sukhāvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Arcī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ’phro </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Arcī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wife of the ancient king Prajñāsārathi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Bimbisāra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs can snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bimbisāra </term>
                            <term type="definition">A king of Magadha at the time of the Buddha, the
                                father of Ajātaśatru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high-ranking deity, presiding over a divine
                                world where other beings consider him the creator; he is also
                                considered to be the “Lord of the Sahā World” (our universe).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dA na shI la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet
                                during the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient buddha who prophied Buddha
                                Śākyamuni’s awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Jinamitra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian Kashmiri paṇḍita who was resident in
                                Tibet during the late eighth and early ninth centuries. He worked
                                with several Tibetan translators on the translation of several
                                sūtras. He is also the author of the<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyāyabindupiṇḍārtha</title>(Toh 4233), which is contained in
                                the Tibetan Tengyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</title>)
                                collection.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Kauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsus po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term type="definition">A senior student of Buddha Śākyamuni, famous for
                                his analytical knowledge.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Keturājñī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tog gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Keturājñī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A wife of the ancient king Prajñāsārathi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Kṣemavatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye ba ldan, bde ldan ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Kṣemavatī, *Kṣemā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mother of Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā, who was
                                married to King Bimbisāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Lord of Death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">Usually the Lord of Death who directs the
                                departed into the next realm of rebirth, but here refers to the Lord
                                of the hungry ghost realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A senior student of Buddha Śākyamuni, famous for
                                his austere lifestyle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahākātyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kA tyA’i bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākātyāyana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the hearers present during the delivery
                                of the sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his miraculous abilities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Maheśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maheśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of Śiva; sometimes refers
                                specifically to one of the forms of Śiva or to Rudra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha
                                to follow Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, “Beautiful Glory,” or
                                “Lovely Splendor.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The demon opposing the Buddha’s teaching; in the
                                plural (māras) it denotes all such nonhuman beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Munivarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu ni war+ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Munivarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet
                                during the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Prajñāsārathi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kha lo sgyur ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Prajñāsārathi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Avabhāsakara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snang byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Avabhāsakara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in attendance as the Buddha
                                delivers this teaching.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog tu dga’ ba’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in attendance as the Buddha
                                delivers his teaching.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ’od zer </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Puṇyaraśmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Puṇyodgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ’phags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Puṇyodgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams ma’i bu gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa Maitrāyaṇīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the Heaven of the
                                Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni </term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha of this age; the historical
                                buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyasiṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Lion of the S̄ākyas,” this is the
                                name under which Buddha Śākyamuni was prophesied for awakening by
                                Buddha Dīpaṃkara.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ra twa ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his pure observance of discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śaśiketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Śaśiketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">An ancient buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Siṃhapradyota</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge rab snang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Siṃhapradyota</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva who is attending the Buddha’s
                                teaching in this sūtra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Śrībhadrā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Śrībhadrā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of King Bimbisāra’s queens.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his profound understanding of emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser mchog snang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*Suvarṇottamaprabhāsā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of King Bimbisāra’s queens.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Not available </term>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the
                                late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>




                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Black Peaks</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri nag po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālaparvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Nine Black Mountains found on the northern
                                edge of the continent of Jambudvīpa. There are three sets of three
                                of these peaks, and behind them lies the great snow mountain that is
                                the source of the Ganges River. A description of this cosmology can
                                be found in chapter three of the<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośabhāṣya</title>of Vasubandhu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second heaven of the desire realm located
                                above Mount Meru and reigned over by Indra, otherwise known as
                                Śakra, and thirty-two other gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent to the south of Mt. Sumeru, where
                                according to Buddhist cosomology “the world as we know it” is
                                located.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Kalandanivāpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ka la da ka’i gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalandakanivāpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The Squirrel Feeding Ground.” A
                                location within the Veṇuvana where the Buddha stayed. The place
                                received its name from the many squirrels living there, being fed by
                                humans. It should be noted that Tibetan translations misunderstand
                                the Sanskrit term<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalandaka</title>to be a kind of
                                bird (Tib.<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya</title>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Lokāntarika Hell</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten gyi bar </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lokāntarika</term>
                            <term type="definition">According to abhidharma cosmology, when
                                different world systems form, they drift into each other, but remain
                                divided by massive rings of stone. Thus, a space remains between two
                                world-systems’ stone walls—one that is completely dark, untouched by
                                any light. These frigid and desolate spaces are populated by beings
                                with very negative karma. They cling to the cliffs, climbing around
                                in darkness searching for sustenance. When they encounter fellow
                                sufferers, they try to push each other, tumbling into the icy waters
                                below.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Magadha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ga dhA </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Magadha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest kingdom of Northern India during the
                                time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Meru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Meru</term>
                            <term type="definition">The great mountain at the center of the universe
                                according to ancient Indian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Pleasing Light </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The palace of a king known as Puṇyodgata.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i bab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important city in ancient India in the state
                                of present day Bihar.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm in which Buddha Amitābha
                                lives.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Vaijayanta Palace </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam rgyal khang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaijayanta </term>
                            <term type="definition">The palace of Śakra, an epithet for the god
                                Indra, in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Veṇuvana </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ma’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Veṇuvana </term>
                            <term type="definition">The famous bamboo grove near Rājagṛha where the
                                Buddha regularly stayed and gave teachings. It was situated on land
                                donated by King Bimbisāra of Magadha and, as such, was the first of
                                several landholdings donated to the Buddhist comunity during the
                                time of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛdhrakūṭaparvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mountain where many Great Vehicle teachings
                                were delivered by Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place">
                            <term>Sahā World</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahāloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A name for the world as we know it, where Buddha
                                Śakyamuni has appeared and taught.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>