<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ma lta bu’i ting nge ’dzin</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Illusory Absorption</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māyopama­samādhi</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན་ཅེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sgyu ma lta bu’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                    mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra, The Illusory Absorption</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­māyopama­samadhi­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-78">Zachary Beer</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-46">Khenpo Trokpa Tulku</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-48">Lama Tenzin Sangpo</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-49">Lama Karma Oser</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.2 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-055-004"/>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh130" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 130</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 55 (mdo sde, da), folios 210.b–230.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi </author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="41">
                        <start volume="55" page="422"/>
                        <end volume="55" page="462"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11710" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:29:48 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="198">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In this sūtra Buddha Śākyamuni explains how to attain the absorption known as “the illusory
                    absorption,” a meditative state so powerful that it enables awakening to be attained very quickly. He also
                    teaches that this absorption has been mastered particularly well by two bodhisattvas, Avalokiteśvara and
                    Mahā­sthāmprāpta, who live in Sukhāvatī, the distant realm of Buddha Amitābha. Buddha Śākyamuni
                    summons these two bodhisattvas to this world and, when they arrive, recounts the story of how they first
                    engendered the mind of awakening. Finally the Buddha reveals the circumstances surrounding the future
                    awakening of Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="199">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche.
                    Andreas Doctor produced the translation and wrote the introduction. Zachary Beer compared the draft
                    translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text. The translators are grateful to Khenpo Trokpa
                    Tulku, Lama Karma Oser, and Lama Tenzin Sangpo from Ka-Nying Shedrub Ling Monastery for their assistance in
                    resolving several difficult passages. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="200">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Illusory Absorption</title> is a sūtra that belongs to the general sūtra section
                        of the Kangyur. In the fashion typical of Great Vehicle sūtras, the Buddha’s discourse unfolds within a
                        worldview vastly different in scope from ordinary reality. Here we meet bodhisattvas who have journeyed
                        across billions of universes to hear the Buddha’s teaching, bringing with them samples of the splendors
                        and pleasures that adorn their distant buddha realms. The vast scope of this sūtra pertains not only to
                        the distances traveled, but also to the timespan covered. Through his omniscience, the Buddha recalls
                        events that happened at the dawn of time and predicts affairs yet to unfold in a far-distant future. In
                        this way our ordinary perceptions of time and space are challenged as we enter the worldview of the Great
                        Vehicle. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The sūtra begins outside Vārāṇasī, in the Deer Park where the Buddha first turned the wheel of
                        Dharma after his awakening. This time, however, he is not just speaking to his five previous companions,
                        the audience for his first teaching. Now, we are told, there are 20,000 monks, 12,000 bodhisattvas, 20,000
                        deities, and several hundred thousand other beings present. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">As is customary in sūtra literature, the Buddha delivers his Dharma talks at the request of someone
                        who poses a particular question and asks for clarification. In this particular sūtra, the role of the
                        questioner is played by a bodhisattva named Padmaśrīgarbha, who asks the Buddha how one can attain a
                        particular type of absorption known as “the illusory absorption” and, after attaining
                        that absorption, quickly attain complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The Buddha is pleased with this request and praises Padmaśrīgarbha for asking such a meaningful
                        question. He then proceeds to explain that there is one quality that underlies all attainments of awakened
                        qualities and the state of awakening itself. When in possession of this one quality, a bodhisattva will
                        naturally proceed along the path until finally gaining perfect buddhahood. The Buddha reveals that this
                        crucial and indispensable quality is not to abide anywhere in the three realms, whether internally in the
                        mental sphere or externally in the outer world. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">If one is able not to abide in this manner, one will come to understand that all phenomena are
                        unborn, an understanding that enables one to practice the bodhisattva path. With the realization that all
                        phenomena are unborn comes the understanding that phenomena are likewise illusory and empty. This is the
                        point at which one attains the illusory absorption. When this absorption is attained, one is able to
                        display a variety of bodies in order to teach and guide sentient beings. At that point, full and complete
                        awakening is not far off. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">Padmaśrīgarbha continues to ask the Buddha about the illusory absorption, and he wonders whether
                        anyone among his peers in the Buddha’s retinue might have obtained this absorption. Indeed, the Buddha
                        confirms, several students have gained this absorption, but all of them have attained their realization by
                        associating with two bodhisattvas, Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta, who live in Sukhāvatī, the distant
                        realm of Buddha Amitābha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">Padmaśrīgarbha implores the Buddha to manifest a miraculous sign that will summon these two
                        bodhisattvas, so that others may be blessed by their presence in this world and likewise attain the
                        illusory absorption. The Buddha consents and emits a light from the hair between his eyebrows, a light so
                        bright that it illuminates the entire world of Sukhāvatī. When all the bodhisattvas in Sukhāvatī ask
                        Amitābha about the origin of this light, he reveals that it is being emitted by Buddha Śākyamuni to
                        indicate that a Dharma teaching will shortly be delivered. Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta request
                        permission to attend the teaching, and Amitābha encourages them to go. The two bodhisattvas bring with
                        them on the journey no fewer than 840 million other bodhisattvas, who each manifest a beautiful mansion as
                        an offering to the Buddha Śākyamuni. Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta multiply this offering by
                        emanating 840 million exact copies within each mansion, thus producing a mind-boggling display of gifts. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">The pilgrimage to this world is not an arduous one by any means, being completed within a single
                        second. Once the bodhisattvas arrive, they pay homage to Buddha Śākyamuni and sing his praises in a series
                        of beautiful verses. The bodhisattvas and hearers in the retinue of Buddha Śākyamuni are, of course,
                        amazed by the arrival of all the bodhisattvas from Sukhāvatī and their impressive display of offerings. So
                        they ask the Buddha about the merit that allows Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta to perform such a
                        display. The Buddha reveals how these two bodhisattvas are able to multiply their bodies in inconceivable
                        ways, thus gaining merit by serving countless buddhas in endless realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">Next, Buddha Śākyamuni recounts the story of how Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta first gave
                        rise to the mind of awakening that signifies the beginning of the bodhisattva path. We hear how these two
                        beings, in a far, far distant past, were born miraculously from two lotus flowers in the realm of a buddha
                        known as King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, who himself was a previous emanation of Buddha Amitābha. The
                        place where it all unfolded, we are told, was none other than the world of Sukhāvatī, at that time known
                        as Boundless Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of Happiness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">As is typical of many Great Vehicle sūtras, the Buddha proceeds to reveal the circumstances
                        surrounding the future awakening of the protagonists in question, in this case Avalokiteśvara and
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta. Once Buddha Amitābha has passed into nirvāṇa and no trace remains of his teachings,
                        Avalokiteśvara will fully awaken at dawn on the very next day and receive the name Buddha
                        Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja. At that point the realm will no longer be known as Sukhāvatī, but
                        rather Complete Gathering of Wealth. Next, once this particular buddha passes into nirvāṇa,
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta will awaken in a similar fashion and be known as Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-13"/>
                    <p tid="14">The names of these two future buddhas turn out to be of key importance in the sūtra, because
                        anyone who happens to hear them will be irreversibly destined to unsurpassed and perfect awakening. The
                        blessing of hearing these two names is also such that any woman will be able to put an end to future
                        female rebirths, and in that way join the saṅgha of monks. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-14"/>
                    <p tid="15">At this point the Buddha’s teaching is complete, and everyone in attendance rejoices and arouses
                        the mind set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Many of the listeners in attendance develop various
                        signs of accomplishment and become free from obscurations. Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta also cause
                        a miracle so that the entire retinue can behold all the limitless, uncountable buddhas in all directions,
                        who are making prophecies for their unsurpassed and perfect awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-15"/>
                    <p tid="16">As is typical of Great Vehicle sūtras, toward the end of the story the Buddha speaks of the great
                        amount of merit to be gained by upholding and propagating the sūtra, and everyone gathered at the occasion
                        promises to spread the teaching to the best of their ability. The Buddha repeats his statement that any
                        woman who hears this teaching will be transformed immediately into a man. (Today’s readers should keep in
                        mind that these teachings were given in a society where the status of women was generally low, and women
                        were expected to be subservient and deferential to men. It is also important to remember that the Buddha
                        did allow women into his order, which at the time was a radical endorsement of women as worthy spiritual
                        practitioners.) </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-16"/>
                    <p tid="17">Finally, while thousands of gods scatter flowers and praise on the Buddha and the assembled
                        bodhisattvas, a young girl stands up and announces that she has decided to give up the negative emotions
                        that cause beings to be born as women. Instead, she promises, she will set her mind on complete awakening.
                        In front of the Buddha she vows to become an example for other women by relinquishing her female body, and
                        she requests the Buddha’s blessings to help her do so. Immediately her body is transformed and becomes
                        that of a man. With this metamorphosis complete, the Buddha foretells that she is destined to become a
                        future buddha known by the name Repeller of All Disturbing Emotions, and the sūtra comes to an end. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-17"/>
                    <p tid="18">No Sanskrit version of the text is known to exist, but in addition to this Tibetan translation the
                        sūtra survives in two earlier Chinese translations. The Tibetan translation, by Surendrabodhi and Bandé
                        Yeshé Dé, must have been completed in the early translation period, as it is listed in both early ninth
                        century inventories, the Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>) and Phangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phang thang ma</title>). According to the catalogues of both the Degé and Narthang
                        Kangyurs, the sūtra has nine chapters or sections (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">le’u</foreign>),
                        and the Narthang catalogue mentions that the existence of nine <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">le’u</foreign> is mentioned by the Great Fifth Dalai Lama in the list of texts of which he received
                        the transmission (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gsan yig</foreign>). However, no such formal
                        section breaks can be seen in the Tibetan text as preserved in the different Kangyurs, and it would be
                        unusual for a relatively short text such as this to be divided into formally distinct chapters. It may be
                        that in this and similar catalogue entries<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-244">See,
                            for example, Dharmachakra 2016, Introduction <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-056-002.html#UT22084-056-002-9">i.7</ref>.</note>
                        the term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">le’u</foreign> is being used to denote “episodes” or
                        “scenes,” rather than in its more usual sense of chapters; it would not be impossible to discern nine or
                        more parts to the narrative in this text.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-18"/>
                    <p tid="19">Unlike the names of some of the specific absorptions described in sūtras, “the illusory
                        absorption” is a term that occurs in a wide range of canonical texts, including the Prajñāpāramitā sūtras,
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laṅkāvatāra</title>, and in several tantras and their Tengyur
                            commentaries.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-245">Particularly in texts of the
                            Ārya, or <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’phags lugs</foreign>, commentarial tradition related
                            to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja</title>.</note> This sūtra, as would be expected from its
                        title, is indeed sometimes mentioned or cited in later Tibetan works in connection with the illusory
                        absorption itself. More often, however, it is mentioned as one of the scriptural sources of the stories of
                        Avalokiteśvara and Mahā­sthāmprāpta. The other notable source is the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇā­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 112), which contains a similar but much more detailed account of the
                        predictions of these two bodhisattvas’ future attainment of complete buddhahood, as well as a different
                        episode from their previous lives.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-246">For a
                            translation, see Roberts and Bower (forthcoming).</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="201">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="202">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="203">The Illusory Absorption</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-19"/>
                    <p tid="20">
                        <ref cRef="F.210.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-20"/>
                    <p tid="21">Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in the Deer Park by the Hill of the
                        Fallen Sages near Vārāṇasī, together with a great saṅgha of twenty thousand worthy monks and twelve
                        thousand bodhisattvas that included the bodhisattva great beings Harisiṃha, Siṃhamati,
                        Su­pratiṣṭhita­buddhi, Anupamamati, Dharaṇīṃdhara, Agnidatta, Varuṇa, Ratnākara, Guhyagupta, Bhadrapāla,
                        Vidyutdeva, Vairocana, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, Jñānākara, Anikṣiptadhura, Amoghadarśin, and the bodhisattva
                        great being Maitreya. Also in attendance were twenty thousand gods who had all entered the Great Vehicle,
                        such as Susīma and Su­pratiṣṭhita­buddhi. <ref cRef="F.211.a"/> At that time the Blessed One, surrounded
                        and venerated by a retinue of several hundred thousand beings, was teaching the Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-21"/>
                    <p tid="22">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha <!--modularPassage type="kneelingRequest"-->stood up,
                        draped his shawl over one shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. With his palms together, he bowed toward
                        the Blessed One, and inquired of the Blessed One,<!--/modularPassage-->
                        “<!--modularPassage type="permissionQuestion"-->If this is an opportune moment for the Blessed One to
                        grant me answers to some questions of mine, may I put them to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy,
                        completely perfect Buddha?<!--/modularPassage-->” </p>
                    <p tid="23">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha, “Padmaśrīgarbha,
                        <!--modularPassage type="grantQuestion"-->it is always opportune for the Thus-Gone One to address your
                        concerns. Padmaśrīgarbha, ask the Thus-Gone One, the worthy, completely perfect Buddha, whatever you wish,
                        and I will address your questions, so that you may feel at ease.<!--/modularPassage-->” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-22"/>
                    <p tid="24">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, how is it that
                        bodhisattva great beings render irreversible their progress to unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening,
                        come to possess the five types of clairvoyance, and attain the illusory absorption? How is it that, as
                        soon as they attain that absorption, they emanate whatever bodies in whatever way will perfect sentient
                        beings’ roots of virtue, and teach the Dharma according to sentient beings’ inclinations? How do they
                        quickly awaken to unsurpassed and completely perfect buddhahood?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-23"/>
                    <p tid="25">The Blessed One said to the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha, <ref cRef="F.211.b"/>
                        “Padmaśrīgarbha, excellent! Padmaśrīgarbha, previously you have served the victorious ones, gathered the
                        roots of virtue, and venerated a myriad buddhas. You feel love and compassion for all beings, and that is
                        why you ask the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha about this. That is excellent!
                        Padmaśrīgarbha, therefore, listen well and pay attention. Then I shall explain it to you.” </p>
                    <p tid="26">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha said to the Blessed One, “Wonderful!” and he listened
                        as the Blessed One had directed him. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">The Blessed One said, “Padmaśrīgarbha, there is one quality that, if bodhisattva great beings
                        possess it, renders irreversible their progress to unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening, and
                        grants them the five types of clairvoyance and the illusory absorption. Moreover, as soon as they attain
                        that absorption, they emanate whatever bodies in whatever way will perfect sentient beings’ roots of
                        virtue, teach the Dharma according to sentient beings’ inclinations, and quickly awaken to unsurpassed
                        and completely perfect buddhahood. </p>
                    <p tid="28">“What is that single quality? Padmaśrīgarbha, those bodhisattvas must not abide anywhere in the three
                        realms, neither abiding internally nor externally. As they do not abide, they will see reality. As they see
                        reality, they will unite with reality. As they unite with reality, nothing will impede their mind. As nothing
                        impedes their mind, they will engage in authentic conduct. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-25"/>
                    <p tid="29">“What does it mean to engage in authentic conduct? It is as follows. <ref cRef="F.212.a"/> All
                        phenomena arise in dependence. There is no phenomenon that can remain constantly. All phenomena arise from
                        circumstances. There is no phenomenon that arises without circumstances. Any phenomenon that arises in
                        dependence is unborn. Therefore all phenomena are unborn. To realize that all phenomena are unborn is to
                        know how to practice the bodhisattva’s path. In this way, one attains the basis for benefiting all beings
                        and can proceed with a compassionate outlook. With such conviction, one comes to understand that all
                        phenomena are illusory. All phenomena are magically manifest because they are imputed. Those imputations
                        are also utterly empty. The realization that all phenomena are empty is the attainment of the illusory
                        absorption. </p>
                    <p tid="30">“As soon as one attains this absorption, one emanates whatever bodies in whatever way will perfect
                        sentient beings’ roots of virtue, and one teaches the Dharma according to sentient beings’ inclinations. In
                        this way, one quickly awakens to unsurpassed and completely perfect buddhahood.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-26"/>
                    <p tid="31">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, is there any
                        bodhisattva great being here in this gathering who has attained this illusory absorption?” </p>
                    <p tid="32">“Padmaśrīgarbha,” replied the Blessed One, “there are sixty holy beings here in this gathering who
                        intentionally wear the armor and who have attained the illusory absorption. There are sixty holy beings,
                        including the bodhisattva great beings Maitreya and Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, who have attained this illusory
                        absorption.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-27"/>
                    <p tid="33">Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, did these holy beings <ref cRef="F.212.b"/>
                        attain this illusory absorption here in this world? Or did these holy beings attain this illusory
                        absorption in some other realm?” </p>
                    <p tid="34">The Blessed One answered, “Padmaśrīgarbha, to the west of this buddha realm, passing through one
                        trillion buddha realms, there is a realm known as Sukhāvatī. Right now the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Amitābha resides there, flourishes there, lives there, and teaches the Dharma. In his
                        buddha realm live the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta, both of whom have attained this absorption. Padmaśrīgarbha, it is from conversations
                        lasting seven days with those two holy beings that other bodhisattva great beings attain this illusory
                        absorption.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-28"/>
                    <p tid="35">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, there must be
                        many bodhisattva great beings who attained the illusory absorption in that buddha realm. Blessed One, the
                        reason is that the bodhisattva great beings who are born in that buddha realm can engage in Dharma
                        conversations with those two holy beings without any effort.” </p>
                    <p tid="36">“Padmaśrīgarbha, it is exactly as you say,” said the Blessed One. “The bodhisattva great beings who
                        abide there within the illusory absorption are indeed limitless and countless.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-29"/>
                    <p tid="37">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha implored the Blessed One, “Blessed One, <ref cRef="F.213.a"/> thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha, please use your miraculous powers to
                        show a mental sign by which the two holy beings will come to this Sahā world, and the whole Sukhāvatī
                        world together with the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha will also arrive here in
                        this world. The reason is, Blessed One, that if those two holy beings come to this buddha realm, the sons
                        and daughters of noble family who follow the vehicle of the bodhisattvas will perfect their roots of
                        virtue. They will hear the Dharma talks of those two holy beings, and they, too, will thereby attain the
                        illusory absorption. Here in this buddha realm they will be able to behold Sukhāvatī as well as the
                        Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha. Witnessing that, the sons and daughters of noble
                        family will arouse the mind of unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening. They will make aspirations to
                        be born in that buddha realm and, as soon as they are born there, they will render irreversible their
                        progress to unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-30"/>
                    <p tid="38">The Blessed One, understanding the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha’s request, emitted a
                        bright light from the hair between his eyebrows. The light pervaded this entire trichiliocosm with a
                        bright golden radiance. Throughout the entire trichiliocosm, all mountain ranges and forests as well as
                        the central mountain, the Mucilinda Mountains, the Greater Mucilinda Mountains, the surrounding mountains,
                        the greater surrounding mountains, and all places of deep darkness throughout the world were bathed in
                        that golden light, <ref cRef="F.213.b"/> eclipsing even the sun and the moon—so well known for their great
                        miraculous ability, great strength, and great power—to the point of invisibility. Toward the west,
                        crossing through a trillion buddha realms, that brilliant golden light pervaded the entire realm of
                        Sukhāvatī. There, the light prostrated at the feet of the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha
                        Amitābha, circumambulated him seven times, and, in that blessed one’s presence, disappeared. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-31"/>
                    <p tid="39">The beings who lived in Sukhāvatī, including the bodhisattvas and the great hearers, looked toward
                        this Sahā world and saw the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni surrounded by the
                        gathering of bodhisattvas and attended upon by the saṅgha of hearers. As they saw it all, as clearly as
                        seeing an āmalakī fruit right in their own hand, they were filled with joy and great happiness, and
                        exclaimed, “Homage to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-32"/>
                    <p tid="40">Here in the Sahā world, the assembled retinue of the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha
                        Śākyamuni consisted of monks, nuns, laymen, laywomen, gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, demigods, garuḍas,
                        kiṃnaras, and mahoragās, humans, nonhumans, Śakra, Brahmā, the guardians of the world, and bodhisattvas.
                        All of them could now also vividly see the world of Sukhāvatī and the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Amitābha, <ref cRef="F.214.a"/> who was shining like the king of mountains, surrounded by
                        the assembly of bodhisattvas and attended upon by the saṅgha of hearers. They saw the entire buddha realm
                        in this way. Just as a person with perfect sight can see the face of another person only a fathom away
                        without any strain, from this world and this buddha realm they saw the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Amitābha, as well as the world of Sukhāvatī, which appeared in a great display of fine
                        features, filled with trillions of qualities. Witnessing it, they were filled with joy and great
                        happiness, and exclaimed, “Homage to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha
                        Amitābha!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-33"/>
                    <p tid="41">When that buddha realm was shown to them, 84,000 beings here in this buddha realm, who had not
                        previously aroused the mind of awakening, now gave rise to the mind set upon unsurpassed and completely
                        perfect awakening. They dedicated the roots of virtue toward taking birth in the world of Sukhāvatī, as
                        well as toward unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening. </p>
                    <p tid="42">In the world of Sukhāvatī, the assembled bodhisattva great beings and great hearers saw the Sahā
                        world and were amazed. They joined the palms of their hands and prostrated toward the Blessed One, the
                        thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni while they called out, “Homage to the Blessed One,
                        the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni!” </p>
                    <p tid="43">As soon as the bodhisattva great beings and the great hearers had spoken these words,
                        <!--modularPassage type="earthquake"-->the entire world shook in six ways: <ref cRef="F.214.b"/> it
                        vibrated, shuddered, and reeled; quivered, trembled, and quaked; wobbled, rocked, and swayed; boomed,
                        thundered, and roared; rattled, shook, and convulsed; and clattered, rattled, and
                        clanged.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-34"/>
                    <p tid="44">Then the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta
                        went before the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha. Prostrating with
                        their heads to the Blessed One’s feet, they respectfully stood to one side. Standing together, the two
                        holy beings said to the Blessed One, “The Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha
                        Śākyamuni has attained very stable powers. Blessed One, it is amazing. Blissful One, it is amazing. Why?
                        Blessed One, it is like this. When so much as the name of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Śākyamuni was pronounced, even this inanimate earth shook in six ways.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-35"/>
                    <p tid="45">The Thus-Gone Amitābha said to the two holy beings, “Sons of noble family, not only was the name
                        of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni pronounced in this buddha
                        realm, the name of that Blessed One was also pronounced in many other buddha realms. Those buddha realms,
                        too, all shook in six ways when touched by that light. In those buddha realms, limitless and countless
                        beings heard the name of the Thus-Gone Śākyamuni, <ref cRef="F.215.a"/> and thereby perfected their
                        roots of virtue and rendered irreversible their progress to unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening.
                        Then, from among the assembly of bodhisattvas, four hundred million bodhisattvas heard the name of the
                        Blessed One, the thus-gone Śākyamuni. When they heard it, they all gathered and, in a single voice,
                        dedicated the roots of virtue toward unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening. The Blessed One also
                        prophesied that they would render irreversible their progress to unsurpassed and completely perfect
                        awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-36"/>
                    <p tid="46">Then the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta
                        said to the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha, “The Blessed One, the thus-gone
                        Śākyamuni, has sent forth a light that we have previously never seen nor heard of. Now, since the Blessed
                        One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, would not emit such a wonderful and
                        beautiful light without causes or circumstances, please tell us what the causes and conditions are for the
                        Blessed One, the thus-gone Śākyamuni, to send forth such a wonderful and beautiful light.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-37"/>
                    <p tid="47">The Thus-Gone Amitābha said to the two holy beings, “Sons of noble family, what you say is true.
                        That Blessed One would not send forth such a wonderful and beautiful light without any causes and
                        conditions. And why? Because the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni,
                        is about to deliver a Dharma teaching on how to accomplish the precious absorption known as ‘the
                        bodhisattvas’ application.’ That is why <ref cRef="F.215.b"/> the Blessed One Śākyamuni
                        emitted this wonderful and beautiful light as an omen of that Dharma teaching.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-38"/>
                    <p tid="48">Then the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta
                        said to the Thus-Gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha, “In order to gaze upon, honor,
                        venerate, and serve the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, and also
                        to hear his Dharma teaching, we, Blessed One, will travel to that Sahā world.” </p>
                    <p tid="49">The thus-gone one Amitābha said, “Sons of noble family, you know that the time has come for the
                        Blessed One, the thus-gone Śākyamuni, to teach the Dharma to an assembly headed by the two of you, so
                        please do go ahead.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-39"/>
                    <p tid="50">With this permission, the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta called out to the four hundred million bodhisattvas assembled in the retinue of the
                        Blessed One, the thus-gone Amitābha, “Sons of noble family, come! In order to behold, honor, venerate, and
                        serve the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, and also to hear his
                        Dharma teaching, let us travel to the Sahā world. Why? Because the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy,
                        completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, gave up all the many perfectly pure buddha realms and, through his
                        aspirations and great compassion, manifested in that afflicted buddha realm. Because he undertook
                        austerities, it was amidst those sentient beings who have base desires and raging attachment, anger, and
                        delusion, <ref cRef="F.216.a"/> that he fully awakened to unsurpassed and completely perfect buddhahood.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-40"/>
                    <p tid="51">As soon as the two holy beings had spoken these words, all of the bodhisattva great beings in the
                        world of Sukhāvatī assembled and said in a single voice, “Blessed One, any being who even hears the name
                        of the Blessed One, the thus-gone Śākyamuni, reaches excellent attainments. That being so, what need is there
                        to mention those who actually see him with their physical eyes and engender faith? Blessed One, we shall
                        also travel to the Sahā world in order to behold, honor, venerate, and serve the Blessed One, the
                        thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, and also to hear his Dharma teaching.” </p>
                    <p tid="52">The Blessed One said, “Sons of noble family, you know that the time has come, so please go ahead.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-41"/>
                    <p tid="53">So the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta set
                        out from the world of Sukhāvatī, surrounded and preceded by 840 million bodhisattvas. At that point they
                        manifested their miraculous powers, and by those miraculous powers 840 million bodhisattvas each emanated
                        840 million mansions. The miraculously manifested mansions were square, structured around four pillars,
                        even and well proportioned, and of excellent design. Each of the mansions was twelve leagues tall and
                        eight leagues wide. Some mansions were made of gold; <ref cRef="F.216.b"/> some were made of silver; some
                        were made of beryl; some were made of crystal; some were made of red pearl, emerald, and coral; some were
                        made of combinations of gold and silver; some were made of combinations of gold, silver, and beryl; some
                        were made of combinations of gold, silver, beryl, and crystal; some mansions were made of combinations of
                        gold, silver, beryl, crystal, and red pearl; some mansions were made of combinations of gold, silver,
                        beryl, crystal, red pearl, and coral; some mansions were made of combinations of gold, silver, beryl,
                        crystal, red pearl, coral, and emerald; some mansions were made of red sandalwood; some were made of
                        uragasāra sandalwood; some were made of aloeswood and sandalwood; some were made of black aloeswood and
                        sandalwood; some mansions were made of all types of sandalwood; some mansions were made of blue lotuses,
                        pink lotuses, water lily, and white lotuses; some mansions were made of flowers of nutmeg, jasmine,
                        magnolia, pāṭalam, mountain ebony, aloe flower, and gotaraṇi; some mansions were made of danuskari
                        flowers; some mansions were made of māndārava and mahāmāndārava flowers; some mansions were made of
                        flowers of pāruṣaka, mahāpāruṣaka, mañjuṣaka, mahāmañjuṣaka, roca, mahāroca, cakra, mahācakra, sarvacakra,
                        atyartha­śobhati­cakra, candra, mahācandra, atyartha­śobhati­candra, paramacandra, sthāla, and mahāsthāla;
                            <ref cRef="F.217.a"/> some mansions were made of all types of flowers; and some were made of flowers of
                        various colors, multiple colors, hundreds of thousands of colors, beautiful, pure, and shining. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-42"/>
                    <p tid="54">In each mansion were emanated 84,000 goddesses. Some of the goddesses held conches, drums, clay
                        kettle drums, wooden kettle drums, lutes, and flutes, while others sang melodiously, and yet others held
                        up reed pipes, one-stringed lutes, and three-stringed lutes. In this way they were playing instruments,
                        singing songs, and making music in abundance. Some goddesses were holding vessels of powdered red
                        sandalwood; some goddesses were holding vessels of powdered uragasāra sandalwood; some goddesses were
                        holding vessels of powdered aloeswood and sandalwood; some goddesses were holding vessels of powdered
                        black aloeswood and sandalwood; some goddesses were holding vessels of all types of powdered sandalwood;
                        some goddesses were holding vessels of powdered blue lotuses, pink lotuses, water lilies, and white
                        lotuses; some goddesses were holding vessels of powdered flowers of māndārava, mahāmāndārava, pāruṣaka,
                        mahāpāruṣaka, mañjuṣaka, mahāmañjuṣaka, roca, mahāroca, cakra, mahācakra, sarvacakra,
                        atyartha­śobhati­cakra, candra, mahācandra, atyartha­śobhati­candra, paramacandra, sthāla, and mahāsthāla;
                        some goddesses were proffering vessels of all types of powdered flowers, perfume, incense, flower
                        garlands, and ointments. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-43"/>
                    <p tid="55">In each mansion appeared an ornately decorated lion throne upon which the form of a thus-gone one
                        was seated, adorned with the thirty-two marks of a great being. <ref cRef="F.217.b"/> In each of the
                        mansions appeared 84,000 pearl garlands, made of white, red, and blue pearls. In each of the mansions
                        appeared 84,000 victory banners made of divinely manufactured fabric, each of them covered in a lattice of
                        small golden bells. In each of the mansions appeared 84,000 censers of incense. In each of the mansions
                        appeared 84,000 parasols of various colors, multiple colors, hundreds of thousands of colors, beautiful,
                        well-crafted, and of fine proportions. In each of the mansions appeared 84,000 rows of palm trees. In each
                        of the mansions appeared 84,000 jewel trees. In each of the mansions appeared 84,000 lattices of small
                        bells that, when stirred by the wind, sounded tunes resembling the music performed by skilled musicians
                        playing trillions of divine instruments. Such were the sweet and beautiful tunes that rang out from those
                        bells when stirred by the wind. In each of the mansions appeared ponds, the bottom of each lined with gold
                        dust, adorned with beryl and crystal, and encircled by a ring of the seven precious gemstones. The ponds
                        were filled with blue and pink lotuses, water lilies, and white lotus flowers, and on them were wild geese
                        calling out. The ponds were filled to the brim with water of eight properties, making them excellent for
                        the birds to quench their thirst. Each of the mansions was surrounded by seven rows of jewel trees, and
                        84,000 jewel strings bound them all together. The light shining from each of the mansions extended for
                        84,000 leagues. Such was the layout of all the mansions. <ref cRef="F.218.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="56">Inside each of those mansions, the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva
                        great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta then again emanated the entire display of all the mansions that they had
                        produced, along with all of their elaborate internal contents, in a precise copy. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-44"/>
                    <p tid="57">Once the two bodhisattva great beings had emanated those displays inside each of the mansions, the
                        displays together with 840 billion bodhisattvas all vanished from the world of Sukhāvatī and arrived here
                        in this Sahā world in just a single moment, a single second, a single instant. It happened as quickly as
                        it takes for a strong person to extend his arm and flex it again. At that point the two bodhisattvas
                        miraculously transformed this Sahā world so that it became as even as the palm of a hand. Such was the
                        miracle that they manifested. All the bodhisattvas also arrived together with the 840 million mansions.
                        This great display of qualities was absolutely resplendent. The light that shone from the mansions
                        pervaded this entire trichiliocosm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-45"/>
                    <p tid="58">Then the two bodhisattvas went before the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Śākyamuni. They prostrated with their heads at the feet of the Blessed One, the thus-gone,
                        the worthy, completely perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, and circumambulated him three times before standing off
                        to one side. As they stood there, those two holy beings, <ref cRef="F.218.b"/> in a single tune and a
                        single voice, praised the Blessed One with these verses: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-46"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“We prostrate to your unrivaled splendor, your mass of qualities! </l>
                        <l>Great Omniscient Sage, you have perfected all good qualities.</l>
                        <l>You outshine everyone and transcend the desirous path of the three realms.</l>
                        <l>Supreme leader of the Śākyas, we prostrate before your stainless, moon-like face.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-47"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“Your body is beautiful, like the stainless sun.</l>
                        <l>You wear the armor of the thirty-two perfect signs,</l>
                        <l>And light up the world with your adornments, the excellent marks.</l>
                        <l>Perfect man, no one in the three worlds can compare to you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-48"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“When faced by the light from the body of the Blissful One,</l>
                        <l>The light of the sun, the moon, every jewel and fire in the world,</l>
                        <l>That of any human, or gods like Śakra and Brahmā,</l>
                        <l>Is eclipsed, dimmed, and shines no more than a pool of ink.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-49"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“Victorious One, while present in one realm,</l>
                        <l>You instantaneously go to limitless others for the sake of beings.</l>
                        <l>No one can comprehend the departure and arrival of the teacher.</l>
                        <l>Your many deeds and disciplines tame beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-50"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“In a single pore you can display limitless realms,</l>
                        <l>Yet nothing increases or decreases.</l>
                        <l>This is beyond the workings of karma, cause and effect.</l>
                        <l>No being is harmed, and nothing is confused.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-51"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“To some supreme beings you display the pure lands,</l>
                        <l>Where there are no hell beings, animals, or pretas,</l>
                        <l>And which are full of the renowned sons of the victorious ones—</l>
                        <l>A realm of perfect delight beyond the eight unfree states.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-52"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“To remedy others, gods and humans lacking fear and careless in their ways,</l>
                        <l>Once you show them the unbearably afflicted realms,</l>
                        <l>The states to which they could go as hell beings, animals, and pretas,</l>
                        <l>They all take refuge fully in the Blissful One. <ref cRef="F.219.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-53"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“In some other realms you manifest in the form of space;</l>
                        <l>Likewise, in other realms you blaze in the form of fire and flames.</l>
                        <l>You manifest by filling other realms with water—</l>
                        <l>These emanations are the domain of omniscient wisdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-54"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“In order to tame others you display limitless forms.</l>
                        <l>To some you appear in the shining form of the Lord of Desire,</l>
                        <l>Lord of the Brahma realm who attained the supremely peaceful absorption,</l>
                        <l>And the Lord of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, the thousand-eyed blazing vajra.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-55"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“Many hundreds of beings are delighted and worship you;</l>
                        <l>Through the ten virtues, limitless beings are tamed.</l>
                        <l>You are supreme among ministers, merchants, and royal counselors;</l>
                        <l>Fearless when enemies descend, you are unharmed by their attacks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-56"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“With the four means of attracting disciples, you gather beings</l>
                        <l>And establish them on the path to perfect awakening.</l>
                        <l>Through meritorious action you become a universal monarch</l>
                        <l>Who masters the four continents in possession of the seven riches.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-57"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>“To some, here in this world, you demonstrated birth,</l>
                        <l>And taking seven steps over the ground,</l>
                        <l>With your beautiful voice endowed with eight aspects, you said:</l>
                        <l>‘This birth of mine will bring an end to birth and death.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-58"/>
                    <lg tid="71">
                        <l>“During the time of Dīpaṃkara you had abandoned all defilements,</l>
                        <l>And yet, to ripen beings for the supreme wisdom of awakening,</l>
                        <l>To some you stayed, a pure being, amidst a retinue of queens.</l>
                        <l>Lord of Men, you also taught the queens and your son.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-59"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>“You gave up your parents, your cherished retinue of friends and relatives,</l>
                        <l>Your kingdom, wealth, and many treasuries of jewels.</l>
                        <l>Śakra, Brahmā, and the demigods revered you;</l>
                        <l>Great Sage, you left home and lived in the forest.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-60"/>
                    <lg tid="73">
                        <l>“To benefit beings, for six years you underwent hardship, <ref cRef="F.219.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Focused in supreme and precious all-pervasive concentration.</l>
                        <l>In order to defeat all the hordes of extremists,</l>
                        <l>You, a pure being, went to the foot of the Bodhi tree.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-61"/>
                    <lg tid="74">
                        <l>“In order to ripen beings for the supreme wisdom of a buddha,</l>
                        <l>Lord of Men, you entered into the supreme illusory absorption;</l>
                        <l>Victorious One, you took on a physical appearance</l>
                        <l>Of such a kind that would tame the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-62"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>“Just as an illusionist, in order to trick others,</l>
                        <l>Will produce many illusory manifestations, so too, you,</l>
                        <l>Lamp of the World, in order to tame beings</l>
                        <l>Produced the many manifestations of your buddhahood.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-63"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>“Heroic Sage, to some you showed the taming of Māra and his armies,</l>
                        <l>And did what no one else out of all the extremist hosts has done:</l>
                        <l>You attained immaculate omniscience beyond nirvāṇa,</l>
                        <l>And turned the unsurpassable and unchanging wheel.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-64"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>“Over many billions of eons you discovered awakening;</l>
                        <l>On all paths you turned the wheel.</l>
                        <l>Lord of Men, like a moon reflected in water, you appear to all;</l>
                        <l>Self-Originated Blissful One in infinite places, we prostrate to you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-65"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>“To some, you show the Dharma body of a Buddha,</l>
                        <l>The permanent, stable, enduring, unchanging,</l>
                        <l>Immutable, unborn, stainless, and unceasing Dharma.</l>
                        <l>It pervades all the ten directions, which are like an optical illusion.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-66"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>“To some you say, ‘In no time at all, you will be separated from your loved ones,</l>
                        <l>So it is no good for you to put your trust in this compounded world.’</l>
                        <l>And thus you show them how all beings are like a dream, an illusion, a mirage,</l>
                        <l>And impermanent, unstable, and momentary.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-67"/>
                    <lg tid="80">
                        <l>“The physical activity of the Blissful One knows no bounds or borders;</l>
                        <l>The domains of your verbal and mental activity are also unfathomable. <ref cRef="F.220.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Like the sky, the deeds of the Teacher are impossible to measure;</l>
                        <l>The domain of the Victorious One cannot be understood by sentient beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-68"/>
                    <lg tid="81">
                        <l>“Even if all the beings throughout the ten directions</l>
                        <l>Were as knowledgeable as Śāriputra,</l>
                        <l>They could not fathom the limitless scope of the victorious Dharma King’s nature,</l>
                        <l>Nor the entirety of the Victorious One’s domain.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-69"/>
                    <lg tid="82">
                        <l>“The wisdom of the perfect Buddha is limitless like the sky,</l>
                        <l>And the experience of the victorious ones is entirely inconceivable.</l>
                        <l>The assemblies of sons of the victorious ones, hearers,</l>
                        <l>And <term>circumstantial victorious ones</term>
                            <note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-247">
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rkyen gyi rgyal ba</foreign>, a term that from the context is very likely a synonym of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyeka­buddha</foreign>
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rang sangs rgyas</foreign>). The term is found only in
                                one other canonical text, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūrya­garbha­mahā­vaipulya­sūtra</title>
                                (Toh 257). The Sanskrit equivalent would be <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyaya­jina</foreign>, which is rare or unknown, but <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyaya­buddha</foreign> is well attested. Norman (1997, p. 87) has argued that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyaya­buddha</foreign>, or <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">pacceya­buddha</foreign> in Pali, may have been the original, more correct form of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyeka­buddha</foreign>.</note> cannot comprehend it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-70"/>
                    <lg tid="83">
                        <l>“Thus you show them boundless physical deeds,</l>
                        <l>Skillfully performed to tame infinite beings.</l>
                        <l>You have bodies as infinite as the element of space.</l>
                        <l>Protector devoid of concept and thought, we prostrate to you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-71"/>
                    <lg tid="84">
                        <l>“You have crossed to the other shore of the vast ocean of suffering.</l>
                        <l>We praise you, Victorious One, tamer of disturbing emotions, and foremost being.</l>
                        <l>May all the merit gained thereby go to all beings</l>
                        <l>So that they may reach precious, supreme, peaceful, and blissful awakening!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-72"/>
                    <p tid="85">When the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta
                        had praised the Blessed One with these fitting verses, they asked the Blessed One about his health, saying,
                        “The Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha is asking if the Blessed One is in
                        good health. Are you free from any misfortune and agitation? Are you enjoying good health and well-being?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-73"/>
                    <p tid="86">They also said, “Hearers of the Blessed One, behold how delightful the world has become.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="87">When the bodhisattvas and great hearers here in the Sahā world <ref cRef="F.220.b"/> saw the great
                        display of mansions that pervaded this entire world, as well as its many riches, they were amazed and
                        thought to themselves, “Is it due to the power of the Thus-Gone One, or is it due to the power of these
                        bodhisattva great beings, that all of this has arrived here from the world of Sukhāvatī?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-74"/>
                    <p tid="88">At that point, inspired by the Buddha, the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha asked the
                        Blessed One, “Blessed One, all these many mansions that now fill up and adorn this Sahā world are amazing!
                        Blissful One, they are truly amazing! Did all of this arrive here in the Sahā world from the world of
                        Sukhāvatī due to the power of the Thus-Gone One or due to the power of these bodhisattvas?” </p>
                    <p tid="89">The Blessed One answered the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha, “Padmaśrīgarbha, that these
                        many jewel mansions now fill up and adorn this Sahā world is not due to the power of the Thus-Gone One.
                        Rather, it is due to the power of the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great
                        being Mahā­sthāmprāpta.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-75"/>
                    <p tid="90">Padmaśrīgarbha exclaimed, “Because of their power, this Sahā world is now filled and adorned with
                        these many jewel mansions. The perfection of the aspirations and roots of virtue of these two holy beings
                        is inconceivable! Blessed One, it is amazing! Blissful One, it is truly amazing!” </p>
                    <p tid="91">
                        <ref cRef="F.221.a"/> “Padmaśrīgarbha, it is just as you say,” said the Blessed One. “For
                        innumerable trillions of eons, these two holy beings have perfected the roots of virtue. Padmaśrīgarbha,
                        these two holy beings have attained the illusory absorption. As they abide within the illusory absorption,
                        they can demonstrate such miraculous emanations. Padmaśrīgarbha, when you look toward the east, what do
                        you see?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-76"/>
                    <p tid="92">When the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha looked toward the east with the unobscured divine
                        eye of a bodhisattva, he saw as many buddha realms as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges, with
                        as many blessed buddhas as there are grains of sand in the river Ganges. At the feet of all of those
                        blessed buddhas were the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta, prostrating and inquiring about their health, saying, “The Blessed One, the thus-gone,
                        worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha is asking if the Blessed One is in good health. Are you free
                        from any misfortune and agitation? Are you enjoying good health and well-being?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-77"/>
                    <p tid="93">The same thing occurred in the south, in the west, in the north, below, above, and in all the ten
                        directions. In all directions Padmaśrīgarbha saw as many buddha realms as there are grains of sand in the
                        Ganges River, filled with and adorned by a great display of mansions made of various precious substances.
                        In all those buddha realms he saw blessed buddhas, and he witnessed the two holy beings prostrating before
                        all those blessed buddhas. As he saw this, he was filled with great wonder. </p>
                    <p tid="94">The bodhisattva great being <ref cRef="F.221.b"/> Padmaśrīgarbha was amazed, and exclaimed to the
                        Blessed One, “The accomplishment of the illusory absorption by these two holy beings is inconceivable!
                        Blessed One, it is amazing! Blissful One, it is truly amazing! Why do I say so? Because these two holy
                        beings abide in that absorption, and thus are present in all buddha realms.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-78"/>
                    <p tid="95">The Blessed One then produced a miraculous display so that the bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha could
                        see the buddha realms in all ten directions. He could also behold blessed buddhas in those buddha realms,
                        and he saw how the two holy beings prostrated at the feet of the blessed ones. In a similar way, the
                        entire retinue present could see the buddha realms in all ten directions, behold the blessed buddhas in
                        those buddha realms, and see the two holy beings prostrated at the feet of the blessed ones. Witnessing
                        this, thirty-two thousand beings in the retinue of the Blessed One developed the mind set on unsurpassed
                        and completely perfect awakening. Such were the miracles that the Blessed One produced. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-79"/>
                    <p tid="96">Then the bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, from which thus-gone one
                        did these two holy beings develop the mind set on unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening? And how
                        long ago was that? What was his name? Blessed One, thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha, please
                        tell us!” </p>
                    <p tid="97">The Blessed One replied, “It is thus that other bodhisattvas, too, should perfect their conduct,
                        actions, and aspirations. <ref cRef="F.222.a"/> Therefore, Padmaśrīgarbha, listen very well and keep in
                        mind what I will now explain.” </p>
                    <p tid="98">The bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha said, “Blessed One, excellent!” and he listened as the Blessed One
                        had advised. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-80"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Padmaśrīgarbha,” continued the Blessed One, “previously, in times past, an inconceivable number of
                        eons ago, an endless number of eons ago, at a time stretching further back than any number of eons, a
                        number of eons so great that the number of atoms found in 100,000 worlds—all the limitless and
                        inconceivable number of such atoms—would not equal the number of eons, there was a world called Boundless
                        Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of Happiness. In that world was a blessed, thus-gone,
                        worthy, completely perfect buddha who had perfect knowledge and conduct. He was a blissful one who knew
                        the world, an unsurpassed charioteer who trained beings, and a teacher of gods and men. His name was
                        Blessed Buddha King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-81"/>
                    <p tid="100"> “Padmaśrīgarbha, in the buddha realm of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect
                        Buddha King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, there was a display of precious qualities. I will only give
                        you a mere illustration of this, just to mention a few of the qualities, so listen. Padmaśrīgarbha, tell
                        me, are there many displays of precious qualities in the buddha realm of the Blessed One, the thus-gone,
                        worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha?” </p>
                    <p tid="101">Padmaśrīgarbha replied, “Blessed One, there are indeed—inconceivably many. They are limitless,
                        and it would not be easy to describe them in words.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-82"/>
                    <p tid="102">The Blessed One said, “Padmaśrīgarbha, consider this analogy. Imagine a person splits the tip of
                        a hair into one hundred pieces, and then uses the tip of one of those pieces to lift up one drop of water
                        from the ocean. <ref cRef="F.222.b"/> Tell me now, Padmaśrīgarbha, which would be greater, the amount of
                        water that has been extracted or the water that remains?” </p>
                    <p tid="103">Padmaśrīgarbha replied, “Blessed One, the extracted water would be less. The amount remaining is
                        measureless.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-83"/>
                    <p tid="104">“Padmaśrīgarbha, think about this and understand it,” said the Blessed One. “The amount of water
                        extracted from the ocean in a single drop by that person using a hundredth of a hair tip represents the
                        displays of precious qualities in the buddha realm of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely
                        perfect Buddha Amitābha, while the body of water remaining in the ocean represents the displays of
                        precious qualities in Boundless Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of Happiness, the
                        buddha realm of the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha, King of the Golden-Hued
                        Lion’s Play. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-84"/>
                    <p tid="105">“His saṅgha of hearers was also endless. Right now the Thus-Gone Amitābha’s saṅgha of hearers is
                        said to be boundless, but the saṅgha of hearers belonging to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy,
                        completely perfect Buddha, King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, was a hundred thousand times larger than
                        that. His saṅgha of bodhisattvas was also of comparable size. That blessed, thus-gone one taught the
                        Dharma exclusively within the three vehicles. Padmaśrīgarbha, even if I had as many eons as there are
                        grains of sand in the Ganges River to describe the display of precious qualities in the buddha realm of
                        the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha, King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, as
                        well as the display of qualities of his hearers and the causes for their happiness, I would not run out of
                        things to say, and I would be unable to complete my description of the display of qualities in that buddha
                        realm. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-85"/>
                    <p tid="106">“Padmaśrīgarbha, <ref cRef="F.223.a"/> back then, during the life of the blessed Thus-Gone One,
                        King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, there was a virtuous and religious king who ruled over a thousand
                        worlds. He was known as Glorious Splendor. Padmaśrīgarbha, King Glorious Splendor had one billion sons.
                        All the young princes had the twenty-eight marks of a great being, and all of them had genuinely attained
                        unsurpassed and completely perfect awakening. Padmaśrīgarbha, King Glorious Splendor also had seventy-six
                        thousand pleasure groves for his enjoyment, while each of his sons had ten thousand pleasure groves.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-86"/>
                    <p tid="107">Then the bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, were there no women in
                        that buddha realm?” </p>
                    <p tid="108">“No, Padmaśrīgarbha, there were not,” answered the Blessed One. “In that buddha realm not even the
                        word ‘woman’ was heard. All those young princes had been born out of chastity. They were all born in a
                        miraculous manner. All those beings sustained themselves on the joy of concentration and the joy of the
                        Dharma, and in that buddha realm there was no gross type of food. Padmaśrīgarbha, King Glorious Splendor
                        had no formal duties, so together with his sons he worshipped the Blessed One for 840 trillion years. That
                        Blessed, Thus-Gone One knew the king’s good intentions, so he taught him how to gain expertise in the mode
                        of Dharma known as <distinct>the boundless seal</distinct>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-87"/>
                    <p tid="109">“Padmaśrīgarbha, you may wonder what that ‘expertise in the mode of Dharma known as <distinct>the
                            boundless seal</distinct>’ might be. Well, Padmaśrīgarbha, it is that bodhisattva great beings never
                        fail to strive for boundless activities. <ref cRef="F.223.b"/> They never fail to undertake boundless
                        efforts. And why? Because those bodhisattvas’ generosity is boundless. Their discipline is boundless.
                        Their patience is boundless. Their diligence is boundless. Their concentration is boundless. Their
                        knowledge is boundless. Their embrace of saṃsāra is boundless. Their love for beings is boundless. Their
                        display of realms is boundless. Their hearers are boundless. Their perfect forms are boundless. Their
                        voices are boundless. Their eloquence is boundless. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-88"/>
                    <p tid="110">“Padmaśrīgarbha, bodhisattvas will dedicate any root of virtue that has been created, even a
                        single instance of the thought of awakening, so that it becomes boundless. You may wonder how dedication
                        can make it boundless. Well, at the time bodhisattvas dedicate that root of merit to all sentient
                        beings, the non-birth of all those sentient beings is actualized, and it is through their passing into the
                        parinirvāṇa of a buddha that they will pass into parinirvāṇa. That, son of noble family, is called
                            <distinct>boundless dedication</distinct>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-89"/>
                    <p tid="111">“Their emptiness is boundless. Their signlessness is boundless. Their wishlessness is boundless.
                        Their lack of conditioned existence is boundless. In this way they are free of desire and liberated
                        within the realm of phenomena, the limit of reality. They are unborn, serene, free, beyond suffering, and
                        boundless. Son of noble family, in short, all phenomena are boundless. Therefore all phenomena are said to
                        be unborn and unceasing. Whatever is unborn and unceasing is boundless. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-90"/>
                    <p tid="112">“Padmaśrīgarbha, the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha, King of the
                        Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, taught King Glorious Splendor perfectly how to gain expertise in the mode of
                        Dharma known as <distinct>the boundless seal</distinct>, so that he, too, could reflect on the boundless
                        Dharma. Then, as King Glorious Splendor received the teaching on the boundless Dharma from that blessed
                        one, <ref cRef="F.224.a"/> he was satisfied and pleased. He rejoiced and was extremely delighted. Since he
                        was so joyful and happy, together with his sons he praised that blessed one with these verses: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-91"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“ ‘Guide, you are the master of all dharmas.</l>
                        <l>You conquer the hordes of theoreticians;</l>
                        <l>You eliminate all of the demons’ disputes and disturbing emotions.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, incomparable ocean of wisdom.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-92"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“ ‘The sun, the moon, and the light of fires,</l>
                        <l>The radiance of Śakra, Brahmā, jewels, and lightning,</l>
                        <l>Are eclipsed by the splendor of the Blissful One.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, luminous leader of men.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-93"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“ ‘Sage, throughout an ocean of eons,</l>
                        <l>You perform many hardships.</l>
                        <l>Since the result of that activity is so beautiful,</l>
                        <l>Beings never tire of beholding you.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-94"/>
                    <lg tid="116">
                        <l>“ ‘Seeing that beings are pained by many sufferings,</l>
                        <l>And tormented by birth, old age, sickness, and death,</l>
                        <l>Great sage, your compassion for them</l>
                        <l>Will never change as you teach the Dharma of peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-95"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“ ‘You are like a physician for all beings in the three existences;</l>
                        <l>You purify all attachment, anger, and darkness.</l>
                        <l>Dharma physician, you develop compassion</l>
                        <l>And teach on the unsurpassed state of peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-96"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“ ‘You know well all beings’ actions.</l>
                        <l>Since you understand everyone in the infinite worlds,</l>
                        <l>You teach the Dharma that brings them</l>
                        <l>To supreme nirvāṇa.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-97"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>“ ‘Supreme man, your compassion is such</l>
                        <l>That it is a compassion unrivaled</l>
                        <l>By all hearers and conditioned sages</l>
                        <l>In all the infinite worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-98"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“ ‘A gathering of merit endowed with the supreme marks,</l>
                        <l>The body of the Victor is like a golden mountain,</l>
                        <l>More splendorous than ten million suns.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, unrivaled perfect man.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-99"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“ ‘When from the expansive cloud of Dharma<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-248">While most other Kangyurs have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sprin rgyal
                                    las</foreign>, the Degé Kangyur has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sprin rgya
                                    las</foreign>, and the Stok Palace Kangyur <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos sprin
                                    rgyas las</foreign>. The latter two readings seem more likely.</note> the rain of teachings
                            falls,</l>
                        <l>Those who have the vast inclinations to be within its scope,</l>
                        <l>And were not intimidated by the acts of previous buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Always find themselves before the blissful one.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-100"/>
                    <lg tid="122">
                        <l>“ ‘During an inconceivable number of trillions of eons,</l>
                        <l>It is exceedingly difficult to behold the perfect man.</l>
                        <l>Yet through the workings of merit the mind is purified <ref cRef="F.224.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And the guides become visible.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-101"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“ ‘The bodies of the Victor fill the entire realm of phenomena </l>
                        <l>And are present in all infinite realms.</l>
                        <l>They know no actual coming or going,</l>
                        <l>And yet fill the world like a vessel.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-102"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>“ ‘You who see the truths and teach the ultimate,</l>
                        <l>You are a benefactor of the Dharma with a peaceful mind;</l>
                        <l>Having crossed over, you liberate others who were in bondage.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, Blissful One.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-103"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>“ ‘You have pulled out the tree of rebirth by its root;</l>
                        <l>You have reduced to rubble the massive mountain of pride;</l>
                        <l>You know no agitation and are beyond deceit and deception.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, who are completely at peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-104"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>“ ‘Perfect man, you have gone beyond all attachments,</l>
                        <l>And your realization is like earth, water, and fire.</l>
                        <l>Victor, you are impartial toward all beings.</l>
                        <l>We prostrate to you, who are like wind and space.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-105"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“ ‘Great sage, your qualities are like a treasure;</l>
                        <l>Your body appears from an ocean of merit.</l>
                        <l>Even if we had billions of eons to speak of them</l>
                        <l>We would be unable to exhaust the ocean of your qualities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-106"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“ ‘Gods and men worship your ocean of qualities,</l>
                        <l>And I with my sons offer worship as well.</l>
                        <l>By whatever merit accrues from worshipping the Victor,</l>
                        <l>May we become a great sage like you!’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-107"/>
                    <p tid="129">“Padmaśrīgarbha, on another occasion King Glorious Splendor was in his pleasure grove practicing
                        concentration, when two beautiful and captivating lotus flowers made of uragasāra sandalwood sprang up on either side of him. From those two lotus
                        flowers, two beings miraculously appeared: one bore the name Precious Mind, and the other was called
                        Perfect Wealth. They sat cross-legged in the flowers. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-108"/>
                    <p tid="130">“Padmaśrīgarbha, when King Glorious Splendor arose from his absorption, he saw those two beings
                        sitting there, cross-legged, and at the sight he spoke this verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>“ ‘Are the two of you gods or nāgas?</l>
                        <l>Or yakṣas, gandharvas, or kiṃnaras?</l>
                        <l>Or humans or nonhumans?</l>
                        <l>Friends, please answer this question.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-109"/>
                    <p tid="132">“Padmaśrīgarbha, <ref cRef="F.225.a"/> the being who had appeared on King Glorious Splendor’s
                        right replied with these verses to King Glorious Splendor: </p>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>“ ‘My friend, all phenomena are empty,</l>
                        <l>So why do you ask their names?</l>
                        <l>Since all phenomena are devoid of names,</l>
                        <l>What name are you asking for?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-110"/>
                    <lg tid="134">
                        <l>“ ‘In emptiness, there are no gods,</l>
                        <l>No nāgas or rākṣasas,</l>
                        <l>Nor any humans or nonhumans.</l>
                        <l>None of them exist within emptiness.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-111"/>
                    <p tid="135">“Padmaśrīgarbha, the other being then spoke to King Glorious Splendor in these verses:</p>
                    <lg tid="136">
                        <l>“ ‘Name is empty of name;</l>
                        <l>In names there are no names.</l>
                        <l>All phenomena are devoid of names,</l>
                        <l>And still they are described using names.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-112"/>
                    <lg tid="137">
                        <l>“ ‘Whatever nature a name might have</l>
                        <l>It cannot be seen or heard,</l>
                        <l>And no action can bring it to an end,</l>
                        <l>So what name are you asking for?<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-249">We are unsure
                                of the meaning in the two last lines of this verse.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-113"/>
                    <lg tid="138">
                        <l>“ ‘Conventionally names are formed,</l>
                        <l>And names are given and spoken.</l>
                        <l>Thus, my name is Precious Mind,</l>
                        <l>And he is Perfect Wealth.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-114"/>
                    <p tid="139">“Padmaśrīgarbha, once these two beings had spoken these verses, the king attained the five types
                        of clairvoyance. Together with King Glorious Splendor, the two beings then went before the Blessed One,
                        the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play. They prostrated with
                        their heads to the blessed one’s feet, circumambulated the blessed one three times, joined the palms of
                        their hands together, and stood to one side. Padmaśrīgarbha, these two beings then spoke these verses to
                        the blessed one, as if in a single voice: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-115"/>
                    <lg tid="140">
                        <l>“ ‘Victorious one, how should we venerate you?</l>
                        <l>Should it be with lotus flowers, perfume,</l>
                        <l>Flower garlands, clothing,</l>
                        <l>Or perhaps with food and drink?</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-116"/>
                    <lg tid="141">
                        <l>“ ‘Perfect buddha, foremost among men,</l>
                        <l>How should we venerate you?</l>
                        <l>Please teach us this point,</l>
                        <l>And we shall follow your advice!’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-117"/>
                    <p tid="142">“Padmaśrīgarbha, then the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha <ref cRef="F.225.b"/> spoke the following verses to the two beings:</p>
                    <lg tid="143">
                        <l>“ ‘If you give rise to the mind of awakening</l>
                        <l>In order to help all embodied beings,</l>
                        <l>You will be venerating the buddhas</l>
                        <l>With their thirty-two major marks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-118"/>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“ ‘A being may make offerings</l>
                        <l>By filling as many buddha realms</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in the Ganges River</l>
                        <l>With flowers for the protectors of the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-119"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“ ‘Yet if a person joins his palms</l>
                        <l>And bows to the mind of awakening,</l>
                        <l>His merit will be much larger</l>
                        <l>And know no bounds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-120"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“ ‘The one with superior intelligence has shown</l>
                        <l>The mind of awakening, precisely as it is.</l>
                        <l>There is no other comparable offering,</l>
                        <l>And no other similar glory.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-121"/>
                    <p tid="147">“Padmaśrīgarbha, once again the two beings addressed the blessed one in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“ ‘In the presence of the protector of the world,</l>
                        <l>We make a firm commitment.</l>
                        <l>Gods and men, listen</l>
                        <l>To this unsurpassed lion’s roar.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-122"/>
                    <lg tid="149">
                        <l>“ ‘However long it may have been </l>
                        <l> Since saṃsāra’s unknowable beginning,</l>
                        <l>For that long, even if it takes many eons,</l>
                        <l>We shall act for the welfare of beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-123"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“ ‘For as many eons as have passed</l>
                        <l>Since the very beginning, for that many eons</l>
                        <l>We shall act as you have taught</l>
                        <l>In order to help beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-124"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“ ‘If, from today on,</l>
                        <l>We should feel any desire,</l>
                        <l>We will have betrayed</l>
                        <l>The buddhas in the ten directions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-125"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“ ‘So, too, for any feelings of anger, dullness,</l>
                        <l>Jealousy, and avarice.</l>
                        <l>We shall always speak truthfully</l>
                        <l>And give up all lies.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-126"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“ ‘If, from today on,</l>
                        <l>Without attaining stainless awakening,</l>
                        <l>Our attitude should become like that of the hearers,</l>
                        <l>This pledge would have been a lie.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-127"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“ ‘We shall also abstain from</l>
                        <l>Delighting in the ways of solitary buddhas.</l>
                        <l>For ten million eons,</l>
                        <l>We shall feel compassion for beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-128"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“ ‘Guide, just as your realm</l>
                        <l>Has tens of millions of other qualities</l>
                        <l>Beyond these accomplishments,</l>
                        <l>So shall we, too, produce a perfect realm.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-129"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l>“ ‘In that realm there shall be no hearers,</l>
                        <l>Nor any guides who are solitary buddhas.</l>
                        <l>At that time, there shall only be bodhisattvas</l>
                        <l>Numbering tens of millions. <ref cRef="F.226.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-130"/>
                    <lg tid="157">
                        <l>“ ‘The beings who enjoy this realm</l>
                        <l>Will all be stainless.</l>
                        <l>As they hold the treasury of the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>They will perfect the dharmas of the Buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-131"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>“ ‘If things are certain to be like that,</l>
                        <l>And not in any other way,</l>
                        <l>May this entire earth shake</l>
                        <l>With its oceans and mountains.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-132"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“As soon as they said this,</l>
                        <l>The entire world shook,</l>
                        <l>And musical instruments all sounded</l>
                        <l>Without even being played.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-133"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“Billions of gods</l>
                        <l>Scattered a beautiful rain</l>
                        <l>Of a million flowers, powders,</l>
                        <l>Incense, and clothing.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-134"/>
                    <p tid="161">“Padmaśrīgarbha, you should not have any doubts or uncertainties as to whether the person who at
                        that time, at that point, was named King Glorious Splendor was somebody else. And why? Because at that
                        time, at that point, the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha Amitābha was named
                        King Glorious Splendor. Padmaśrīgarbha, you should also not think that at that time, at that point, the
                        two beings called Precious Mind and Perfect Wealth were anybody else. And why? Because at that time, at
                        that point, the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara was the being called Perfect Wealth, and the
                        bodhisattva great being Mahā­sthāmprāpta was the being called Precious Mind. Son of noble family, this was
                        the first time that these two beings developed the mind set upon unsurpassed and completely perfect
                        awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-135"/>
                    <p tid="162">Then the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, it is
                        amazing how these two holy beings, devoting themselves so much to the profound and without apprehending
                        their own names, have both been developing the mind of awakening for so long! How many other blessed
                        buddhas apart from that thus-gone one have these two holy beings served?” </p>
                    <p tid="163">“Son of noble family,” said the Blessed One, “it may be possible to count the number of grains of
                        sand in the Ganges River. <ref cRef="F.226.b"/> But it is not possible to count the blessed buddhas who
                        were venerated by those two holy beings since the time of that thus-gone one. That is how long these two
                        have been developing the mind of awakening. Those two holy beings wear inconceivable armor and possess
                        boundless skills. In fact it is impossible to comprehend the scope of those two beings’ qualities.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-136"/>
                    <p tid="164">Then the bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “From here, in which
                        direction is that world called Boundless Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of Happiness
                        where the Blessed One, the thus-gone King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play lived?” </p>
                    <p tid="165">The Blessed One said, “Son of noble family, at that time, at that point, the world of Sukhāvatī
                        in the west was that world called Boundless Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of
                        Happiness.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-137"/>
                    <p tid="166">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha requested of the Blessed One, “Please tell us what kind of
                        display of precious qualities the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, completely perfect Buddha manifested
                        in the buddha realm of those two holy beings in order to aid many beings, show love for the world, and
                        bring happiness and health to all, including gods and men. How were his perfect hearers? How long did they
                        live? What kind of enjoyments did they have? What was their radiance like? And what were the names of the
                        two holy beings after they awakened to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood? Why, you may wonder,
                        am I making this request? It is so that other bodhisattvas may hear the Thus-Gone One describe the great
                        aspirations of those two holy beings, <ref cRef="F.227.a"/> so that they, too, may perfect similar great
                        aspirations.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-138"/>
                    <p tid="167">The Blessed One said, “Son of noble family, the extent of the Thus-Gone One Amitābha’s life is
                        boundless. Even if you had a trillion eons to describe its limits, it would not be easy. Son of noble
                        family, although the life of the Thus-Gone One Amitābha is boundless, all compounded phenomena are empty,
                        unstable, without solidity, and fleeting. Therefore, son of noble family, in a distant future the Blessed
                        One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Amitābha will also pass into nirvāṇa. Though he will pass into
                        nirvāṇa, his sacred Dharma will remain for 84 trillion eons. Just as when he was alive, his passing into
                        nirvāṇa will also accomplish sentient beings’ roots of virtue to their full extent. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-139"/>
                    <p tid="168">“At that point, however, other sentient beings will no longer behold that thus-gone one. Yet the
                        bodhisattvas will obtain the absorption of remembering the Buddha. They will always and continuously
                        behold the Buddha and not be separate from him. Son of noble family, when Amitābha passes into nirvāṇa,
                        lotus flowers and trees made of the seven gems will emit several hundred Gates of Dharma similar to the
                        Dharma teachings that the thus-gone one taught. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-140"/>
                    <p tid="169">“Son of noble family, after the Thus-Gone One Amitābha has passed into nirvāṇa, there will come a
                        night when the sacred Dharma disappears. As soon as that happens, at the break of dawn on the very next
                        day, <ref cRef="F.227.b"/> the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara will awaken to unsurpassed and
                        perfect buddhahood at the foot of a Bodhi tree made of various gems. As he perfectly and completely
                        awakens, he will be known as Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja. The precious qualities displayed in
                        the buddha realm of the Thus-Gone One Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja will be so extensive that even
                        a thus-gone one who is otherwise able to recount how many grains of sand there are in the river Ganges
                        will not be able to be comprehend them. There are so many causes for happiness and the precious qualities
                        found in that buddha realm, but, son of noble family, let me just give you a brief illustration of their
                        number. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-141"/>
                    <p tid="170">“The display of precious qualities in the buddha realm of the Blessed One, the thus-gone King of
                        the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, which I described before, would not equal even one hundredth of this display
                        of qualities. Nor would it measure one thousandth, or ever one hundred thousandth of it. In fact no
                        number, analogy, or illustration would suffice. In this buddha realm even the names of hearers and
                        solitary buddhas do not exist. This buddha realm is entirely filled with bodhisattvas. Son of noble
                        family, even if one were to gather all of the hearers, solitary buddhas, and bodhisattvas of the Blessed
                        Amitābha, they would not equal even one hundredth of the bodhisattva saṅgha of the Blessed One, the
                        Thus-Gone One Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja. Nor would they measure one thousandth, or even one
                        hundred thousandth of that. In fact no number, analogy, or illustration would suffice. As for his
                        lifespan, it will be 96 trillion eons. The sacred Dharma that he teaches will remain for 630 million
                        eons.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-142"/>
                    <p tid="171">The bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, <ref cRef="F.228.a"/>
                        “Blessed One, will the name of that world also be Sukhāvatī?” </p>
                    <p tid="172">The Blessed One said, “No, son of noble family, it will not. That world will be called Complete
                        Gathering of Wealth. Son of noble family, during the lifetime of Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja,
                        until he passes into nirvāṇa, he will be worshipped by the bodhisattva Mahā­sthāmprāpta. After he passes
                        into nirvāṇa, that bodhisattva will uphold his sacred Dharma and propagate it, so that the sacred Dharma
                        may remain for long. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-143"/>
                    <p tid="173">"Later, when the sacred Dharma has disappeared in that buddha realm, Mahā­sthāmprāpta will awaken
                        there to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood. He will appear in that world as a thus-gone, worthy, perfect
                        buddha, a learned and virtuous being, a blissful one, someone who knows the world, an unsurpassed
                        charioteer who tames beings, a teacher of gods and men, a blessed buddha known as
                        Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja. Just as were the perfect bodhisattvas and the perfect environment
                        belonging to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja,
                        so will they be, precisely and without any difference, for the Blessed One, the thus-gone
                        Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja. His lifespan and the period of his sacred Dharma will also be the
                        same. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-144"/>
                    <p tid="174">“Any son or daughter of noble family who hears the names of the Blessed One, the thus-gone
                        Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja, or the Blessed One, the thus-gone
                        Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja, will render irreversible their progress to unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening. <ref cRef="F.228.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="175">“Padmaśrīgarbha, any woman who hears the account of how the Blessed One, the thus-gone King of
                        the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play, passed into nirvāṇa, and who hears the name of these two future buddhas, will
                        no longer have the identity of a woman, and after 400 million eons she will destroy saṃsāra. She will
                        render irreversible her progress to unsurpassed and perfect awakening. She will always see the Buddha,
                        listen to the Dharma, and serve the Saṅgha; and as she moves to the next life, she will take ordination.
                        She will recollect her past lives and attain unimpeded eloquence and retention.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-145"/>
                    <p tid="176">Then, from within the retinue, 960 million gods, men, and other beings called out in a single
                        voice, “We pay homage to all thus-gone ones: those yet to come, those who presently remain, and those in
                        the ten directions who have passed into nirvāṇa. We rejoice in their names!” And they continued, “Blessed
                        One, this entire gathering now engenders the mind of unsurpassed and perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <p tid="177">Then the Blessed One prophesied their unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Eight trillion four
                        hundred thousand million beings purified their eye of Dharma regarding phenomena so that it became
                        stainless and unobscured. Seven thousand monks freed their minds from defilements without further
                        clinging. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-146"/>
                    <p tid="178">Then, at that time, the bodhisattva great being Avalokiteśvara and the bodhisattva great being
                        Mahā­sthāmprāpta caused a miracle by which the entire retinue could see all the limitless, uncountable
                        blessed ones in the ten directions making prophecies for their unsurpassed and perfect awakening. <ref cRef="F.229.a"/> Such was the miracle that they performed. </p>
                    <p tid="179">At this spectacle, everyone present exclaimed, “Blessed One, we now see the extent to which these
                        two bodhisattva great beings are cared for by those blessed buddhas! It is amazing to see so many blessed
                        buddhas making prophecies regarding these two holy beings!” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-147"/>
                    <p tid="180">Then the bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, how much merit is
                        created when a son or daughter of noble family remembers this sūtra taught by the Thus-Gone One, carries
                        it, reads it, comprehends it, and extensively and genuinely teaches it to others?” </p>
                    <p tid="181">The Blessed One said, “Son of noble family, it could be asked what would be accomplished and what
                        would be the reason for me to reply to the question you have put to the Thus-Gone One. Son of noble
                        family, it is because base sentient beings may distrust the Thus-Gone One’s teachings, and will therefore
                        continue to meet with harm, unhelpful situations, unhappiness, and misfortune.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-148"/>
                    <p tid="182">Padmaśrīgarbha said, “Blessed One, in this assembly there are sons and daughters of noble family
                        who are dedicated to the vast, indeed extremely dedicated; this teaching will also appear to beings yet to
                        come. So it is for the sake of the welfare and happiness of many beings that I request the Thus-Gone One
                        to explain.” </p>
                    <p tid="183">The Blessed One said, “Padmaśrīgarbha, that being so, I ask you to listen well to what I will say
                        and keep it in mind.” </p>
                    <p tid="184">The bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha said, “Blessed One, excellent!” and he listened as the Blessed One
                        had instructed him. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-149"/>
                    <p tid="185">Then the Blessed One said, “Son of noble family, say there is a man who is strong, powerful, and
                        with great amounts of merit. Now, however many beings one may think there are in what one thinks of as the
                        realm of beings, the Thus-Gone One has said that there are many more than that; <ref cRef="F.229.b"/> it
                        is not like the realm of the earth. All those beings that person supports with his head, shoulders, or
                        hands for limitless tens of millions of eons. For as long as he lives, he offers them clothing and food,
                        and provides them with all types of pleasant provisions and services.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-250">We have not been able to translate this analogy with confidence. This
                            represents no more than our best guess at this passage</note> Now tell me, Padmaśrīgarbha, would that
                        man’s merit increase greatly on this basis?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-150"/>
                    <p tid="186">Padmaśrīgarbha said, “A lot of merit is created when just a single person develops a loving
                        attitude, even if only for as long as it takes him to snap his fingers. So how much more would be created
                        if someone embraces all beings with love and serves them with all necessities for their happiness for
                        endless, limitless, tens of millions of eons?” </p>
                    <p tid="187">The Blessed One said, “Padmaśrīgarbha, you should be inspired by this, and you should fully
                        understand it: any son or daughter of noble family who, immersed in faith and full of interest, develops
                        the mind of awakening based on a sūtra that the Thus-Gone One has taught, like this one, and takes hold of
                        the sūtra, remembers it, reads it, understands it, and teaches it extensively to others will, based on
                        that foundation, give rise to a much greater amount of merit.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-151"/>
                    <p tid="188">The bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha declared to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, when the Thus-Gone One
                        has passed into nirvāṇa, I will take hold of this sūtra, which has been taught by the Thus-Gone One, and
                        grasp it, read it, understand it, and teach it extensively to others.” </p>
                    <p tid="189">The bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha and the 960 million bodhisattvas then all declared, in a single
                        voice, “Blessed One, we too will take hold of this sūtra and grasp it, read it, understand it, <ref cRef="F.230.a"/> and teach it extensively to others.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-152"/>
                    <p tid="190">The Blessed One said to the bodhisattva Padmaśrīgarbha, “Padmaśrīgarbha, if any woman hears this
                        Dharma teaching, she will immediately be transformed from the state of a woman, unless there are the two
                        causative factors, jealousy and stinginess.” </p>
                    <p tid="191">Then Śakra, who is lord of the gods, Brahmā, who rules the Sahā world, the four great kings, and
                        many hundreds of thousands of gods scattered divine māndārava flowers on the Blessed One and the bodhisattva great beings. While playing
                        billions of divine instruments, they called out, “Those sentient beings who hear this Dharma teaching,
                        grasp it, and teach it extensively to others will reap a great profit.” </p>
                    <p tid="192">The Blessed One said, “Sons of noble family, what you have said is true. Any sentient being who
                        holds this Dharma teaching in their hands or hears it, and subsequently feels devotion for it, will give
                        rise to roots of virtue before ten thousand buddhas.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-153"/>
                    <p tid="193">Then a young girl named Viraja rose from her seat in the congregation and, motivated by
                        altruistic thoughts, announced, “Blessed One, with an altruistic motivation I have decided to give up any
                        jealousy and stinginess, and instead develop the mind of unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Blessed
                        Thus-Gone One, you speak the truth. Blessed One, if it is so that were I to become a buddha, and other
                        women should happen to hear this Dharma teaching, they will also be freed from being a woman as soon as
                        they hear it, to that end, Blessed One, may all my woman’s organs now disappear from my body, and those of
                        a man appear!” <ref cRef="F.230.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-154"/>
                    <p tid="194">Instantly the girl’s female organs vanished, and her body became that of a man, of whom the
                        Blessed One prophesied that his progress to unsurpassed and perfect awakening had now been rendered
                        irreversible, and that he would become a thus-gone one, a worthy one, a perfect buddha named Repeller of
                        All Disturbing Emotions. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="195"><!--modularPassage type=concludingPraise-->When the Blessed One had spoken this teaching, the
                        bodhisattva great being Padmaśrīgarbha, the monks, and the many bodhisattvas, as well as the world with
                        its gods, men, demigods, and gandharvas, rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had
                        said.<!--/modular passage-->
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="204">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-155"/>
                    <p tid="196">This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Illusory
                            Absorption</title>.</p>
                    <p tid="197">
                        <!--tibTranslators-->Translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholar Surendrabodhi and the
                        translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé.<!--/tibTranslators-->
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="205">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="206">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-004-156">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sgyu ma lta bu’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­māyopama­samadhi­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 130,
                        Degé Kangyur vol. 55 (mdo sde, da), folios 210b3–230b4. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-004-157">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sgyu ma lta bu’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo. bka’
                            ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">krung go’i
                            bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang</title> (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation
                        Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 55, pp. 552–600. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-004-158"> Dharmachakra Translation Committee (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Absorption That Encapsulates All Merit</title> (Toh 134). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha,
                        2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-004-159">Norman, K.R. <title xml:lang="en">A Philological Approach to
                        Buddhism</title>. London: School of Oriental and African Studies, 1997. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-055-004-160">Roberts, Peter, and Bower, Emily (trs.). <title xml:lang="en">The White
                            Lotus of Compassion</title>. 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming). </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-161">
                            <term>āmalakī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyu ru ra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱུ་རུ་ར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmalakī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-162">
                            <term>atyartha­śobhati­cakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu mdzes pa’i ’khor lo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་མཛེས་པའི་འཁོར་ལོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atyartha­śobhati­cakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-163">
                            <term>atyartha­śobhati­candra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu mdzes pa’i zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་མཛེས་པའི་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atyartha­śobhati­candra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-164">
                            <term>bodhi tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub shing </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཤིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhivṛkṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-165">
                            <term>cakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog ’khor lo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་འཁོར་ལོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Wheel”; here, a flower.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-166">
                            <term>candra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">candra</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Moon”; here, a flower.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-167" mode="marked">
                            <term>circumstantial victorious one</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rkyen gyi rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྐྱེན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">*pratyayajina</term>
                            <term type="definition">A being who attains victory (i.e. awakening) through specific circumstances.
                                Almost certainly a synonym for a solitary buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-168">
                            <term>eight unfree states</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi khom brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་ཁོམ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭākṣaṇāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Being born as a hell being, preta, animal, god, barbarian, human with wrong
                                views, where there is no buddha, or as a human with impaired faculties.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-169">
                            <term>four means of attracting disciples</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsdu ba’i dngos po bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྡུ་བའི་དངོས་པོ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catuḥsaṃgraha­vastu</term>
                            <term type="definition">Generosity, kind talk, meaningful actions, and practicing what one
                                preaches.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-170">
                            <term>illusory absorption</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ma lta bu’i ting nge ‘dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྱུ་མ་ལྟ་བུའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māyopama­samadhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The realization that all phenomena are illusory and empty, which occurs when a
                                bodhisattva understands the unborn nature of phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-171">
                            <term>mañjuṣaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ny+dzu Sha ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ཉྫུ་ཥ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mañjuṣaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-172">
                            <term>mental sign</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems kyi mtshan ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེམས་ཀྱི་མཚན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cittanimitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A high level of absorption reached through mastery of concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-173">
                            <term>paramacandra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba mchog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བ་མཆོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paramacandra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-174">
                            <term>pāruṣaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pa ru Sha ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པ་རུ་ཥ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāruṣaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-175">
                            <term>realm of phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The "sphere of dharmas," a synonym for the nature of things.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-176">
                            <term>roca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdog mdzes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མདོག་མཛེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">roca</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-177">
                            <term>roots of virtue</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i rtsa ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་རྩ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kuśalamūla</term>
                            <term type="definition">Wholesome actions that are conducive to happiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-178">
                            <term>sthāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">s+tha la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྠ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sthāla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-179">
                            <term>palm tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing ta la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ཏ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tāla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-180">
                            <term>ten virtues</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བ་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśakuśala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Abstaining from killing, taking what is not given, sexual misconduct, lying,
                                uttering divisive talk, speaking harsh words, gossiping, covetousness, ill will, and wrong
                                views.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-181">
                            <term>beryl</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bai dU rya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཻ་དཱུ་རྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaidūrya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-182">
                            <term>emerald</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">marakata</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-183">
                            <term>coral</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤུག</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-184">
                            <term>uragasāra sandalwood</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsan dan sbrul gyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཙན་དན་སྦྲུལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">uragasāra­candana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-185">
                            <term>aloe wood</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a ka ru </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་ཀ་རུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aguru</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-186">
                            <term>black aloe wood</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a ga ru nag po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་ག་རུ་ནག་པོ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-187">
                            <term>blue lotus</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ud pa la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨུད་པ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">utpala</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-188">
                            <term>water lily</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku mu da </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུ་མུ་ད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumuda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-189">
                            <term>nutmeg</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sna ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jāti</term>
                            <term type="definition">May also mean a type of jasmine.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-190">
                            <term>jasmine</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bar sha ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བར་ཤ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vārṣika</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-191">
                            <term>magnolia</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsam pa ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཙམ་པ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">campaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-192">
                            <term>pāṭalam</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skya snar </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱ་སྣར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pāṭalam</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-193">
                            <term>mountain ebony</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a ti mug ta ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་ཏི་མུག་ཏ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">atimuktaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-194">
                            <term>aloe flower</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ta ra ni </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏ་ར་ནི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">taraṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-195">
                            <term>gotaraṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">go ta ra ni </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གོ་ཏ་ར་ནི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gotaraṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-196">
                            <term>danuskari</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">da nu ska ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ད་ནུ་སྐ་རི།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-197">
                            <term>māndārava</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">man dA ra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མན་དཱ་ར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māndārava</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-198">
                            <term>sarvacakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu ’khor lo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་འཁོར་ལོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvacakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-199">
                            <term>twenty-eight marks of a great being</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyes bu chen po’i mtshan nyi shu rtsa brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེས་བུ་ཆེན་པོའི་མཚན་ཉི་ཤུ་རྩ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭa­viṃśati­mahā­puruṣa­lakṣaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A variation on the more usual set of 32 such marks; this set is mentioned only
                                in this sūtra and in three others: the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍa­vyūha</title> (ch. 45 of Toh
                                44), the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathā­gatācintya­guhya­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 47), and the longest
                                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­mati­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 153). None of these texts give a
                                list.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-200">
                            <term>Agnidatta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mes byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Agnidatta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-201">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-202">
                            <term>Amoghadarśin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthong ba don yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐོང་བ་དོན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amoghadarśin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-203">
                            <term>Anikṣiptadhura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson pa mi gtong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་པ་མི་གཏོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anikṣiptadhura</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-204">
                            <term>Anupamamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe med blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔེ་མེད་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anupamamati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-205">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-206">
                            <term>Bhadrapāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang skyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་སྐྱོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrapāla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-207">
                            <term>Bandé Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ban de ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བན་དེ་ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-208">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-209">
                            <term>Dharaṇīṃdhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharaṇīṃdhara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-210">
                            <term>Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མར་མེ་མཛད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṃkara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-211">
                            <term>Glorious Splendor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi gzi brjid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་གཟི་བརྗིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-212">
                            <term>Guhyagupta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phug sbas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུག་སྦས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhyagupta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-213">
                            <term>Harisiṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge’i seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེའི་སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Harisiṃha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-214">
                            <term>Jñānākara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes ’byung gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་འབྱུང་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānākara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-215">
                            <term>Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan shin tu gnas pa nor bu brtsegs pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་ཤིན་ཏུ་གནས་པ་ནོར་བུ་བརྩེགས་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Supra­tiṣṭhita­guṇa­maṇi­kūṭa­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">“King Jewel Mound Full of Enduring Qualities.” The name that Mahā­sthāmprāpta
                                will have when he becomes a tathāgata. The Sanskrit name is attested in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇā­puṇḍarīka­sūtra</title>, but in the Tibetan translation of that text
                                it is rendered as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rab tu brtan pa yon tan nor bu brtsegs
                                    pa’i rgyal po</foreign>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-216">
                            <term>Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer kun nas ’phags pa’i dpal brtsegs rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་ཀུན་ནས་འཕགས་པའི་དཔལ་བརྩེགས་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samanta­raśmyabhyudgata­śrī­kūta­rāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">“King of Heaped Splendors That Shine Above All.” The name that Avalokiteśvara
                                will have when he becomes a tathāgata. The Sanskrit name is attested in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇā­puṇḍarīka­sūtra</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-217">
                            <term>King of the Golden-Hued Lion’s Play</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser ’od seng ge’i rnam par rol pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསེར་འོད་སེང་གེའི་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-218">
                            <term>Mahā­sthāmaprāpta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu chen thob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་ཆེན་ཐོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sthāmaprāpta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-219">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-220">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-221">
                            <term>Padmaśrīgarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad ma’i dpal gyi snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མའི་དཔལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Padmaśrīgarbha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-222">
                            <term>Perfect Wealth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen mchog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་མཆོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-223">
                            <term>Precious Mind</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-224">
                            <term>Ratnākara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkon mchog ’byung gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཀོན་མཆོག་འབྱུང་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnākara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-225">
                            <term>Repeller of All Disturbing Emotions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs pa thams cad zlog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཟློག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-226">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-227">
                            <term>Śākyamuni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA kya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་ཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-228">
                            <term>Śāriputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-229">
                            <term>Siṃhamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃhamati</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-230">
                            <term>Su­pratiṣṭhita­buddhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs par gnas pa’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་པར་གནས་པའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Su­pratiṣṭhita­buddhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-231">
                            <term>Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">su ren dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surendrabodhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-232">
                            <term>Susīma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་བཟངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Susīma</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-233">
                            <term>Vairocana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par snang byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་སྣང་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vairocana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-234">
                            <term>Varuṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Varuṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-235">
                            <term>Vidyutdeva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glog lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གློག་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vidyutdeva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-236">
                            <term>Viraja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdul dang bral ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡུལ་དང་བྲལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viraja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-237">
                            <term>Boundless Accumulation of Precious Qualities and Full Display of Happiness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan rin chen bsag pa dpag tu med pa bde ba kun tu ston pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་རིན་ཆེན་བསག་པ་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ་བདེ་བ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྟོན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-238">
                            <term>Greater Mucilinda Mountains</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">btang bzung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཏང་བཟུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāmucilinda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-239">
                            <term>Hill of the Fallen Sages</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">drang srong lhung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲང་སྲོང་ལྷུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ṛṣipatana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-240">
                            <term>Mucilinda Mountains</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">btang bzung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཏང་བཟུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mucilinda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-241">
                            <term>Sahā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The present world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-242">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm in which Buddha Amitābha lives.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-055-004-243">
                            <term>Complete Gathering of Wealth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen kun nas bsags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཀུན་ནས་བསགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm in which Avalokiteśvara will become a fully enlightened
                                buddha. Probably the same as Sarvaratnasannicaya attested in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇā­puṇḍarīka­sūtra</title>, where the Tibetan rendering is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin
                                    po che tham cad yang dag par sags pa</foreign>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>