<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཆོས་བདུན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara­paripṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག་གིས་ཞུས་པ་ཆོས་བདུན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya
                    ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en"> The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven
                    Qualities”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryāvalokiteśvara­paripṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-35">Translated by the University of Calgary Buddhist Studies team<lb/> under the
                    patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-207">James B. Apple</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.26 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-057-009"/>
                <date>2014-10-31</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh150" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 150</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios 331.a – 331.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dīpaṃkaraśrījñāna</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Gewai Lodrö</author>
                    <location count-pages="2">
                        <start volume="57" page="663"/>
                        <end volume="57" page="664"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11741" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-21T14:33:44.925Z" user="admin">21/06/2019 14:33:44</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.25" date-time="2019-06-18T02:52:49.706Z" user="celso">v 1.25 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.26" date-time="2019-06-21T14:33:41.986Z" user="celso">v 1.26 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!--Contents											
		Summary												
	             Acknowledgments
		Introduction
		The Translation
		 The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities
		Notes
		Bibliography-->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="27">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-1"/>
                <p tid="1">The sūtra is introduced with the Buddha residing on Vulture Peak Mountain in Rājagṛha, together with a
                    great monastic assembly of 1,250 monks and a multitude of bodhisattva mahāsattvas. The Buddha is approached
                    and asked by the bodhisattva mahāsattva Avalokiteśvara about the qualities that should be cultivated by a
                    bodhisattva who has just generated the altruistic mind set on attaining awakening. The Buddha briefly expounds
                    seven qualities that should be practiced by such a bodhisattva, emphasizing mental purity and cognitive
                    detachment from conceptuality. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="28">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translation by the University of Calgary Buddhist Studies team. This sūtra was introduced and
                    translated by James B. Apple.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="29">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara‌ on the Seven Qualities</title>
                        <note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-50">Within the title, D, Go, He, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>, L have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug</foreign>; F, S, Z have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug</foreign>. Go has the title <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa
                                spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gyis zhus pa / byang chub sems dpa’i slab pa bdun pa</foreign> (“The
                            Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara: the Seven Points of a Bodhisattva’s Training”).</note> is a brief sūtra
                        describing seven qualities that should be cultivated by a bodhisattva immediately upon generating the
                        altruistic mind set on attaining awakening. The mind of awakening is the intention or resolution to attain
                        full and complete buddhahood for the benefit of oneself and all sentient beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The structure of the sūtra is in three parts: the opening formula that gives the time, place, and
                        Buddha’s retinue when the discourse was taught; the prescription of seven dharmas to be cultivated; and a
                        formulaic conclusion.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-5"/>
                    <p tid="6"> The Buddha delivers his teaching in response to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Avalokiteśvara’s
                        inquiry. What is unusual in the formulaic inquiry phrases of this sūtra is that Avalokiteśvara places his
                        right knee in the center of a lotus flower; in most sūtras that follow such a pattern, the questioner
                        places his knee on the ground. This implicitly demonstrates the reverence in which Avalokiteśvara was held
                        by the compilers or transmitters of this sūtra. The Buddha prescribes seven qualities or dharmas that one
                        should cultivate after producing the mind of awakening. They emphasize mental purity and cognitive
                        detachment from conceptuality. These prescriptions are straightforward and easy to understand according to
                        the overview of the sūtra by Pekar Sangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad dkar bzang po</foreign>, see
                        bibliography).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities</title> was initially translated
                        from an Indian language, most likely Sanskrit, into Tibetan by Atiśa Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna (982-1054) and
                        the Tibetan monk Gewai Lodrö.</p>
                    <p tid="8">The translation took place in all probability at the monastery of Tholing in West Tibet, where the
                        rulers of Ngari (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnga’ ris</foreign>) first officially welcomed
                        Atiśa and where Gewai Lodrö was active.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-51">See
                            Chattopadhyaya 1967: 325.</note> Gewai Lodrö collaborated with the great Kaśmīri scholar
                            <term>Subhūtiśrī</term>(śānti) in Tholing before working with Atiśa. Atiśa and Gewai Lodrö worked
                        together on several translations found in editions of the Tengyur, including the verses of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­patha­pradīpa</title> (<ref>Toh 3947</ref>) and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title> (<ref>Toh 3969</ref>), and two texts found in most Kangyurs,
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇḍi­samaya­sūtra</title> (<ref>Toh 299</ref>) and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­mahā­tantra­rāja</title> (<ref>Toh 544</ref>, <ref>Degé
                            541</ref>).<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-52">See Dharmachakra Translation Group
                            2016.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-7"/>
                    <p tid="9"> Atiśa makes explicit reference to this sūtra in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­mārga­pradīpa­pañjikā</title>, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title>,
                        and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­karaṇḍodghāṭa­nāma­madhyamakopadeśa</title> (<ref>Toh 3930, English
                            translation Apple 2010: 142-43</ref>). In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­mārga­pradīpa­pañjikā</title> this sūtra is mentioned in the sections discussing the mind of
                        awakening (Sherburne 2000: 101), the monastic life (Sherburne 2000: 127), and the supersensory knowledges
                        (Sherburne 2000: 209). The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cittotpāda­saṃvara­vidhikrama</title> also advocates
                        the practice of this sūtra’s prescriptions for a bodhisattva who wishes to attain supersensory knowledge
                        quickly (Sherburne 2000: 540-541).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-8"/>
                    <p tid="10">The present translation from Tibetan is based upon a critical edition of ten Kangyur exemplars. A
                        detailed philological analysis of the extant editions of this sūtra indicates that the oldest copies of
                        this sūtra are preserved among Western Kangyur collections such as the Gondhla Collection, Hemis Kangyur,
                        and Phudrak (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phug brag</foreign>) Kangyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="30">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="31">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="32">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the Seven Qualities </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-9"/>
                    <p tid="11">
                        <ref cRef="F.331.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to the Bhagavān Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="thusDid">-->Thus have I heard at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling in
                        Rājagṛha<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-53">Go, L, S, Z <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab na</foreign>; D, F, He, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi> <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab</foreign>
                        </note> on the Vulture Peak mountain<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-54">F, Go, L, S, Z
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod kyi phung po</foreign>; D, He, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi> <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po</foreign>
                        </note> together with a great monastic assembly of 1,250 monks and a multitude of bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas.<!--</modularPassage>--> At that time, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Noble Avalokiteśvara rose
                        from his seat, arranged his upper robe on one shoulder, and placed his right knee in the center of a lotus
                        flower. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">Joining his hands in devotion toward the Bhagavān, he asked him, “Bhagavān, in how many qualities
                        should a bodhisattva train, just after generating the altruistic mind set on attaining awakening?”<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-55"> F, Go, He, L, S, Z <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang
                            chub tu sems</foreign>; D, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi> <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="14">The Bhagavān replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Noble Avalokiteśvara’s inquiry with the
                        following words.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-12"/>
                    <p tid="15">“Kulaputra, bodhisattvas should train in seven qualities just after generating the altruistic mind
                        set on attaining awakening.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-56"> D, F, Go, He, L, S, Z
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu sems bskyed</foreign>; J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi> <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems bskyed</foreign>
                        </note> What are the seven? They are as follows. </p>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <p tid="20">“(1) One should not have sexual enjoyment even in thought, not to mention joining together
                                the two sexual organs. <ref cRef="F.331.b"/>
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="21">“(2) One should not take up with a non-virtuous friend even in dreams.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="22">“(3) With a mind free like a bird, one should be completely without grasping.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="23">“(4) With mastery in skill and wisdom, one should be without pride and reified conceptions
                                of ‘I.’ </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="24">“(5) One should abandon conceptions of existence and non-existence and be firm in the
                                emancipation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimokṣa</foreign>) of emptiness.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="25">“(6) One should not take delight in saṃsāra through an inauthentic conceptual
                                understanding, saṃsāra being like a magical illusion or dream.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <p tid="26">“(7) And one should refrain from deprecating the law of cause and effect. </p>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <p tid="16">“Kulaputra, a bodhisattva who has just generated the altruistic mind set on attaining
                        awakening<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-57">D, F, Go, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi> <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub tu sems bskyed</foreign>; He, L, S, Z <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems
                                bskyed</foreign>
                        </note> should train in these seven qualities.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-13"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="finalPraise">-->When the Bhagavān had spoken, the bodhisattva Noble
                        Avalokiteśvara, along with the monks and bodhisattvas, rejoiced and praised highly what had been
                        proclaimed by the Bhagavān.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                        <note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-58">Go omits <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa
                                spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug dang / dge slong de dag dang byang chub sems dpa’ de dag yi rangs te/
                                bcom ldan ’das kyis gsungs pa la mngon par bstod do</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-14"/>
                    <p tid="18">This completes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Inquiry of Avalokiteśvara on the
                        Seven Qualities</title>.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-59">D, F, He, J, K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>, L, S,
                            Z <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bdun pa</foreign>; Go <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang sems dpa’i /
                                slab pa bdun pa</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="33">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-60"/>
                    <p tid="19">Translated and edited by the Indian master Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna and the translator monk Gewai
                        Lodrö.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="34">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="35">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-15">
                        <abbr>MsK</abbr>
                        <expan>Manuscript Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-16">
                        <abbr>PK</abbr>
                        <expan>Printed Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-17">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (sde dge) PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-18">
                        <abbr>F</abbr>
                        <expan>Phug brag MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-19">
                        <abbr>Go</abbr>
                        <expan>Gondhla Collection MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-20">
                        <abbr>He</abbr>
                        <expan>Hemis MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-21">
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>Lithang PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-23">
                        <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Qianlong PK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-22">
                        <abbr>L</abbr>
                        <expan>London MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-24">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-009-25">
                        <abbr>Z</abbr>
                        <expan>Shey Palace MsK</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="36">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="37">Tibetan Kangyur Editions</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-26"> (rKTs = University of Vienna Resources for Kanjur and Tanjur Studies, <ref target="https://www.istb.univie.ac.at/kanjur/rktsneu/sub/index.php">https://www.istb.univie.ac.at/kanjur/rktsneu/sub/index.php</ref>.
                        For other abbreviations, see Notes.)</bibl>
                    <lb/>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-27">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo (Āryāvalokiteśvara­pari­pṛcchā­sapta­dharmaka­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra)</title>. Toh 150,
                        rKTs-K150, D 150, Degé Kangyur (PK) vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios 331a-331b. <ref target="http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W22084">tbrc.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-28">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, He48.6, Hemis Kangyur (He) (MsK), mdo sde, nga, folios 296b-299b.
                        Digital scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-29">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, J94, Lithang (li thang) Kangyur (J) (PK), vol. 52 (mdo sde, pa),
                        folios 278a-279a. <ref target="http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W4CZ7445">tbrc.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-30">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, Q 817, Peking Qianlong (K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>) (PK), vol. 33 (mdo sna tshogs, nu),
                        folios 293b-294b (p 36 in bound edition). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-31">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba theg
                            pa chen po’i mdo.</title> bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i
                        bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the
                        China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China
                        Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009, vol. 57, pp. 875-878.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-32">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug gyis zhus pa / byang chub sems dpa’i slab
                            pa bdun pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Go16,04, Gondhla Collection (Go) (MsK), vol. 16
                        (ka), folios 49a-49b. Digital scans from rKTs. See also Tauscher (2008) below.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-33">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, L154, London Kangyur (L) (MsK), vol. 52 (mdo sde, za),
                        folios 8b-9a. Digital scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-34">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, C790, Phug brag Kangyur (F) (MsK), vol. 80 (mdo sde, la),
                        folios 371b-372b. Institute for Advanced Studies of World Religions. 1990. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-35">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, Z242, Shey Palace Manuscript Kangyur (Z) (MsK), vol.69 (mdo,
                        za), folios 7a-8a. Digital scans from rKTs. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-36">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs kyi dbang phyug gis zhus pa chos bdun pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K150, S211, Stok Palace Manuscript Kangyur (stog pho brang bris
                        ma) (S) (MsK), vol. 73 (mdo sde, za) folios 7b-8b. TBRC W22083. 109 vols. leh: smanrtsis shesrig dpemzod,
                        1975-1980. <ref target="http://tbrc.org/link?RID=W22083">tbrc.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="38">Other references</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-37">Apple, James B. 2010. “Atiśa’s Open Basket of Jewels: A Middle Way Vision in
                        Late Phase Indian Vajrayāna.” <title xml:lang="en">The Indian International Journal of Buddhist Studies
                            11</title>: 117-198.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-38">Chattopadhyaya, Alaka. 1967. <title xml:lang="en">Atīśa and Tibet Life and
                            Works of Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna in relation to the History and Religion of Tibet.</title> (Reprinted) New
                        Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1999, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-39">Dharmachakra Translation Group. 2016. <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of
                            Siddhaika­vīra.</title> Toh 544, in Tantra / Tantra Collection / Action tantras. 84000: Translating
                        the Words of the Buddha.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-40">Pad dkar bzang po (author), mi nyag mgon po (editor). “ ’phags pa spyan ras
                        gzigs dbang phyug gis zhus pa’i chos bdun pa’i mdo.” In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde spyi’i rnam
                            bzhag</title>, p. 426. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang (Minorities Publishing House), 2006. TBRC
                        W1PD76588. <ref target="http://tbrc.org/link?RID=O2DB70299|O2DB702992DB70539$W1PD76588">tbrc.org</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-41">Sherburne, Richard. 2000. <title xml:lang="en">The Complete Works of Atīśa
                            Śrī Dīpaṃkara Jñāna, Jo-bo-rje: The Lamp for the Path and Commentary, together with the newly
                            translated Twenty-Five Key Texts (Tibetan and English Texts)</title>. New Delhi: Aditya
                        Prakashan.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-009-42">Tauscher, Helmut. 2008. <title xml:lang="en">Catalogue of the Gondhla
                            proto-Kanjur</title>. Vienna: Arbeitskreis für Tibetische und Buddhistische Studien Universität
                        Wien.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-43">
                            <term>generating the altruistic mind set on attaining awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems bskyed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས་བསྐྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicittotpāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The altruistic resolve to achieve complete and perfect Buddhahood for the sake
                                of oneself and all sentient beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-44">
                            <term>opening formula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gleng gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གླེང་གཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nidāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-45">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva who first appears in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī­vyūha</title> sūtra (Toh 115) and then in a number of other Mahāyāna sūtras such as
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sad­dharma­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113). <term type="ignore">Avalokiteśvara</term> develops into
                                a great bodhisattva who embodies compassion with multiple forms in Indian, Chinese, and Tibetan
                                Buddhism.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-46">
                            <term>Atiśa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a ti sha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་ཏི་ཤ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atiśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Atiśa</term> Dīpaṃkara­śrī­jñāna (982–1054 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), often referred to in Tibetan as
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jo bo</foreign>, “(The) Lord,” was a renowned figure in the history
                                of Tibetan Buddhism famous for coming to Tibet and revitalizing Buddhism there during the early
                                eleventh century.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-47">
                            <term>Gewai Lodrö</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Ma <term type="ignore">Gewai Lodrö</term> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma dge ba’i blo gros</foreign>), a
                                Tibetan lotsāva, was an important disciple of Rinchen Zangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen
                                    bzang po</foreign>, 958-1055) who translated several texts with Atiśa and worked with the
                                Kaśmīri master Subhūti­śri­bhadra to translate a number of pramāṇa texts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-48" mode="marked">
                            <term>Subhūtiśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                            <term xml:lang="bo"/>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūtiśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Subhūtiśrī(śānti) was a paṇḍita from Kaśmīr invited to Western Tibet during
                                the reign of the king Lha Dé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Lha lde</foreign>) who translated a
                                number of Prajñāpāramitā texts, sūtras, and works of pramāṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-009-49">
                            <term>Tholing</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tho ling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐོ་ལིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The important West Tibetan monastery founded in 996 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> by King Yeshé Ö
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes ’od</foreign>) and the translator Rinchen Zangpo (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bzang po</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>