<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog par 'jug pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avikalpapraveśa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Entering into Non-conceptuality</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">'phags pa rnam par mi rtog par 'jug pa zhes bya ba'i gzungs</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāvikalpapraveśanāmadhāraṇī</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Dhāraṇī Entitled “Entering into Non-conceptuality”</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog par 'jug pa'i gzungs/</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9"/>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">Dr. James Duncan
                    Gentry</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-257">Raynald
                    Prévèreau</editor>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-99">Thomas
                    Cruijsen</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.00 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-057-001"/>
                <date>2019-10-06</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh142" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 142</ref>
                    <biblScope>vol.57, ff.1r-6v(pp.1-12)</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="11">
                        <volume number="57" start-page="2" end-page="12"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11729" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-10-06T14:29:38.986Z" user="andre">06/10/2019 14:29:38</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2019-09-17T21:25:58.793Z" user="james">2.a</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-1"/>
                <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Dhāraṇī Entitled “Entering into
                        Non-conceptuality”</title> is a short Mahāyāna sūtra that came to be
                    particularly influential in Yogācāra circles. The central theme of the sūtra is
                    the attainment of the non-conceptual realm, which is reached through the
                    practice of relinquishing all conceptual signs by not directing the mind toward
                    them. The sūtra presents the progressive stages through which bodhisattvas can
                    abandon increasingly subtle conceptual signs and eliminate the erroneous ideas
                    that lead to the objectification of phenomena.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-2"/>
                <p tid="4">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Entering into Non-conceptuality</title> was translated by
                    the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of Chokyi Nyima
                    Rinpoche. Ryan Damron prepared the translation and introduction. Miguel Sawaya
                    compared the English translation with the Tibetan translation found in the Degé
                    Kangyur and edited the text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="6">Main Section</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</title> (APD), also known
                        by the synonymous title <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</title>, is a short but influential Mahāyāna
                            sūtra.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-4"> Though not explicitly identified as a Mahāyāna
                            sūtra, the APD states that it was taught to a gathering of bodhisattvas,
                            with the bodhisattva Avikalpaprabhāsa serving as the primary
                            interlocutor.</note> Despite being labeled a dhāraṇī, the text
                        demonstrates the style of a sūtra and is cataloged as such in the Tibetan
                        Kangyur collections. Though the genre of dhāraṇī is difficult to define, the
                        term is typically applied to Buddhist scriptures that contain a specific
                        mantra-like formula that is to be recited in order to bring about a desired
                        meritorious or even magical result. The APD contains no such formula and
                        otherwise bears little resemblance to the extensive body of scripture
                        preserved in the dhāraṇī section of the Tibetan Kangyur. It is possible,
                        however, to understand this designation by considering the basic meaning of
                        the Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhāraṇa</foreign>.
                        The term commonly means to “hold,” “uphold,” or “maintain,” and by extension
                        is frequently used in reference to memory and learning. In the context of
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</title>, the term
                            <distinct>dhāraṇī</distinct> identifies the text as a mnemonic support
                        for the Buddha’s discourse on non-conceptuality, presenting his teaching in
                        a manner that can be easily memorized and frequently recollected. As the
                        Buddha states at the beginning of the sūtra, a bodhisattva who keeps this
                        teaching in mind (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dhārayan</foreign>)
                        will make rapid progress on the path to buddhahood.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-5"/>
                    <p tid="8">A popular sūtra in both India and Tibet, the <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</hi> was particularly influential in Yogācāra
                        circles. From an early period it was closely associated with the Five
                        Treatises of Maitreya and is now widely considered a source text for
                        Maitreya’s <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</foreign>.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-6"> On the relationship
                            between the APD and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</title>, see Brunnhölzl 2012, pp. 49–52;
                            Mathes 2005, pp. 12–13; Meinert 2003, p. 180; Robertson 2006, p.
                            91.</note> At least two major Indian commentaries were composed on the
                            <fix>Avikalpapreveśdhāraṇī</fix>: Kamalaśīla’s (fl. 740–95) <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇīṭīkā</title> and a similarly
                        titled work, now lost, by Śākyamitra (fl. ninth century).<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-7">
                            This is the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog pa la ’jug pa’i
                                gzung gyi ’grel pa</title>, which is listed as text no. 552 in the
                            ldan dkar ma catalog (Lalou 1953, p. 332).</note> Renowned Yogācārins
                        such as Sthiramati (fl. 510–70) and Ratnākaraśānti (fl. eleventh century)
                        cited the APD in their commentarial works, the latter quoting it in his
                        treatises on both sūtric and tantric scriptures.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The <fix>Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</fix> proved equally influential in Tibet,
                        particularly during the early spread of Buddhist teachings in the seventh
                        through ninth centuries. It was first translated in this period,<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-9"> It is listed as text no. 197 in the Denkarma catalog
                                (<fix>ldan dkar ma</fix>) (Lalou 1953, p. 324).</note> and became an
                        important text in the debate over the primacy of gradual or sudden paths to
                            awakening.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-10"> For more on the debate between proponents
                            of the gradual and spontaneous paths to awakening, see Meinert 2003, pp.
                            179–80, particularly footnote 13; Robertson 2006, pp. 36–87.</note> The
                        APD was claimed by proponents of both positions; Kamalaśīla, who strenuously
                        supported the gradualist position, paraphrased the APD in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanākrama</title> series and composed a commentary
                        on it, possibly while residing in Tibet and taking part in this debate.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-11"> See Robertson 2006, pp. 87–91.</note> Conversely,
                        Vimalamitra cites the APD in support of the instantaneous position in his
                            *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sakṛtpraveśikanirvikalpabhāvanārtha</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-12"/>
                    <p tid="10">Nubchen Sangyé Yeshé (gnubs chen sangs rgyas ye shes, fl. ninth century)
                        similarly invoked the <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</hi> in his <title xml:lang="en">Lamp for the
                            Eye of Meditation</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan mig
                            sgron</title>), a text in which he cataloged and hierarchically ranked
                        the four primary Buddhist systems of his day: the gradual path promoted by
                        Kamalaśīla, the instantaneous path famously championed by the Chinese Chan
                        master Heshang Moheyan, the tantric system of Mahāyoga, and the teachings of
                        the Great Perfection. Nubchen’s analysis of these four paths hinges on their
                        particular understanding of non-conceptuality, for which he cites numerous
                        scriptural sources. In the context of these arguments he locates the APD as
                        a source text for the gradualist position.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-13"> For a detailed
                            discussion of the relationship between the APD and the <title xml:lang="en">Lamp for the Eye of Meditation</title>, see Meinert
                            2003.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-14"/>
                    <p tid="11">In the later spread of Buddhist teachings in Tibet the APD continued to
                        feature in Yogācāra-themed literature, especially in the commentarial
                        traditions surrounding the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnagotravibhāga</title>.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-15"> See Brunnhölzl 2012, pp.
                            150–151; Mathes 2005, passim.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="12">Summary of the Text</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-16"/>
                    <p tid="13">The central theme of <title xml:lang="en">Entering into
                            Non-conceptuality</title> is the practice of relinquishing all
                        conceptual signs by not directing the mind toward them. The sūtra presents
                        the progressive stages through which bodhisattvas can abandon increasingly
                        subtle conceptual signs and eliminate the erroneous ideas that lead to the
                        objectification of phenomena. This serves to undermine the conceptual
                        reification of appearances and facilitate direct contact with the
                        non-conceptual realm.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-17"/>
                    <p tid="14">The sūtra begins in the North Indian town of Rājagṛha, where the Buddha is
                        residing together with an assembly of monks and bodhisattvas. From among the
                        bodhisattvas, Avikalpaprabhāsa (Radiance of Non-conceptuality) approaches
                        the Buddha and beseeches him to teach <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī
                            Entitled “Entering into Non-conceptuality.”</title> The Buddha assents,
                        and begins by explaining the progressively subtle sets of conceptual signs
                        that need to be abandoned. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-18"/>
                    <p tid="15">The first set of conceptual signs to be abandoned consist of are those that
                        are most fundamental, which in the context of this sūtra refers to any
                        defiled subjective or objective phenomena in general, and to the five
                        aggregates in particular. The method for abandoning such conceptual
                        signs—the primary technique emphasized throughout the text—is to refrain
                        from mentally engaging them, and to recognize that they are mere appearances
                        that do not correspond to real phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-19"/>
                    <p tid="16">This formula is repeated with the remaining three categories of conceptual
                        signs. The second category of conceptual signs comprises those that arise in
                        relation to the antidotes applied when striving to overcome the conceptual
                        reification of the defiled entities listed in the previous category. These
                        antidotes include the six perfections: generosity, discipline, patience,
                        diligence, meditative concentration, and insight. This category also
                        includes any conceptual signs that arise through an examination of the
                        antidotes’ intrinsic natures, qualities, and essences.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-20"/>
                    <p tid="17">The third category of conceptual signs comprises those that pertain to any
                        true reality one believes to have been realized once the antidotes have been
                        applied. This includes any conceptual mark that may arise in the context of
                        examining traditional Buddhist designations for ultimate reality: emptiness,
                        suchness, the absolute, ultimate truth, and so forth. This also includes any
                        further marks that arise when one analyzes these designations in terms of
                        their intrinsic natures, qualities, or essences. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-21"/>
                    <p tid="18">The fourth and final set of conceptual signs consists of those pertaining to
                        the attainments that are believed to arise after true reality has been
                        realized. These include those marks that arise when examining everything
                        from the ten bodhisattva levels through to the attainment of omniscience. As
                        in the case of the previous two sets of conceptual signs, this category also
                        includes those marks that arise through an examination of this set in terms
                        of intrinsic natures, qualities, and essences. And, as before, all of these
                        conceptual signs are to be abandoned by not directing the mind toward them
                        and thereby recognizing them as mere appearances.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-22"/>
                    <p tid="19">The Buddha next points out that the abandonment of these conceptual signs is
                        not itself sufficient for attaining a direct experience of the
                        non-conceptual realm. The abandonment of conceptual signs brings about a
                        state of meditative absorption conducive to approaching the non-conceptual,
                        but it is only through the repeated application and perfection of this
                        method that bodhisattvas are able to experience non-conceptuality. The
                        Buddha explains that the non-conceptual realm transcends all imputations and
                        is independent of all emotional and cognitive obscurations. It is
                        immaterial, indemonstrable, and unmanifest. Bodhisattvas who become
                        established in the non-conceptual realm will see that all phenomena are
                        equivalent to space, that they are nothing more than an illusion, a mirage,
                        a dream, and so forth. Stability in the non-conceptual realm grants a
                        bodhisattva great power to perform all manner of awakened activity for the
                        benefit of beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-23"/>
                    <p tid="20">To illustrate the progressive process of meditation outlined in the sūtra,
                        the Buddha provides an analogy. Just as a person who desires a
                        wish-fulfilling jewel buried deep beneath the earth must forsake all other
                        precious minerals unearthed as they dig deeper and deeper toward the
                        wish-fulfilling jewel, so a bodhisattva who wishes to reach the
                        non-conceptual realm must unrelentingly relinquish progressively subtler
                        conceptual signs, not stopping until non-conceptuality is reached.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-24"/>
                    <p tid="21">The Buddha next presents a sequence of reflections to be used to relinquish
                        conceptual signs and thereby reach the non-conceptual realm. Whenever a
                        conceptual mark arises, bodhisattvas should not entertain the idea that such
                        a mark is their own or belongs to another; bodhisattvas should not regard
                        that mark as actually representing a real phenomenon that arises or ceases,
                        is pure or defiled, exists or does not exist, or has an intrinsic nature;
                        they should not think of the phenomenon as being a cause, an effect, or any
                        type of action; bodhisattvas should not apprehend any phenomena apart from
                        the act of cognitive representation (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vijñapti</foreign>. Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par rig pa</foreign>)<fix>,</fix> nor should they
                        consider that which is distinct from cognition to be unreal; they should not
                        think cognition itself to be either real or unreal; and finally, when they
                        no longer engage with any of these concepts, they should even give up the
                        idea “this is the non-conceptual.” Only when bodhisattvas become stable in
                        this realization do they enter into the non-conceptual realm.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-25"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Buddha ends his discourse by extolling the great merit that will accrue
                        to anyone who trains in this teaching, or even writes it down or recites it
                        aloud. After offering a summary verse to cap the sūtra, the Buddha finishes
                        his teaching as the entire retinue, along with the complete host of worldly
                        and celestial beings, rejoices.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-26"/>
                    <p tid="23">
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Recensions, Editions, and Translations</hi>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-27"/>
                    <p tid="24">The present translation is based on the Sanskrit edition of the APD prepared
                        by Kazunobu Matsuda, who relied on the two extant Sanskrit witnesses: a
                        largely complete but slightly damaged manuscript currently held by the
                        Institute of Oriental Studies at the Academy of Sciences of Russia in St.
                        Petersburg, and a fragmented manuscript from Gilgit presently held in New
                        Delhi, India.<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-28"> See Matsuda, 1996. </note> The Tibetan
                        translation, as preserved in the Degé Kangyur, has also been consulted for
                        this translation. Significant variants between the Sanskrit text and Tibetan
                        translations have been noted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-29"/>
                    <p tid="25">In addition to the canonical version of the Tibetan translation, two
                        incomplete Tibetan manuscripts of the APD were discovered among the Dunhuang
                        documents. One of the manuscripts (IOL Tib J 51) is a copy of the canonical
                        translation prepared by Jinamitra, Dānaśīla, and Kawa Peltsek. The second
                        (IOL Tib J 52) preserves a different translation, but it demonstrates only
                        minor variants that are primarily due to the lexical preferences of the
                            translator.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-30"> The extant folia of IOL Tib J 52
                            correspond to folios 2.b.7–4.b.2 and 5.b.3–6.a.3 of the Degé Kangyur
                            recension. It should be noted that the digitized images of the scans are
                            disordered and one folio is reversed. The Arabic numerals on the right
                            side of the folia do not represent the correct order. There also appears
                            to be one folio missing in the sequence. Only variants that suggest
                            differences between Sanskrit recensions have been noted.</note> In both
                        cases the colophons are missing, making it difficult to precisely determine
                        the details of their composition. There are also two extant Chinese
                        translations of the APD: a Dunhuang manuscript by an unknown translator with
                        the title <title xml:lang="Input Language">Ru wu fenbie zongchi
                        jing</title>, and an early eleventh-century translation by Dānapāla, the
                            <title xml:lang="Input Language">Fo shuo ru wu fenbie famen jing</title>
                        (Taishō 654).<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-31"> See Meinert 2003, pp. 178–179; Ueyama 1983,
                            pp. 34–35. Ueyama presents an edition of the <title xml:lang="Input Language">Ru wu fenbie zongchi jing</title> in the
                            same publication, pp. 38–40.</note> The latter is a translation of an
                        otherwise unknown recension of the Sanskrit text.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-32"/>
                    <p tid="26">The APD has previously been translated into English twice. Raymond Robertson
                        translated the APD along with Kamalaśīla’s commentary in his 2006
                        multi-volume work on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</title>. Karl Brunnhölzl includes a translation
                        of the APD in an appendix to his 2012 study of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</title> and its commentarial tradition.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="27"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="28">The Noble Dhāraṇī</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="29">Entering into Non-conceptuality</head>
                <!--In the rare case that there is initial text before the first chapter begins, the script will place the
                        text here. However, this will cause the two headings for the "Honorific Title" and "Main Title" to be duplicated below
                        as <p> elements. Markup Editors, please delete these initial duplicated <p> elements along with their milestones and delete this comment.-->
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-33"/>
                <p tid="30">
                    <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The Noble Dhāraṇī</hi>
                </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-34"/>
                <p tid="31">
                    <hi type="wordfile-remnant">Entering into Non-conceptuality</hi>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head tid="32">Main Section</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-35"/>
                    <p tid="33">Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-36"/>
                    <p tid="34">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One, together with a great assembly
                        of monks and bodhisattvas, was residing at Rājagṛha in the palace at the
                        heart of the non-conceptual realm of phenomena, a place superior to
                        everything within the three realms. Together with him were the bodhisattvas,
                        the great beings, Avikalpa, Avikalpaprabhāsa, Avikalpacandra,
                        Nirvikalpavīra, Nirvikalpadharmanirdeśakuśala, Nirvikalpasvabhāva,
                        Nirvikalpamati, Nirvikalpanāda, Nirvikalpaspharaṇa, Nirvikalpasvara,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-37"> Instead of Nirvikalpasvara, the Degé translation reads
                            Nirvikalpeśvara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par med dbang
                                phyug</foreign>). " aing Faśīla, and Kawa Peltstegterpretation would
                            accord with the Tib.ng the Tib. here. Best to note this, and it seems to
                            me t</note> Maheśvara,<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-38"> The Degé translation adds
                            Nirvikalpa- to the name of Maheśvara (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam
                                par rtog med dbang phyug chen po</foreign>).</note> [F.2.a]
                        Nirvikalpamahāmaitrīśvara, and the bodhisattva, the great being,
                        Avalokiteśvara.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-39"/>
                    <p tid="35">At that time, the Blessed One, surrounded and esteemed by an assembly of
                        hundreds of thousands, taught the Dharma<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-40"> The Degé
                            translation includes the statement “according to the Mahāyāna” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">theg pa chen po la</foreign>).</note>
                        concerning the non-conceptuality of phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-41"/>
                    <p tid="36">The Blessed One surveyed the entire assembly of bodhisattvas and addressed
                        them, “Noble sons, you should keep in mind the dhāraṇī called <title xml:lang="en">Entering into Non-conceptuality</title>. Keeping it in
                        mind, a bodhisattva, a great being, will swiftly perfect the qualities of a
                        buddha and will make steady, excellent progress.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-42"/>
                    <p tid="37">The bodhisattva, the great being named Avikalpaprabhāsa, rose from his seat
                        in the assembly, draped his upper robe over his shoulder, and knelt with his
                        right knee on the ground. He bowed toward the Blessed One with hands folded
                        and addressed the Blessed One, “Blessed One, please explain the dhāraṇī
                            <title xml:lang="en">Entering into Non-conceptuality</title>. Once they
                        have heard it, bodhisattvas, great beings, will keep it in mind, recite it,
                        contemplate it properly, and teach it extensively to others.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-43"/>
                    <p tid="38">Thus addressed, the Blessed One said, “Then listen well, noble sons, and be
                        attentive as I explain the dhāraṇī <title xml:lang="en">Entering into
                            Non-conceptuality</title>.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-44"/>
                    <p tid="39">“That is excellent, Blessed One!” replied the bodhisattvas, the great beings.
                        [F.2.b] They then listened to the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-45"/>
                    <p tid="40">The Blessed One said to them: “Noble sons, those bodhisattvas, great beings,
                        who hear teachings on the topic of non-conceptuality and then settle into
                        non-conceptuality, will abandon all conceptual signs.<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-46"> A
                            “conceptual sign” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vikalpanimitta</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par rtog pa’i mtshan ma</foreign>) should here be
                            understood to refer to those signs that arise through conceptual
                            engagement with the phenomenon under examination or discussion.</note>
                        First, bodhisattvas abandon the most fundamental conceptual signs, those of
                        subject and object. The most fundamental conceptual signs are those marks
                        that belong to a defiled entity. ‘Defiled entity’ refers to the five
                        aggregates as the bases for clinging: the aggregate of matter as a basis of
                        clinging, the aggregate of sensation as a basis of clinging, the aggregate
                        of perception as a basis of clinging, the aggregate of karmic dispositions
                        as a basis for clinging, and the aggregate of consciousness as a basis for
                        clinging. How do bodhisattvas abandon these fundamental conceptual signs?
                        They abandon them by not directing their minds toward what is experientially
                        evident. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-47"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Once bodhisattvas have progressively abandoned those conceptual signs,
                        another set of conceptual signs based on an examination of antidotes arises
                        and becomes experientially evident. This includes the conceptual signs that
                        arise through examining generosity, examining discipline, examining
                        patience, examining diligence, examining meditative concentration, and the
                        conceptual signs based on examining insight. Whether they are examined in
                        terms of intrinsic natures, examined in terms of qualities, or examined in
                        terms of essences, bodhisattvas also abandon conceptual signs based on
                        examining antidotes by not directing their minds toward them.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-48"/>
                    <p tid="42">“Once bodhisattvas have abandoned those signs, another set of conceptual
                        signs based on the examination of true reality arises and becomes
                        experientially evident. [F.3.a] This includes conceptual signs based on
                        examining emptiness, examining suchness, examining the absolute, examining
                        the absence of signs, examining ultimate truth, and those based on examining
                        the field of phenomena. Whether they are examined in terms of particular
                        features, examined in terms of qualities, or examined in terms of essences,
                        bodhisattvas also abandon the conceptual signs based on examining true
                        reality by not directing their minds toward them.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-49"/>
                    <p tid="43">“Once bodhisattvas have abandoned those signs, another set of conceptual
                        signs based on examining the attainments arises and becomes experientially
                        evident. This includes the conceptual signs based on examining the
                        attainment of the first through tenth bodhisattva levels, conceptual signs
                        based on examining the attainment of the acceptance that phenomena do not
                        arise, conceptual signs based on examining the attainment of prophecy,
                        conceptual signs based on examining the attainment of the ability to purify
                        buddhafields, conceptual signs based on examining the attainment of the
                        ability to ripen beings, and conceptual signs based on examining the
                        attainment of initiation up to conceptual signs based on examining the
                        attainment of omniscience. Whether they are examined in terms of intrinsic
                        natures, examined in terms of qualities, or examined in terms of essences,
                        bodhisattvas also abandon the conceptual signs based on examining the
                        attainments by not directing their minds toward them.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-50"/>
                    <p tid="44">“Once bodhisattvas, great beings, have thus abandoned every type of
                        conceptual sign by not directing their minds toward them, they are well
                        oriented to the non-conceptual but have yet to experience the non-conceptual
                        realm. They do, however, possess the fundamental meditative absorption
                        conducive to experiencing the non-conceptual realm. [F.3.b] As a consequence
                        of cultivating this genuine method, training in it repeatedly, and correctly
                        orienting their minds, bodhisattvas will experience the non-conceptual realm
                        without volition or effort, and gradually purify their experience.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-51"/>
                    <p tid="45">“For what reason, noble sons,<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-52"> The Degé translation lacks
                            “noble sons,” but the phrase appears in the Dunhuang version.</note> is
                        the non-conceptual realm called ‘non-conceptual’? It completely transcends
                        all conceptual analysis, completely transcends all imputations of
                        instruction and illustration, completely transcends all conceptual
                            signs,<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-53"> The Degé translation and Dunhuang version lack
                            “completely transcends all conceptual signs.”</note> completely
                        transcends all imputation via the sense faculties, completely transcends
                        imputation as sense objects, completely transcends imputation as cognitive
                        representations, and is not based in the cognitive obscurations or in the
                        obscurations of the afflictive and secondary afflictive emotions.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-54"> The Degé translation lacks “secondary afflictive emotions,”
                            but the phrase does appear in the Dunhuang version.</note> For this
                        reason the non-conceptual realm is called ‘non-conceptual.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-55"/>
                    <p tid="46">“What, then, is the non-conceptual? The non-conceptual is immaterial,
                        indemonstrable, unsupported, unmanifest, imperceptible, and without
                        location. Those bodhisattvas, great beings who are established in the
                        non-conceptual realm see, with their non-conceptual knowing that is
                        indistinguishable from what is known, that all phenomena are like the
                        expanse of space. Through the ensuing mode of knowing they see all phenomena
                        as illusions, mirages, dreams, hallucinations, echoes, reflections, the
                        image of the moon in water, and as magical creations.<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-56">
                            These lines are cited by Ratnākaraśānti in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvarahasyanibandha</title>, a commentary on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvarahasya Tantra</title> (Isaacson,
                            forthcoming, p. 16), and in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāratamā</title>, a commentary on the <title xml:lang="en">Perfection of Wisdom in 8000 Lines</title> (Jaini 1979, p. 82). It
                            is also cited by Sthiramati in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Triṃśikāvijñaptibhāṣya</title> (Buescher 2002, p. 45, lines
                            16–18).</note> They then attain the full expression of the power of
                        sustaining great bliss.<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-57"> The Tibetan translations lack an
                            equivalent for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vibhutva</foreign>, “power.”</note> They attain the full expression of
                        the mind’s vast capacity. They attain the full expression of great knowledge
                        and wisdom. They attain the full expression of the power of maintaining the
                        great teaching.<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-58"> The Degé translation and the Dunhuang
                            version lack an equivalent for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vihāra</foreign>, “maintaining.” </note> In all circumstances they
                        are able to bring every type of benefit to all beings, never ceasing in
                        their effortless performance of awakened activity.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-59"/>
                    <p tid="47">[F.4.a] “Noble sons, consider this analogy: beneath a solid, hard sheet of
                        rock there is a great trove of precious minerals, a variety of great
                        wish-fulfilling jewels that shimmer with light, including precious silver,
                        precious gold, and precious emerald. Along comes a man seeking great
                        treasure. Another man who is able to perceive the great treasure says to
                        him, ‘Excuse me sir, beneath this solid, hard sheet of rock there is a great
                        precious treasure filled with glimmering precious minerals. But beneath that
                        there is a great<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-60"> The Degé translation omits “great” here,
                            which is attested in the Sanskrit.</note> precious treasure, a
                        wish-fulfilling jewel. First you must remove the bedrock. Once that is
                        removed, you will discover rocks that appear to be silver, but you should
                        not consider this the great treasure. Recognizing this, continue digging. As
                        you dig, you will discover rocks that appear to be gold, but again you
                        should not consider this the great treasure. Recognizing this once again,
                        dig. As you dig, you will discover rocks that appear to be various minerals,
                        but again you should not consider this to be the great treasure. Recognizing
                        this once again, dig. Sir, once you have toiled in unearthing these
                        minerals, you will effortlessly and without any further exertion discover a
                        great precious treasure, the wish-fulfilling jewel. Once you have found that
                        great precious treasure, the wish-fulfilling jewel, you will become rich,
                        affluent, prosperous, and fully able to benefit yourself and others.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-61"/>
                    <p tid="48">“Noble sons, this analogy is meant to provide some understanding of our
                        topic. The solid, hard sheet of rock represents the various karmic
                        dispositions that reinforce duality and the afflictive emotions. The great
                        treasure that lies beneath that rock, the precious wish-fulfilling jewel,
                        represents the non-conceptual realm. The person who seeks the great
                        treasure, the precious wish-fulfilling jewel, represents the bodhisattva,
                        the great being. [F.4.b] The person with knowledge of the great treasure is
                        the Thus-Gone One, the Worthy One, the Perfect Buddha. The bedrock
                        represents the most fundamental conceptual signs. The command to dig
                        represents not directing the mind toward them. The rock resembling silver
                        represents the conceptual signs related to the examination of
                            antidotes.<note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-62"> The Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnyen po la rnam par mi rtog pa’i mtshan ma</foreign>
                            here lacks an equivalent for the Sanskrit <fix>°</fix>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirūpaṇa</foreign> in the compound
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratipakṣanirūpaṇavikalpanimitta</foreign>.</note> The rock
                        resembling gold represents the conceptual signs related to emptiness and so
                        on. The rock resembling various gemstones represents the conceptual signs
                        related to the attainments. Finding the great treasure, the wish-fulfilling
                        jewel, represents experiencing the non-conceptual realm. Noble sons, through
                        this analogy, you should understand entering into non-conceptuality.<note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-63"> The Degé translation reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnam par mi rtog pa’i dbyings</foreign>, “the
                            non-conceptual realm.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-64"/>
                    <p tid="49">“How then, noble sons, do bodhisattvas, great beings, reflect on the
                        conceptual signs as they have been taught here and enter the non-conceptual
                        realm? Noble sons, when a fundamental conceptual sign related to the
                        aggregate of matter<note place="end" index="25" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-65"> The Degé translation should be emended
                            from <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzungs</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzugs</foreign> following the Sanskrit
                            and the variant attested in the Kangxi and Lhasa Kangyurs.</note>
                        manifests, bodhisattvas, great beings who are established in the
                        non-conceptual realm, should reflect in this way: ‘to think, “this is my
                        material form” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “this
                        material form belongs to others” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to
                        think, “this is matter” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think,
                        “matter arises,” “it ceases,” “it is afflicted,” or “it is purified” is to
                        entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “there is no matter” is to
                        entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “matter does not exist
                        intrinsically,” “it does not exist causally,” “it does not exist as a
                        result,” “it does not exist through action,” “it does not exist in relation
                        to anything,” [F.5.a] or “it is not a mode of being” is to entertain a
                        conceptual thought; to think, “matter is mere cognitive representation” is
                        to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “just as matter does not exist,
                        so cognitive representation appearing as matter does not exist” is to
                        entertain a conceptual thought.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-66"/>
                    <p tid="50">“Therefore, noble sons, the bodhisattvas, great beings, do not apprehend
                        matter, nor do they apprehend cognitive representations appearing as matter.
                        In no way do they bring cognitive representation to an end, nor do they
                        apprehend any phenomenon as being distinct from cognitive representation.
                        They do not consider that cognitive representation to be non-existent, nor
                        do they consider non-existence to be something distinct from cognitive
                        representation. They do not consider the non-existence of a cognitive
                        representation appearing as matter to be the same as that cognitive
                        representation, nor do they consider it to be different. They do not
                        consider a non-existent cognitive representation to be existent, nor do they
                        consider it to be non-existent. Noble sons, those who do not conceptualize
                        through any of these conceptual modes do not think, ‘this is the
                        non-conceptual realm.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-67"/>
                    <p tid="51">“Noble sons, this is the way of entering the non-conceptual realm. In this
                        way, bodhisattvas, great beings, become established in the non-conceptual
                        realm. The same should be applied to sensation, perception, karmic
                        dispositions, and consciousness. The same should be applied to the
                        perfection of generosity, the perfection of discipline, the perfection of
                        patience, the perfection of diligence, the perfection of meditative
                        concentration, and the perfection of insight. And the same should be applied
                        to emptiness and so on, up to omniscience.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-68"/>
                    <p tid="52">[F.5.b] “Noble sons, when conceptual signs<note place="end" index="26" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-69"> The Degé
                            translation omits “sign.”</note> related to an examination<note place="end" index="27" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-70"> The Degé reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">spyod pa</foreign> should be emended here to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpyod pa</foreign> in accordance with
                            the Sanskrit <fix>°</fix>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirūpaṇa</foreign>.</note> of omniscience manifest, bodhisattvas,
                        great beings, should reflect as follows: ‘to think, “this is my omniscience”
                        is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “this is the omniscience of
                        others” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “this is
                        omniscience” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “omniscience is
                        attained” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “omniscience is
                        meant to destroy all cognitive obscurations and the obscurations of the
                        afflictive emotions” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “once
                        purified, the three worlds are nothing other than omniscience”<note place="end" index="28" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-71"> The Tibetan translation reads, “omniscience is
                            purification,” thus omitting “the three worlds.”</note> is to entertain
                        a conceptual thought; to think, “omniscience arises,” “it ceases,” “it is
                        afflicted,” or “it is purified” is to entertain a conceptual thought;<note place="end" index="29" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-72"> The Degé translation omits the clause beginning with “to
                            think, ‘omniscience arises.’ ” The Dunhuang version reads, “is
                            difficult” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rab tu dka’
                                ba</foreign>) instead of “is purified.” </note> to think,
                        “omniscience does not exist” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think,
                        “omniscience does not exist intrinsically,” “it does not exist causally,”
                        “it does not exist as a result,” “it does not exist through action,” “it
                        does not exist in relation to anything,” and “it is not a mode of being” is
                        to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “omniscience is mere cognitive
                        representation” is to entertain a conceptual thought; to think, “just as
                        omniscience does not exist, so cognitive representation appearing as
                        omniscience does not exist” is to entertain a conceptual thought.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-73"/>
                    <p tid="53">“Therefore, noble sons,<note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-74"> We have followed the Degé
                            translation in including “noble sons” here.</note> just as bodhisattvas,
                        great beings, do not apprehend omniscience, they likewise do not apprehend
                        cognitive representations appearing as omniscience. In no way do they bring
                        cognitive representation to an end, nor do they apprehend any phenomenon as
                        being distinct from cognitive representations. They do not consider that
                        cognitive representation to be non-existent, nor do they consider
                        non-existence to be something distinct from cognitive representation. They
                        do not consider the non-existence of that cognitive representation to be
                        identical to that cognitive representation, [F.6.a] nor do they consider it
                        to be different. They do not consider the non-existence of that cognitive
                        representation to be existent, nor do they consider it to be non-existent.
                        Noble sons, those who do not conceptualize through any of these conceptual
                            modes<note place="end" index="31" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-75"> The Degé translation reads, “through any
                            concepts of omniscience” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnam
                                pa thams cad mkhyen pa’i rnam par rtog pa thams cad kyis</foreign>).
                            The repetition of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rnam pa thams
                                cad mkhyen pa</foreign>, “omniscience,” in the Tibetan passage
                            suggests the possibility that <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkhyen pa</foreign> was added here by scribal error.</note> do not
                        think, ‘this is the non-conceptual field of phenomena.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-76"/>
                    <p tid="54">“This is the way of entering the non-conceptual realm. Noble sons, this is
                        how bodhisattvas, great beings, become established in the non-conceptual
                        realm.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-77"/>
                    <p tid="55">“Noble sons, the merit from taking up this discourse on the Dharma, writing
                        it down,<note place="end" index="32" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-78"> The Degé translation includes “memorizing it”
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’chang
                            ba</foreign>).</note> and reciting it is much greater than giving away
                        one’s body as many times as there are grains of sand in the river Ganga,
                        much greater than offering jewel-filled world systems as numerous as grains
                        of sand in the river Ganga, and much greater than the heap of merit created
                        by commissioning images of the thus-gone ones to fill world systems as
                        numerous as grains of sand in the river Ganga.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-79"/>
                    <p tid="56">Then, on that occasion, the Blessed One spoke these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-80"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“With this true doctrine the Victor’s heir, intent upon the
                            non-conceptual,</l>
                        <l>Transcends the quagmire of concepts and gradually reaches the end of
                            thought.</l>
                        <l>A bodhisattva thereby attains a non-conceptual bliss that is peaceful and
                            unwavering,</l>
                        <l>Supreme, under their control, and both equaled and unequaled.”<note place="end" index="33" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-81">
                                <hi type="wordfile-remnant">These verses are cited in the
                                    </hi>
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇavatīṭīkā</title>
                                <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, Ratnākaraśānti’s commentary on the
                                    </hi>
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyā Tantra</title>
                                <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> (Damron 2014, p. 90). Regarding the
                                    phrase “equaled and unequaled” (</hi>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">samāsama</foreign>
                                <hi type="wordfile-remnant">),
                                    Ratnākaraśānti comments: “[Non-conceptual bliss] is ‘equaled’
                                    because it is equivalent with general classes of bliss that are
                                    other than it. It is ‘unequaled’ because is distinct through
                                    those [previously mentioned] four distinctions.”</hi>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-82"/>
                    <p tid="58">When the Blessed One finished his discourse, the bodhisattva, the great being
                        Avikalpaprabhāsa and the entire retinue together with the world of gods,
                        humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced as they praised the teachings of the
                        Blessed One.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head tid="59">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-83"/>
                    <p tid="60">This completes <fix>The Noble Dhāraṇī Entitled</fix>
                        <title xml:lang="en">Entering into Non-conceptuality</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-84"/>
                    <p tid="61">This was translated and finalized by the Indian scholars Jinamitra and
                        [F.6.b] Dānaśīla, together with the chief editor and translator Kawa
                        Peltsek.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="62">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head tid="63">Abbreviations</head>
                    <fix/>
                    <!-- In this section, markup editors need to move the expanded form of the
                            abbreviation out of the "abbr" element and put it into the "expan" element. Delete
                           this comment and the "fix" tag when you are done. If there are no abbreviations in 
                            this text, then delete this entire "list" element, but leave the "div" and "head"
                            entitled "notes"-->
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-057-001-85">
                        <abbr>APD <fix>Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</fix>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan/>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="64">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="65">Tibetan Editions</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-86">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">’phags pa rnam par mi rtog par ’jug pa zhes bya
                            ba’i gzungs</title>. Toh 142, Degé Kangyur vol. 57 (mdo sde, pa), folios
                        1a–6b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-87">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">’phags pa rnam par mi rtog par ’jug pa zhes bya
                            ba’i gzungs</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of
                        the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe
                        sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                        Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 57, pp.
                        1–14.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-88">IOL Tib J 51. British Library, London. Accessed through The International
                        Dunhuang Project: The Silk Road Online (IOL Tib J 51). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-89">IOL Tib J 52. British Library, London. Accessed through The International
                        Dunhuang Project: The Silk Road Online (IOL Tib J 52). </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="66">Sanskrit Editions</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-90">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Matsuda, Kazunobu, ed. </title>“<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpapraveśadhāraṇī</title>, Sanskrit Text and
                        Japanese Translation.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of the Research
                            Institute of Bukkyo University</title> 3 (1996): 89–113.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="67">Secondary Literature</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-91">Brunnhölzl, Karl. <title xml:lang="en">Mining for Wisdom within Delusion:
                            Maitreya’s “Distinction between Phenomena and the Nature of Phenomena”
                            and Its Indian and Tibetan Commentaries</title>. Boston: Snow Lion
                        Publications, 2012.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-92">Buescher, Hartmut. “The Triṃśikāvijñaptibhāṣya of Sthiramati: Critical
                        Editions of the Sanskrit Text and its Tibetan Translation, along with an
                        Historical Study: The Inception of Yogācāra-Vijñānavāda.” PhD. diss.,
                        University of Copenhagen, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-93">Damron, Ryan. “The Great Illusion: a Preliminary Study of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyā Tantra</title> and its Corpus.” MA Thesis, UC
                        Berkeley, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-94">Dharmachakra Translation Committee, trans.<title xml:lang="en">
                            Distinguishing Phenomena from Their Intrinsic Nature: Maitreya’s
                            “Dharmadharmatāvibhaṅga,” with Commentaries by Khenpo Shenga and Ju
                            Mipham</title>. Boston: Snow Lion Publications, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-95">Isaacson, Harunaga and Francesco Sferra. “The Commentary by Ratnākaraśānti
                        on the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarvarahasyatantra</title>,”
                        forthcoming.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-96">Jaini, Padmanabh S. <title xml:lang="en">Sāratamā: A Pañjikā on the
                            Aṣṭasāhasrikā Prajñāpāramitā Sūtra by Ācārya Ratnākaraśānti</title>.
                        Tibetan Sanskrit Works Series no. XVIII. Patna: Kashi Prasad Jayaswal
                        Research Institute, 1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-97">Kamalaśīla. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rnam par mi rtog par ’jug
                            pa zhes bya ba’i gzungs kyi rgya cher ’grel pa (</title>
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇīṭīkā</title>). Toh 4000, Degé
                        Tengyur vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios 123a–145b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-98">———. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanākrama I</title>. In <title xml:lang="en">Minor Buddhist Texts Part II</title>, edited by Giuseppe
                        Tucci, pp. 185–282. Serie Orientale Roma 9:2. Rome: Istituto Italiano per il
                        Medio ed Estremo Oriente, 1958.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-99">———. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāvanākrama III</title>. In <title xml:lang="en">Minor Buddhist Texts Part III,</title> edited by Giuseppe
                        Tucci. pp. 1–34. Serie Orientale Roma 43. Rome: Istituto Italiano per il
                        Medio ed Estremo Oriente, 1971.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-100">Lalou, Marcelle. “Les textes bouddhiques au temps du roi
                        Khri-sroṅ-lde-bcan.” <title xml:lang="Input Language">Journal
                            asiatique</title> 241, vol. 3 (1953): 313–53.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-101">Maitreya. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos dang chos nyid rnam par ’byed pa
                            (</title>
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāga</title>). Toh
                        4022, Degé Tengyur vol. 225 (mdo ’grel, phi), folios 45b–49a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-102">Mathes, Klaus-Dieter. “’Gos Lo tsā ba gZhon nu dpal’s Commentary on the
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Dharmatā</foreign> Chapter of the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmadharmatāvibhāgakārikās</title>.” <title xml:lang="en">Studies in Indian Philosophy and Buddhism, University of
                            Tokyo</title> 12 (2005): 3–39.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-103">Meinert, Carmen. “Structural Analysis of the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bSam
                            gtan mig sgron</title>: A Comparison of the Fourfold Correct Practice in
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryāvikalpapraveśanāmadhāraṇī</title> and the
                        Contents of the Four Main Chapters of the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bSam gtan
                            mig sgron</title>.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International
                            Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 26.1 (2003): 175–95.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-104">Robertson, Raymond E. <title xml:lang="en">A Study of the
                            “Dharmadharmatāvibhaṅga” (Volume 1): The Root Text and its Scriptural
                            Source (the “Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇī”), with Excerpts from Kamalaśīla’s
                            “Avikalpapraveśadhāraṇīṭīkā”</title>. Beijing: China-Tibet Publishing
                        House, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-105">Ueyama, Daishun, Kennenth W. Eastman, and Jeffrey L. Broughton. “The
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpapraveśa-dhāraṇī</title>: The Dharani of
                        Entering Non-Discrimination.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of Institute of
                            Buddhist Cultural Studies</title> 22 (1983): 32–42.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-057-001-106">Vimalamitra. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cig car ’jug pa rnam par mi rtog
                            pa’i bsgom don (</title>*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sakṛtpraveśikanirvikalpabhāvanārtha</title>). Toh 3910, Degé Tengyur
                        vol. 110 (dbu ma, ki), folios 6b–13b.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-107">
                <term>acceptance that phenomena do not arise</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattikadharmakṣānti</term>
                <term type="definition">A bodhisattva’s realization that all phenomena are
                    unproduced and empty. It sustains them on the difficult path of benefitting all
                    beings so that they do not succumb to the goal of personal liberation. Different
                    sources link this realization to the first or eighth bodhisattva level
                        (<fix>bhūmi</fix>).</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-108">
                <term>aggregates as the bases of clinging</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar len pa’i phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པའི་ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādānaskandha</term>
                <term type="definition">The five aggregates (<fix>skandha</fix>) of matter
                        (<fix>rūpa</fix>), sensation (<fix>vedanā</fix>), perception
                        (<fix>saṃjñā</fix>), karmic dispositions (<fix>saṃskāra</fix>), and
                    consciousness (<fix>vijñāna</fix>). They are referred to as the ‘bases for
                    clinging’ (<fix>upādāna</fix>) insofar as all conceptual grasping arises on the
                    basis of these aggregates.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-109">
                <term>bodhisattva levels</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūmi</term>
                <term type="definition">The stages a bodhisattva must traverse before reaching
                    perfect buddhahood; traditionally ten in number, though some systems present
                    more. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-110">
                <term>cognitive representation</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rig pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རིག་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñapti</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-111">
                <term>English</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Tibetan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཊིབེཏན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sanskrit</term>
                <term type="definition">Definition</term>
                <term type="alternative">Alternative</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-112">
                <term>field of phenomena</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་དབྱིངས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                <term type="definition">The non-conceptual, boundless field (<fix>dhātu</fix>) in
                    which all phenomena (<fix>dharma</fix>) appear. A term for ultimate
                    reality.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-113">
                <term>fundamental</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang bzhin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་བཞིན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prakṛti</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-114">
                <term>Great Perfection</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzogs pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫོགས་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <term type="definition">A system of uncontrived, non-conceptual meditation developed
                    in Tibet based on Indian and Chinese Buddhist influences; the pinnacle of
                    meditation training in the Nyingma lineage of Tibetan Buddhism.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-115">
                <term>imputation</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par brtag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་བརྟག་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikalpa</term>
                <term type="alternative">conceptual</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-116">
                <term>insight</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                <term type="definition">The sixth of the pāramitās.</term>
                <term type="alternative">knowedge, wisdom</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-117">
                <term>karmic dispositions</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</term>
                <term type="definition">One of the five aggregates; the very subtle karmic
                    tendencies that give shape to an individual’s saṃsāric experieince. In
                    Abhidharma literature there are typically fifty-one saṃskāras.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-118">
                <term>knowing</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                <term type="alternative">mode of knowing</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-119">
                <term>matter</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpa </term>
                <term type="definition">The first of the five aggregates, defined in Abhidharma
                    literature as anything comprised of the four major elements (earth, air, fire,
                    and water), either alone or in combination.</term>
                <term type="alternative">material form</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-120">
                <term>non-conceptual realm</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog pa’i dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པའི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avikalpadhātu</term>
                <term type="definition">The state of non-conceptuality.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-121">
                <term>not direct the mind</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid la mi byed pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་ལ་མི་བྱེད་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amanasikāra</term>
                <term type="definition">To not conceptually engage or even direct the mind toward an
                    object of peception.</term>
                <term type="alternative">not mentally engage</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-122">
                <term>omniscience</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam pa thams cad mkhyen pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvākārajñatā</term>
                <term type="definition">A description of the mode of omniscience in which all
                    possible phenomena as well as their ultimate nature in known.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-123">
                <term>secondary afflictive emotions</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye ba’i nyon mongs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བའི་ཉོན་མོངས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upakleśa</term>
                <term type="definition">A subsidiary set of afflictive emotions that differ in
                    number depending on the system of Abhidharma that presents them.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-124">
                <term>sign</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་མ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nimitta</term>
                <term type="definition">Any imagined mark or feature of an object, the misperception
                    of which serves as the basis of peception and the arising of coarse
                    conceptuality. </term>
                <term type="alternative">mark</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-125">
                <term>six perfections</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol tu phyin pa drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaṭpāramitā</term>
                <term type="definition">Generosity (Skt. dāna ; Tib. byin pa ), discipline (Skt.
                    śīla ; Tib. tshul khrims ), patience (Skt. kṣānti ; Tib. bzod pa ), diligence
                    (Skt. vīrya ; Tib. brtson ’grus ), meditative concentration (Skt. dhyāna ; Tib.
                    bsam gtan ), and insight (Skt. prajñā ; Tib. shes rab ). </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-126">
                <term>suchness</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā</term>
                <term type="definition">A common term describing ultimate reality.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-127">
                <term>the absolute</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                <term type="definition">A term for ultimate reality.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-128">
                <term>worthy one</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                <term type="definition">A person who has accomplished the final fruition of the path
                    of the hearers and is liberated from saṃsāra.</term>
                <term type="alternative">arhat</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-129">
                <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                <term type="definition">The bodhisattva who is the epitome of compassion.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-130">
                <term>Avikalpa</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpa</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Non-conceptual.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-131">
                <term>Avikalpacandra</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpacandra</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Moon of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-132">
                <term>Avikalpaprabhāsa</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par mi rtog snang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་མི་རྟོག་སྣང་བ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avikalpaprabhāsa</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Light of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-133">
                <term>English</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Tibetan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཊིབེཏན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sanskrit</term>
                <term type="definition">Definition</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-134">
                <term>Heshang Moheyan</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <term type="definition">Fl. Eighth century. A Chinese master of the Chan tradition
                    who tradition holds lost a debate with Kamalaśīla regarding sudden versus
                    gradual paths to awakening. He upehld the view of the sudden path. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-135">
                <term>Kamalaśīla</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad ma’i ngang tshul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མའི་ངང་ཚུལ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kamalaśīla</term>
                <term type="definition">Fl. late eighth century. An Indian monastic scholar
                    important in the transmission of Buddhism to Tibet.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-136">
                <term>Maheśvara</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med dbang phyug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་དབང་ཕྱུག་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpamaheśvara</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’“Great Lord”; the name of a bodhisattva in the
                    Avikalpraveśdhāraṇī, this is more commonly used as an epithet Śiva.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-137">
                <term>Nirvikalpadharmanirdeśakuśala</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med chos ston mkhas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་ཆོས་སྟོན་མཁས་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpadharmanirdeśakuśala</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Skilled in Teaching the Dharma
                    of Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-138">
                <term>Nirvikalpamahāmaitrīśvara</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med byams pa chen po dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་བྱམས་པ་ཆེན་པོ་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpamahāmaitrīśvara</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Lord of Non-conceptual Great
                    Love.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-139">
                <term>Nirvikalpamati</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpamati</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Wise in
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-140">
                <term>Nirvikalpanāda</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med nga ro </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་ང་རོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpanāda</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Roar of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-141">
                <term>Nirvikalpaspharaṇa</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med khyab byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་ཁྱབ་བྱེད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpaspharaṇa</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Pervading
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-142">
                <term>Nirvikalpasvabhāva</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med ngo bo nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་ངོ་བོ་ཉིད།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpasvabhāva</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Having the Nature of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-143">
                <term>Nirvikalpasvara</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpasvara</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Lord of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-144">
                <term>Nirvikalpavīra</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rtog med dpa’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྟོག་མེད་དཔའ་བོ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirvikalpavīra</term>
                <term type="definition">111 ’Name of a bodhisattva; “Hero of
                    Non-conceptuality.”</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-145">
                <term>Nubchen Sangyé Yeshé</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnub chen sangs rgyas ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནུབ་ཆེན་སངས་རྒྱས་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <term type="definition">Fl. eleventh century. An early Tibetan master of the Nyingma
                    tradition.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-146">
                <term>Ratnākaraśānti</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’byung gnas zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་གནས་ཞི་བ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnākaraśānti</term>
                <term type="definition">Fl. late tenth–early eleventh century. An important Indian
                    monastic scholar who commented on both Mahāyāna and Vajrayāna texts.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-147">
                <term>Sthiramati</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros brtan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་བརྟན་པ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sthiramati</term>
                <term type="definition">Fl. sixth century. An important Indian commentator on the
                    Yogācāra system.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-148">
                <term>Vimalamitra</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med bshes gnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མེད་བཤེས་གཉེན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalamitra</term>
                <term type="definition">Fl. eighth century. An Indian master important in the
                    transmission of Buddhism to Tibet.</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-149">
                <term>English</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Tibetan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཊིབེཏན།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sanskrit</term>
                <term type="definition">Definition</term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
        <item>
            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-057-001-150">
                <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                <term type="definition">The ancient capital of Magadha. Vulture Peak, the site of
                    many of the historical Buddha's teachings, is located nearby. </term>
            </gloss>
        </item>
    </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>