<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen
                    po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yana­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-27">Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (Tsechen Kunchab Ling
                    Division)<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-173">Venerable Khenpo Kalsang Gyaltsen</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-175">Reverend Dr. Chodrung Kunga Chodron</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-306">Simeon Joffe</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.12 <date>2011 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-058-002"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2011-12-16</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh155" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 155</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 58 (mdo sde, pa), folios 205.a-205.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="2">
                        <start volume="58" page="411"/>
                        <end volume="58" page="412"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11751" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-01T17:30:56.294Z" user="admin">01/03/2019 17:30:56</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!--Contents 
            Summary Acknowledgments Introduction 
            The Translation 
            The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara 
            Bibliography Notes -->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="22">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-1"/>
                <p tid="1"> In this very short sūtra, the Buddha explains to a nāga king and an assembly of monks that reciting
                    the four aphorisms of the Dharma is equivalent to recitation of all of the 84,000 articles of the Dharma. He
                    urges them to make diligent efforts to engage in understanding the four aphorisms (also called the four
                    seals), which are the defining philosophical tenets of the Buddhist doctrine: (1) all compounded phenomena are
                    impermanent; (2) all contaminated phenomena are suffering; (3) all phenomena are without self; (4) nirvāṇa is
                    peace. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="23">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-2"/>
                <p tid="2"> Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (Tsechen Kunchab Ling Division), comprising
                    Venerable Khenpo Kalsang Gyaltsen and Reverend Dr. Chodrung Kunga Chodron. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="24">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-3"/>
                    <p tid="4"> In the Tibetan canon there are three sūtras entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the
                            Nāga King Sāgara</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title>): a long
                        version (Toh 153), one of middle length (Toh 154), and a short sūtra (Toh 155).<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-53">They correspond respectively to the Chinese translations T. 598, 601, 599.
                        </note> They have quite different contents and are all to be found in a group of sūtras in the Kangyur
                        entitled “The Questions of …” (… <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paripṛcchā</foreign>), including
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Brahmā</title>, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                            Mañjuśrī</title>, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of an Old Lady</title>, and several others. There
                        is also another nāga king whose questions were the occasion for a sūtra in this group entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King Anavatapta</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavatapta­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title>), Toh 156. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The text translated here is the shortest of the three <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title> sūtras. The Buddha’s teaching of this very brief sūtra to an
                        assembly of monks is presumed—from the title—to be in response to a question or questions put to him by a
                        king of the supernatural beings known as nāgas, serpents who guard the Dharma, although in this sūtra the
                        questions themselves are not explicitly stated. The Buddha explains that recitation of the four aphorisms
                        of the Dharma is equivalent to recitation of the entire 84,000 articles of the Dharma, and that they
                        constitute the inexhaustible doctrine of the bodhisattvas. The four are: </p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="6">
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-5"/>
                            <l>all compounded phenomena are impermanent (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</foreign>);</l>
                            <l>all contaminated phenomena are suffering (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</foreign>);</l>
                            <l>all phenomena are without self (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</foreign>);</l>
                            <l>nirvāṇa is peaceful/peace (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śānta/śānti</foreign>).</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">These four aphorisms, or tenets—also called the four seals—are central to Buddhist philosophy and
                        characterize the Buddhist view of the nature of reality. The Buddha stated that any doctrine characterized
                        by these four seals is genuinely in accord with the philosophical view of Buddhism, just as a document
                        purportedly written by a king that has the proper seals is known as genuine. Because the concepts of
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya(tva)</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</foreign>, and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</foreign> are central to the Buddhist philosophical view, over the
                        centuries, countless commentaries and elaborations on these concepts have been written by scholars from
                        every Buddhist tradition.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-54">For a modern presentation
                            in English, see Khyentse 2007.</note> Various sūtras and commentaries focus on one, two, three or all
                        four of the concepts.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-55">Stanley 2009, p.
                            149-154.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">Indian texts speak of the four aphorisms of the Dharma as well as of the four seals. The Sanskrit
                        of the four aphorisms can be extracted from Vasubandhu’s commentary to verse XVIII.80 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­yāna­sūtrālaṃkāra</title> of Asaṅga (fifth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>):</p>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="9">
                            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-8"/>
                            <l>
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvasaṃskārā anityāḥ</foreign> (all compounded phenomena
                                are impermanent);</l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvasaṃskārā duḥkhāḥ</foreign> (all compounded phenomena
                                are suffering);</l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvadharmā anātmānaḥ</foreign> (all phenomena are without
                                self);</l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntaṃ nirvāṇaṃ</foreign> (peaceful is nirvāṇa).<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-56">Sanskrit in Lévi 1907, 1911, tome I, p. 149.
                                    For an English translation, see Jamspal et al. 2004 (the commentary is to verse XVIII.81 in
                                    that translation). Note that <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed</foreign> in these contexts and in the four seals is not being
                                    used to mean “formative factors” or “karmic conditioning,” but seems to be used in the same
                                    sense as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskṛta</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dus
                                        byas</foreign>, i.e. “compounded phenomena.” Edgerton had noticed this usage of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</foreign>. See Edgerton 1985, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra, saṃskṛta</foreign>. Cf. also Jamspal et al. 2004, who translate the term as
                                    “creations.”</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">The same four aphorisms are listed and described in chapter 17 of Asaṅga’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattva­bhūmi</title>.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-57">Sanskrit in Dutt 1978 and Wogihara 1978. For a recent English translation, see Engle 2016, pp
                            454-463.</note> The only minor difference in these formulations of them, compared to the four
                        aphorisms as set out in the present sūtra, is that here the second aphorism does not speak of “all
                        contaminated phenomena,” but simply “all compounded phenomena.”<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-58">Note that the Pāli Dhammapada includes the first three concepts in verses
                            277, 278, and 279: <foreign xml:lang="fr">sabbe saṅkhārā aniccā’ ti...sabbe saṅkhārādukkhā’ ti...sabbe
                                saṅkhārā anattā’ ti...</foreign>
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">Although this sūtra’s Sanskrit original is no longer extant, the colophon to the Tibetan
                        translation of the sūtra tells us that it was translated from Sanskrit to Tibetan by the Indian abbot
                        Surendrabodhi and the Tibetan editor-translator Yeshé Dé (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ye shes
                            sde</foreign>). We can thus infer that this sūtra was translated from Sanskrit to Tibetan sometime
                        during the late eighth to early ninth century. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">This sūtra is also included in the Chinese Buddhist canon (T. 599).<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-59">The Chinese version was translated during the Tang dynasty by Yijing
                            (635-713; his name is also variously transliterated as I-Tsing, I-Ching, Yi-Tzing). An English
                            translation of the Chinese version by an unattributed translator is posted on the internet by Fodian
                            (see bibliography).</note> Both the Tibetan and Chinese versions of the sūtra are very similar in
                        their brevity, meaning and story line, although there are a few minor differences between them.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-60">On Yijing, see Keown 2004.</note> A twelfth-century
                        fragment containing this sūtra in the Tangut, or Xixia,<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-61">The Western Xia (Xixia), or Tangut Empire (1038-1227), was a Buddhist
                            empire located in what are now the Chinese provinces of Ningxia, Gansu, Eastern Qinghai, Northern
                            Shaanxi as well as parts of Xinjiang and Inner Mongolia. It was known as Minyak (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi nyag</foreign>) in Tibetan. The Tanguts adopted Buddhism from both Chinese
                            and Tibetan sources. The language, which has its own very elaborate script, has been partially
                            deciphered by modern scholarship.</note> language was discovered, among other pieces of the Tangut
                        canon, at Khara-khoto along the ancient Silk Road by the British explorer Sir Aurel Stein during his
                        1913-1916 journey.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-62">Grinstead 1967.</note> Now in
                        the British Museum, the Tangut version is very close to the Chinese version, indicating that it was likely
                        translated from the Chinese.<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-63">Nie 2007.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">The present translation from Tibetan<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-64">In
                            the process of research on this sūtra, another translation from the Tibetan was found; it was done by
                            Geshe Lhakdor in 2010 for a workshop presented at the India Habitat Centre in Delhi under the auspices
                            of the Foundation for Universal Responsibility (see bibliography).</note> is based on the version in
                        the Degé (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</foreign>) Kangyur, with reference to the
                        differences between this and various other versions noted in the Pedurma (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe sdur ma</foreign>) comparative edition of the Degé Kangyur. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="25">The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="26">The Noble Māhayāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="27">The Questions of the Nāga King Sāgara </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-13"/>
                    <p tid="14">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->
                        <ref cRef="F.205.a"/> Prostrations to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-14"/>
                    <p tid="15">
                        <!--<modularPassage type="thusDid">-->Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān <ref cRef="F.205.b"/> was
                        dwelling at the place of the nāga king Sāgara together with a great assembly of
                        1,250<!--</modularPassage>--> bhikṣus as well as a multitude of bodhisattvas and mahāsattvas. At that time
                        the Bhagavān said to the nāga king Sāgara: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-15"/>
                    <p tid="16">“Lord of the nāgas, if one utters these four aphorisms of the Dharma, in uttering them one is
                        expressing all 84,000 articles of the Dharma. What are the four? They are as follows. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-16"/>
                    <p tid="17">“To fully engage in understanding the inexhaustible doctrine of the bodhisattva mahāsattvas that
                        all compounded phenomena are impermanent; to fully engage in understanding the inexhaustible doctrine of
                        the bodhisattva mahāsattvas that all contaminated phenomena are suffering; to fully engage in
                        understanding the inexhaustible doctrine of the bodhisattva mahāsattvas that all phenomena are without
                        self; and to fully engage in understanding the inexhaustible doctrine of the bodhisattva mahāsattvas that
                        nirvāṇa is peace.<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-65">DNQ: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba</foreign> (peace/peaceful) C: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhes
                                bya</foreign> (known as). </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-17"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Lord of the nāgas, if one utters these four aphorisms of the Dharma, in uttering them one is
                        expressing all 84,000 articles of the Dharma.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-18"/>
                    <p tid="19">When the Bhagavān had spoken in this way, the bhikṣus and bodhisattvas rejoiced and greatly
                        praised the teachings of the Bhagavān.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="28">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-19"/>
                    <p tid="20">This completes the Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga King
                            Sāgara</title>. </p>
                    <p tid="21">Translated and finalized by the Indian abbot Surendrabodhi and the senior editor-translator, the
                        monk Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="29">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="30">Abbreviations:</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-058-002-20">
                        <abbr>C</abbr>
                        <expan>Coné Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-058-002-21">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-058-002-22">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-058-002-23">
                        <abbr>Q</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-058-002-24">
                        <abbr>T</abbr>
                        <expan>Taishō Tripiṭaka (Chinese Buddhist canon)</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="31">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-25">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yana­sūtra</title>),
                        Toh 155, Degé Kangyur, vol. 58 (mdo sde, pha), folios 205.a-205.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-26">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa klu’i rgyal po rgya mtshos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title>, Toh 155, Vol 58, pp 557-558, bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the
                        Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                        Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
                        skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-27">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>, <title xml:lang="zh">Fo
                            wei hai long wang shuo fa yin jing</title> (佛為海龍王說法, “The Dharma-Seal Sūtra Spoken by the Buddha for
                        the Nāga King Sāgara”). T. 599. In <title xml:lang="en">CBETA Chinese Electronic Tripiṭaka</title>.
                        Retrieved October 12, 2011, from <ref target="http://tripitaka.cbeta.org/T15n0599 ">cbeta.org.</ref>
                        <!-- http://www.cbeta.org/result/normal/T15/0599_001.htm.-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-28">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Dharma-Seal Sutra Spoken by the Buddha for Ocean Dragon King</title>. (English
                        translation from Chinese). Retrieved October 12, 2011, from <ref target="http://www.fodian.net/world/0599.html">fodian.net.</ref>
                        <!-- http://www.fodian.net/world/0599.html.-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-29">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhammapada</title>. Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia: Selangor Buddhist Vipassana Society,
                        2004. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-30">Dutt, Nalinaksha, ed. (1978). <title xml:lang="fr">Bodhisattvabhūmiḥ</title>. Patna: K. P. Jayaswal Research Institute, 1978.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-31">Edgerton, F. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit
                            Dictionary</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1985. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-32">Engle, Artemus B., trans. (2016). <title xml:lang="fr">The Bodhisattva Path
                            to Unsurpassed Enlightenment: A Complete Translation of the Bodhisattvabhūmi</title>. Tsadra
                        Foundation Series. Boston: Snow Lion, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-33">Grinstead, E.D. (1967). “The Dragon King of the Sea.” <title xml:lang="en">The British Museum Quarterly</title> 31 (3/4), 96-100. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-34">Jamspal, L. et al. (2004). <title xml:lang="en">The Universal Vehicle
                            Discourse Literature (Mahāyānasūtrālaṃkāra) by Maitreyanātha/Āryāsaṅga Together with its Commentary
                            (Bhāṣya) by Vasubandhu</title>. Translated from the Sanskrit, Tibetan, and Chinese by L. Jamspal, R.
                        Clark, J. Wilson, L. Zwilling, M. Sweet, R. Thurman. Tanjur Translation Initiative. Treasury of Buddhist
                        Sciences Series. New York: American Institute of Buddhist Studies at Columbia University, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-35">Keown, D. (2004). “I-Ching.” In <title xml:lang="en">A Dictionary of
                            Buddhism</title>. Retrieved 12, 2011, from <ref target="http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/I-Ching.aspx#1-1O108:Iching-full">encyclopedia.com.</ref>
                        <!-- http://www.encyclopedia.com/topic/I-Ching.aspx#1-1O108:Iching-full-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-36">Khyentse, Dzongsar Jamyang (2007). <title xml:lang="fr">What Makes You Not a
                            Buddhist</title>. Boston: Shambhala Publications, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-37">Lévi, Sylvain (1907, 1911). <title xml:lang="fr">Asaṅga.
                            Mahāyāna-Sūtrālaṃkāra, Exposé de la doctrine du grand véhicule selon le système Yogācāra, édité et
                            traduit par Sylvain Lévi</title>. Bibliothèque de l’École des Hautes Études, sciences historiques et
                        philologiques, fascicules 159 et 190, Tome I - Texte (1907), Tome II - Traduction, introduction, index
                        (1911). Paris: Librairie Honoré Champion, 1907, 1911. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-38">Lhakdor, Geshe. (2010). <title xml:lang="en">Short Sutra on the Four
                            Seals</title>. The Foundation for Universal Responsibility of His Holiness the Dalai Lama
                        (www.furhhdl.org). Retrieved October 12, 2011, from <ref target="http://www.furhhdl.org/files/Short%20Sutra%20on%20the%20Four%20Seals.pdf">furhhdl.org.</ref>
                        <!--http://www.furhhdl.org/files/Short%20Sutra%20on%20t he%20Four%20Seals.pdf.-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-39">Nie Hongyin 聂鸿. (2007). “Ying zang xixiawen ‘Hai long wang jing’ kaobu”
                        (英藏西夏文《海龙王经》考补). In <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Ningxia Shehui Kexue</title> 宁夏社会科学, <title xml:lang="en">Social Sciences in Ningxia</title>, 1, 90-92. Retrieved October 12, 2011, from <ref target="http://hk.plm.org.cn/e_book/xz-5439.pdf">Social Sciences in Ningxia.</ref>
                        <!-- http://hk.plm.org.cn/e_book/xz-5439.pdf-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-40">Stanley, D. P. (2009). <title xml:lang="en">The Threefold Formal, Practical,
                            and Inclusive Canons of Tibetan Buddhism in the Context of a Pan-Asian Paradigm</title> (Unpublished
                        doctoral dissertation). University of Virginia, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-058-002-41">Wogihara, Unrai, ed. (1978). <title xml:lang="fr">Bodhisattvabhūmiḥ</title>.
                        Reprint edition. Tokyo: Sankibo Buddhist Book Store, 1978.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-42">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk of the Buddhist Saṅgha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-43">
                            <term>compounded phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-44">
                            <term>impermanent</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་རྟག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-45">
                            <term>contaminated phenomena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa dang bcas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟག་པ་དང་བཅས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāsrava</term>
                            <term type="definition">The phenomena of saṃsāra. <term type="ignore">Contaminated phenomena</term> are those influenced by the
                                defilements (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs</foreign>) and karma. Thus, e.g., even virtues that are under the
                                influence of defilements like ignorance are categorized as contaminated in this way.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-46">
                            <term>suffering</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdug bsngal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྡུག་བསྔལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-47">
                            <term>without self</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdag med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདག་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-48">
                            <term>nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-49">
                            <term>peaceful</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śānta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śānti</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">peace</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-50">
                            <term>four aphorisms of the Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi mdo bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་མདོ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmoddāna­catuṣṭaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The main topic of this sūtra; known also in Tibetan by the synonym <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ rtags kyi phyag rgya bzhi</foreign> (“the four seals of the
                                [Buddha’s] teaching”), in Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturmudrā</foreign>
                                (“the four seals”) or <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dṛṣṭi­nimitta­mudrā</foreign> (“the
                                seals that are the marks of the [Buddhist] view”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-51">
                            <term>four seals</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag rgya bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱག་རྒྱ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturmudrā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for the “four aphorisms of the Dharma,” q.v. Often seen in Tibetan
                                in the expanded form <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ rtags kyi phyag rgya
                                    bzhi</foreign> (“the <term type="ignore">four seals</term> of the [Buddha’s] teaching”), the nearest Sanskrit equivalent
                                being <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dṛṣṭi­nimitta­mudrā</foreign> (“the seals that are
                                the marks of the [Buddhist] view”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-058-002-52">
                            <term>Nāga King Sāgara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu’i rgyal po rgya mtsho </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུའི་རྒྱལ་པོ་རྒྱ་མཚོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgaranāgarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a king of a race of supernatural serpents who protect the
                                doctrine.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>