<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dra ba can gyis zhus pa'i
                    mdo/</title>
                <!--Translator omitted sūtra/pa'i mdo-->
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnajāliparipṛcchāsūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Questions of
                    Ratnajālin</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱིས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rin chen dra ba can gyis zhus pa
                    zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Questions
                    of Ratnajālin”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryaratnajāliparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee <lb/> under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay,
                    Dr.</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.2 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to
                    make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-059-006"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2020-01-08</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh163" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 163</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 59 (mdo sde, cha), folios 144.a–159.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">t. t. Jñānagarbha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">ye shes snying po</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">r. dpal brtsegs</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="32">
                        <volume number="59" start-page="287" end-page="318"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11765" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-01-14T15:55:54.088Z" user="admin">14/01/2020 15:55:54</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2019-07-02T14:44:08.116Z" user="john">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-28T15:12:17.584Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2019-11-28T15:12:17.584Z" user="andreas">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2019-12-04T08:54:19.146Z" user="andreas">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-01-05T15:29:22.409Z" user="andreas">2.a</note>
            
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.2" date-time="2020-01-14T15:55:51.25Z" user="laura">v 0.1.2</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-1"/>
                <p tid="2">Prompted by a dream, the young Licchavi boy Ratnajālin invites the Buddha
                    to the city of Vaiśālī. When the Buddha arrives Ratnajālin asks whether there
                    are other buddhas whose names, when heard, bring benefit to bodhisattvas. The
                    Buddha replies that there are, and he proceeds to describe the power of the
                    names of buddhas in the four cardinal directions as well as above and below.
                    Once Ratnajālin has understood the teaching on the power of the names of these
                    thus-gone ones, the Buddha provides encouragement for the future propagation of
                    this discourse.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance
                    of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Timothy Hinkle, who
                    also wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor checked the translation against the
                    Tibetan and edited the text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnajālin</title> belongs to the
                        General Sūtra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</foreign>) section of the
                        Kangyur. It was translated into Tibetan some time during the late eighth or
                        early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> by a certain Yeshé Nyingpo
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes snying po</foreign>) (of whom we
                        know very little apart from his name) and the Indian scholar Jñānagarbha,
                        who participated in numerous translation projects in Tibet during the early
                        translation period.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-4">
                            Interestingly, Yeshé Nyingpo is a Tibetan translation of Jñānagarbha,
                            and they could perhaps be coreferential terms. As far as we are aware,
                            this was the only sūtra translated jointly by these two figures.</note>
                        The translation was subsequently edited during the same period by the
                        prolific translator Kawa Paltsek (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ska ba dpal
                            brtsegs</foreign>). Therefore, the Tibetan translation, which we have
                        rendered into English here, would have been completed during the early
                        translation period, a dating that is also attested by the text’s inclusion
                        in the early-ninth-century Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar
                            ma</foreign>) catalogue.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-5"> The Denkarma catalogue is dated to c. 812
                                <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. In this catalogue, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnajālin</title> is included among
                            the Miscellaneous Sūtras (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde sna
                                tshogs</foreign>) less than ten sections (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign>) long. See Denkarma, 298.b.4. See also
                            Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p. 86, no. 159.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-6"/>
                    <p tid="8">The original Sanskrit no longer seems to be extant, but a single
                        translation was made into Chinese (Taishō vol. 14, no. 433). This Chinese
                        translation was produced much earlier than the Tibetan, sometime during the
                        end of the third century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> by the Indo-Scythian
                        monk Dharmarakṣa (c. 233–310 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>). Dharmarakṣa was
                        one of the most prolific translators of early Chinese Buddhism, producing
                        more than 150 translations of canonical scriptures during his life. With
                        this Chinese translation, we thus have a very early <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">terminus ante quem</foreign> for the composition of this
                        discourse that places it right in the formative period of the literature of
                        the Great Vehicle in India. The fact that it was translated into Chinese and
                        Tibetan with more than five hundred years separating the two events also
                        points to a certain popularity and longevity of the text in Buddhist
                            India.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-7">Additionally, the sūtra was also translated into Mongolian from
                            Tibetan, seemingly around the fourteenth century, although the colophon
                            dates the translation to the seventeenth century (Higuchi 2015). The
                            other mentions of the sūtra that we have come across are two brief
                            references to it in Schopen 1983, pp. 121, 127. </note> In producing
                        this translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while
                        consulting the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) as well as the Stok Palace manuscript. We have
                        also occasionally consulted the Chinese translation and included any such
                        influence on the translation in the annotations.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnajālin</title> is primarily
                        concerned with the benefits that arise from knowing the names of various
                        buddhas in different realms. Like many sūtras, this scripture begins with an
                        interlocutor raising a question to the buddha. In this case, it is the young
                        boy Ratnajālin who asks whether or not there are buddhas whose very names
                        carry such transformative power as to elevate the knower to buddhahood in
                        addition to arousing virtually all other important spiritual qualities. The
                        buddha replies that there are, in fact, several buddhas whose names hold
                        such power and he proceeds to describe and name these buddhas and their
                        realms as well as declare the specific effects that knowledge of their names
                        enacts. The notion that a devotee can become destined for awakening merely
                        by hearing the names of buddhas who live in other realms is shared by a
                        number of Great Vehicle sūtras. In the Degé Kangyur, however, since a number
                        of organizing principles were at play when the editors structured the canon,
                        the texts concerned with the liberating effects of the names of various
                        buddhas ended up not being grouped together based on their shared subject
                        matter but instead became dispersed throughout the different sūtra
                        collections due to other editorial concerns. Therefore, we find <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnajālin</title> grouped together with
                        the twenty-six sūtras that all share a similar title element (<title xml:lang="en">The Questions of</title> . . .).<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-9"> In the Degé Kangyur we find these
                            sūtras placed from Toh 148–174.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-10"/>
                    <p tid="10">As for the events in the sūtra, the story begins in Vaiśālī with
                        Ratnajālin, an eight-year-old boy of the Licchavi clan. Based on a dream,
                        Ratnajālin leaves the city to invite the Buddha and the saṅgha to visit
                        Vaiśālī for their daily alms round. The following day, the Buddha arrives in
                        Vaiśālī as many miracles delight the people. At the proper time Ratnajālin
                        asks the Buddha about the power inherent in the names of the buddhas, in
                        particular whether there are buddhas whose names, simply upon being heard,
                        have the efficacy to propel the listener forward on the path to awakening.
                        In reply, the Buddha mentions six specific buddhas living in distant buddha
                        realms in the four cardinal directions as well as in the directions above
                        and below. He mentions them by name and declares that trust in their names
                        and existence is the key factor that ensures a number of desired benefits,
                        including the eventual attainment of awakening. Thus, as long as one trusts
                        them, these buddha names have tremendous beneficial powers. Concluding his
                        teaching, the Buddha describes the benefits that ensue from hearing this
                        discourse—primarily that those who hear it will be able to attract many
                        beings and propel them onto the path of awakening. Lastly, he advises the
                        assembled community to uphold this discourse and offers Ratnajālin a
                        prophecy of his future meeting with the buddha Maitreya.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="11"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="12">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="13">The Questions of Ratnajālin</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-13"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <ref cRef="F.144.a" type="folio"/>
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-14"/>
                    <p tid="19">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Vaiśālī
                        in a mansion located by the Monkey Pond, together with a great assembly of
                        monks. In the assembly were four hundred twenty million bodhisattvas. Some
                        of the bodhisattvas, such as Maitreya, were held back by just one birth,
                        while others were held back by two, three, four, five, ten, thirty, or forty
                        births, with some bodhisattvas even held back by one thousand births. Also
                        in the assembly were six hundred million worthy ones and nine hundred ninety
                        million gods including the gods in the desire realm and form realm, the four
                        great kings, Śakra who rules the gods, <term>Brahmā</term> who rules the
                        Sahā world, the god Great Splendor, the god Candraprabha, the god
                        Sūryaprabha, the god Pinnacle of Renown, and the god <term>Joyful</term>. In
                        attendance were also the nāga kings Anavatapta, Sāgara, Vāsukin, Manasvin,
                        Nanda, Upananda, Mucilinda, and Mahāmucilinda, as well as the demigod
                        sovereign Rāhu and the retinues of all the other demigod sovereigns.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-16"/>
                    <p tid="20">At that time, in the city of Vaiśālī, there was a Licchavi named
                        Limitless Strength, who was the son of Siṃha the captain. Limitless
                        Strength, son of Siṃha, himself had a son, a young Licchavi boy known as
                        Ratnajālin. Since this child had previously served many buddhas, <ref cRef="F.144.b" type="folio"/> he had come to possess the lamp that
                        shines with the immense light of the Dharma way. One time, when he was
                        around eight years old, he had a dream as he slept. In his dream, the god
                        Saṁtuṣita descended from the Heaven of Joy and spoke to him, encouraging
                        Ratnajālin with this melodious song: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-17"/>
                    <lg tid="21">
                        <l>“The essential being, the Victor, the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>Abides, illuminating the entire trichiliocosm.</l>
                        <l>With vast accumulations of merit, he appears in golden hue.</l>
                        <l>The appearance of this great being is beautiful in all respects.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-18"/>
                    <lg tid="22">
                        <l>“He is endowed with the light of ten million suns</l>
                        <l>And shines like a thousand or even ten million</l>
                        <l>Luminous full moons—</l>
                        <l>As many as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-19"/>
                    <lg tid="23">
                        <l>“Shining like many millions of suns— </l>
                        <l>He shines like the supreme disk in the east,</l>
                        <l>Those in the south and the west,</l>
                        <l>And the supreme disk in the north.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-20"/>
                    <lg tid="24">
                        <l>“The light rays that stream forth</l>
                        <l>From each pore of this shining protector of the world</l>
                        <l>Will, each and every one, </l>
                        <l>Make all full moons appear gloomy. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-21"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>“From each pore in the skin of those who are omniscient,</l>
                        <l>Light streams forth.</l>
                        <l>The light that shines from him illuminates as many worlds</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in sixty-six Ganges rivers.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-22"/>
                    <p tid="26">In the morning, the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin told his father
                        Limitless Strength, “Father, last night the god Saṁtuṣita arrived from the
                        Heaven of Joy and encouraged me with a melodious song. Father, I am telling
                        you this so that we can begin the practice of worshiping the Thus-Gone One.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-23"/>
                    <p tid="27">At this point the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin sang these verses to his
                        father Limitless Strength:</p>
                    <lg tid="28">
                        <l>“The captain of all beings, the perfect Buddha,</l>
                        <l>The great being inconceivably learned in the ways of the world— </l>
                        <l>Please, may you worship this protector, <ref cRef="F.145.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>For such a guide rarely appears in the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-25"/>
                    <lg tid="29">
                        <l>“Just like the uḍumbara flower,</l>
                        <l>He has a beautiful color and delicious scent and fragrance. </l>
                        <l>He is stainless and without afflictions.</l>
                        <l>Such a perfect flower is hard to find.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-26"/>
                    <lg tid="30">
                        <l>“Father, thus I supplicate you: </l>
                        <l>Right now, may you joyfully agree</l>
                        <l>To worship the luminous protector of the world</l>
                        <l>Who perceives the ultimate!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-27"/>
                    <p tid="31">The Licchavi Limitless Strength was delighted and addressed the
                        Licchavi Siṃha:</p>
                    <lg tid="32">
                        <l>“O Captain, follow my son’s advice</l>
                        <l>To worship the Victorious One!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-29"/>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>To worship the Guide, the Lion of the Śākyas,</l>
                        <l>And to delight the wonderful youth,</l>
                        <l>Six hundred million householders set to work.</l>
                        <l>Śakra with his thousand divine eyes, </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-30"/>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>The powerful gods <term>Brahmā</term> and Īśvara</l>
                        <l>And Susārthavāha, son of <term>Māra</term>, </l>
                        <l>Together with ten million earthly gods,</l>
                        <l>All came to the delight of Vaiśālī. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-31"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>Here they produced</l>
                        <l>Billions of thrones made of gold and silver</l>
                        <l>And ornamented with the seven precious substances.</l>
                        <l>Each throne had billions of precious items.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-32"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>Each side of the thrones was adorned with jewels</l>
                        <l>And had a fine victory banner of the seven precious substances
                            attached.</l>
                        <l>The size of the thrones was several leagues.</l>
                        <l>The victory banners were half a league high. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-33"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>On either side of the victory banners</l>
                        <l>Was a platform higher than a league</l>
                        <l>Made exclusively of a single substance—</l>
                        <l>Precious jewels rising more than a league in height.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-34"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>In between the thrones divine banners were hung </l>
                        <l>More than a league long.</l>
                        <l>The banners featured nets of golden tassels </l>
                        <l>Adorned with strings of bells. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-35"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>Beneath the thrones were well-fastened columns,</l>
                        <l>More than one billion of them.</l>
                        <l>All of these perfect thrones</l>
                        <l>Were firmly placed, as if bolted to the ground.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-36"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>The surface of the thrones was made of gold—</l>
                        <l>Golden and with silver and beryl,</l>
                        <l>Crystal, coral, and emerald too. <ref cRef="F.145.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Also, at the bottom and the base</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-37"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>Were placed natural pearl parasols, </l>
                        <l>Numbering in the billions</l>
                        <l>And colored red with deep red sandalwood.</l>
                        <l>Having produced the thrones</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-38"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>And the heavenly ornaments,<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-39"> Here “heavenly ornaments” translates
                                the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mkha’
                                    rten</foreign>. The Sanskrit listed in the Negi dictionary for
                                this term is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vyomaka</foreign>, which Monier-Williams defines as “a kind of
                                ornament.” </note> clear as water, on the thrones,<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-40">Translated based on Stok:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khri rnams dang ni khri
                                    la chu lta bu’i/ /mkha’ rten dag kyang byas nas de la
                                    ni</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">
                                    khri rnams dang ni khril tshul lta bu yi / mkha’ rten dag kyang
                                    byas nas de la ni</foreign>. Yongle, Peking Kangxi, and
                                Narthang: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khri rnams dang ni
                                    khril chu lta ba’i / mkha’ rten dag kyang byas nas de la
                                    ni</foreign>. Lhasa Zhol: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">khri rnams dang ni khri tshul lta bu yi / mkha’
                                    rten dag kyang byas nas de la ni</foreign>. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Golden nets were placed on them</l>
                        <l>And adorned with gold, </l>
                        <l>Silver, beryl, and crystal.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-41"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>Having produced the ornaments of coral and emerald, </l>
                        <l>Affixed to those were sweet-sounding bells</l>
                        <l>Resounding with the voice of the Guide.</l>
                        <l>Fumigants were placed there for veneration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-42"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>In the sky above Vaiśālī </l>
                        <l>Was a canopy sewn of golden thread. </l>
                        <l>From each and every golden thread</l>
                        <l>Hung billions of tassels of the finest jewels</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-43"/>
                    <lg tid="45">
                        <l>And billions of ornamental garlands of pearl</l>
                        <l>Strung with golden thread.</l>
                        <l>All the Licchavis who lived in the city of Vaiśālī</l>
                        <l>Were joyful, regardless of where they went.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-44"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>They covered the ground of the city of Vaiśālī</l>
                        <l>With pieces of cloth the length of seven men</l>
                        <l>Printed with lattices of red sandalwood</l>
                        <l>And made of well-spun fabrics.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-45"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>On the right side, seventy billion instruments</l>
                        <l>Of thousands of different varieties rang forth.</l>
                        <l>On the left side, a further seventy billion</l>
                        <l>Were also engaged in venerating the Lion of the Śākyas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-46"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>Having set forth such a great array, </l>
                        <l>The Licchavi boy named Ratnajālin</l>
                        <l>Joyfully announced to his parents,</l>
                        <l>“I am going before the Buddha.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-47"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>This learned one left the city</l>
                        <l>And went to where the great victorious lord was staying.</l>
                        <l>The young man bowed his head at the feet of this ocean of virtues</l>
                        <l>And stood to one side.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-48"/>
                    <p tid="50">Then the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin left the city of Vaiśālī and went
                        to where the Blessed One was staying. He bowed to the feet of the Blessed
                        One and stood to one side. With him standing there to the side, the Blessed
                        One <ref cRef="F.146.a" type="folio"/> delivered a Dharma discourse to the
                        Licchavi boy Ratnajālin that delighted, captivated, and uplifted him, and
                        made him utterly delighted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-49"/>
                    <p tid="51">The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then stood up, draped his shawl over one
                        shoulder, and knelt on his right knee. With his palms together he bowed
                        toward the Blessed One and asked, “Would the Blessed One and his monastic
                        saṅgha agree to take tomorrow’s midday meal at my home?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-50"/>
                    <p tid="52">Out of love for the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin, the Blessed One showed
                        his acceptance of the offer by remaining silent. The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin
                        understood that the Blessed One had accepted through his silence, and so he
                        circumambulated the Blessed One three times before taking his leave. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-51"/>
                    <p tid="53">The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then entered the city of Vaiśālī along
                        with Śakra who rules the gods, <term>Brahmā</term> who rules the Sahā world,
                        and the god Great Splendor. With enthusiasm and delight, they began to
                        prepare abundant varieties of food. When the night had passed, they set out
                        cushions and decorated Vaiśālī. They then returned to the Blessed One, bowed
                        to him, and stood to one side. The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then said to the
                        Blessed One, “Blessed One, it is time for the midday meal. If it please you,
                        your meal is ready. The time has come.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-52"/>
                    <p tid="54">Accordingly, on that morning the Blessed One donned his lower
                        garments and Dharma robes. Bearing his alms bowl, with his infinite saṅgha
                        of monks he rose into the sky to the height of seven men <ref cRef="F.146.b" type="folio"/> and traveled to the city of Vaiśālī.
                        <!--module starts-->As soon as he moved, the transformative power of the
                        Thus-Gone One caused all the worlds of the great trichiliocosm to shake six
                        times as they quivered, trembled, and quaked; wobbled, rocked, and swayed;
                        vibrated, shuddered, and reeled; clattered, rattled, and clanged; and
                        tremored, shook, and convulsed. Thus they shook six times with eighteen
                        omens.<!--module ends--> He also displayed trillions of miracles as he
                        traveled to the city of Vaiśālī. At that time, trillions of gods scattered
                        and tossed blue, pink, red, and white lotuses, flowers made of precious
                        divine substances, the powdered aloewood of the gods, powdered gems, gold
                        from the Jambū river, and powdered divine gems upon the Blessed One.
                        Trillions of divine instruments resounded. Unfathomable divine ornaments
                        adorned him. In the sky above, a steady rain of red sandalwood powder fell
                        to the depth of a chariot axle.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-53"/>
                    <p tid="55">The Blessed One then arrived at the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin’s home
                        and sat upon the seat that had been prepared for him along with the saṅghas
                        of fully ordained monks and nuns and the assemblies of novice monks and
                        nuns. Seeing that he had arrived, the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin personally
                        served the Blessed One with an abundance of the finest food, drink, and
                        sweets, to please him and serve him everything he wished for. When the
                        Licchavi boy Ratnajālin noticed that the Blessed One had finished eating, he
                        picked up the alms bowl, offered water, and covered the Blessed One’s hands.
                            <ref cRef="F.147.a" type="folio"/> He then dressed the Blessed One with
                        a priceless set of the three Dharma robes. He also dressed the saṅghas of
                        fully ordained monks and nuns and the assemblies of novice monks and nuns
                        with sets of the three Dharma robes. Why? He did this because he was moved
                        by the power of the Blessed One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-54"/>
                    <p tid="56">The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then asked the Blessed One, “If the
                        Blessed One were to grant me the opportunity to request a teaching, I would
                        like to ask the Blessed Thus-Gone One a few questions.”</p>
                    <p tid="57">The Blessed One responded to the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin, “Young
                        man, you may ask the Thus-Gone One anything you are concerned with. Then I
                        shall delight you with teachings that answer your questions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-56"/>
                    <p tid="58">The Licchavi boy Ratnajālin then asked the Blessed One, “Blessed
                        One, in other worlds, are there blessed buddhas that through their previous
                        aspirations have names that, when merely heard, help noble sons and
                        daughters who follow the Bodhisattva Vehicle to end all doubt and
                        hesitation, to become irreversible and fully awaken to unsurpassed and
                        perfect buddhahood, to gain recollection of past lives, to never have a
                        stingy attitude, to be surrounded by the bodhisattva assembly and to be
                        without the assembly of hearers, to acquire countless trillions of virtues,
                        to satisfy all beings by pleasing all the buddhas, to terrify the māras, to
                        purify all buddha realms, to cleanse the stains in the minds of all beings,
                            <ref cRef="F.147.b" type="folio"/> to inspire all beings to the virtuous
                        Dharma, to be protected by the gods, to be considered by the bodhisattvas,
                        to be blessed by the thus-gone ones, to never be separated from the blessed
                        buddhas, to perfect bodhisattva conduct by possessing the finest qualities,
                        to gain the entirety of the 84,000 verbal expressions, to attain the voice
                        of <term>Brahmā</term>, and to gain a voice that is in conformity with all
                        worlds?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-57"/>
                    <p tid="59">The Blessed One answered the Licchavi boy Ratnajālin, “Excellent,
                        excellent, young man. Your thought to ask the Thus-Gone One about such
                        subjects reflects excellent eloquence and fine analysis. Thus, listen well,
                        young man, and bear what I say in mind. Then I will teach you.” </p>
                    <p tid="60">“Blessed One, I shall do just that.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-59"/>
                    <p tid="61">The bodhisattva Ratnajālin listened as the Blessed One had
                        instructed, and so the Blessed One said, “Young man, to the east of here
                        there is a world called Pearled. Young man, consider this: There are as many
                        peaks of existence as there are grains of sand in the Ganges. And all those
                        too are filled with the smallest possible particles. If a person then came
                        along and carried away one single such particle and placed it in a spot past
                        as many trillions of buddha realms as there are smallest particles in all
                        those world systems under the peaks of existence—then, young man, by
                        repeating this in the same way for a long time, would that great mass of
                        particles eventually run out <ref cRef="F.148.a" type="folio"/> and reach
                        its limit? Now, young man, tell me, would it be easy to consider, count,
                        assess, or determine the places in the universe where that person placed or
                        did not place those particles?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-60"/>
                    <p tid="62">“Blessed One, it would not be easy. Blessed One, for that reason,
                        anyone who gets the right sense of this analogy that you have expressed
                        would gain a great degree of understanding.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-61"/>
                    <p tid="63">The Blessed One said, “Young man, if all the worlds in which that
                        person placed a particle, or alternatively the worlds in which that person
                        did not place a particle—ranging from the mass of water underlying these
                        worlds up to their peaks—were filled with minute particles, and if a second
                        person came along and removed a single particle from them at a time and
                        placed it in a spot past as many trillions of buddha realms as there were
                        minute particles in those worlds, then, young man, by repeating this for a
                        long time, eventually that great mass of particles would become dispersed.
                        Young man, by this way of proceeding, the latter person would travel past
                        nine million nine hundred thousand incalculable numbers of worlds and thus
                        arrive past countless trillions of buddha realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-62"/>
                    <p tid="64">“That is where the world called Pearled is located. There the
                        thus-gone one, the worthy one, the perfect buddha Majestic King with the
                        Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by Precious Moonlight lives, abides,
                        and teaches the Dharma. Young man, those noble sons or daughters who abide
                        in the Bodhisattva Vehicle, who have no doubt regarding the name of the
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice
                        of Learning Adorned by Precious Moonlight, <ref cRef="F.148.b" type="folio"/> and who trust in my vision, will attain the dominion of a universal
                        monarch after their lives are over. A buddha will appear within their
                        dominions. When they see that thus-gone one, they will perform boundless
                        veneration, practice pure conduct, and master the five types of miraculous
                        abilities. Immediately upon beholding that thus-gone one, they will achieve
                        the <distinct>hundred-swirled</distinct> retention. They will serve as many
                        buddhas as there are grains of sand in the Ganges. They will turn away from
                        saṃsāra for an equivalent number of eons. Their minds will be undeluded, and
                        they will fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood. Their bodies
                        will become solid like that of Nārāyaṇa. Residing in a single place, they
                        will possess the four necessities.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-63"> Translation tentative. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lus dbyibs gcig la spi dza bzhi par
                                ’gyur</foreign>. The Pedurma edition records no variants. Stok:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rus dbyibs gcig la spi dza
                                bzhi bar ’gyur</foreign>. Here we have translated this line based on
                            the corresponding passage in the Chinese version, which reads <foreign xml:lang="zh" type="quote">住在一處具足四事</foreign>: “Residing in a single
                            place, they will possess the four necessities” (i.e., shelter, clothing,
                            food, and medicine). </note> Their bodies will take on golden
                        complexions. They will be adorned with the thirty-two major marks of a great
                        being. They will gain the melodious voice of <term>Brahmā</term>. They will
                        eliminate all unfree states and attain an abundance of leisure.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-64"/>
                    <p tid="65">In order to elaborate on the meaning of what he had taught, the
                        Blessed One then spoke in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this world protector</l>
                        <l>And entertain no doubt,</l>
                        <l>Trusting in what I see,</l>
                        <l>Shall become worthy of veneration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-66"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“They will attain the eternal dominion</l>
                        <l>Of universal monarchs and behold buddhas.</l>
                        <l>Having beheld them, they will perform</l>
                        <l>Boundless and inconceivable veneration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-67"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“They will always practice pure conduct.</l>
                        <l>They will realize all forms of miraculous abilities.</l>
                        <l>Once they see the buddha, they will achieve</l>
                        <l>The <distinct>hundred-swirled</distinct> retention. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-68"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“They will behold as many buddhas</l>
                        <l>As there are sands in the Ganges.</l>
                        <l>They will abandon saṃsāra</l>
                        <l>For that many billions of eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-69"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of the world protector</l>
                        <l>Spoken to the assemblies and saṅghas <ref cRef="F.149.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Will become undeluded,</l>
                        <l>And it will be a cause for awakening to buddhahood.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-70"/>
                    <lg tid="71">
                        <l>“They will always be like Nārāyaṇa.</l>
                        <l>Residing in a single place, they will possess the four necessities.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-71"> Translation
                                tentative. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lus dbyibs
                                    gcig la spi dza bzhi</foreign>. The Pedurma edition records no
                                variants. Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rus dbyibs
                                    gcig la spi dza bzhi</foreign>. Although the Chinese translation
                                does not include this line, we have adopted the meaning from the
                                seemingly identical line that occurred above (see <ptr target="#UT22084-059-006-63"/>). </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Their bodies will be golden colored</l>
                        <l>And display the thirty-two marks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-72"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>“Those who hear his name</l>
                        <l>And prostrate with their five points<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-73"> Hands, feet, and head.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Will permanently gain the voice of <term>Brahmā</term>
                        </l>
                        <l>And abandon the unfree states.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-74"/>
                    <lg tid="73">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this world protector</l>
                        <l>And entertain no doubt</l>
                        <l>Will not shy away from awakening.</l>
                        <l>They shall never have any hesitation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-75"/>
                    <lg tid="74">
                        <l>“Those who remember the victor’s name</l>
                        <l>For a full seven days and nights</l>
                        <l>Will purify the infinite seeing eyes</l>
                        <l>Praised by the buddhas. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-76"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>“They shall refine the eyes of flesh</l>
                        <l>Into the eyes of a god.</l>
                        <l>They will perceive as many buddhas</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-77"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>“They will venerate each of them</l>
                        <l>And receive teachings from each as well.</l>
                        <l>Seeing all the buddhas with their own eyes,</l>
                        <l>They will bring comfort to all humanity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-78"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this thus-gone one</l>
                        <l>Have already offered unfathomable service</l>
                        <l>To the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>All of whom they will recollect.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-79"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>“If his name is relayed</l>
                        <l>Before any being at all,</l>
                        <l>When those other beings hear this name,</l>
                        <l>They too will definitely proceed to awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-80"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>“By generating faith in this buddha,</l>
                        <l>The unfree states are dispelled,</l>
                        <l>While by engaging in debate and quarreling,</l>
                        <l>One will be born into the unfree states.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-81"/>
                    <lg tid="80">
                        <l>“Once beings have heard</l>
                        <l>The name of this great sage,</l>
                        <l>They shall no longer be interested</l>
                        <l>In debate and quarreling. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-82"/>
                    <lg tid="81">
                        <l>“The actions that lead to the Hell of Ultimate Torment,</l>
                        <l>Which could last for eons,</l>
                        <l>As well as the actions that produce a simple headache—</l>
                        <l>All such actions will not ripen for these beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-83"/>
                    <lg tid="82">
                        <l>“They shall not be burned by fire,</l>
                        <l>Nor drown in water.</l>
                        <l>Even when they draw the ire of the king,</l>
                        <l>It shall be quickly assuaged. <ref cRef="F.149.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-84"/>
                    <lg tid="83">
                        <l>“Those who remember this sage’s name</l>
                        <l>Shall be spared many illnesses</l>
                        <l>Including blindness, defective sight, </l>
                        <l>Paralysis, hunchback, and decrepitude.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-85"/>
                    <lg tid="84">
                        <l>“Evil and malevolent</l>
                        <l>Yakṣas, gandharvas, demigods, </l>
                        <l>Kumbhāṇḍas, rākṣasas, and humans</l>
                        <l>Shall be unable to harm them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-86"/>
                    <lg tid="85">
                        <l>“Those who remember this sage’s name</l>
                        <l>Shall be favored and preferred</l>
                        <l>By all the bhūtas, gandharvas, yakṣas,</l>
                        <l>Nāgas, and gods.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-87"/>
                    <lg tid="86">
                        <l>“Those who hear this protector’s name</l>
                        <l>Shall swiftly attain vast accumulations,</l>
                        <l>Sublime voices, and absorption.</l>
                        <l>Their myriad virtues will be renowned.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-88"/>
                    <lg tid="87">
                        <l>“Having heard this world protector’s name</l>
                        <l>Without doubting it,</l>
                        <l>They will hew to awakening</l>
                        <l>Throughout all their subsequent lives.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-89"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>“Those who hear this great sage’s name</l>
                        <l>Shall uphold and preach</l>
                        <l>The way of the well-spoken Dharma </l>
                        <l>Taught by the buddhas who have gone beyond anguish.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-90"/>
                    <lg tid="89">
                        <l>“They shall uphold the teachings</l>
                        <l>Well spoken by all the buddhas.</l>
                        <l>They shall manifest the supreme array</l>
                        <l>And serve all the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-91"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>“Once they pass away,</l>
                        <l>They will swiftly behold myriad buddhas</l>
                        <l>And uphold the teachings</l>
                        <l>Spoken by the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-92"/>
                    <lg tid="91">
                        <l>“Those who hear this protector’s name</l>
                        <l>Shall earnestly train and establish</l>
                        <l>Millions of beings on the path,</l>
                        <l>Bringing them all to awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-93"/>
                    <lg tid="92">
                        <l>“Those who trust what I have seen</l>
                        <l>Shall uphold the teachings</l>
                        <l>Of all the buddhas, the protectors,</l>
                        <l>And additionally venerate the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-94"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>“Those who have faith in this buddha’s wisdom,</l>
                        <l>Trusting in what I have seen,</l>
                        <l>Shall be liberated from many fetters.</l>
                        <l>They will cross the abyss and become fearless.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-95"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>“Whosoever abandons the sublime Dharma</l>
                        <l>Is among <term>Māra</term>’s ranks.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-96"> In the Tibetan text, this verse has
                                only two lines.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-97"/>
                    <lg tid="95">
                        <l>“The body hairs of every being</l>
                        <l>Who migrates among the five types of beings</l>
                        <l>Could be consolidated within</l>
                        <l>A single hair on the teacher’s kneecap.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-98"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>“From a single pore</l>
                        <l>Of the protector, the guardian of the world, <ref cRef="F.150.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>As many rays of light as there are</l>
                        <l>Grains of sand in the Ganges stream forth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-99"/>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>“Those who trust in the <term type="ignore">infinite light</term>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of the world protector</l>
                        <l>Shall in one life behold many buddhas—</l>
                        <l>Millions of buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-100"/>
                    <lg tid="98">
                        <l>“Those who hear the teaching</l>
                        <l>Of this discourse by the Dharma king</l>
                        <l>And never doubt it</l>
                        <l>Shall become like me.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-101"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>“Those who hear the teaching</l>
                        <l>Of this discourse in Vaiśālī</l>
                        <l>Shall themselves preach it to others</l>
                        <l>At a later time.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-102"/>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>“Those who preach this widely</l>
                        <l>Shall come to pervade as many worlds</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in the Ganges</l>
                        <l>With a single burst of light.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-103"/>
                    <lg tid="101">
                        <l>“One may fill with gold</l>
                        <l>All the buddha realms,</l>
                        <l>The numbers of which defy counting,<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-104"> Translated based on Yongle, Peking
                                Kangxi, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chod</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mchod</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>And offer it to the world protectors.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-105"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>“Yet, in comparison, those who hear this name</l>
                        <l>And who are truly delighted by it</l>
                        <l>And utter their homage to the buddhas</l>
                        <l>Obtain inconceivably more merit.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-106"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“The mass of merit gained</l>
                        <l>By repeatedly paying homage</l>
                        <l>To all the world protectors</l>
                        <l>Cannot be expressed by any measure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-107"/>
                    <lg tid="104">
                        <l>“Those who hear the world protector’s name</l>
                        <l>And do not hesitate about it</l>
                        <l>Will have their bodies filled with light</l>
                        <l>And become like precious gems.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-108"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“After they have passed beyond,</l>
                        <l>Those who remember the name of the sage</l>
                        <l>Will have the sweet scent of divine red sandalwood</l>
                        <l>Waft from their mouth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-109"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name</l>
                        <l>Of the buddha, the protector, the essential being,</l>
                        <l>Will have light stream from their pores,</l>
                        <l>Beautifying their bodies.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-110"/>
                    <lg tid="107">
                        <l>“In all of their ensuing lives </l>
                        <l>They will become deeply learned.</l>
                        <l>They will retain their unfathomable erudition,</l>
                        <l>Just like Ānanda does for the Buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-111"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>“When they behold the one who illuminates the world,</l>
                        <l>They will attain boundless happiness.</l>
                        <l>As they engage in bodhisattva conduct,</l>
                        <l>They will recall all their lives.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-112"/>
                    <lg tid="109">
                        <l>“Even when they see the victors’ heart sons,</l>
                        <l>They will attain boundless happiness. <ref cRef="F.150.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>They will make extensive offerings </l>
                        <l>With incense, flowers, and ointments.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-113"/>
                    <lg tid="110">
                        <l>“This does not include those who do not remember</l>
                        <l>The name of this world protector when it is spoken,</l>
                        <l>Or those who are on <term>Māra</term>’s side,</l>
                        <l>Or those who have previously been extremists.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-114"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“As I have taught this Dharma way,</l>
                        <l>Those who have heard it now</l>
                        <l>Shall also receive this discourse in their hands</l>
                        <l>In a future life.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-115"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“Those who hear the explanation</l>
                        <l>Of this sublime discourse</l>
                        <l>Have previously venerated and served,</l>
                        <l>And they shall receive it in their hands again.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-116"/>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>“Those who make aspirations</l>
                        <l>Shall, in a future life,</l>
                        <l>Receive into their hands</l>
                        <l>This discourse spoken by the Dharma King.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-117"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“Having faith in this discourse</l>
                        <l>Brings even more merit</l>
                        <l>Than honoring countless buddhas</l>
                        <l>With a one-pointed mind.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-118"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“They forever will have beautiful bodies and lots of merit</l>
                        <l>And be fearless and wealthy.</l>
                        <l>They will be mindful </l>
                        <l>And ornamented with the major marks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-119"/>
                    <lg tid="116">
                        <l>“Thus, having heard</l>
                        <l>The teaching of this discourse,</l>
                        <l>In the future retain it, teach it,</l>
                        <l>And explain it to others!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-120"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“Those who have honored hundreds of thousands</l>
                        <l>Of buddhas, universal monarchs,</l>
                        <l>Shall also in the future</l>
                        <l>Have vision free from doubt.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-121"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“Those who have performed service</l>
                        <l>For countless world protectors in the past</l>
                        <l>Will trust what they hear and see</l>
                        <l>Of this world protector.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-122"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>“Those who hear his name</l>
                        <l>Will actualize the form of a buddha.</l>
                        <l>They will guard the teachings </l>
                        <l>And the sublime Dharma of all the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-123"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“However, those who abandon the teachings of awakening</l>
                        <l>Shall become like sheep—mute and with poor eyesight,</l>
                        <l>Or even with no eyes at all</l>
                        <l>For millions of eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-124"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“Compared to destroying countless reliquaries,</l>
                        <l>With one’s own hands,</l>
                        <l>It is a far viler deed</l>
                        <l>To abandon this discourse.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-125"/>
                    <lg tid="122">
                        <l>“Thus when, at a future time, </l>
                        <l>You attain that which I am preaching, <ref cRef="F.151.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Do not harbor any doubt</l>
                        <l>About the unsurpassed wisdom of the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-126"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“Once you have heard this discourse,</l>
                        <l>Perform respectful veneration</l>
                        <l>With flowers, incense, streamers,</l>
                        <l>Parasols, and powders!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-127"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>Then, with his soft and supple hands,</l>
                        <l>The Thus-Gone One</l>
                        <l>Repeatedly caressed</l>
                        <l>The Licchavi boy’s head.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-128"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>After this, the gods </l>
                        <l>Made a loud cry</l>
                        <l>And scattered pleasing divine flowers,</l>
                        <l>Filling the realm.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-129"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>The gods, having remained in the sky,</l>
                        <l>Then sang countless songs.</l>
                        <l>Millions of brahmā gods</l>
                        <l>Cast down a rain of red sandalwood powder.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-130"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>When Ratnajālin heard this discourse</l>
                        <l>Spoken by the Thus-Gone One,</l>
                        <l>He was pleased and delighted,</l>
                        <l>And spoke these words to the Thus-Gone One:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-131"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“In the future, </l>
                        <l>I will become a monk</l>
                        <l>And fearlessly preach this discourse</l>
                        <l>In towns and villages.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-132"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l>“I will act according to the Buddha’s teaching,</l>
                        <l>Which the perfect Buddha has spoken so gloriously.</l>
                        <l>Traveling millions of leagues</l>
                        <l>I will preach the way.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-133"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“I will serve all the gods, nāgas,</l>
                        <l>And kiṃnaras, </l>
                        <l>And other non-human beings,</l>
                        <l>Satisfying them with the gift of Dharma.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-134"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>When this unsurpassed discourse</l>
                        <l>Was taught by the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>The assembly of demigods celebrated</l>
                        <l>And scattered countless flowers.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-135"/>
                    <lg tid="132">
                        <l>A single hair of the Dharma King,</l>
                        <l>The Lion of the Śākyas, </l>
                        <l>Who is the supreme being in all buddha realms,</l>
                        <l>Illuminated all the realms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-136"/>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>Then, the tongue of the Teacher,</l>
                        <l>The great being, the essential being, </l>
                        <l>Emerged and covered millions of realms </l>
                        <l>As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-137"/>
                    <lg tid="134">
                        <l>As the Thus-Gone One covered millions of realms</l>
                        <l>Throughout the ten directions of the universe,</l>
                        <l>The youth Ratnajālin,</l>
                        <l>As well as other heroes and Licchavis</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-138"/>
                    <lg tid="135">
                        <l>Numbering six hundred million,</l>
                        <l>Arrived saying, “Please teach us!”</l>
                        <l>The Teacher then introduced <ref cRef="F.151.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>The Dharma to them all.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-139"/>
                    <lg tid="136">
                        <l>The buddhas gift every form of happiness,</l>
                        <l>And their eyes are unimpeded.</l>
                        <l>The countless thus-gone ones</l>
                        <l>Have abandoned doubt about awakened qualities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-140"/>
                    <lg tid="137">
                        <l>The buddhas’ wisdom is unimpeded—</l>
                        <l>It perceives the three times.</l>
                        <l>Given that they have dominion over all phenomena,</l>
                        <l>There is nothing unknown to the buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-141"/>
                    <lg tid="138">
                        <l>The Guide of Humans preaches</l>
                        <l>That the aggregates are nonexistent.</l>
                        <l>The four elements are as if hollow,</l>
                        <l>And nowhere are there sounds to be attached to.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-142"/>
                    <lg tid="139">
                        <l>The essence of the aggregates</l>
                        <l>Of form, feeling, perception,</l>
                        <l>Thoughts, formations, and consciousness</l>
                        <l>Should be known to be nonexistent.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-143"/>
                    <lg tid="140">
                        <l>Just as the Buddha has taught,</l>
                        <l>If one uncovers the aggregates,</l>
                        <l>One will swiftly attain retention</l>
                        <l>And become undeluded.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-144"/>
                    <lg tid="141">
                        <l>All phenomena are void—</l>
                        <l>All of them are empty and without self.</l>
                        <l>Of this there can be no debate or delusion.</l>
                        <l>This is what the Thus-Gone One has taught.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-145"/>
                    <p tid="142">“Young man, located in the south, past twelve buddha realms
                        reckoned as twice the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy,
                        there is a world called Adorned by the Moon. There resides the thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect buddha King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays. He is
                        alive and well and teaches the Dharma. Young man, when those noble sons or
                        daughters who abide in the Bodhisattva Vehicle hear the name of the blessed
                        one, the thus-gone one King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays—as long as
                        they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will achieve the
                        absorption of <distinct>emitting light rays</distinct> once they have passed
                        away. They will become knowledgeable in ten thousand countless trillions of
                        methods to gain absorption. <ref cRef="F.152.a" type="folio"/> They will
                        become knowledgeable in sixty countless trillions of dhāraṇī methods—from
                        the <distinct>oceanic</distinct> dhāraṇī to the <distinct>precious
                            treasury</distinct> dhāraṇī. They will be undeluded in this regard until
                        reaching the end of awakening. When they die, ten million buddhas will come
                        from the east and reveal themselves, and the same will occur from all other
                        directions. They will retain the Dharma that these blessed buddhas teach.
                        Until they reach awakening they will not lose this Dharma way. Having worked
                        to turn away from cyclic existence for five hundred eons starting from the
                        time they began as bodhisattvas, they will reach unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-146"/>
                    <p tid="143">The Blessed One then expressed this in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“Hearing the name of this protector,</l>
                        <l>The lord of humans, the world protector,</l>
                        <l>They will eliminate five hundred eons</l>
                        <l>Of cyclic existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-148"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“When death comes to those noble sons and daughters,</l>
                        <l>Millions of buddhas will appear to them.</l>
                        <l>Having seen them, paying homage with their faculties,</l>
                        <l>They will listen to the Dharma and retain it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-149"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“When they hear that thus-gone one’s name</l>
                        <l>And engage in sacred practice,</l>
                        <l>They will not waste the Dharma taught by them—</l>
                        <l>Even for millions of eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-150"/>
                    <lg tid="147">
                        <l>“By proclaiming the name of this buddha,</l>
                        <l>They will attain seventy thousand </l>
                        <l>Absorptions known as <distinct>precious</distinct>,</l>
                        <l>And they will proclaim millions of virtues.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-151"/>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“Those who apprehend the name of this sage</l>
                        <l>Will come to abide</l>
                        <l>In countless millions</l>
                        <l>Plus sixty million absorptions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-152"/>
                    <lg tid="149">
                        <l>“Thus, when heroes of equilibrium</l>
                        <l>Engage in bodhisattva conduct,</l>
                        <l>They establish many thousands of beings</l>
                        <l>In supreme awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-153"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“Until reaching perfect awakening,</l>
                        <l>They will not engage in desirous conduct.</l>
                        <l>The beings to whom they teach the name of this buddha</l>
                        <l>Will also turn away from desire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-154"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this buddha <ref cRef="F.152.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And teach it to all beings</l>
                        <l>Will never again enter unfree states;</l>
                        <l>It will not be hard for them to find leisure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-155"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“By pleasing the excellent<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-156">Translated based on Yongle and Peking
                                Kangxi: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shin tu bzang
                                    ba</foreign>. Degé and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shin tu bzung ba</foreign>.</note> buddhas </l>
                        <l>That appear,</l>
                        <l>They will abandon all the unfree states<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-157"> Translated based on Yongle, Peking
                                Kangxi, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nga
                                    yis</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nga
                                    yi</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>That I have described.<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-158"> Translated based on Yongle, Peking
                                Kangxi, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstan</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsten</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-159"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“Young man, if you were to understand</l>
                        <l>What the guide knows,</l>
                        <l>Once you knew the name of this teacher,</l>
                        <l>You would spread it throughout the ten directions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-160"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“Thus, young man, </l>
                        <l>If you share this name with others,</l>
                        <l>You will acquire genuine awakening</l>
                        <l>And become a protector of the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-161"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“Those who hear this buddha’s name,</l>
                        <l>Remember it without distraction,</l>
                        <l>And share it with others,</l>
                        <l>Will guard their awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-162"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l>“Those who hear this discourse</l>
                        <l>And teach it to others</l>
                        <l>Will guard these teachings</l>
                        <l>Of the well-spoken Dharma way.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-163"/>
                    <p tid="157">“Young man, located in the west, past worlds numbering three times
                        the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy, there is a world
                        called Citraratna. There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha King of
                        Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers lives. He is alive and well and teaches the
                        Dharma. Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great
                        Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one King of Blossoming Sal Tree
                        Flowers—as long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will
                        acquire five qualities once they have passed away. What are these five? When
                        their bodies are destroyed, buddhas will appear and they will attain the
                        position of a universal monarch, the five forms of miraculous abilities, the
                        recall of Dharma teachings, the <distinct>thousand-swirled</distinct>
                        dhāraṇī, and the thirty-two marks of a great being until they attain
                        awakening. They will achieve these five qualities.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-164"/>
                    <p tid="158">The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse: <ref cRef="F.153.a" type="folio"/>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this leader of men, this protector,</l>
                        <l>And are faithful, without hesitation,</l>
                        <l>Will acquire these five qualities,</l>
                        <l>Which shall not be lost until they attain awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-166"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“They will gain a golden-colored appearance,</l>
                        <l>The supreme knowledge of a universal monarch,</l>
                        <l>Merit rivaling that of Nārāyaṇa,</l>
                        <l>And the unceasing turning of the wheel of the sacred Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-167"/>
                    <lg tid="161">
                        <l>“They will be fortunate and have a thousand sons</l>
                        <l>Who are heroic and courageous, capable of defeating their opponents.</l>
                        <l>Adorned with marks, their bodies will have perfect limbs.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, their power will resemble that of a supreme ruler.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-168"/>
                    <lg tid="162">
                        <l>“They will have many thousands of queens </l>
                        <l>Who are fine and beautiful, with golden complexions.</l>
                        <l>Going late to bed and rising early,</l>
                        <l>They will never cause their supreme rulers any sorrow.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-169"/>
                    <lg tid="163">
                        <l>“The vassals, ministers, and major householders </l>
                        <l>Living in his realm</l>
                        <l>Will never cause the king any grief when they meet.</l>
                        <l>Their merit will even be greater than that.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-170"/>
                    <lg tid="164">
                        <l>“Even the crafty gods will find them difficult to match.</l>
                        <l>All the yakṣas and nāgas living in the human world</l>
                        <l>And all the other beings living in his realm</l>
                        <l>They will establish at the seat of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-171"/>
                    <lg tid="165">
                        <l>“Their dominion will expand and the harvests grow bountiful.</l>
                        <l>Their realm will be happy and buddhas will appear.</l>
                        <l>They will perform sacred worship of them.</l>
                        <l>The land of the king will be free from malice.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-172"/>
                    <lg tid="166">
                        <l>“Even those scholars who hear the perfect name of this buddha,</l>
                        <l>Yet doubt it or become displeased with it,</l>
                        <l>Will benefit from the perfect Dharma</l>
                        <l>In the sublime discourse that I have spoken today.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-173"/>
                    <lg tid="167">
                        <l>“However, this is not the case for those who abandoned the Dharma</l>
                        <l>Of previous victors, or those in the grip of demons,</l>
                        <l>Or those who in the past despised</l>
                        <l>The essential beings, the perfect victors. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-174"/>
                    <lg tid="168">
                        <l>“Young man, those who haven’t witnessed the delights</l>
                        <l>Of the royal palace and this realm of the Licchavis </l>
                        <l>And who haven’t seen me <ref cRef="F.153.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Will harbor doubts when they hear the name of this buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-175"/>
                    <p tid="169">“Young man, located in the north, past sixty buddha realms reckoned
                        as thrice the number of smallest particles in the previous analogy, there is
                        a world called Covered with a Jewel Net. There the thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect buddha Pure Moon Disk lives. He is alive and well and teaches the
                        Dharma. Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide in the Great
                        Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one Pure Moon Disk—as long as they do
                        not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will obtain the absorption called
                            <distinct>source of jewels</distinct> and behold as many buddhas as
                        there are grains of sand in the Ganges once they have passed away. For as
                        many millions of eons, they will turn away from cyclic existence. Such
                        beginning bodhisattvas will reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening. They
                        will also attain the absorption called <distinct>pleasant melody</distinct>.
                        They will not turn away from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-176"/>
                    <p tid="170">“Should women hear the name of the blessed thus-gone one Pure Moon
                        Disk without feeling any hesitation or doubt and with trust in my vision,
                        they will abandon their female faculties and gain male faculties once they
                        have passed away. They will establish many beings in unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening. They will achieve the absorption called <distinct>pleasant
                            melody</distinct>. They will not turn back from unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-177"/>
                    <p tid="171">The Blessed One then expressed this in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="172">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this sublime human</l>
                        <l>And do not doubt it</l>
                        <l>Will, after as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges, <ref cRef="F.154.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Abandon rebirth and change to a state free from anguish.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-179"/>
                    <lg tid="173">
                        <l>“They will behold and venerate</l>
                        <l>Buddhas as numerous as the sands of the Ganges. </l>
                        <l>All those buddhas they will venerate</l>
                        <l>In a single life, as the victors pass beyond anguish.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-180"/>
                    <lg tid="174">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this leader of men</l>
                        <l>As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening</l>
                        <l>And remember it without ever doubting it</l>
                        <l>Will achieve a similar exalted state.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-181"/>
                    <lg tid="175">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this supreme human</l>
                        <l>And do not doubt it at all</l>
                        <l>Shall obtain self-existing wisdom, buddhahood itself,</l>
                        <l>And skillfully attain the absorption called <distinct>pleasant
                                voice</distinct>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-182"/>
                    <lg tid="176">
                        <l>“As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening,</l>
                        <l>They will achieve the faculties of a pure individual.</l>
                        <l>They will be beautiful and endowed with all qualities—</l>
                        <l>Such distinctions they will attain.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-183"/>
                    <lg tid="177">
                        <l>“They will shine in all directions</l>
                        <l>And proceed to countless millions of realms.</l>
                        <l>As they behold the great sage engaging with the world,<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-184"> The translation “engaging
                                with the world” is tentative. All Tibetan versions consulted read:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’jig rten spyod
                                    pa</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>They will escape anguish and later discover awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-185"/>
                    <lg tid="178">
                        <l>“Having heard the name</l>
                        <l>Of that great lord, that thus-gone one,</l>
                        <l>One will attain such distinctions as perfect miraculous powers,</l>
                        <l>And also the desire to attain awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-186"/>
                    <lg tid="179">
                        <l>“Having developed interest in immaculate awakening,</l>
                        <l>They will share the name of the victor with others.</l>
                        <l>They will obtain virtues similar to his—</l>
                        <l>As brilliant as the full moon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-187"/>
                    <lg tid="180">
                        <l>“Such learned persons will establish </l>
                        <l>Fathomless multitudes of beings in supreme awakening.</l>
                        <l>Like the chariot of the moon in the sky,</l>
                        <l>They will be beautiful and shine brightly.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-188"/>
                    <lg tid="181">
                        <l>“Those who remember the name of this victor</l>
                        <l>Will have bodies that are just as beautiful.</l>
                        <l>Yet some scholars who hear the name of this victor</l>
                        <l>Might doubt it, finding displeasure in it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-189"/>
                    <lg tid="182">
                        <l>“As they engage in the perfect actions of sacred awakening, </l>
                        <l>These teachings will be helpful for them.</l>
                        <l>Due to the supreme great sage who engages with the world,</l>
                        <l>Such scholars will not come to ruin. <ref cRef="F.154.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-190"/>
                    <p tid="183">“Young man, located below us, past ninety-nine times the number of
                        particles in the previous analogy, there is a world called Lord of the
                        Supreme Banner. There resides the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha King Who
                        Is Peaceful and Splendorous in His Learning and Rich in Melody. He is alive
                        and well and teaches the Dharma. Young man, when those noble sons or
                        daughters who abide in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one
                        King Who Is Peaceful and Splendorous in His Learning and Rich in Melody—as
                        long as they do not doubt this but trust in my vision—they will achieve the
                        absorption called <distinct>utterly illuminating</distinct> once they have
                        passed away. At the time of death, they will see trillions of buddhas. In
                        all directions, as in the east, they will see trillions of buddhas. They
                        will retain all the Dharma teachings given by these blessed buddhas. Until
                        reaching awakening, they will be blessed by trillions of buddhas. Such
                        beginning bodhisattvas, having turned from cyclic existence for ninety-nine
                        trillion eons, will reach unsurpassed and perfect awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-191"/>
                    <p tid="184">The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="185">
                        <l>“Those in this world who hear<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-193"> Translated based on Yongle, Peking
                                Kangxi, Narthang, Lhasa Zhol, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thos</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thob</foreign>.</note> the supreme name</l>
                        <l>Of this buddha with an ocean of virtues</l>
                        <l>Will swiftly perform unsurpassed veneration</l>
                        <l>Of one hundred billion buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-194"/>
                    <lg tid="186">
                        <l>“Once they have venerated these limitless beings free from stains,</l>
                        <l>They will engage in the splendorous activity</l>
                        <l>Of the magnificent buddhas in all existences.</l>
                        <l>Later, they will also reach the perfect insight of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-195"/>
                    <lg tid="187">
                        <l>“Those who, in a single life, venerate as many guides</l>
                        <l>As there are grains of sand in the Ganges</l>
                        <l>Attain the <distinct>utterly illuminating</distinct> absorption <ref cRef="F.155.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And subsequently reach awakening beyond anguish.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-196"/>
                    <lg tid="188">
                        <l>“Having obtained immaculate awakening, great awakening,</l>
                        <l>They will turn the sublime wheel of Dharma,</l>
                        <l>Whereby they will establish beings in the supreme awakening of
                            buddhahood,</l>
                        <l>Transcending anguish just as rainfall quenches flames.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-197"/>
                    <lg tid="189">
                        <l>“The guide of humans, the charioteer of humans, </l>
                        <l>Is the single field of merit, the single mount of merit. </l>
                        <l>If people simply develop faith toward that buddha,</l>
                        <l>They will instantly discard all unfree states.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-198"/>
                    <lg tid="190">
                        <l>“Those who recite the name of this blissful one</l>
                        <l>Will obtain human bodies and gain leisure.</l>
                        <l>Then these wise persons will create merit</l>
                        <l>In the limitless ocean wherein the thus-gone ones dwell.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-199"/>
                    <lg tid="191">
                        <l>“Those who chant the name of this buddha</l>
                        <l>A mere one hundred thousand times will attain concordant acceptance</l>
                        <l>And the attainment of the divine eye, just as I did.<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-200"> This and the following
                                verse only have three lines in the Tibetan.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-201"/>
                    <lg tid="192">
                        <l>“When I saw the buddha Dīpaṃkara I scattered flowers</l>
                        <l>And thereby attained acceptance.</l>
                        <l>They will acquire that sort of acceptance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-202"/>
                    <lg tid="193">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this illuminating sage </l>
                        <l>Who protects the world are sure to be proper vessels.</l>
                        <l>This goes for everyone except extremists</l>
                        <l>And those who suffer from jealousy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-203"/>
                    <lg tid="194">
                        <l>“Those who hear such a discourse taught</l>
                        <l>Directly from the guide, the buddha,</l>
                        <l>Will remember it in the future</l>
                        <l>And teach it to others.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-204"/>
                    <p tid="195">“Young man, located above this buddha realm, as in the previous
                        analogy, past as many realms as there are grains of sand in the Ganges,
                        there is a world called Wide Open. There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect
                        buddha Stable in Immeasurable Diligence lives. He is alive and well and
                        teaches the Dharma. Young man, when those noble sons or daughters who abide
                        in the Great Vehicle hear the name of the thus-gone one Stable in
                        Immeasurable Diligence—as long as they do not doubt this <ref cRef="F.155.b" type="folio"/> but trust in my vision—their diligence will never
                        decrease once they have passed away. Never again will they indulge in
                        desire. Never again will they be stained by the suffering of a mother. Never
                        again will they be stained by the suffering of a father, relative, and
                        friend. Never will they be stained by the suffering of a sister. Never again
                        will they be stained by the suffering of a companion, ally, clansman, or
                        kinsman. Never will their bodies not be adorned by the thirty-two marks of a
                        great being. Never again will their attachment, aggression, and ignorance
                        increase. Never again will any diseases proliferate. Never again will any
                        anguish grow. Instead, they will gain limitless happiness. On the way to
                        awakening, they will gain countless trillions of limitless virtues.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-205"/>
                    <p tid="196">The Blessed One then expressed the meaning of this in verse:</p>
                    <lg tid="197">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this world protector</l>
                        <l>And do not doubt it</l>
                        <l>Will never have to witness</l>
                        <l>The suffering of parents and many relatives.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-207"/>
                    <lg tid="198">
                        <l>“Above us abides the supreme human,</l>
                        <l>Who illuminates the world.</l>
                        <l>He illuminates the three realms of existence</l>
                        <l>And teaches beings the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-208"/>
                    <lg tid="199">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this perfect buddha</l>
                        <l>And teach it to others</l>
                        <l>Will be perennially adorned</l>
                        <l>With the thirty-two marks.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-209"/>
                    <lg tid="200">
                        <l>“Those who remember the name of this sage</l>
                        <l>Will not have their insight impaired.</l>
                        <l>When they are engaged in the practices of awakening,</l>
                        <l>They will venerate the bodhisattvas as well.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-210"/>
                    <lg tid="201">
                        <l>“By teaching this buddha’s name,</l>
                        <l>When later they practice for awakening,</l>
                        <l>These insightful ones shall constantly venerate</l>
                        <l>Inconceivable millions of buddhas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-211"/>
                    <lg tid="202">
                        <l>“Those who hear the name of this perfect buddha</l>
                        <l>And then reveal it to others</l>
                        <l>Will obtain a mass of merit <ref cRef="F.156.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>The measure of which is impossible to describe. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-212"/>
                    <lg tid="203">
                        <l>“Those who hear this name</l>
                        <l>Shall never come to doubt—</l>
                        <l>Even for the longest time in the future—</l>
                        <l>The unsurpassed wisdom of buddhahood.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-213"/>
                    <lg tid="204">
                        <l>“Those who see this perfect buddha</l>
                        <l>And render service and honor unto him</l>
                        <l>Shall receive this discourse</l>
                        <l>In their hands at a future time.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-214"/>
                    <lg tid="205">
                        <l>“Those who see me surrounded by bodhisattvas,</l>
                        <l>As well as Ratnajālin,</l>
                        <l>And hear this discourse</l>
                        <l>Will not come to doubt it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-215"/>
                    <lg tid="206">
                        <l>“They will abandon any doubt </l>
                        <l>In the boundless thus-gone ones and their buddha qualities.</l>
                        <l>They will continue their earlier practices</l>
                        <l>For many billions of eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-216"/>
                    <lg tid="207">
                        <l>“They will give up their hands and legs</l>
                        <l>And give away their ears, noses, heads,</l>
                        <l>Sons, daughters, and subjects</l>
                        <l>Without any displeasure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-217"/>
                    <lg tid="208">
                        <l>“When those who hear this discourse</l>
                        <l>Come in contact with it in the future,</l>
                        <l>They shall teach it to others,</l>
                        <l>And so become worthy of veneration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-218"/>
                    <lg tid="209">
                        <l>“Let those who desire complete awakening,</l>
                        <l>Which is the domain of all the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Never doubt the teachings</l>
                        <l>Of the world protector!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-219"/>
                    <lg tid="210">
                        <l>“Those who have heard this discourse</l>
                        <l>Must uphold it free from deceit.</l>
                        <l>They should preach this discourse again and again,</l>
                        <l>Wherever they may go.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-220"/>
                    <lg tid="211">
                        <l>“If they can perfect the meaning of this discourse, </l>
                        <l>Entirely within three months,</l>
                        <l>They shall attain the wisdom of retention</l>
                        <l>That recollects all teachings.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-221"/>
                    <p tid="212">Once the Young Licchavi Ratnajālin had heard these well-spoken
                        teachings of the Blessed One, he draped the Blessed One in priceless fabrics
                        ornamented with gold. Then the Blessed One performed a miracle such that
                        from every pore of the Blessed One’s body, light streamed forth,
                        illuminating all the countless, infinite worlds in the east. All the beings
                        born in those buddha realms beheld this buddha realm, and all the beings
                        gathered in the Thus-Gone One’s <ref cRef="F.156.b" type="folio"/> assembly
                        in this buddha realm also beheld this buddha realm. At that moment as many
                        blessed buddhas, including their fourfold assemblies, were illuminated as
                        ninety-nine times the number of grains of sand in the Ganges. Such was the
                        miracle that he performed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-222"/>
                    <p tid="213">The Blessed One then asked the young Licchavi Ratnajālin, “Young
                        man, when you look above, do you see all the blessed buddhas, who are so
                        unfathomably, innumerably, limitlessly, immeasurably, and indescribably
                        many?”</p>
                    <p tid="214">“Blessed One, I see them. Blissful One, I see them.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-224"/>
                    <p tid="215">“Noble son, the names of these thus-gone ones vastly outnumber the
                        names of the gods and humans gathered in the worlds of the great
                        trichiliocosm. Each of them has an inconceivable and boundless agglomeration
                        of names. This also applies to the thus-gone one Majestic King with the
                        Elegant Peaceful Voice in the east, and likewise to the thus-gone one Pure
                        Moon Disk, the thus-gone one King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays, the
                        thus-gone one King of Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers, and the thus-gone one
                        Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by Precious
                        Moonlight. Just as it is with the name of a single thus-gone one, so it is
                        with that of any thus-gone one. Do you see that?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-225"/>
                    <p tid="216">“Blessed One, I see it. Blissful One, I see it. So it is in the
                        south, in the west, in the north, below, <ref cRef="F.157.a" type="folio"/>
                        and above—in each of the ten directions there are countless names of the
                        individual thus-gone ones and myriad different names of the thus-gone ones.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-226"/>
                    <p tid="217">“Young man, do you see how the blessed buddhas vastly exceed those
                        who abide in the realm of a universal monarch?”</p>
                    <p tid="218">“Blessed One, I see it. Blissful One, I see it.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-228"/>
                    <p tid="219">The young Licchavi Ratnajālin became pleased, delighted, joyful,
                        and happy. At that moment when he was happy and delighted the earth quaked.
                        A great burst of light appeared that benefitted all beings, brought them
                        happiness, pleased their minds, and aroused roots of virtue in them.
                        Trillions of gods stationed in the sky cast down powdered gold from the
                        divine Jambū River. Trillions of brahmā gods tossed, scattered, and
                        sprinkled divine red sandalwood powder upon the Blessed One. Trillions of
                        gods tossed, scattered, and sprinkled divine blue, pink, red, and white
                        lotuses, as well as smaller and larger māndārava flowers. Trillions of gods
                        offered thousands of jeweled parasols. Trillions of gods wept as they bowed
                        their heads to the Blessed One’s feet, recalling trillions of their past
                        lives. It was the blessings of the Blessed Buddha that allowed these
                        trillions of miracles to occur. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-229"/>
                    <p tid="220">About this, it was said,</p>
                    <lg tid="221">
                        <l>Billions of gods</l>
                        <l>Stationed in the periphery</l>
                        <l>Tossed fine red sandalwood powder</l>
                        <l>Upon the perfect Buddha. <ref cRef="F.157.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-231"/>
                    <lg tid="222">
                        <l>Tens of billions of <term type="ignore">śakra</term> gods</l>
                        <l>Stationed in the sky</l>
                        <l>Tossed much powdered gold from the Jambū River</l>
                        <l>Upon the Thus-Gone One.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-232"/>
                    <lg tid="223">
                        <l>Ten million brahmā gods arrived</l>
                        <l>And tossed powdered red sandalwood</l>
                        <l>Upon the perfect Buddha </l>
                        <l>And sang melodious songs.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-233"/>
                    <lg tid="224">
                        <l>Seeing the immaculate light,</l>
                        <l>The gods arrayed themselves in the sky.</l>
                        <l>They sang countless songs</l>
                        <l>And waved fabrics in the sky.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-234"/>
                    <lg tid="225">
                        <l>The gods arrayed in the sky,</l>
                        <l>Holding thousands of lotus flowers,</l>
                        <l>Displayed them to the World Illuminator</l>
                        <l>And venerated him with banners and such.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-235"/>
                    <lg tid="226">
                        <l>With minds filled with joy,</l>
                        <l>They honored the unparalleled supreme Victor, the Lord of Sages.</l>
                        <l>They praised him and scattered upon him</l>
                        <l>Garlands of precious jewels and pearls.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-236"/>
                    <lg tid="227">
                        <l>A trillion people</l>
                        <l>Venerated the unparalleled supreme Victor.</l>
                        <l>They remembered hundreds of their past lives</l>
                        <l>And bowed their heads to the unparalleled Lord of Sages.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-237"/>
                    <lg tid="228">
                        <l>Then, the World Illuminator</l>
                        <l>Beat the Dharma drum;</l>
                        <l>Its sound was heard throughout many billions</l>
                        <l>Of buddha realms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-238"/>
                    <lg tid="229">
                        <l>At that moment, </l>
                        <l>Countless millions of beings arrived from all directions.</l>
                        <l>They were established in the wisdom of buddhahood</l>
                        <l>By the perfect Buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-239"/>
                    <lg tid="230">
                        <l>The young man was delighted;</l>
                        <l>He offered a seat of uraga sandalwood</l>
                        <l>And venerated the supreme Buddha</l>
                        <l>With powdered gems.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-240"/>
                    <lg tid="231">
                        <l>The light of one precious gem</l>
                        <l>Shone throughout thousands of worlds.</l>
                        <l>The light of that single gem</l>
                        <l>Radiated throughout billions of worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-241"/>
                    <lg tid="232">
                        <l>In the same way, light sprang forth</l>
                        <l>From every gem without exception.</l>
                        <l>At that moment, they also</l>
                        <l>Illuminated Vaiśālī.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-242"/>
                    <lg tid="233">
                        <l>All of these gems were used</l>
                        <l>To venerate the principle Buddha.</l>
                        <l>A great pile of gems</l>
                        <l>Also was offered to the Great Sage. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-243"/>
                    <lg tid="234">
                        <l>Parasols adorned</l>
                        <l>With pearl garlands surrounded him.</l>
                        <l>Each had twenty-five thousand</l>
                        <l>Surrounding layers.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-244"/>
                    <lg tid="235">
                        <l>They venerated the Great Sage</l>
                        <l>Through such excellent means. <ref cRef="F.158.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Woven fabrics were offered</l>
                        <l>To all the bodhisattvas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-245"/>
                    <lg tid="236">
                        <l>Before emanated trees of awakening</l>
                        <l>Lion thrones were placed.</l>
                        <l>All told, two hundred fifty million</l>
                        <l>Were set out.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-246"/>
                    <lg tid="237">
                        <l>For millions of years,</l>
                        <l>Countless bodhisattvas—</l>
                        <l>Hundreds of millions in fact—</l>
                        <l>Arrived there.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-247"/>
                    <lg tid="238">
                        <l>They arrived first from the east,</l>
                        <l>And then from the south, west, and north,</l>
                        <l>From above and below,</l>
                        <l>And from the intermediate directions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-248"/>
                    <lg tid="239">
                        <l>The golden-colored light</l>
                        <l>Of the Refuge, the World Protector,</l>
                        <l>Filled as many realms</l>
                        <l>As the eye could see.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-249"/>
                    <lg tid="240">
                        <l>Bodhisattvas arrived</l>
                        <l>From all worlds</l>
                        <l>To the place where the Teacher was sitting</l>
                        <l>And the Dharma was shining.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-250"/>
                    <lg tid="241">
                        <l>In this fashion, Ratnajālin,</l>
                        <l>The young Licchavi,</l>
                        <l>Performed boundless,</l>
                        <l>Limitless, and inconceivable homage.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-251"/>
                    <lg tid="242">
                        <l>Then the great person,</l>
                        <l>The supreme human, the Lion of the Śākyas,</l>
                        <l>Brought comfort to the assembled</l>
                        <l>Gods, nāgas, and humans:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-252"/>
                    <lg tid="243">
                        <l>“Standing before me,</l>
                        <l>You have performed such veneration.</l>
                        <l>This veneration has been done with offerings </l>
                        <l>As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-253"/>
                    <lg tid="244">
                        <l>“Those who hear this discourse, </l>
                        <l>Which has been taught for the sake of Ratnajālin,</l>
                        <l>Shall not turn back from awakening;</l>
                        <l>They will become supreme preachers of buddhahood.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-254"/>
                    <lg tid="245">
                        <l>“One cannot describe</l>
                        <l>The measure of the mass of merit</l>
                        <l>That ensues from remembering this discourse</l>
                        <l>By saying, ‘It shall be this much.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-255"/>
                    <lg tid="246">
                        <l>“While one can describe the extent</l>
                        <l>Of the earth, water, fire, and wind</l>
                        <l>Throughout the ten directions,</l>
                        <l>It is impossible to describe this mass of merit.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-256"/>
                    <lg tid="247">
                        <l>“When a monk or nun,</l>
                        <l>Or a novice monk or nun,</l>
                        <l>Hears this discourse,</l>
                        <l>All beings including gods, nāgas, and mahoragas</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-257"/>
                    <lg tid="248">
                        <l>“Will arrive near them</l>
                        <l>And find their splendor overwhelming.</l>
                        <l>While it is possible that fire can turn cold,</l>
                        <l>Their splendor will never diminish. <ref cRef="F.158.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-258"/>
                    <lg tid="249">
                        <l>“When someone who remembers this discourse</l>
                        <l>Engages in the conduct of awakening,</l>
                        <l>All beings will attend to them</l>
                        <l>And venerate the mind of awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-259"/>
                    <lg tid="250">
                        <l>“A powerful person</l>
                        <l>Might hold up a thousand worlds </l>
                        <l>For millions of eons </l>
                        <l>On the tip of a hair that has been split a billion times.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-260"/>
                    <lg tid="251">
                        <l>“Still, compared to that, during the latter days</l>
                        <l>One may teach to others</l>
                        <l>A discourse of the buddhas’ awakening </l>
                        <l>That one has heard in this fashion.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-261"/>
                    <lg tid="252">
                        <l>“In that case the great wonder</l>
                        <l>Of the former example</l>
                        <l>Shall not measure even a hundredth of that—</l>
                        <l>As no number, figure, or example could suffice.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-262"/>
                    <lg tid="253">
                        <l>“In the latter days,</l>
                        <l>When people hear the unsurpassed teachings</l>
                        <l>Of the lion’s roar in this manner,</l>
                        <l>It will not be contradicted or opposed. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-263"/>
                    <lg tid="254">
                        <l>“In the future, when people hear</l>
                        <l>Of those who have seen the World Protector—</l>
                        <l>The shining perfect Buddha—</l>
                        <l>They will act with respect and reverence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-264"/>
                    <lg tid="255">
                        <l>“If all beings</l>
                        <l>In millions of buddha realms</l>
                        <l>Were endowed with the wisdom of buddhahood—</l>
                        <l>As many of them as there are grains of sand in the Ganges—</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-265"/>
                    <lg tid="256">
                        <l>“One might perform service to them</l>
                        <l>For many hundreds of eons,</l>
                        <l>And offer them as many fine temples</l>
                        <l>As there are worlds in the great trichiliocosm.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-266"/>
                    <lg tid="257">
                        <l>“The temples could be made of sandalwood;</l>
                        <l>And each supreme and divine temple</l>
                        <l>Would have ten billion assembly halls.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-267"> In the Tibetan this verse only has
                                three lines.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-268"/>
                    <lg tid="258">
                        <l>“Each of the billion assembly halls</l>
                        <l>Could be made from divine jewels as an offering.</l>
                        <l>One could arrange thrones for everyone,</l>
                        <l>Complete with a billion servants.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-269"/>
                    <lg tid="259">
                        <l>“Skillfully, one could take nets of jewels</l>
                        <l>And adorn the thrones.</l>
                        <l>For eons as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges,</l>
                        <l>The great sages who wander through the world could then abide there.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-270"/>
                    <lg tid="260">
                        <l>“One could offer all that is fit to be offered</l>
                        <l>To each of those buddhas.</l>
                        <l>One could also create reliquaries for their parinirvāṇas</l>
                        <l>As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-271"/>
                    <lg tid="261">
                        <l>“One could create a reliquary to every single buddha</l>
                        <l>In all the worlds of the great trichiliocosm—</l>
                        <l>Composed of jewels, with thousands of divine doors, <ref cRef="F.159.a" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Reaching as high as the peak of existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-272"/>
                    <lg tid="262">
                        <l>“One could offer parasols as numerous as the grains of sand in the
                            Ganges</l>
                        <l>To each of these reliquaries.</l>
                        <l>The parasols offered at that time would be</l>
                        <l>Covered with ornamental garlands of pearl.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-273"/>
                    <lg tid="263">
                        <l>“One could also offer millions of streamers</l>
                        <l>As numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges</l>
                        <l>And billions of banners made of various precious jewels</l>
                        <l>To these reliquaries as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-274"/>
                    <lg tid="264">
                        <l>“One could play billions of instruments</l>
                        <l>At each reliquary of the omniscient illuminators.</l>
                        <l>Trillions of respectful humans too</l>
                        <l>Would join in making offerings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-275"/>
                    <lg tid="265">
                        <l>“They would offer hundreds of flowers and parasols to the reliquary</l>
                        <l>And venerate the great sages in this manner every day</l>
                        <l>For as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges.<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-276"> In the Tibetan
                                this verse only has three lines. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-277"/>
                    <lg tid="266">
                        <l>“Compared to all this, hearing just one verse from this discourse</l>
                        <l>While not doubting it, developing interest,</l>
                        <l>And reciting these victors’ names</l>
                        <l>Brings merit that is unsurpassed and supreme.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-278"/>
                    <lg tid="267">
                        <l>“Wise ones should listen to the names of absorptions,</l>
                        <l>Maintain flawless discipline, remember these names,</l>
                        <l>And venerate the thus-gone buddhas.</l>
                        <l>Thereby, they will behold as many buddhas as the grains of sand in the
                            Ganges.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-279"/>
                    <lg tid="268">
                        <l>“Having directed their minds to the sacred veneration</l>
                        <l>Of the supreme humans, the great sages,</l>
                        <l>They will always be sane, they will teach the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>And for millions of eons they will remain undeluded.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-280"/>
                    <lg tid="269">
                        <l>“As the World Protector teaches</l>
                        <l>This supreme king of discourses, </l>
                        <l>Those who hear what the Supreme Victor has previously seen</l>
                        <l>Will obtain happiness in the future.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-281"/>
                    <lg tid="270">
                        <l>“They will discard desires, knowing them to have faults,</l>
                        <l>Like a person tossing away a vessel filled with foul-smelling
                            excrement.</l>
                        <l>Such wise beings will delight in emancipation and peace,</l>
                        <l>Be constantly sane, and rely on the protectors.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-282"/>
                    <lg tid="271">
                        <l>“Those who saw me teach this</l>
                        <l>In the city of Vaiśālī,</l>
                        <l>Including Ratnajālin, who beheld and venerated me,</l>
                        <l>Shall remember this supreme discourse in the future.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-283"/>
                    <lg tid="272">
                        <l>“Those of my children who always follow me,</l>
                        <l>Engage in the supreme acts of awakening and peace,</l>
                        <l>And constantly train beings <ref cRef="F.159.b" type="folio"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shall uphold this supreme discourse in the future.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-284"/>
                    <lg tid="273">
                        <l>“Those who serve the buddhas, the guides,</l>
                        <l>As they engage in the fathomless and incalculable practices,</l>
                        <l>And likewise engage in perfect worship,</l>
                        <l>Shall uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-285"/>
                    <lg tid="274">
                        <l>“One could have engaged in pure conduct for a million eons</l>
                        <l>Or previously worked for the benefit of infinite worlds;</l>
                        <l>Yet the merit of hearing this discourse in the future</l>
                        <l>Shall not be countable at all.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-286"/>
                    <lg tid="275">
                        <l>“Let those intelligent beings who desire to behold</l>
                        <l>These peaceful and immortal buddhas—</l>
                        <l>The unfathomable and limitless buddhas—</l>
                        <l>Uphold the unfathomable greatness of this discourse!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-287"/>
                    <lg tid="276">
                        <l>“Let those who wish to behold all these buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Including Amitāyus, Akṣobhya, Vimalaprabhā,</l>
                        <l>and Siṃhaketu,</l>
                        <l>Uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-288"/>
                    <lg tid="277">
                        <l>“Let those who wish to behold these principle illuminators,</l>
                        <l>The buddhas Maitreya and Vimalaprabhā,</l>
                        <l>Mahātmā, and Siṃhaketu,</l>
                        <l>Uphold this teaching of the Supreme Victor in the future!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-289"/>
                    <lg tid="278">
                        <l>“I have taught this noble and supreme discourse</l>
                        <l>to Ratnajālin.</l>
                        <l>In the future, </l>
                        <l>Do not stay in heedless places!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-290"/>
                    <lg tid="279">
                        <l>“When the future times come,</l>
                        <l>Be careful and always keep your discipline flawless.</l>
                        <l>Then, when your time comes to die,</l>
                        <l>You will go to the realm of the victor Infinite Light.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-291"/>
                    <lg tid="280">
                        <l>“His realm is known as Jeweled,</l>
                        <l>And is located in a world above us.</l>
                        <l>Following that, when your time comes to die,</l>
                        <l>You will swiftly behold the buddha Maitreya.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-292"/>
                    <p tid="281">Once the Blessed One gave this teaching, the young Licchavi
                        Ratnajālin as well as four hundred million bodhisattvas such as Maitreya,
                        and also six hundred million worthy ones and nine hundred ninety million
                        gods rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-293"/>
                    <trailer tid="282">This completes the Great Vehicle sūtra “<title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnajālin</title>.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="283">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-294"/>
                    <p tid="284">It was translated by the Indian scholar Jñānagarbha and the
                        translator Venerable Yeshé Nyingpo. It was proofed and finalized by the
                        editor-translator Venerable Paltsek.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="285">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="287">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-295">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rin chen dra ba can gyis zhus pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­ratna­jāli­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 163, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 144a–159b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-296">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rin chen dra ba can gyis zhus pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative
                        Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
                        bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China
                        Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
                        skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 59, pp.
                        388–432.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-297">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ʼphags pa rin chen dra ba can gyis zhus pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen poʼi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­ratna­jāli­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Stok Palace
                        Kangyur vol. 65 (mdo sde, pha), folios 53a–74a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-299">“Bǎo wǎng jīng <foreign xml:lang="zh">寶網經</foreign>.” In <title xml:lang="Ja-Ltn">Taishō Tripiṭaka</title>,
                        edited by Junjirō Takakusu and Kaigyoku Watanabe, vol. 14, no. 433.
                        Tokyo: Taishō issaikyō kankōkai, 1924–1934.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-298">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang
                            stod thang ldan [/ lhan] dkar gyi chos 'gyur ro cog gi dkar
                        chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-300">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische
                            übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der
                        Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-301">Higuchi, Koichi. “Linguistic and Philological
                        Value of Mongolian Buddhist Works: The case of Mongolian versions of
                        Ratnajāli.” <title xml:lang="la">Acta Linguistica Petropolitana</title> vol.
                        XI, part 3 (2015): 541–47.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-006-302">Schopen, Gregory. “The Generalization of an
                        Old Yogic Attainment in Medieval Mahāyāna Sūtra Literature: Some Notes on
                        Jātismara.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of
                            Buddhist Studies</title> 6/1 (1983): 109–147.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-303">
                            <term>bhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A general term for spirit, ghost, or demon
                                (either positive or negative).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-304">
                            <term>kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grul bum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲུལ་བུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of dwarf beings subordinate to the great
                                king of the south, Virūḍhaka. The name uses a play on the word
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āṇḍa</foreign>, which
                                means “egg” but is a euphemism for testicle. Thus, they are often
                                depicted as having testicles as big as pots (from <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">khumba</foreign>, or
                                “pot”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-305">
                            <term>rākṣasa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣasa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A flesh-eating demon that haunts frightening
                                places.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-306">
                            <term>reliquary</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Usually a heap or circular archeological
                                structure containing relics of the masters of the past.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">reliquaries</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-307">
                            <term>Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi bskyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་བསྐྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five tathāgatas.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-308">
                            <term>Amitāyus</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚེ་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitāyus</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha associated with longevity.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-309">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>

                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-310">
                            <term>Anavatapta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma dros pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་དྲོས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavatapta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-311">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine being who rules the brahmā realm; a
                                member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-312">
                            <term>Candraprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A god; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-313">
                            <term>Dīpaṃkara </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me mdzad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མར་མེ་མཛད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṃkara</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the most renowned of former
                                buddhas.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-314">
                            <term>Great Splendor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu dpal bzang ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་དཔལ་བཟང་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A god; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-315">
                            <term>Infinite Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer mtha’ yas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་མཐའ་ཡས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-316">
                            <term>Īśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Īśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important god known also as Śiva; a member of
                                the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-317">
                            <term>Jñānagarbha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dza+nyA na gar bha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛྙཱ་ན་གར་བྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānagarbha </term>
                            <term type="definition">The Indian scholar who assisted in the
                                translation of this discourse.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-318">
                            <term>Joyful</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par dga’ ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་དགའ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A god; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-319">
                            <term>King of Blossoming Sal Tree Flowers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog rgyas pa sA la’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་རྒྱས་པ་སཱ་ལའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm to the west
                                of this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-320">
                            <term>King of Knowledge of Floral Light Displays</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog gi ’od kyis rnam par rol pa mngon par
                                mkhyen pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་གི་འོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་རོལ་པ་མངོན་པར་མཁྱེན་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm to the
                                south of this world. </term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-321">
                            <term>King Who Is Peaceful and Splendorous in His Learning and Rich in
                                Melody</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu zhi ba mkhas pa’i gzi brjid dbyangs kyi
                                dbang phyug gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm below this
                                world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-322">
                            <term>Limitless Strength</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs mtha’ yas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་མཐའ་ཡས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A leader of the Licchavis.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-323">
                            <term>Mahāmucilinda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">btang bzung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཏང་བཟུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmucilinda</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-324">
                            <term>Mahātmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdag nyid chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདག་ཉིད་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahātmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-325">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha
                                to follow Śākyamuni.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-326">
                            <term>Majestic King with the Elegant Peaceful Voice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs par rab tu zhi ba'i dpal dbyangs kyi dbang
                                phyug gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་པར་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བའི་དཔལ་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives to the east of this
                                world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-327">
                            <term>Majestic King with the Splendorous Voice of Learning Adorned by
                                Precious Moonlight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od zer zla bas brgyan pa mkhas pa’i
                                gzi brjid dbyangs kyi dbang phyug gi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འོད་ཟེར་ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ་མཁས་པའི་གཟི་བརྗིད་དབྱངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་གི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm to the east
                                of this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-328">
                            <term>Manasvin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Manasvin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-329">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The main adversary of the Buddha and the
                                embodiment of evil.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-330">
                            <term>Mucilinda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">btang bzung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཏང་བཟུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mucilinda</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-331">
                            <term>Nanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-332">
                            <term>Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sred med kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲེད་མེད་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the epithets of Kṛṣṇa.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-333">
                            <term>Paltsek</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The editor of this discourse.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-334">
                            <term>Pinnacle of Renown</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags pa’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲགས་པའི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A god; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-335">
                            <term>Pure Moon Disk </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i dkyil ’khor rnam dag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བའི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར་རྣམ་དག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm to the
                                north of this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-336">
                            <term>Rāhu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the kings of the demi-gods; the demon who
                                causes an eclipse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-337">
                            <term>Ratnajālin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dra ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnajālin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A young Licchavi; the main interlocutor of this
                                discourse.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-338">
                            <term>Sāgara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ་མཚོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-339">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important god who rules the Heaven of the
                                Thirty-Three; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-340">
                            <term>Saṁtuṣita</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su dga’ ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོངས་སུ་དགའ་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṁtuṣita</term>
                            <term type="definition">The god who appears to Ratnajālin in a dream
                                inspiring him to meet the Buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!-- Not in text <item>
                        <gloss type="person" mode="marked" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-341">
                            <term>Siṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-342">
                            <term>Siṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">And elder of the Licchavis.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-343">
                            <term>Siṃhaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ge tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་གེ་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siṃhaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-344">
                            <term>Stable in Immeasurable Diligence </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus grangs med pas yang dag par rab tu
                                gnas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས་གྲངས་མེད་པས་ཡང་དག་པར་རབ་ཏུ་གནས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in a buddha realm above this
                                world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-345">
                            <term>Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ma’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་མའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A god; a member of the Buddha's retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-346">
                            <term>Susārthavāha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ded dpon bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེད་དཔོན་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Susārthavāha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A god identified as a child of
                                <term>Māra</term>.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-347">
                            <term>Upananda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upananda</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-348">
                            <term>Vāsukin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vāsukin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A nāga king; a member of the Buddha's
                                retinue.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-349">
                            <term>Vimalaprabhā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med pa’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-350">
                            <term>Yeshé Nyingpo</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The Tibetan translator of this discourse.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-351">
                            <term>Adorned by the Moon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla bas brgyan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བས་བརྒྱན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm to the south.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-352">
                            <term>Citraratna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bkra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་བཀྲ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Citraratna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm to the west.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-353">
                            <term>Covered with a Jewel Net</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dra bas g.yogs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བས་གཡོགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm to the north.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-354">
                            <term>Heaven of Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tuṣita</term>
                            <term type="definition">The fourth of the six heavens of the desire
                                realm. In Buddhist thought it is where all future buddhas dwell
                                prior to their awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-355">
                            <term>Hell of Ultimate Torment </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnar med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མནར་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avīci </term>
                            <term type="definition">The worst hell realm.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-356">
                            <term>Jambū river</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambū</term>
                            <term type="definition">A divine river whose gold is believed to be
                                especially fine.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-357">
                            <term>Jeweled</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha realm of the buddha Infinite Light,
                                located above this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-358">
                            <term>Licchavi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">li tsa+tsha bI </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལི་ཙྪ་བཱི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Licchavi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ancient republican state of the Licchavi
                                people. Its capital was Vaiśālī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-359">
                            <term>Lord of the Supreme Banner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal mtshan mchog gi bdag po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་མཚན་མཆོག་གི་བདག་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm below this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-360">
                            <term>Monkey Pond</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spre’u rdzing </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྲེའུ་རྫིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Markaṭahrada</term>
                            <term type="definition">A pond in the city of Vaiśālī.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-361">
                            <term>Pearled</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu tig can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་ཏིག་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm to the east.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-362">
                            <term>Sahā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The universe in which we live.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-363">
                            <term>Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs pa can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡངས་པ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ancient capital of the Licchavi republican
                                state, the Buddha visited this city several times during his
                                lifetime. It is perhaps most famous as the location where, on
                                different occasions, the Buddha cured a plague, admitted the first
                                nuns into the Buddhist order, was offered a bowl of honey by
                                monkeys, and announced his parinirvāṇa three months prior to his
                                departure. </term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-006-364">
                            <term>Wide Open</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu rnam par phye ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་རྣམ་པར་ཕྱེ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha realm above this world.</term>
                            
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>