<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bgres mos zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བགྲེས་མོས་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of an Old Lady</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahallikā­paripṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་བགྲེས་མོས་ཞུས་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bgres mos zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Questions of an Old Lady”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­mahallikā­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-27">
                    Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy
                    Division)<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-174">Khenpo Ngawang Jorden</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-176">Venerable Jampa Losal</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-178">YangDol Tsatultsang</author>
                <!-- <author role="translatorEng">YangDol Tsatultsang</author> -->
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-306">Simeon Joffe</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.34 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-059-014"/>
                <date>2011-11-16</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh171" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 171</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 310.b–314.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Unknown</author>
                    <location count-pages="8">
                        <start volume="59" page="622"/>
                        <end volume="59" page="629"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11777" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-18T02:54:24.053Z" user="admin">18/06/2019 02:54:24</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 2.34" date-time="2019-06-18T02:54:21.031Z" user="celso">v 2.34 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="48">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-1"/>
                <p tid="1">This sūtra contains teachings given by the Buddha to a 120-year-old woman in the city of Vaiśalī. Upon
                    meeting the Buddha, she asks him questions concerning the four stages of life, the aggregates, the elements
                    and the faculties. In response, the Buddha gives her a profound teaching on emptiness, using beautifully
                    crafted examples to illustrate his point. </p>
                <p tid="2">After hearing these teachings her doubts are dispelled and she is freed from clinging to the perception
                    of a self. Ānanda asks the Buddha why he has given such profound teachings to this woman. The Buddha reveals
                    that the woman has been his mother five hundred times in previous lifetimes and that he had generated the root
                    of virtue for her to become enlightened. Because of her own strong aspirations, after dying, she would be born
                    in the buddha field of Sukhāvatī; and after sixty-eight thousand eons she would finally become the buddha
                    Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="49">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-2"/>
                <p tid="3">This sūtra was translated from Tibetan into English under the supervision of Khenpo Ngawang Jorden by
                    the Venerable Jampa Losal and the laywoman YangDol Tsatultsang, members of the Sakya Pandita Translation Group
                    (International Buddhist Academy Division), Kathmandu.</p>
                <p tid="4">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="50">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-3"/>
                    <p tid="5">Considering the cultural norms of the time, the fact that the teaching contained in this sūtra was
                        given entirely to a laywoman and, moreover, to a very old and impoverished laywoman, makes it stand
                        apart.</p>
                    <p tid="6">The setting of this text is Vaiśalī, the ancient capital of the Licchavis and of the Vṛji
                        confederacy of which the Licchavi republic was a member. The old lady, whose name we are never told, asks
                        the Buddha such profound questions that Ānanda realises this is no ordinary woman but one whose wisdom
                        comes from merit collected in past lifetimes. As it turns out, the Buddha reveals that she has been his
                        mother for five hundred lifetimes.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-4"/>
                    <p tid="7">The main body of the text, which consists of the Buddha’s teachings in answer to the old lady’s
                        questions, is an explanation of emptiness. To put it briefly, the Buddha says no phenomenon arises of its
                        own accord. Neither does any phenomenon give rise to any other phenomenon. All phenomena arise owing to
                        their dependence upon collections of causes and conditions. Hence, there is no independent phenomenon,
                        though we may use terms to indicate various phenomena as if they were independent. After the Buddha’s
                        teaching the old lady realizes this profound truth. The Buddha prophesies that she herself will one day
                        become a buddha. In earlier lifetimes he had planted roots of virtue and made strong aspirations for her
                        to do so.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-5"/>
                    <p tid="8">The following modern works should be mentioned. Frye (1979) provides us with an English translation
                        from the Mongolian version of the sūtra. Research on the date and translator attributions of the Chinese
                        versions is to be found in Nattier (2007). Durt (2005) discusses the theme of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahallikā</foreign> (old lady) and the three Chinese versions (Taishō 559, 560, 561)
                        of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahallikā­paripṛcchā</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-6"/>
                    <p tid="9">There is no Sanskrit version extant. The primary Tibetan text used for the present translation was
                        the version in the Degé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</foreign>) Kangyur, versions in the other
                        Kangyurs being also compared. The colophon of the sūtra states that it was translated under the guidance
                        of the abbots Jinamitra and Dānaśīla by the Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye
                            shes sde</foreign>), from which we can conclude that this text must have been translated from Sanskrit
                        to Tibetan in the early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> during the first major phase of the translation of Buddhist
                        texts into Tibetan.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="51">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="52">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="53">The Questions of an Old Lady</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-7"/>
                    <p tid="10">
                        <ref cRef="F.310.b"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-8"/>
                    <p tid="11">Thus did I hear at one time. When the Bhagavān was travelling in the land of Vṛji, he went to the
                        great city of Vaiśālī, together with a large saṅgha of one thousand two hundred and fifty bhikṣus and a
                        vast number of bodhisattva mahāsattvas. At that time, he came across an old woman from the city gathering
                        grass in the countryside. She was decrepit and had reached the end of her life-span, being one hundred and
                        twenty years old.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-9"/>
                    <p tid="12">The woman saw the Bhagavān coming from afar—handsome, inspiring, with senses tamed, mind tamed,
                        endowed with supreme discipline and serenity, guarded, faultless, senses controlled, pure and clear like
                        the sea, unclouded, upright like a golden sacrificial post, radiant with splendor clear and distinct,
                        wonderfully adorned with the thirty-two signs of a great being. When she saw him, faith grew in her mind.
                        Then full of devotion she approached <ref cRef="F.311.a"/> the Bhagavān, bowed her head at his feet,
                        circumambulated the Bhagavān three times and sat to one side. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-10"/>
                    <p tid="13">Bowing with her palms together in the direction of the Bhagavān, the woman then asked him, “O
                        Bhagavān, where does birth come from? Where does aging come from? Where do they go? O Bhagavān, where does
                        sickness come from? Where does death come from? Where do they go? O Bhagavān, where does form come from?
                        Where do sensation, notions, <term>formative factors</term> and consciousness come from? Where do they go?
                        O Bhagavān, where does the earth element come from? Where do the water element, the fire element, the wind
                        element, the space element and the element of consciousness come from? Where do they go? O Bhagavān, where
                        does the eye come from? Where do the ear, the nose, the tongue, the body and the mind come from? Where do
                        they go?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-11"/>
                    <p tid="14">The Bhagavān replied, “Sister, birth does not come from anywhere. Aging does not come from
                        anywhere. They do not go anywhere. Sister, sickness does not come from anywhere. Death does not come from
                        anywhere. They do not go anywhere. Sister, form does not come from anywhere. Sensation, notions,
                            <term>formative factors</term> and consciousness do not come from anywhere. They do not go anywhere.
                        Sister, the earth element does not come from anywhere. The water element, the fire element, the wind
                        element, the space element and the element of consciousness do not come from anywhere. They do not go
                        anywhere. Sister, the eye does not come from anywhere. The ear, the nose, the tongue, the body and the
                        mind do not come from anywhere. They do not go anywhere.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-12"/>
                    <p tid="15">“Sister, it is as follows: as an analogy, a fire arises based on a stick to rub with, a stick to
                        rub on, and and also a person’s effort to generate it. That fire, moreover, once it has burnt the grass
                        and wood, will have no more causes and will die. Sister, where do you think the fire comes from and where
                        does it go?” </p>
                    <p tid="16">She answered, “O Bhagavān, that fire comes into being owing to the power of a collection of
                        causes. It ceases and dies when it lacks the collection of causes.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-13"/>
                    <p tid="17">The Bhagavān said, “Sister, likewise, all phenomena <ref cRef="F.311.b"/> come into being owing to
                        the power of a collection. They cease and die when they lack the collection. Whatever the phenomena, they
                        do not come from anywhere, nor do they go anywhere. Sister, it is as follows: although the eye
                        consciousness arises based upon the eye and form, the eye consciousness does not have a producer, nor
                        anything that makes it cease. Nowhere is it brought together at all. The aggregates do not come from
                        anywhere, nor do they go anywhere. When one has accumulated karma through the conditions of the
                        consciousnesses, the fruits manifest as the results of three types<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-83">The results of three types (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bras
                                bu rnam pa gsum</foreign>) may refer to three sorts of karmic “ripening” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipāka</foreign>), i.e., pleasant, unpleasant and neutral. </note> in the three
                        realms. That fruit is empty too. It has no coming. It has no going. No one makes it arise. It is not
                        stopped by anybody. Sister, all phenomena have stopped due to their very natures.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-14"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Likewise, although the mental consciousness arises based upon the ear and sound, the nose and
                        smell, the tongue and taste, the body and touch, and the mind and phenomena, the mental consciousness<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-84">Whereas the previous paragraph spoke of the visual
                            or eye consciousness, the present paragraph now discusses the “mental consciousness” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manovijñāna</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid
                                kyi rnam par shes pa</foreign>) that is able to grasp all that exists, i.e., all phenomena
                            (dharma). See glossary.</note> does not have a producer nor has it anything that makes it cease.
                        Nowhere is it brought together at all.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-85">N <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang yang sogs pa med</foreign>; D <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang yang sogs pa
                                yang</foreign>. N is probably correct as it is consistent with previous similar passages.</note>
                        The aggregates do not come from anywhere, nor do they go anywhere either. When one has accumulated karma
                        through the condition of mental consciousness, the fruits manifest as the results of three types in the
                        three realms. That fruit is empty too. It has no coming. It has no going. No one makes it arise. It is not
                        stopped by anybody. Sister, all phenomena are inherently stopped.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-15"/>
                    <p tid="19">“Sister, it is as follows: as an analogy, the sound of a drum arises based on wood, hide and a
                        stick, and also on a person’s effort to make it arise. The past sound of that drum was empty, the future
                        sound will be empty and the sound that arises at present is empty. The sound does not dwell in the wood,
                        neither does it dwell in the hide, nor does it dwell in the stick, nor does it dwell in the person’s hand.
                        However, because of these conditions, it is termed sound. That which is termed sound is also empty. It has
                        no coming. It has no going. No one makes it arise. It is not stopped by anybody. Sister, all phenomena are
                        inherently stopped.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-16"/>
                    <p tid="20"> “Sister, likewise, all phenomena depend solely on conditions, i.e., ones such as ignorance,
                        craving, karma and consciousness. When these latter phenomena are present, the terms death and birth are
                        designated. <ref cRef="F.312.a"/> That which is designated death and birth is also empty. It has no
                        coming. It has no going. No one makes it arise. It is not stopped by anybody. Sister, all phenomena are
                        inherently stopped. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-17"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Sister, in this way, whoever understands the nature of a drum’s sound well also understands
                        emptiness well. Whoever understands emptiness well, understands nirvāṇa well. Whoever understands nirvāṇa
                        well has no attachment to any entity, and despite designating conventional things with all sorts of
                        terms—‘this is mine,’ or ‘that is me,’ or ‘sentient being,’ or ‘life force,’ or ‘living being,’ or ‘man,’
                        or ‘person,’ or ‘born of Manu,’ or ‘son of Manu,’ or ‘agent,’ or ‘inciter of action,’ or ‘appropriator,’
                        or ‘discarder’—he teaches Dharma without attachment to these. He teaches Dharma well. He teaches the final
                        reality. He teaches the final reality well.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-18"/>
                    <p tid="22">“Sister, it is as follows: an artist or an artist’s apprentice spreads various paints on a canvas
                        that has been thoroughly cleaned or on a flat piece of wood or on the surface of a wall that has been
                        wiped clean. He paints with ease whatever bodily shape he might wish, such as the features of a man’s
                        physical form, the features of a woman’s physical form, the features of an elephant’s physical form, the
                        features of a horse’s physical form or the features of a donkey’s physical form, with complete limbs,
                        parts of limbs and all the sense faculties. Well executed though the painting may be, it does not involve
                        any phenomenon at all being transferred from the artist’s hand or mind to the physical form depicted; and
                        yet we designate that form as a result of those conditions. That which is designated form is also empty.
                        It has no coming. It has no going. No one makes it arise. It is not stopped by anybody. Sister, all
                        phenomena are inherently stopped.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-19"/>
                    <p tid="23">“Sister, it is likewise when there are meritorious formative factors. That is to say, although
                        bodies conducive to merit might result amongst gods and humans, in that case not even an atom is
                        transferred from this world to the world beyond. However, due to the formative factors, <ref cRef="F.312.b"/> there are various kinds of rebirths. They are represented as physical bodies with
                        their bases of cognition. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-20"/>
                    <p tid="24">“It is likewise when there are demeritorious <term>formative factors</term>. That is to say,
                        although bodies that are not meritorious result amongst hell beings, or in the animal state, or in the
                        world of the Lord of Death, or among the demigods, not even an atom is transferred in such a case from
                        this world to the world beyond. However, due to the formative factors there are various kinds of rebirths.
                        They are understood to be physical forms with their bases of cognition. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-21"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Sister, it is as follows: as an analogy, a vast gathering of clouds arises because of the
                        nāga-power of the nāgas,<!--moved to gloss <note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-86">Nāgas are associated with
                            springs, streams, rivers, and water in general, and among their many magical powers are the ability to
                            produce rain. Presumably this ability is what is meant here by “nāga-power” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu’i mthu</foreign>), although this appears to be the only mention of the term
                            in the Kangyur in connection with clouds and rain.</note>--> and when those huge nets of clouds cover the
                        earth they let fall a heavy deluge of rain. After the heavy deluge of rain has fallen, the hills and the
                        valleys are quenched. When the hills and valleys are quenched, the rain later subsides. But these things
                        do not originate from the nāgas’ bodies or minds. The nāgas produced the vast gathering of clouds by
                        virtue of the nāga-powers of nāgas alone. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-22"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Sister, it is likewise when there are meritorious formative factors, that is to say, when
                        meritorious bodies result amongst gods or humans. It is likewise, too, when there are demeritorious
                        formative factors. That is to say, although bodies that are not meritorious result amongst hells beings or
                        in the animal state or the world of the Lord of Death or among the demigods, in such cases the activity of
                        the formative factor is empty, the agent of the formative factor is empty and the fruits of the formative
                        factor are also empty. Sister, when there are formative factors for remaining static, consciousness will
                        reincarnate amongst the beings of the formless realms. That on account of which the consciousness
                        reincarnates amongst beings of the formless realms is empty, and the consciousness which reincarnates
                        amongst the beings of the formless realms is empty too. Why is this so? Sister, it is because all
                        phenomena are empty of essence. Even so phenomena are designated. The learned are not attached to them. As
                        they have no attachment they do not dispute. Having no disputes is the supreme quality of the religious
                        mendicant.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-23"/>
                    <p tid="27">The woman said, <ref cRef="F.313.a"/> “Since the Bhagavān has taught the profound Dharma in this
                        way, O Bhagavān, I, too, have penetrated these teachings with the eye of wisdom and will never be of two
                        minds about them again. I have no doubts. O Bhagavān, earlier, as I hadn’t yet heard these teachings I did
                        have doubts. Now I am old, I am decrepit, I suffer, I am poor, I have no protector, I have no life and yet
                        I do not die. O Bhagavān, after hearing these teachings I realize that there is no aging, no poverty, no
                        happiness, no sickness, nor is anyone ever ill, wealthy or poor at all. I am freed from the notion of a
                        self.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-24"/>
                    <p tid="28">Then the Venerable Ānanda inquired of the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, why have you taught such a profound
                        Dharma discourse as this? I wonder whether it is because this woman, who has investigated so well in this
                        way, is meritorious, learned and naturally wise.”</p>
                    <p tid="29">The Bhagavān replied, “Ānanda, so it is. Ānanda, it is indeed just as you say. This woman is
                        meritorious, learned and naturally wise. Ānanda, this woman was my mother for five hundred lifetimes.
                        Ānanda, in each of those lifetimes I also generated the roots of virtue so she could attain unsurpassable
                        and perfectly complete enlightenment. Ānanda, I cherished, revered and respected this woman greatly. She,
                        too, thought, ‘I will engage in whatever conduct my son engages in and attain the unsurpassable and
                        perfectly complete enlightenment of the vehicle of happiness.’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-25"/>
                    <p tid="30"> Ānanda inquired, “Bhagavān, why is she so poor in this way?”</p>
                    <p tid="31">The Bhagavān answered, “Ānanda, when I took up the conduct of a bodhisattva, I became a renunciate
                        in the doctrine of the Bhagavān, the tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete Buddha Krakucchanda. At that
                        time, Ānanda, this woman was my mother. Because of her attachment she did not want to let me go, so I
                        stopped eating my one meal per day. Later, she agreed to let me go. Ānanda, it is because of the ripening
                            <ref cRef="F.313.b"/> of that karma that she is as poor as she is. Ānanda, this is the last time she
                        will be poor. Ānanda, after death, this woman, who no longer craves a woman’s faculties, will obtain a
                        man’s faculties in the Sukhāvatī buddhafield of the bhagavān, the perfectly complete buddha Amitābha. Once
                        born there, she will make offerings to an innumerable, immeasurable, inconceivable number of buddhas;
                        guide an innumerable, immeasurable, inconceivable number of sentient beings to enlightenment; make an
                        innumerable, immeasurable, inconceivable number of sentient beings ripe for enlightenment; bring an
                        innumerable, immeasurable, inconceivable number of sentient beings to enlightenment, and having brought an
                        innumerable, immeasurable, inconceivable number of sentient beings to enlightenment, in six million eight
                        hundred thousand kalpas she will become the Tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete Buddha named
                        Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara in this trichiliocosm. Ānanda, the wealth and enjoyments of sentient beings of this
                        buddha field will be like those of the gods of the Thirty-Three.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-26"/>
                    <p tid="32">Thus did the Bhagavān announce, and having spoken these words, the Sugata, the Teacher, added the
                        following verses:</p>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>“Ānanda, behold this old lady,</l>
                        <l>Before me with palms joined,</l>
                        <l>Who will become a buddha, excellent among humans, </l>
                        <l>Named Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-27"/>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>“She, giving up a woman’s form,</l>
                        <l>Will go to the realm of Sukhāvatī.</l>
                        <l>Venerate the victor Amitāyus,</l>
                        <l>And become a peerless buddha, conqueror of the three realms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-28"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>“Venerating, too, the many guides</l>
                        <l>Who dwell in other worlds,</l>
                        <l>The great sages who benefit those realms, </l>
                        <l>She will become a peerless buddha, excellent among humans. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-29"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>“Having also heard the Dharma from them all, </l>
                        <l>With a purified mind, she will become accomplished in the same fashion. <ref cRef="F.314.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Remaining in the immovable, supreme mind of enlightenment, </l>
                        <l>She will cause‌ countless sentient beings to practice the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-30"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>“At that time there will be no inferior beings,</l>
                        <l>No beings with various bad bodies or bad color,</l>
                        <l>None dull, lame, and likewise none blind,</l>
                        <l>And no lepers with stumps for arms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-31"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>“At that time the sun and moon, fire, lightning, and gems </l>
                        <l>Will no longer be what shines, </l>
                        <l>For the guide Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara’s mighty light</l>
                        <l>Will everywhere be all-illuminating.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-32"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“The same stature, marks, and complexion</l>
                        <l>As those of the supreme gods of the Thirty-Three</l>
                        <l>Will be natural to those beings who at that time</l>
                        <l>Will fill that exceptional buddhafield.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-33"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“There will be no women belonging to Māra’s faction. </l>
                        <l>No female māras, no retinue of Māra.</l>
                        <l>When the Tathāgata teaches the Dharma there, </l>
                        <l>Even the word ‘tīrthika’ will be unknown.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-34"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“When the Tathāgata teaches the Dharma there,</l>
                        <l>Even the words ‘the lower realms,’ </l>
                        <l>‘The pretas,’ ‘animal birth,’ ‘the beings of hell,’</l>
                        <l>And even the word ‘woman,’ will ever stay unheard.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-35"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>“At that time, there will be no classifications of vehicles, </l>
                        <l>Like the vehicles of the śrāvakas and the pratyekabuddhas in this world.</l>
                        <l>All will be endowed with a complete mind of enlightenment, </l>
                        <l>Dwell in loving-kindness, and be compassionate. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-36"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>“As birth in that buddhafield will always be miraculous,</l>
                        <l>Everyone there will be free from birth in the womb. </l>
                        <l>They will remember past lives and, supremely intelligent and learned,</l>
                        <l>Retain on hearing it whatever excellent teachings they study.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-37"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>“Such are the qualities arrayed as features of that realm</l>
                        <l>That, even by speaking of them for eons at a time, </l>
                        <l>The tiny fraction of them one could thus describe</l>
                        <l>Would be less than a single drop of water compared to the ocean.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-38"/>
                    <p tid="45">When the Bhagavān had spoken, the venerable Ānanda and the old lady, the bodhisattvas and bhikṣus,
                        and the world with its gods, humans, demigods and gandharvas all rejoiced, and praised highly what the
                        Bhagavān had taught.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-39"/>
                    <p tid="46">This completes the Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of an Old
                        Lady</title>.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="54">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-88"/>
                    <p tid="47">The translation was made, edited, and approved by the Indian preceptors Jinamitra and Dānaśīla and the chief editor and translator Bandé Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="55">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="56">Abbreviations:</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-059-014-40">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-059-014-41">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="57">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-42">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bgres mos zhus pa zhes bya theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­mahallikā­paripṛcchā­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh. 171, Degé Kangyur vol.
                        59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 310.b–314.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-43">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bgres mos zhus pa zhes bya theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
                        bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009,
                        vol. 59, pp 883-893. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-44">Dharmachakra Translation Group (trans.). <title xml:lang="en">The Play in
                            Full</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title>). 84000: Translating the Words of the
                        Buddha, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-45">Durt, Hubert (2005). “Kajaṅgalā, Who Could Have Been the Last Mother of the
                        Buddha.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International College for Advanced Buddhist Studies</title> 9, 2005, pp
                        65-87. <ref target="http://ci.nii.ac.jp/vol_issue/nels/AA11260687/ISS0000414347_en.html">http://ci.nii.ac.jp/vol_issue/nels/AA11260687/ISS0000414347_en.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-46">Edgerton, F. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit
                            Dictionary</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1985. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-47">
                        <author>Frye, Stanley</author> (<date>1979</date>). “The Sūtra Requested by the Old Women.” <title xml:lang="en">Tibet Journal</title>. 4/1, 1979, pp 28-33.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-48">
                        <author>Nattier, Jan</author> (<date>2007</date>). “A Reassessment of the Dates and Translator
                        Attributions of the <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Laonüren jing</title> (T. 559) and the <title xml:lang="Zh-Ltn">Laomu
                            jing</title> (T. 561).” <title xml:lang="en">Annual Report of the International Research Institute for
                                Advanced Buddhology at Soka University</title> 10, 2007, pp 529-532. <ref target="http://iriab.soka.ac.jp/orc/Publications/ARIRIAB/index_ARIRIAB.html">http://iriab.soka.ac.jp/orc/Publications/ARIRIAB/index_ARIRIAB.html</ref>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-014-49">Rotman, Andy (2008). <title xml:lang="en">Divine Stories: Divyāvadāna, Part
                            I</title>. Somerville, MA: Wisdom Publications, 2008. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-50">
                            <term>three realms</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tridhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">three realms</term> are the desire realm (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāmadhātu</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod khams</foreign>), form realm
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs khams</foreign>) and the formless realm (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārūpyadhātu</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs med
                                    khams</foreign>), i.e., the three worlds that make up saṃsāra. The first is composed of the
                                six sorts of beings (gods, demigods, humans, animals, hungry ghosts and hell beings), whereas the
                                latter two are only realms of gods and are thus higher, more ethereal states of saṃsāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-51">
                            <term>aggregate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Five collections or “heaps” of impersonal mental and physical elements
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-52">
                            <term>cause</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāraņa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hetu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The primary <term type="ignore">cause</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-53">
                            <term>condition</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rkyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྐྱེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The concomitant circumstances and influences in a causal process.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-54">
                            <term>demigod</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <term type="definition">The titans who inhabit one of the six types of “worlds” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">loka</foreign>) that make up saṃsāra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-55">
                            <term>arhat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">Sometimes translated “worthy one,” a term for one who is liberated and who has
                                extirpated the passions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-56">
                            <term>formative factors</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par ’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhisaṃskāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term is used in this text in the same way as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</foreign> (<term type="ignore">formative factors</term>, q.v. second
                                entry).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-57" mode="marked">
                            <term>formative factors</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The various conditioning factors and circumstances that affect rebirth,
                                including primarily (but not only) karma. <term type="ignore">Formative factors</term> also
                                constitute one of the five aggregates and figure as one of the links in the twelve links of
                                dependent arising to account for how karma eventually leads to rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-58">
                            <term>formless realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs med khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་མེད་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārūpyadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three realms. See glossary s.v. three realms (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams gsum</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-59">
                            <term>notions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃjñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five aggregates. It is also one of the five mental omnipresent
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvatraga</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun ’gro</foreign>) mental factors that necessarily accompany any
                                cognition.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-60">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong sum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་སུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term in Abhidharma cosmology refers to 1,000³ world systems, i.e., 1,000
                                “dichiliocosms,” or “two thousand great thousand world realms” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvi­sāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</foreign>), which are in turn made up of
                                1,000 first-order world systems each with its own Mt. Meru, continents, sun, moon, as well as
                                desire, form and formless realms, heavens of gods, etc.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-61">
                            <term>thirty-two signs</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan sum cu rtsa gnyis </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚན་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གཉིས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvātriṃśan mahā­puruṣa­lakṣaṇāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">The distinctive physical attributes of the Buddha. These are the “signs of a
                                great man” (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā­puruṣa­lakṣaṇa</foreign>, Tib.
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye bu chen po’i mtshan bzang</foreign>) that
                                following Indian tradition characterize cakravartin kings (world sovereigns) as well as buddhas.
                                For a descriptive list, see Dharmachakra (2013), 26.145-173</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-62">
                            <term>bases of cognition</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">There are twelve <term type="ignore">bases of cognition</term> in all: the five physical sense organs
                                plus the mind and their respective six sorts of objects. The six inner bases from eye to mind are
                                what apprehend; and the six outer bases from form to mental objects are the objects that are
                                apprehended.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-63"> Not in text
                            <term>form realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three realms. See glossary s.v. three
                                realms (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams
                                gsum</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-64">
                            <term>mental consciousness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid kyi rnam par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manovijñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Abhidharma speaks of five consciousnesses that grasp physical objects
                                (form, sound, smells, tastes, bodily sensations) and are correlated with their respective physical
                                sense faculties (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po</foreign>), i.e. the eye, ear, etc. The <term type="ignore">mental consciousness</term>, on
                                the other hand, is said to have as its faculty simply the mind (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manas</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid</foreign>). It
                                grasps all that exists, including what is presented by the physical consciousnesses as well as
                                mental and abstract objects. These six consciousnesses, added to the twelve bases of cognition,
                                constitute the Abhidharma schema of eighteen domains or spheres (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-65">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lit. “smell eater.” <term type="ignore">Gandharvas</term> are a class of spirits and minor gods (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</foreign>) in both Hindu and Buddhist cosmologies. They are
                                supposedly messengers, singers and skilled musicians and dancers. Often closely associated with
                                various nature-spirits (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</foreign>), they are on
                                occasion depicted as disturbing to monks practicing meditation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-66">
                            <term>sacrificial post</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod sdong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་སྡོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A post set up as a marker to which offerings may be presented. Described in
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyāvadāna</title> (“The Story of Maitreya”), which in the
                                Kangyur is found within the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajya­vastu</title> (in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1, Degé Kangyur, vol. kha, folios 29a-32b); a
                                matching passage from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title> is translated in Rotman,
                                2008, pp 121-124.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-67">
                            <term>born of Manu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shed las skyes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེད་ལས་སྐྱེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manuja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Manu being the archetypal human, the progenitor of mankind, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­bhārata</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Purāṇas</title>, and
                                other Indian texts, “<term type="ignore">born of Manu</term>” is a synonym of “human being” or
                                mankind in general. Also rendered “son of Manu.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-68">
                            <term>son of Manu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shed bu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེད་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mānava</term>
                            <term type="definition">Manu being the archetypal human, the progenitor of mankind, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­bhārata</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Purāṇas</title>, and
                                other Indian texts, “<term type="ignore">son of Manu</term>” is a synonym of “human being” or
                                mankind in general. Also rendered “born of Manu.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-69">
                            <term>final reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ultimate state that can be experienced in the realization of reality, and
                                a near-synonym of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</foreign>; sometimes also translated as “the
                                reality limit” in contexts describing a partial nirvāṇa that needs to be transcended.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-70">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Buddha of the Sukhāvatī buddha field.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-71">
                            <term>Amitāyus</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚེ་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitāyus</term>
                            <term type="definition">Another name for Amitābha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-72">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The personal attendant and cousin of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-73">
                            <term>Bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavān</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Illustrious One,” an epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-74">
                            <term>Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag gi me tog byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག་གི་མེ་ཏོག་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyaṅga­puṣpa­kara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-75">
                            <term>Krakucchanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor ba ’jig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་བ་འཇིག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Krakucchanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first buddha of our eon; the fifth buddha of the “seven generations of
                                buddhas” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas rab bdun</foreign>). Also found as
                                Kakutsanda, Kakutsunda, etc. See Edgerton (1985), s.v. <term type="ignore">Krakucchanda</term>, for the various
                                spellings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-76">
                            <term>great sage</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">drang song chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲང་སོང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāṛṣi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-77">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddhas.</term>
                            <term type="definition">Here used as a specific epithet of Buddha Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-78">
                            <term>Lord of Death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">God of the lower realms.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-79">
                            <term>Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs pa can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡངས་པ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ancient capital of the Vṛji (q.v.) confederacy and Licchavi
                                republic.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-80">
                            <term>Vṛji</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bri dzi na </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲི་ཛི་ན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vṛji</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaji</term>
                            <term type="definition">The land and people of <term type="ignore">Vṛji</term> or Vaji (Pāli <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Vajji</foreign>), a country situated on the
                                north eastern Gangetic plain, and one of the 16 mahājanapada of Ancient India. It was run by a
                                confederacy of eight or nine clans, including the <term type="ignore">Vṛji</term>, Licchavi, and Videha, who sent
                                representatives to an administrative council led by an elected ruler. Its capital was Vaiśālī. See
                                Edgerton, s.v. <term type="ignore">Vṛji</term> and Vaji.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-81">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddhafield of Buddha Amitābha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-82">
                            <term>Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indra’s paradise on the summit of Sumeru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-86">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Nāgas</term> are associated with springs, streams, rivers, and water in general, and among their many magical powers are the ability to
                                produce rain.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-014-87">
                            <term>nāga-power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu’i mthu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུའི་མཐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Among the many magical powers of the nāgas are the ability to produce rain. Presumably this ability is what is meant here by “<term type="ignore">nāga-power</term>,” although this appears to be the only mention of the term in the Kangyur in connection with clouds and rain.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>