<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde byed kyis zhus pa'i mdo/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣemaṃkaraparipṛcchāsutra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṃkara</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">'phags pa bde byed kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryakṣemaṅkaraparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra entitled: The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde byed kyis zhus pa/</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣemaṃkaraparipṛcchā</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
            <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-263">Anne Klein</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-257">Raynald Prévèreau</editor>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="proofreader" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
            <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-55">Ven. Ani Jinpa (Eugenie De Jong)</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.00 <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-059-008"/>
                <date>2019-03-05</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh165" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 165</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba); folios 167.b-171.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Prajñāvarman</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">ye shes sde</author>
                    <location count-pages="9">
                        <start volume="59" page="336"/>
                        <end volume="59" page="344"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11769" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-13T19:29:15.536Z" user="andre">13/03/2019 19:29:15</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.00" date-time="2019-03-13T17:52:31.555Z" user="andre">v 1.00 2018</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.00" date-time="2019-03-13T18:46:37.719Z" user="andre">v 1.00 2018</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
            <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-1"/>
            <p tid="2">
                <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title> contains a teaching given by Buddha Śākyamuni to the Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara, in response to a question he poses about the qualities of bodhisattvas and how to develop such qualities. The Buddha teaches him about the bodhisattvas’ qualities, first in prose and later reiterated in poetic verse, and then equates the teaching of this sūtra with the perfection of insight, stating that even if one practices the first five perfections for many eons, one will not make much progress without knowing this sūtra.</p>
        </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. Ani Jinpa Palmo produced the translation and wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor checked the translation against the Tibetan and edited the text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="7">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-4"/>
                    <p tid="9">The setting of this short sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title>, is the Nyagrodha Park near Kapilavastu, the city in the ancient Śākya kingdom that contained the family home where Prince Siddhārtha grew up. It is assumed to be some ten kilometers to the west of his birthplace, Lumbini, in present-day Nepal. The sūtra describes a conversation between Buddha Śākyamuni and the Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara, who asks the Buddha a lengthy question about the qualities good bodhisattvas should have and how to develop such qualities. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-5"/>
                    <p tid="10">The Buddha’s response unfolds as a teaching on how to practice the bodhisattva path—an uncomplicated instruction given to a layperson. The teaching is without the specialized vocabulary of Buddhist philosophy and does not place strong emphasis on monastic discipline, although it does admonish against involvement with women. For the modern reader it should be kept in mind that such comments regarding women are primarily meant for men as advice in support of celibacy. Moreover, in the overall context of Buddhism they need not be seen as definitive statements on the nature of women, given that the Buddha himself taught women, many of whom achieved high levels of spiritual progress. In fact, toward the end of the sūtra, the Buddha himself refers to both noble sons and daughters who have entered the Great Vehicle.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-6"/>
                    <p tid="11">In this teaching the Buddha offers Kṣemaṅkara a set of ethical advice, such as not retaliating when attacked, combined with teachings aimed at liberation, such as how to realize emptiness in order to successfully complete the bodhisattva path. Delighted by the Buddha’s response, Kṣemaṅkara makes an offering of his jewelry. The Buddha transforms the jewelry into a multitude of magically created beings, who in turn become the basis for a further teaching of the Dharma. Unlike many longer sūtras, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title> does not develop an elaborate storyline, nor are we given much information regarding the setting or the characters. Instead, this is a brief teaching that responds to a simple question. The only other participant in the conversation is Ānanda, in his usual role as witness to the Buddha’s teaching.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-7"/>
                    <p tid="12">Near the end of the sūtra, the evil Māra also makes an appearance and inquires about the benefit of the Buddha’s discourse. The Buddha then equates the teaching of this sūtra with the perfection of insight, stating that no matter how long one practices the first five perfections, unless one knows this teaching, one will be unable to make much progress on the bodhisattva path. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-8"/>
                    <p tid="13">Unfortunately, no Sanskrit version of this sūtra remains extant, but the text was translated into both Chinese and Tibetan. The Chinese translation (T 533) was produced by the prolific translator Chih-ch’ien (third century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>) sometime between 223–53 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. As such this sūtra can be dated to the formative period of India’s Mahāyāna scriptural tradition.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-9"/>
                    <p tid="14">In producing this translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while consulting the Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>), as well as the Stok Palace manuscript. The colophon of the sūtra states that it was translated from Sanskrit by the Indian scholar Prajñāvarman and the prolific Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé. As such, we can date the Tibetan translation to the late eighth to early ninth centuries, a dating that is also attested by the text’s inclusion in the early ninth century Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>) catalogue.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-10"> The Denkarma catalogue is dated to ca. 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. In this catalog, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title> is included among the “Miscellaneous Sūtras” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde sna tshogs</foreign>), which are less than one hundred ślokas long. See Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p. 115, n. 217.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="15"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="16">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra entitled:</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="17">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-13"/>
                    <p tid="21">
                        <ref cRef="F.167.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-14"/>
                    <p tid="22">Thus did I hear at one time: The Blessed One was staying in the Nyagrodha Park of the Śākyas, near Kapilavastu in the Śākya country, together with a great saṅgha of five hundred monks. At that time a Śākya youth<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-15"> 
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzhon nu</foreign> is missing from Yongle, Lithang, Kangxi, Narthang, Choné, and Lhasa. Only Stok and Degé have it.</note> named Kṣemaṅkara departed the city of Kapilavastu for the Nyagrodha Park where the Blessed One was staying. As soon as he arrived there, he touched his head to the feet of the Blessed One and sat down to one side. With folded palms the Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara bowed down to the Blessed One and asked him, “Blessed One, what qualities should bodhisattvas possess in order not to regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening, so that even with just a little effort they will obtain the thirty-two marks of a great being, proceed from buddha realm to buddha realm, pass away free from delusion, possess the five types of superknowledge as soon as they are born, discard all unfree states, obtain leisure and advantages, gain retention, possess unobstructed eloquence, <ref cRef="F.168.a"/> possess the quality of not regressing, gain interest in emptiness, always delight in going forth, and always delight in pure conduct, even when staying in a household?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-16"/>
                    <p tid="23">Upon being asked these questions, the Blessed One replied to the young Śākya Kṣemaṅkara as follows: “Noble son, you have asked the Thus-Gone One about this topic for the sake of benefiting and bringing happiness to a multitude of beings, out of love for the world, for the welfare of numerous people, and in order to benefit and bring happiness to gods and humans. Excellent, excellent! Therefore, noble son, listen carefully and keep the following in mind, as I shall now explain. Bodhisattvas who possess four qualities will attain the qualities you describe. What are these four? Noble son, bodhisattvas who possess the strength of patience and practice patience (1) do not retaliate though others revile them, (2) do not strike back though others beat them, (3) do not quarrel though others quarrel with them, and (4) do not get angry though others are hostile to them. Noble son, bodhisattvas who possess these four qualities will never regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening and will obtain the perfect qualities you described.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-17"/>
                    <p tid="24">When the Blissful One had said this, the Teacher also spoke these words: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-18"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>“Although blamed, do not reciprocate;</l>
                        <l>Having been harmed, do not harm others. </l>
                        <l>Even if it means giving up their human body, </l>
                        <l>Bodhisattvas will attain these qualities. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-19"/>
                    <lg tid="26">
                        <l>“Always guard against evil words, </l>
                        <l>And do not be controlled by a negative mind. </l>
                        <l>Eliminate misdeeds, and you will gain such results </l>
                        <l>And quickly achieve supreme wisdom. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-20"/>
                    <lg tid="27">
                        <l>“Some people take pleasure in striking<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-21"> Translated based on Yongle, Lithang, Kangxi, Choné, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tshog rdung</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tshog rung</foreign>.</note> others, </l>
                        <l>And have a ruthless and malicious attitude. <ref cRef="F.168.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Having forsaken the wisdom of the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>Such unwise people will be burdened with unbearable suffering. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-22"/>
                    <lg tid="28">
                        <l>“Therefore, do not beat others,</l>
                        <l>And abstain from striking anything, animate or inanimate. </l>
                        <l>Benefiting all beings with love and affection, </l>
                        <l>You will quickly attain the supreme wisdom. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-23"/>
                    <lg tid="29">
                        <l>“Deluded beings overwhelmed by anger</l>
                        <l>Are far from the teaching of those who are wise in this world. </l>
                        <l>Because of wrong views, they are bent on negative ways. </l>
                        <l>Therefore, wise people should not disturb them. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-24"/>
                    <lg tid="30">
                        <l>“Bodhisattvas should not get angry, </l>
                        <l>But guard the truth without harming others. </l>
                        <l>Perfecting these rare actions, </l>
                        <l>They will possess all the exquisite thirty-two marks. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-25"/>
                    <lg tid="31">
                        <l>“The unwise always have a destructive and hostile attitude;</l>
                        <l>They<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-26"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’di ni</foreign>. Degé and the other versions in the Comparative Edition: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’di na</foreign>.</note> do not even respect their own parents. </l>
                        <l>They are enmeshed in the roots<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-27"> Translated based on Yongle and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtsa bar</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtsa ba</foreign>.</note> of affliction, </l>
                        <l>Which are the flaws of the lowest type of person. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-28"/>
                    <lg tid="32">
                        <l>“Therefore, always practice nothing but patience, </l>
                        <l>Attend to monks who teach the Dharma, </l>
                        <l>And never forsake spiritual friends. </l>
                        <l>Then supreme awakening will be easy.” </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-29"/>
                    <p tid="33">“Noble son, bodhisattvas who possess four additional qualities will never regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening, and they will achieve the perfect qualities as described. What are these four? Noble son, they are (1) pursuing the Dharma, yearning for the Dharma, and rejoicing, delighting in, and being inspired by the Dharma, as well as retaining and teaching the Dharma; (2) renouncing women and not indulging in women; (3) rejoicing in benefactors and those who share and give, as well as renouncing dullness and sleep;<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-30"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyin pa’i bdag po dang / kun ’gyed pa’i ngang tshul can dang / kun ’gyed pa la dga’ ba dang / rmugs pa / gnyid yongs su spong ba yin</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyin pa’i bdag po dang / kun bged pa’i ngang tshul can dang / kun bged pa la dga’ ba dang / rmugs pa dang / gnyid yongs su spong ba yin</foreign>.</note> and (4) feeling inspired by emptiness and abiding in emptiness. Noble son, bodhisattvas who possess these four qualities will never regress from unsurpassed and perfect awakening and they will achieve the qualities you described.” <ref cRef="F.169.a"/> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-31"/>
                    <p tid="34">When the Blissful One had said this, the Teacher also spoke these words: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-32"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>“Beings who yearn for the Dharma</l>
                        <l>And generate effort for the sake of the Dharma are rare. </l>
                        <l>Anyone who makes the wheel of Dharma turn</l>
                        <l>Will attain supreme wisdom. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-33"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>“Hearing it from others they will genuinely retain it, </l>
                        <l>And then teach the Dharma to others who are interested. </l>
                        <l>Such wise ones will not lose courage in a gathering.</l>
                        <l>They will reach unsurpassed and supreme awakening. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-34"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>“Rejecting women, the cause of downfalls, </l>
                        <l>A son of the victors will always practice pure conduct.</l>
                        <l>Stable in the practice of pure conduct, </l>
                        <l>He will turn the unsurpassed, sacred wheel. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-35"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>“Those who like<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-36"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dga’</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’ga’</foreign>.</note> the features of women</l>
                        <l>Will become miserable, poor, and feeble. </l>
                        <l>Indulging in them will not bring peace, </l>
                        <l>So forsake them and engage in bodhisattva conduct.”</l>
                        <l/>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-37"/>
                    <p tid="39">Upon hearing these teachings, the Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara felt satisfied, delighted, and thrilled. Feeling joyful and happy, he unfastened the ornaments on his body and scattered them before the Blessed One. Through the Blessed One’s power these ornaments now transformed into a mansion made of precious substances, hovering directly above the Blessed One’s crown. From that mansion emanated five hundred people decorated with all manner of ornaments, who scattered their own ornaments in the direction of the Blessed One. In addition, they aroused the mind set on unsurpassed and perfect awakening and said, “Blessed One, we are sharing our roots of virtue with all beings, and we dedicate them toward unsurpassed and perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-38"/>
                    <p tid="40">The Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara also perceived these emanated people. Seeing them, the hairs on his body stood on end, so he asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, where are these people from? Are they from the east, from the south, from the west, from the north, from below, or from above? <ref cRef="F.169.b"/> From which cardinal or intermediate direction did they come?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-39"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Noble son,” replied the Blessed One, “these people are from neither the east, south, west, or north; nor from below or above; nor are they from any cardinal or intermediate direction. They are not gods, they are not nāgas, they are not yakṣas, they are not gandharvas, they are not demigods, they are not garuḍas, they are not kiṁnaras, they are not mahoragas, they are not humans, and they are not non-humans—they do not abide in the earth element, they do not abide in the water element, they do not abide in the fire element, they do not abide in the wind element, and they do not abide in the space element. They have no form, no feeling, no perception, no formation, no thinking, no mind, no consciousness, no karma, no ripening of karma, no present world, no other world, no coming, no going, no dwelling, no death, and no birth. However, noble son, they are known as magical emanations. They are called <distinct>groundless</distinct>, they are called <distinct>lifeless</distinct>, they are called <distinct>beingless</distinct>, they are called <distinct>personless</distinct>, they are called <distinct>characteristicless</distinct>, they are called <distinct>void</distinct>, they are called <distinct>empty</distinct>, and they are called <distinct>essenceless</distinct>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-40"/>
                    <p tid="42">“Kṣemaṅkara, those noble sons and daughters who hold all phenomena to be like magical creations—who accept, understand, and have faith and confidence in them as such, and who are not led astray by others—such noble sons and daughters, Kṣemaṅkara, are called my children. They are known as my descendants, they are known to possess illumination, they are known to be illuminating, they are known to clear away darkness, they are known to abandon afflictions—they are known as <distinct>teachers</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>fields of merit</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>worthy of veneration</distinct>,<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-41"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yon gyi gnas</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yon tan gyi gnas</foreign>.</note> they are known as <distinct>mendicants</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>brahmins</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>learned</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>elephants</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>those who accept that phenomena are unborn</distinct>, <ref cRef="F.170.a"/> they are known as <distinct>bodhisattvas</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>great beings</distinct>, they are known as<distinct> having the quality of non-regressing</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>having the qualities of bodhisattvas</distinct>, and they are known as <distinct>having been prophesied</distinct>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-42"/>
                    <p tid="43">“However, noble children who do not agree that all phenomena are like magical creations, and who do not accept this, do not engage with it, have no faith in it, and lack trust in it—who feel frightened and scared upon hearing about it and start to panic, turn away from it, and challenge it—such noble sons are known as <distinct>not being mendicants</distinct>. They are known as <distinct>not being brahmins</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>non-Buddhists</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>those who apprehend things</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>depraved</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>unwholesome companions</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>people to avoid</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>deceitful bodhisattvas</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>immoral bodhisattvas</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>fake bodhisattvas</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>worthless bodhisattvas</distinct>, they are known as <distinct>corrupted bodhisattvas</distinct>, and they are known as <distinct>savage bodhisattvas</distinct>.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-43"/>
                    <p tid="44">At this point the evil Māra, feeling frustrated and unhappy, went to the location where the Blessed One was staying and asked, “Blessed One, by delivering this Dharma teaching, how many beings’ welfare do you accomplish?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-44"/>
                    <p tid="45">“Evil One,” replied the Blessed One, “by delivering this Dharma teaching, eighty-four thousand deities in the realms of desire and form will attain the acceptance that phenomena are unborn. The minds of five hundred monks will become free of defilements with no further appropriation. Seventy-five nuns will also attain the acceptance that phenomena are unborn. The bodhisattva Kṣemaṅkara and five hundred other laymen will also attain the acceptance that phenomena are unborn. Twenty-five female lay practitioners will purify the eye of Dharma, making it free from dust and dirt with regard to all phenomena, and all of them will attain the acceptance that phenomena are unborn. <ref cRef="F.170.b"/> When passing away, all of them will be reborn in Sukhāvatī, the buddha realm of the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Amitābha. Once born there, they will all jointly uphold the awakening of the buddhahood of<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-45"> Translated based on Yongle and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kyi</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kyis</foreign>.</note> infinite blessed buddhas. They will express it, teach it, and authentically expound it. In the future, after as many eons as there are grains of sand in the Ganges River, during the so-called Good Eon of this trichiliocosm, they will fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-46"/>
                    <p tid="46">The evil Māra felt frustrated and unhappy. With regret, he began to weep. As he was leaving, he said, “Blessed One, please do not deliver this Dharma teaching again!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-47"/>
                    <p tid="47">“Evil one, you should not speak like that!” replied the Blessed One. “And why not? Because the turning of the Dharma wheel of all blessed buddhas is unimpeded!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-48"/>
                    <p tid="48">Then venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, what is this Dharma teaching called, and how should it be identified?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-49"/>
                    <p tid="49">The Blessed One responded, “Ānanda, you may call this Dharma discourse <title xml:lang="en">The Bodhisattva’s Renunciation</title>, or you should call it <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title>. Ānanda, I entrust you with this Dharma discourse. I entrust it to you in order that you retain it, read it aloud, explain it, and accurately teach it to others in great detail. Why? Ānanda, noble sons and noble daughters who have genuinely entered the Great Vehicle <ref cRef="F.171.a"/> might practice the five perfections without the perfection of insight for ten eons. Yet those noble sons and noble daughters who retain this Dharma discourse, hold it, read it aloud, understand it, accurately teach it to others in detail, or even make it into a book and carry it, will create much more merit.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-50"/>
                    <p tid="50">Then the Blessed One spoke these verses:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-51"/>
                    <lg tid="51">
                        <l>“Whoever practices generosity for ten eons, </l>
                        <l>Without hearing about this way, </l>
                        <l>Will not be praised</l>
                        <l>As having unsurpassed generosity. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-52"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“Those who observe mundane discipline</l>
                        <l>Even for tens of eons</l>
                        <l>Will continue to dwell on focal points— </l>
                        <l>Such discipline will not be pure. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-53"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“Those who retain this profound discourse, </l>
                        <l>Which is praised by the buddhas, </l>
                        <l>Will have unsurpassed discipline</l>
                        <l>And themselves be praised by all the buddhas. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-54"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“Though people may advocate patience for tens of eons, </l>
                        <l>And practice patience toward all that revile them, </l>
                        <l>That patience is not praiseworthy, </l>
                        <l>Unless they have heard about this way. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-55"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“Those who retain this discourse, </l>
                        <l>And correctly teach it to others, </l>
                        <l>Will have unsurpassed patience</l>
                        <l>And be praised by all the buddhas. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-56"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Those who have not heard about this way</l>
                        <l>May continue walking, </l>
                        <l>Even for tens of eons, </l>
                        <l>Yet such effort would not be praiseworthy. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-57"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“Those who retain this profound discourse, </l>
                        <l>Explained by the Buddha, </l>
                        <l>Will have unsurpassed effort</l>
                        <l>And be praised by all the buddhas. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-58"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“Those who practice concentration </l>
                        <l>For tens of eons</l>
                        <l>May abide in the taste of concentration, </l>
                        <l>But they will not be called adepts at concentration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-59"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“Yet those who do not conceive<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-60"> Translated based on Yongle and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtog</foreign>. Degé: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtogs</foreign>.</note> of any phenomena at all, </l>
                        <l>Among inner as well as outer things, </l>
                        <l>Have unsurpassed concentration, </l>
                        <l>And are said to be adepts at concentration. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-61"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“In this way, through the sameness <ref cRef="F.171.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Of generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, </l>
                        <l>Concentration, and insight, </l>
                        <l>Awakening will be quickly attained.” </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-62"/>
                    <p tid="61">When the Blessed One had said this, venerable Ānanda, the Śākya youth Kṣemaṅkara, the entire retinue, and the world including its gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-63"/>
                    <trailer tid="62">This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra entitled “<title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Kṣemaṅkara</title>.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="63">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-64"/>
                    <p tid="64">This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholar Prajñāvarman, and the translator and chief editor venerable Yeshé Dé, and others.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="65">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="67">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="68">Main Section</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-008-66">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bde byed kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 165, Degé Kangyur vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 167b.2–171b.3.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-008-67">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bde byed kyis zhus pa ces bya ba thegs pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok no. 308, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</title>, vol. 87 (mdo sde, chi), folios 218b1–224b1.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-008-68">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bde byed kyis zhus pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 59, 455–65.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-008-69">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="Input Language">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-70">
                            <term>five perfections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phar phyin lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕར་ཕྱིན་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcapāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The five perfections of generosity, discipline, patience,
                                diligence, and concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-71">
                            <term>unsurpassed and perfect awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag par rdzogs pa’i byang chub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པར་རྫོགས་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyaksaṁbodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Manifesting the complete enlightenment of a buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-72">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lower class of divine being, under the control of the
                                Guardian King of the East. Capable of flight, they are often described as
                                “celestial musicians.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-73">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lower class of divine being, described as an eagle-type bird
                                with a gigantic wing span. They are traditionally enemies of the nāgas. In the
                                Vedas, they are thought to have brought nectar from the heavens to earth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-74">
                            <term>kiṁnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṁnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings that resemble humans to the
                                degree that their very name—which means “Is that a human?”—suggests some
                                confusion as to their divine status.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-75">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of serpentine non-human beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-76">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in subterranean
                                aquatic environments and who are known to hoard wealth and esoteric teachings.
                                They are associated with snakes and serpents.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-77">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gi ’jigs rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གི་འཇིགས་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasralokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A universe containing one billion worlds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-78">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings said to dwell in the north,
                                under the jurisdiction of the Great King Vaiśravaṇa, otherwise known as
                                Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-79">
                            <term>mendicant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge sbyong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སྦྱོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śramaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A term used broadly to denote a spiritual
                                practitioner.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-80">
                            <term>non-Buddhist</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mu stegs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མུ་སྟེགས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrthika</term>
                            <term type="definition">A <term type="ignore">non-Buddhist</term> religious practitioner who relies on sacred
                                fords (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tīrtha</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-81">
                            <term>those who apprehend things</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aupalambhika</term>
                            <term type="definition">Someone who apprehends things conceptually.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-82">
                            <term>demigod</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the devas (gods) who are
                                frequently portrayed in Brahmanical mythology as having a disruptive effect on
                                cosmological and social harmony.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-83">
                            <term>Good Eon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bskal pa bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྐལ་པ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of our current eon, so-called because one
                                thousand buddhas are prophesied to appear during this time.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                    <!-- personal names -->
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-84">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha who resides in Sukhāvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-85">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Attendant of the Buddha and the one who is said to have
                                memorized the sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-86">
                            <term>Kṣemaṅkara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣemaṅkara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a Śākya youth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-87">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Demon or demonic influence that creates obstacles for
                                spiritual practice and awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-88">
                            <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pradz+ny+A barma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲཛྙཱ་བརྨ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian Bengali paṇḍita resident in Tibet during the late
                                eighth and early ninth centuries. Arriving in Tibet on an invitation from the
                                Tibetan king, he assisted in the translation of numerous canonical scriptures.
                                He is also the author of a few philosophical commentaries contained in the
                                Tibetan Tengyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</foreign>) collection.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-89">
                            <term>Śākya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākya </term>
                            <term type="definition">The name of the family clan into which Buddha Śākyamuni was
                                born.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-90">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Tibetan translator who was active during the late eighth and
                                early ninth centuries. He participated in the translation of more than two
                                hundred texts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    
                    <!-- places -->
                    
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-91">
                            <term>Ganges</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang gA </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་གཱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṅgā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sacred river of North India.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-92">
                            <term>Kapilavastu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ser skya’i gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་སྐྱའི་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kapilavastu </term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital city of the Śākya kingdom, where the Buddha grew
                                up as Prince Siddhārtha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-93">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The pure land of Buddha Amitābha in which a practitioner can
                                take rebirth through a combination of pure faith, sufficient merit, and
                                one-pointed determination.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-059-008-94">
                            <term>Nyagrodha Park</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing nya gro dha’i kun dga’ ra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ཉ་གྲོ་དྷའི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyagrodhārāma</term>
                            <term type="definition">A grove of banyan trees (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nyagrodha</foreign>) near Kapilavastu where the Buddha sometimes took
                                residence. It was a gift to the Buddhist community by King Śuddhodana, the
                                father of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
   
    </text>
</TEI>