<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen zla bas zhus pa'i mdo/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ratnacandraparipṛcchāsūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Questions of
                    Ratnacandra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">'phags pa rin chen zla bas zhus pa zhes
                    bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryaratnacandra­paripṛcchā­nāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen zla bas zhus pa/</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnacandra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnacandraparipṛcchā</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-31">Translated by Tenpa
                    Tsering<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-192">Tenpa Tsering</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</author>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>

            </titleStmt>

            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                    non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages,
                    and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-059-007"/>
                <date>2020-01-08</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh164" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 164</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 160.a–167.b</biblScope>
                    <!--<biblScope>vol.59, ff. 160r-167v(pp.319-334)</biblScope>-->
                    <author role="translatorTib">t. Viśuddhasiṃha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">dge ba dpal</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">r. Vidyākarasiṃha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Devacandra</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="16">
                        <volume number="59" start-page="319" end-page="334"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11767" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-01-08T15:46:11.625Z" user="admin">08/01/2020 15:46:11</note>

                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-11-20T08:43:04.615Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2019-11-20T08:43:15.64Z" user="andreas">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2019-12-04T17:35:19.08Z" user="laura">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2019-12-09T09:26:47.114Z" user="andreas">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-01-05T15:30:18.418Z" user="andreas">2.a</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-1"/>
                <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnacandra</title> is a sūtra in which
                    Ratnacandra, a prince from the country of Magadha, requests Buddha Śākyamuni to
                    reveal the names of the ten buddhas who dwell in the ten directions. Prince
                    Ratnacandra has been told that hearing the names of these ten buddhas ensures
                    that one will attain awakening at some point in the future. The Buddha confirms
                    this and discloses their names, as well as details of their respective buddha
                    realms, such as the names of these realms and their many unique qualities.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by Tenpa Tsering. The translation was edited by Ryan Damron and
                    Andreas Doctor, who also wrote the introduction together. This translation has
                    been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the
                    Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="6">Main Section</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnacandra</title> is a sūtra that
                        takes place on Vulture Peak Mountain outside of the city of Rājagṛha, the
                        capital of the ancient country of Magadha. There Ratnacandra, who is
                        described as one of the sons of King Bimbisāra, the ruler of Magadha,
                        requests Buddha Śākyamuni to reveal the names of the ten buddhas who dwell
                        in the ten directions. Ratnacandra has been told that hearing the names of
                        these ten buddhas guarantees one’s future awakening and so wishes to know
                        them. The buddha confirms the transformative power of these ten names, and
                        during the course of the sūtra he discloses them and provides additional
                        details of their respective buddha realms, such as the names of these worlds
                        and their many unique qualities. Finally, the Buddha concludes the teaching
                        by relating the events of a distant past that led to these ten buddhas
                        conjointly attaining awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-4"/>
                    <p tid="8">The message of the sūtra—that one can ensure the future attainment of
                        awakening by coming into contact with the names of celestial buddhas—is one
                        shared by a number of Great Vehicle sūtras. Nakamura includes this sūtra
                        among more than twenty sūtras in the Chinese canon that prescribe the
                        practice of chanting the names of various buddhas.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                            <note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-5"> Nakamura 1980, pp.
                                177–182.</note>
                        </hi> The Tibetan canon likewise contains a
                        significant number of such sūtras. However, since the organizing principles
                        of the Degé Kangyur are not always thematic but often based on other
                        criteria, such as titles, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                            Ratnacandra</title> is grouped in the Degé Kangyur among the many sūtras
                        named “The Questions of [such-and-such].” This sūtra is a prime example of
                        the genre of Great Vehicle literature that places great emphasis on the
                        transformative power enacted by remembering, chanting, and venerating the
                        names of the many buddhas who occupy other world systems concurrently with
                        Buddha Śākyamuni’s presence here in our realm.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-6"/>
                    <p tid="9">No Sanskrit manuscript of this sūtra appears to be extant, but in addition to
                        the Tibetan translation a single Chinese translation also exists (Taishō
                        437). This translation was produced by the Indian monk Dānapāla (fl. ca. 980
                            <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), a highly prolific translator credited
                        with completing no less than one hundred individual translations. In spite
                        of this relatively late date of translation into Chinese, Nakamura remarks
                        that a certain “prototype” of <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                            Ratnacandra</title> is cited in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Daśabhūmikavibhāṣā</title>, which is attributed to Nāgārjuna (ca.
                        second–third century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>).<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                            <note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-7"> Nakamura 1980, p.
                            234</note>
                        </hi> The attribution of this text to Nāgārjuna is itself a
                        topic of debate, but the text was undoubtedly translated by Kumārajīva, who
                        lived from 344–413 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. This means that the
                        so-called “prototype” of <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of
                            Ratnacandra</title> must have been in circulation in India prior to the
                        middle of the fourth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-8"/>
                    <p tid="10">The colophon of the Tibetan translation lists four figures involved in its
                        production: the Indian scholars Viśuddhasiṃha and Vidyākarasiṃha and the
                        Tibetan translators Gewa Pal (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba
                            dpal</foreign>) and Devacandra (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de ba tsan
                            dra</foreign>). Therefore, the Tibetan translation would have been
                        completed during the early translation period. The ninth-century Denkarma
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</foreign>) catalogue includes a
                        text with a similar title, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Child
                            Ratnacandra</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khye’u rin chen zla bas
                            zhus pa</title>),<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-9"> The Denkarma catalogue is dated to
                            ca. 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. See Denkarma, f. 299.a.4. See
                            also Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p. 99, no. 184.</note> but this title may not
                        refer to the text translated here. The Phukdrak (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phug brag</foreign>) Kangyur uniquely preserves texts with both titles,
                        and while they are similar enough in content to suggest that they are
                        closely related texts, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Child
                            Ratnacandra</title> is substantially different. This sūtra shares the
                        framing narrative and other structural features of <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Ratnacandra</title> but omits many of its specific
                        descriptive elements, especially those concerning the Buddha’s entourage and
                        the features of the individual buddha realms. There is also significant
                        variation in the names of the buddha realms and their attending thus-gone
                        ones, with most, but not all, being unique to each version.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-10"> In the Phukdrak version, the realms and their presiding buddhas are
                            given as follows: to the east is the realm Sorrowless (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan med pa</foreign>) and the buddha
                            Bhadraśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal bzang po</foreign>); to the
                            south is Peaceful (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba</foreign>) and the
                            buddha Ratnaprabhā (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od</foreign>);
                            to the west is Heroic (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo</foreign>) and
                            the buddha Ānandaśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i
                                dpal</foreign>); to the north is the realm Without Conflict
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’khrugs pa</foreign>) and the buddha
                            Ketuśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi dpal</foreign>); to the
                            southeast is Opulent (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod pa can</foreign>)
                            and the buddha Aśokaśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan med pa’i
                                dpal</foreign>); to the southwest is the realm Shining Bright
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi dpal</foreign>) and the buddha
                            Ratnayaṣṭi (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen srog shing</foreign>);
                            to the northwest is Melodious (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbyangs
                                can</foreign>) and the buddha Kusumaśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog dpal</foreign>); to the northeast is Happy (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ldan</foreign>) and the buddha with
                            Supernatural Powers that Revels in the Shining Lotus (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo ’tsher bas rnam par rol pa mngon par shes
                                pa</foreign>); at the nadir is Vast Expanse (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs pa can</foreign>) and the buddha Brilliant
                            Star (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skar ma dpal</foreign>); and at the
                            zenith is the realm Moonlight (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba snang
                                ba</foreign>) and the buddha Dhanaśrī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bnor dpal</foreign>). </note>
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Child Ratnacandra</title> found in
                        the Phukdrak Kangyur also lacks the versified passage that closes <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnacandra</title>. The text recorded in
                        the Denkarma catalogue as <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Child
                            Ratnacandra</title> is listed as a translation made by the same group of
                        Indian scholars and Tibetan translators as <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Ratnacandra</title>, suggesting it may in fact be the work
                        translated here; however, the Phukdrak version lacks a translator’s
                        colophon, making it impossible to determine any contextual relationship
                        between the two translations. To confuse matters more, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of Ratnacandra</title> is preserved under the title
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Child Ratnacandra</title> in
                        extra-canonical dhāraṇī collections.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-11">
                            <hi type="wordfile-remnant"> See, for example, the </hi>
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sngags gsung rab rgya mtsho</title>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’</foreign>
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">i snying po
                                mtshan gzungs mang bsdus</title>
                            <hi type="wordfile-remnant">, vol.
                                vam, ff. 182–205. </hi>
                        </note> In producing this English
                        translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while consulting
                        the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>).
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="11"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="12">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="13">The Questions of Ratnacandra</head>
                <!--In the rare case that there is initial text before the first chapter begins, the script will place the
                        text here. However, this will cause the two headings for the "Honorific Title" and "Main Title" to be duplicated below
                        as <p> elements. Markup Editors, please delete these initial duplicated <p> elements along with their milestones and delete this comment.-->
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-12"/>
                <p tid="14">
                    <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</hi>
                </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-13"/>
                <p tid="15">
                    <hi type="wordfile-remnant">The Questions of Ratnacandra</hi>
                </p>
                <div>
                    <head tid="16">Main Section</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-14"/>
                    <p tid="17">[F.160.a] Homage to the Omniscient One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-15"/>
                    <p tid="18">
                        <lb/>Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was residing in Rājagṛha,
                        on Vulture Peak Mountain, together with a large community of 7,200,000
                        monks, including Śāriputra and Maudgalyāyana. There were also 90,000
                        bodhisattvas, including the bodhisattva great being Maitreya, the
                        bodhisattva great being Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva great being Akṣayamati,
                        the bodhisattva great being Sāgaramati, the bodhisattva great being
                        Anantamati, the bodhisattva great being Dṛḍhamati, the bodhisattva great
                        being Dispeller of the Three Realms, the bodhisattva great being Ratnapāṇi,
                        the bodhisattva great being Vaidyarāja, the bodhisattva great being
                        Ratnākara, and the bodhisattva great being Joy and Sorrow. There were also
                        many billions of gods, including the Four Great Kings, Śakra king of the
                        gods along with his millions of divine attendants, and Brahmā lord of the
                        Enduring world along with his millions of divine attendants from the Brahmā
                        realm. There were also millions of nāgas, including the nāga king Sāgara,
                        the nāga king Anavatapta, the nāga king Elapatra, and the nāga king
                        Resounding†. Along with them were millions of yakṣa generals, such as
                        Āṭavaka, [F.160.b] Sucīromā, Oṣadhi, and Gardabhaka. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-16"/>
                    <p tid="19">One morning the Blessed One put on his lower garments and monk’s robes, took
                        his alms bowl, and left for his alms round in Rājagṛha. At the same time
                        Prince Ratnacandra, the son of King Bimbisāra, left the city of Rājagṛha
                        riding an elephant known as Eight-Trunked. It was adorned with seven kinds
                        of precious materials and covered with golden latticework. Small bells were
                        tied onto the elephant, which was further ornamented with tassels of golden
                        brocade. As the prince emerged incense was burned, flowers petals were
                        scattered, and banners and parasols were unfurled. After riding through the
                        city decorated with parasols and fences, beautified with precious trees, and
                        encircled with seven pavilions, he rode out of the capital displaying both
                        royal wealth and power.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-17"/>
                    <p tid="20">As Prince Ratnacandra was handing out alms to everyone present, he noticed
                        the Blessed One walking in the distance. He was handsome and gracious, with
                        peaceful faculties and mind. He had the most exquisite color. He was
                        perfectly gentle and peaceful, the perfection of a gentle and peaceful
                        being. He had a great presence and was restrained and calm. Like a lake, he
                        was clear and pristine. Like a golden reliquary, his noble body was adorned
                        with the thirty-two major marks and the eighty minor marks of a great being.
                        Due to his supreme splendor, he was shining, bright, and resplendent. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-18"/>
                    <p tid="21">Upon seeing the Blessed One, Ratnacandra was moved to faith. Filled with
                        faith, he immediately alighted from the elephant and approached the Blessed
                        One. Prostrating at the feet of the Blessed One, he circumambulated him
                        three times and sat to one side. [F.161.a] Ratnacandra, the son of King
                        Bimbisāra, folded his palms together and bowed toward to the Blessed One and
                        spoke to him with honorific and respectful words, “O Blessed One, it is said
                        that a faithful noble son or daughter who has heard the names of ten
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddhas who dwell in the ten directions will not
                        fall back from the supreme and perfect state of awakening. Blessed One,
                        please speak of this. Thus-gone One, please tell us about this.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-19"/>
                    <p tid="22">In response, the Blessed One said to Ratnacandra, the son of the king
                        Bimbisāra, “Prince, well done! Well done indeed. Prince, you ask this in
                        order to benefit many beings and bring them happiness. You do so out of love
                        for the world and for the welfare of many beings, to benefit and bring
                        happiness to gods and humans alike, and to assist the bodhisattvas of the
                        present and the future. Prince, it is excellent you thought to ask the
                        Thus-Gone, worthy, perfect Buddha about this point. Prince, your request is
                        excellent, and it is virtuous that you were moved to articulate it.
                        Therefore, Prince, listen carefully and keep this teaching in mind. Listen
                        to me with one-pointed concentration and reflect on what I say as I explain
                        this teaching to you.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-20"/>
                    <p tid="23">Ratnacandra, the son of King Bimbisāra, replied, “Blessed One, excellent!”
                        And he listened as the Blessed One had directed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-21"/>
                    <p tid="24">The Blessed One then said, “Prince, east of this buddha realm, past
                        countless, inconceivably many, limitless billions of buddha realms, there is
                        a realm [F.161.b] called Sorrowless. You may wonder how many boundless
                        buddha realms one must pass through to reach that realm. Well, Prince,
                        suppose the entire trichiliocosm was completely filled with sand, all the
                        way to its summits. If a person were to remove the sand, grain by grain, and
                        place one grain of sand in each buddha realm toward the east until every
                        single grain of sand was placed in a buddha realm in that direction, one
                        would still not have reached the extent and limit of those buddha realms.
                        The realm called Sorrowless lies further away than such boundless and
                        countless billions of buddha realms. That realm is as flat as the palm of
                        the hand, is beautifully decorated with seven kinds of precious substances,
                        and has a ground made of gold. It is laid out in a checkered pattern and
                        ornamented with precious trees. There are no hell beings, animals, hungry
                        spirits, and asuras there, and it is free of grass, dried sticks, thorns,
                        stones, pebbles, gravel, ravines, and precipices. Instead, the ground is
                        covered in flower petals. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-22"/>
                    <p tid="25">“There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Bhadraśrī resides and lives
                        surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He is learned
                        and venerable, a blissful one, a knower of the world, a steersman who guides
                        beings, an unexcelled one, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha.
                        His body, which is adorned with the thirty-two marks of a great being, is
                        like purified and refined gold adorned with precious ornaments. Sitting
                        beautifully amidst the gathering, he teaches a Dharma that is virtuous in
                        the beginning, virtuous in the middle, and virtuous in the end. [F.162.a] He
                        teaches as follows: ‘The earth element does not cease to exist, nor does the
                        water element, the fire element, and the wind element. Likewise, Brahmā who
                        is the lord of beings does not cease to exist, and the same applies to form,
                        feeling, perception, formation, and consciousness.’ Prince, it has been six
                        hundred million eons since the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Bhadraśrī
                        fully awakened to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-23"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Prince, in that buddha realm there are no words for <distinct>day</distinct>
                        and <distinct>night</distinct>, but this example from our world does not
                        really apply. The entire buddha realm is continuously illuminated with the
                        light of the thus-gone one. Moreover, Prince, every teaching given by the
                        thus-gone one establishes countless billions of beings at the level of
                        unborn phenomena<fix>.</fix> He establishes twice as many beings in each of
                        the three types of acceptance. Furthermore, Prince, sentient beings who
                        served past buddhas in other buddha realms and produced roots of virtue with
                        them will attain acceptance that phenomena are unborn when touched by the
                        light born from the power generated from the past aspirations of this
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha. Prince, any noble son or daughter who
                        hears the name of the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Bhadraśrī will never
                        turn back from unsurpassed and perfect awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">“Prince, south of this world, past as many countless billions of buddha
                        realms as mentioned before, there is a realm called Joy<hi type="wordfile-remnant">†</hi>
                        <fix>.</fix> That realm is as flat as the
                        palm of the hand and has all the other qualities described above.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-25"> This and the subsequent statements that reference
                            previously-mentioned material represent intentional scribal elisions
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">peyāla</foreign>) of
                            repetitive passages, and likely originate in the Sanskrit manuscript on
                            which the Tibetan translation is based. The reader is meant to revisit
                            the first passage for the elided material. The complete passage will
                            typically be restated in the final section, which in the context of this
                            text is the passage describing the tenth buddha realm. Such scribal
                            elisions are a common feature in Pali and Sanskrit texts with lengthy
                            passages of repetitive material.</note> [F.162.b] There the thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect buddha Candanaśrī resides and lives surrounded by a
                        gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He teaches them a Dharma that is
                        virtuous in the beginning, virtuous in the middle, and virtuous in the end.
                        He also teaches the same Dharma mentioned previously, up until
                        ‘consciousness.’ Prince, what do you think? Why is the thus-gone one called
                        Candanaśrī? The entire buddha realm of the thus-gone one is filled with
                        houses built of sandalwood. Therefore, the thus-gone one is called
                            Candanaśrī.<hi type="wordfile-remnant">
                            <note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-26"> Candanaśrī
                                means “Sandalwood Splendor”.</note>
                        </hi> Any noble son or daughter,
                        who hears the name Buddha Candanaśrī will never turn back from unsurpassed
                        and perfect awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-27"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Prince, west of here, past as many countless billions of buddha realms as
                        mentioned before, there is a realm called Excellence<fix>.</fix> That realm
                        is as flat as the palm of the hand and has all the other qualities described
                        above. There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Amitābha resides and
                        lives surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He teaches
                        them a Dharma that is virtuous in the beginning, virtuous in the middle, and
                        virtuous in the end. He also teaches the same Dharma mentioned previously,
                        up until ‘consciousness.’ Prince, any noble son or daughter who hears the
                        name of that thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from
                        unsurpassed and perfect awakening and will experience that light.
                        [F.163.a]</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-28"/>
                    <p tid="29">“Prince, north of here, past countless billions of buddha realms, there is a
                        realm called Without Conflict. That realm is as flat as the palm of the hand
                        and has all the other qualities described above. There the thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect buddha Floral Splendor resides and lives surrounded by a
                        gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He teaches them a Dharma that is
                        virtuous in the beginning, virtuous in the middle, and virtuous in the end.
                        He also teaches the same Dharma mentioned previously, up until
                        ‘consciousness.’ Prince, any noble son or daughter who hears the name of
                        that thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from unsurpassed
                        and perfect awakening and will become like a victory banner for the world
                        along with its gods.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-29"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Prince, southeast of here, past countless billions of buddha realms, there
                        is a realm called Moonlight. That realm is as flat as the palm of the hand
                        and has all the other qualities described above. Prince, what do you think?
                        Why is that world called Moonlight? It is because the rays of light from the
                        thus-gone one there illuminate that entire realm. That is why that world is
                        called Moonlight. There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Aśokaśrī
                        resides and lives surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate
                        him. He teaches them the same Dharma mentioned previously, up until
                        ‘consciousness.’ Any noble son or daughter who hears the name of that
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from unsurpassed and
                        perfect awakening. [F.163.b]</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-30"/>
                    <p tid="31">“Prince, southwest of here, past countless billions of buddha realms, there
                        is a realm called Decorated with Banners. That realm is as flat as the palm
                        of the hand and has all the other qualities described above. There the
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Ratnayūpa resides and lives surrounded by
                        a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He teaches them the same
                        Dharma mentioned previously, up until ‘consciousness.’ Any noble son or
                        daughter who hears the name of that thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will
                        never turn back from unsurpassed and perfect awakening and will become as
                        exalted as a jewel in the world.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-31"/>
                    <p tid="32">“Prince, northwest of here, past countless billions of buddha realms, there
                        is a realm called Resounding. That realm is as flat as the palm of the hand
                        and has all the other qualities described above. Prince, what do you think?
                        Why is that world called Resounding? It is because the realm is endowed with
                        the sounds of ‘Buddha,’ ‘Dharma,’ and ‘Saṅgha,’ as well as ‘emptiness,’
                        ‘signlessness,’ and ‘wishlessness.’ Furthermore, it is endowed with the
                        sounds of ‘generosity,’ ‘discipline,’ ‘patience,’ ‘diligence,’
                        ‘concentration,’ ‘insight,’ ‘liberation,’ and ‘wisdom of liberation.’
                        Prince, since that world is endowed with such sounds, it is called
                        Resounding. There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Kusumaśrī resides
                        and lives [F.164.a] surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate
                        him. He teaches them the same Dharma mentioned previously, up until
                        ‘consciousness.’ Any noble son or daughter who hears the name of that
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from unsurpassed and
                        perfect awakening and, like a lotus, will be unstained by nonvirtuous
                        phenomena.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-32"/>
                    <p tid="33"> “Prince, northeast of here, past billions of buddha realms as mentioned
                        before, there is a realm called Happy†. It is affluent, thriving, and happy.
                        It has good harvests and is inhabited by many people. It is as flat as the
                        palm of the hand and has all the other qualities described above. There the
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Reveling in Lesser, Medium, and Higher
                        Superknowledge resides and lives surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas
                        who venerate him. He teaches them the same Dharma mentioned previously, up
                        until ‘consciousness.’ Any noble son or daughter who hears the name of that
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from unsurpassed and
                        perfect awakening, will become skilled in all the actions and ways of
                        bodhisattvas, and will uphold the perfection of knowledge.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-33"/>
                    <p tid="34">“Prince, below here, past billions of buddha realms, there is a realm called
                        Vast Expanse. Prince, what do you think? Why is that world called Vast
                        Expanse? It is because it is as flat as the palm of the hand and it has no
                        mountains, surrounding mountains, or great surrounding mountains. Since even
                        the word <distinct>mountain</distinct> [F.164.b] does not exist in that
                        buddha realm, it is called Vast Expanse. There the thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect buddha Prabhāśrī resides and lives surrounded by a gathering of
                        bodhisattvas who venerate him. He teaches them the same Dharma mentioned
                        previously, up until ‘consciousness.’ Any noble son or daughter who hears
                        the name of that thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn back from
                        unsurpassed and perfect awakening and will be graced with the exhaustion of
                        all their perpetuating afflictions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-34"/>
                    <p tid="35">“Prince, above here, past innumerable, unfathomable, inconceivable, and
                        immeasurable billions of buddha realms, there is a realm called Moonlit. How
                        many unfathomable buddha realms must one pass through to reach Moonlit?
                        Prince, it is like this. Suppose this trichiliocosm were completely filled
                        with sand, all the way to the peak of existence. If a person were to remove
                        the sand, grain by grain, and place one grain of sand in each buddha realm
                        above until every single grain of sand was placed in a buddha realm in that
                        direction, one would still not have reached the extent and limit of those
                        buddha realms. The realm Moonlit lies that many unfathomable and innumerable
                        billions of buddha realms away from here. That realm is as flat as the palm
                        of the hand, is beautifully decorated with seven kinds of precious
                        substances, and has a ground made of gold. It is laid out in a checkered
                        pattern and ornamented with precious trees. There are no hell beings,
                        animals, hungry spirits, and asuras there, [F.165.a] and it is free of
                        grass, dried sticks, thorns, stones, pebbles, gravel, ravines, and
                        precipices. Instead, the ground is covered in flower petals. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-35"/>
                    <p tid="36">“There the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Dhanaśrī resides and lives
                        surrounded by a gathering of bodhisattvas who venerate him. He is learned
                        and venerable, a blissful one, a knower of the world, a steersman who guides
                        beings, an unexcelled one, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha.
                        His body, which is adorned with the thirty-two marks of a great being, is
                        like purified and refined gold adorned with precious ornaments. Sitting
                        beautifully amidst the gathering, he teaches a Dharma that is virtuous in
                        the beginning, virtuous in the middle, and virtuous in the end. He teaches
                        as follows: ‘The earth element does not cease to exist, nor does the water
                        element, the fire element, and the wind element. Likewise, Brahmā who is the
                        lord of beings does not cease to exist, and the same applies to form,
                        feeling, perception, formation and consciousness.’ Any noble son or daughter
                        who hears the name of that thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha will never turn
                        back from unsurpassed and perfect awakening and will receive the precious
                        and supreme Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-36"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Prince, any noble son or daughter who hears the names of these thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect buddhas, who are endowed with perfect conduct, qualities,
                        wisdom, discipline, absorption, insight, liberation, and the vision of the
                        wisdom of liberation, will never turn back from unsurpassed and perfect
                        awakening.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-37"/>
                    <p tid="38">“Prince, long ago in the past, [F.165.b] eons beyond calculation and measure,
                        there was an eon by the name of Ratnākara. In that eon appeared the
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Sāgaraśrī. He was learned and venerable, a
                        blissful one, a knower of the world, a steersman who guides beings, an
                        unexcelled one, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed buddha. At that
                        time, these ten thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddhas came together to generate
                        roots of virtue by making boundless and countless grand offerings of food
                        and drink, flowers, incense, flower garlands, lotions, parasols, flags, and
                        banners to that blessed one. Thereby all of them together generated the mind
                        set upon unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Then, one day, at precisely the
                        same moment, they all achieved acceptance that phenomena are unborn.
                        Thereafter they gradually engaged in bodhisattva conduct and mastered the
                        factors that are conducive for awakening. Then, at precisely the same
                        moment, they all attained unsurpassed and perfect awakening in each of their
                        respective buddha realms. At precisely the same moment, they all turned the
                        wheel of Dharma. They even enjoyed the same lifespan. Prince, these
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddhas will also one day enter into complete
                        nirvāṇa at precisely the same moment.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-38"/>
                    <p tid="39">Ratnacandra, the son of King Bimbisāra, then said to the Blessed One,
                        [F.166.a] “Blessed One, the lifespan of those thus-gone, worthy, perfect
                        buddhas is amazing! Blessed One, out of compassion for sentient beings,
                        those thus-gone ones intentionally live such long lives. Blessed One, how
                        much merit will noble sons or daughters generate if they keep the lifespan
                        of those thus-gone ones in mind and trust in it without disregarding it or
                        ignoring it?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-39"/>
                    <p tid="40">The Buddha replied, “Prince, one could fill up this entire trichiliocosm,
                        along with the buddha realms of these ten thus-gone ones and the other
                        buddha realms in the ten directions, with the seven precious substances of
                        the gods and make daily offerings of them to the thus-gone, worthy, perfect
                        buddhas, continuing this daily offering for countless eons. On the other
                        hand, a noble son or daughter who has heard about the names and lifespan of
                        these buddhas may keep them faithfully in mind without disregarding or
                        disrespecting them and instead trust and agree with them. For that person
                        the heap of merit accrued is far greater than that gathered by the former
                        person. The former does not gather even a hundredth or a thousandth of that.
                        It is, in fact, beyond the scope of illustration.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-40"/>
                    <p tid="41">Then, in order to venerate this teaching and the ten thus-gone ones, Śakra
                        king of the gods, Brahmā lord of the Enduring world, the four guardian
                        kings, and the divine sons Īśvara, Maheśvara, Glorious Fortune<hi type="wordfile-remnant">, </hi>Tuṣita, and Santuṣita scattered divine
                        flowers and sandalwood powder upon the Thus-Gone One. Then they spoke these
                        words: “Blessed One, any noble son or daughter who retains, [F.166.b]
                        carries, reads, and recites this teaching is worthy of reverence. Blessed
                        One, merely holding this teaching in their hand, they will never turn back
                        from unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Blessed One, any noble son or
                        daughter who hears this teaching will not fall under the sway of the evil
                        Māra.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-41"/>
                    <p tid="42">At that point Prince Ratnacandra, the son of the king Bimbisāra, addressed
                        the following verses to the Blessed One:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-42"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>“Blessed One, you are beyond the aggregates!</l>
                        <l>Your eloquent teachings are beyond measure.</l>
                        <l>I and the entire world, along with its gods,</l>
                        <l>Rejoice in the teachings you have given. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-43"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>“We take refuge in the world protectors</l>
                        <l>Who have passed, are present,</l>
                        <l>And who are yet to come,</l>
                        <l>And in the buddhas residing in all directions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-44"/>
                    <lg tid="45">
                        <l>“Of common purpose with all the buddhas,</l>
                        <l>The Dharma and Saṅgha are the utmost peace.</l>
                        <l>Their perfect qualities are inconceivable.</l>
                        <l>We take refuge in the Saṅgha too. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-45"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>“The fearless bodhisattvas</l>
                        <l>Are stable in patience,</l>
                        <l>Grounded in recall<fix>,</fix>
                        </l>
                        <l>And maintain incomparable emptiness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-46"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>“These bodhisattvas train well</l>
                        <l>In the sūtras of characteristics,</l>
                        <l>The scriptures that lead to awakening,</l>
                        <l>And the sūtras that conform to both.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-47"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>“Sage, like them, we too wish to train</l>
                        <l>In the conduct of awakening.</l>
                        <l>You have taught about those naturally arisen ones,</l>
                        <l>The pure arrangement of their realms,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-48"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>“And their practices, domains, and absorptions,</l>
                        <l>As well as their qualities</l>
                        <l>And the lifespan of these supreme sages.</l>
                        <l>Now I too will accomplish these qualities.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-49"/>
                    <p tid="50">Then the Blessed One commended the gods and Ratnacandra, and addressed them
                        with the following verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-50"/>
                    <lg tid="51">
                        <l>“All who recall the names </l>
                        <l>Of these protectors of the world [F.167.a]</l>
                        <l>Will, in future times,</l>
                        <l>Become supreme among humans.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-51"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“They too will live </l>
                        <l>For inconceivably many millions of eons,</l>
                        <l>Like the lifespan of these supreme sages, </l>
                        <l>Which I have just described.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-52"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“Those who recall the names</l>
                        <l>Of these protectors</l>
                        <l>Will be unharmed by fire, bandits, </l>
                        <l>Poison, and weapons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-53"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“Whoever recalls the names of these buddhas</l>
                        <l>Will never drown in rivers,</l>
                        <l>Will never be subject to royal punishment, </l>
                        <l>And will never forsake the Dharma.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-54"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“Recite these names at three times:</l>
                        <l>In the first watch of the night</l>
                        <l>And in the middle and last watches as well.</l>
                        <l>Wise ones who recite the names</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-55"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Of these supreme sages,</l>
                        <l>In the morning, at noon, </l>
                        <l>And in the evening,</l>
                        <l>Will have good dreams.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-56"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“Next, having recalled these names,</l>
                        <l>One must confess all the negative deeds</l>
                        <l>One has committed</l>
                        <l>Over the course of billions of eons.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-57"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“Any negative deed committed,</l>
                        <l>By way of body, speech, and mind,</l>
                        <l>After one has recalled these names,</l>
                        <l>Must also be confessed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-58"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“Touching one’s five points<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-59"> The head, arms, and legs.
                            </note> to the ground,</l>
                        <l>One should rejoice in the merit</l>
                        <l>Of the wholesome deeds accumulated</l>
                        <l>Prior to one’s awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-60"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“Having attained awakening,</l>
                        <l>The kinsmen of the world taught the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>And all beings made offerings</l>
                        <l>To the protectors of the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-61"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“The children of the victors should rejoice in them</l>
                        <l>Three times during the day and night. </l>
                        <l>In this way the perfections that benefit self and others</l>
                        <l>Shall be accomplished.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-62"/>
                    <p tid="62">When the Blessed One had spoken these words, the youth Ratnacandra, son of
                        King Bimbisāra, along with all the bodhisattvas, monks, gods, humans,
                        asuras, and gandharvas, rejoiced in the Buddha’s teaching and offered
                        praise. [F.167.b]</p>
                    <trailer tid="63">This completes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra “<title xml:lang="en">The
                            Questions of Ratnacandra</title>.”</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head tid="64">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-059-007-63"/>
                    <p tid="65">The Indian scholar Viśuddhasiṃha and the translator Venerable Gewa Pal
                        translated this. Later, the Indian scholar Vidyākarasiṃha and the
                        editor-translator monk Devacandra edited and finalized it.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="66">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head tid="67">Abbreviations</head>
                    <fix/>
                    <!-- In this section, markup editors need to move the expanded form of the
                            abbreviation out of the "abbr" element and put it into the "expan" element. Delete
                           this comment and the "fix" tag when you are done. If there are no abbreviations in 
                            this text, then delete this entire "list" element, but leave the "div" and "head"
                            entitled "notes"-->
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="68">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head tid="69">Main Section</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-64">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rin chen zla bas zhus pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryaratnacandraparipṛcchānāmamahāyānasūtra</title>). Toh 164, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 59 (mdo sde, ba), folios 160.a–167.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-65">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa rin chen zla bas zhus pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                        <fix>. </fix>bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
                        [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste
                        gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau
                        of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i
                        bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009,
                        vol. 59, pp. 433–451.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-66">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa khye’u rin chen zla bas zhus pa zhes
                            bya ba’i theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Phukdrak Kangyur (mdo sde, go),
                        folios 57.b–63.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-67">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa khye’u rin chen zla bas zhus pa zhes
                            bya ba’i theg pa chen po’i mdo. </title>
                        <hi type="wordfile-remnant">mdo
                            sngags gsung rab rgya mtsho'i snying po mtshan gzungs mang bsdus (vam)
                            folios 182-205.</hi>
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-68">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan [/ lhan] dkar
                            gyi chos 'gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>). Toh 4364, Degé Tengyur vol.
                        206 (sna tshogs, jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-69">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="Input Language">Die lHan kar
                            ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen
                            Texte</title>
                        <fix>. </fix>Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der
                        Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-059-007-70">Nakamura, Hajime. <title xml:lang="en">Indian Buddhism: A Survey with
                            Bibliographical Notes</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1980.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>