<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun rdzob dang don dam pa’i bden pa bstan pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṃvṛti­paramārtha­satya­nirdeśa</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཀུན་རྫོབ་དང་དོན་དམ་པའི་བདེན་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa kun rdzob dang don dam pa’i bden pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg
                    pa chen po’i mdo </title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­saṃvṛti­paramārtha­satya­nirdeśa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-9" role="translatorMain">
                    Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Group<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-40"/>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-70">Miguel Sawaya</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</author>
                <editor role="mainEditor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-61"/>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-46">Khenpo Trokpa Tulku</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-48"/>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-49">Lama Karma Oser</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.2 <date>2014 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-060-008"/>
                <date>2014-03-24</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh179" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 179</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 60 (mdo sde, ma), folios 244.b–266.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śākyaprabha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dharmatāśīla</author>
                    <location count-pages="45">
                        <start volume="60" page="490"/>
                        <end volume="60" page="534"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11791" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 16/01/2019 at 10:35:21 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="297">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-1"/>
                <p tid="1"> In <title xml:lang="en">Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths</title>, the bodhisattva Mañjuśrī is
                    summoned by Buddha Śākyamuni from a faraway buddha realm to teach in a way that demolishes all dualistic
                    experience. As Mañjuśrī begins to teach, the main message of the sūtra unfolds as an explanation of the two
                    truths. The general theme of Mañjuśrī’s discourse is centered on the particular circumstances in Ratnaketu’s
                    buddha realm, but the message is equally applicable to the experiences of beings here in this world. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="298">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche.
                    Miguel Sawaya and Andreas Doctor produced the translation and wrote the introduction. Catherine Dalton
                    compared the draft translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text. The translators are grateful to
                    Khenpo Trokpa Tulku, Lama Karma Oser, and Lama Tenzin Sangpo from Ka-Nying Shedrub Ling Monastery for their
                    assistance in resolving several difficult passages.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="299">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths</title> is a sūtra significant in the canon
                        of the Great Vehicle, concerned as it is with one of the key themes of Buddhist philosophy, the two
                        truths. These two principles are (1) the relative truth (understanding the world as it appears); and (2)
                        the ultimate truth (understanding the world as it is). Since this bifurcation of reality is one of the
                        frameworks underlying the entirety of Buddhist thought, the message of this sūtra is of importance for all
                        Buddhist traditions, and for the Great Vehicle in particular.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Some readers may be surprised that most of the teaching delivered in this sūtra is spoken not by
                        the Buddha himself, but by his disciple Mañjuśrī. However, as readers familiar with the Great Vehicle
                        sūtras will have noticed, in this literature the Buddha often encourages his students to teach, and
                        subsequently endorses their lectures as <foreign xml:lang="la">bona fide</foreign> “words of the Buddha”
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhavacana</foreign>). In this way Mañjuśrī’s teaching
                        becomes authentic scripture through the awakened activity of the Buddha himself. Still, before Mañjuśrī
                        can deliver his eloquent teaching, he must first arrive in this world, as it turns out that he has
                        temporarily taken up residence in a distant buddha realm, known as Jewel World. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The sūtra, which takes place on Vulture Peak Mountain—a hill just outside the ancient city of
                        Rājagṛha, capital of what was then the state of Magadha—begins with a bodhisattva god named Lord of Peace
                        and Calm asking the Buddha where Mañjuśrī might be found. The Buddha announces that Mañjuśrī has moved to
                        a buddha realm many thousands of world systems away. There, the Buddha explains, Mañjuśrī lives in the
                        assembly of another buddha, Ratnaketu. Lord of Peace and Calm politely requests the Buddha to send a
                        signal to Mañjuśrī summoning him to this world, since Mañjuśrī is the only bodhisattva who is able to
                        teach in a way that demolishes all dualistic experience or, as the text describes it, experience that
                        involves “reference points.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The Buddha obliges and immediately sends forth a light from the magical hair between his eyebrows.
                        The light inspires Mañjuśrī to return to this world, this time joined on his travels by an enormous
                        assembly of bodhisattvas from the buddha realm of Ratnaketu. They arrive and, accompanied by much pomp and
                        festivity, they offer proper worship to Buddha Śākyamuni. Once they have settled here in this world,
                        Mañjuśrī is asked to give the assembly a teaching just like the instructions offered by Buddha Ratnaketu
                        in his far-off buddha realm.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">As Mañjuśrī begins to teach, the main message of the sūtra unfolds in the form of an explanation of
                        the two truths. The general theme of Mañjuśrī’s discourse is centered on the particular circumstances in
                        Ratnaketu’s buddha realm, but the message is equally applicable to the experiences of beings here in this
                        world.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">There are two truths, Mañjuśrī teaches. There is the relative truth in which all types of
                        experiences unfold—good and bad, virtuous and nonvirtuous, pleasant and painful, awakened and confused.
                        This truth also includes all the spiritual trainings that take an ordinary being along the path to the
                        state of awakening itself. And then there is the ultimate truth, in which it is realized that all the
                        phenomena experienced on the relative level are, in their most fundamental state, in Mañjuśrī’s words,
                        “unborn, unarisen, and unreal.” This is the truth that is experienced by awakened beings. Still, even
                        though awakened beings perceive the unborn, unarisen, and unreal nature of all phenomena, they actively
                        participate in the relative aspect of things. In relative terms, awakened beings carry out the trainings
                        on the path, guide confused beings toward the liberated state, and perform a multitude of services to
                        beings in general. Nevertheless, as Mañjuśrī teaches again and again in this sūtra, they train without
                        training, they guide without guiding, and they serve without serving. Through such paradoxical
                        expressions, Mañjuśrī describes the experiences of those who have direct understanding of both the
                        ultimate and relative truths. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">The teaching unfolds organically as Mañjuśrī responds to a series of questions put by several of
                        the bodhisattvas in Buddha Śākyamuni’s retinue. Although the recurring theme of the teaching remains the
                        nature of the two truths, Mañjuśrī covers a variety of topics specific to the questions asked. In this way
                        he describes the qualities of both the hearers and bodhisattvas in Buddha Ratnaketu’s circle and the moral
                        trainings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinaya</foreign>) that they observe.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">Interestingly, Mañjuśrī teaches that the very same acts that the hearers in the assembly avoid,
                        the bodhisattvas adopt as their core training, although with a twist. For example, while the hearers seek
                        to avoid miserliness at all cost, the bodhisattvas engage precisely in “miserliness,” albeit with the
                        understanding that it is the welfare of other beings that they refuse to relinquish, rather than any
                        worldly mammon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">Toward the latter half of the sūtra, the teaching takes on a more personal character as the
                        bodhisattvas interview Mañjuśrī concerning his own personal attainments and practice. In this way we find
                        Mañjuśrī describing his own insights and spiritual prowess, although in somewhat cryptic language.
                        Accordingly, when Lord of Peace and Calm asks him whether he directly comprehends the unarisen nature of
                        phenomena on the ultimate level, Mañjuśrī replies, “Divine son, the utterly unarisen does not comprehend
                        the utterly unarisen. And why? Because, divine son, all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen,
                        and utterly unreal.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">At the end of Mañjuśrī’s teaching, the Buddha praises and approves what he has taught. Here, the
                        Buddha is asked by several bodhisattvas to elaborate on some of the themes raised by Mañjuśrī. In general,
                        throughout the sūtra, it is clear that the teachings and trainings of the bodhisattvas are considered
                        preferable, superior, and far vaster in scope than those of the hearers. This is here confirmed by the
                        Buddha, using a series of analogies that illustrate the superiority of the bodhisattva vehicle. For
                        example, the conceptual wisdom of the hearers is compared to a single drop of water, while the
                        nonconceptual wisdom of the bodhisattvas is taught to be infinitely greater, like the great ocean. The
                        reader is left in no doubt as to where the protagonists in this sūtra stand in terms of their devotional
                        allegiance. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-13"/>
                    <p tid="14">Toward the end of the sūtra, in a final display of his superior spiritual abilities, Mañjuśrī
                        enters an absorption that allows him to alter the perceptions of everyone present, so that they now
                        perceive this world as the buddha realm of Ratnaketu. Encouraged by the Buddha, Mañjuśrī reveals his
                        magically created illusion to everyone, before departing for that distant buddha realm from whence he
                        first arrived. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-14"/>
                    <p tid="15">At the very end of the sūtra, we find the customary inquiry by Ānanda to the Buddha regarding the
                        title of the sūtra, its benefits to potential devotees, and the right way to propagate it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-15"/>
                    <p tid="16">The translation was made based on the Degé block print, with reference to other recensions of the
                        sūtra as listed in the Pedurma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) comparative edition of
                        the Kangyur. Unfortunately, it appears that no Sanskrit manuscript remains extant.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-237">A brief passage from this text in Sanskrit (part of <ptr target="#UT22084-060-008-32"/><!--1.17-->) has, however, survived in Prajñākaramati’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title>. See Vose (2009), 214 n8.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="300">THE TRANSLATION </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="301">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra </head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="302">Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-16"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <ref cRef="F.244.b"/>
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-17"/>
                    <p tid="18"> Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Rājagṛha, on Vulture Peak
                        Mountain, together with a large monastic saṅgha of 8,000 monks and 72,000 bodhisattvas, as well as gods
                        living in the desire and form realms. There, the Blessed One taught the Dharma, surrounded and honored by
                        a retinue of many hundreds of thousands of beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-18"/>
                    <p tid="19">Present in the assembly was a god, called Lord of Peace and Calm. He prostrated at the feet of the
                        Blessed One and, bowing with joined palms in the direction of the Blessed One, asked the Blessed One,
                        “Blessed One, where is <ref cRef="F.245.a"/> Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta now? Blessed One, I myself and everyone
                        here would like that sublime being to teach the Dharma.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-19"/>
                    <p tid="20">The Blessed One replied, “Divine son, if one travels east of this buddha realm and passes beyond
                        18,000 other buddha realms, there is a buddha realm called Jewel World. There, the Thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect Buddha Ratnaketu at present lives and teaches the Dharma; and Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta is there
                        now.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-20"/>
                    <p tid="21">The god Lord of Peace and Calm said to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, it would be wonderful if a
                        sign were made such that Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, upon seeing it, would wish to return here. The reason is,
                        Blessed One, that Dharma teachings such as those of Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta are not to be heard from any of
                        the hearers, solitary buddhas, or those bodhisattvas who rely on reference points. Except for the
                        Thus-gone One, no one else at all is capable of teaching the Dharma in that manner. Blessed One, when
                        Mañjuśrī teaches the Dharma, all the dwellings of the demons lose their luster. Moreover, all demons
                        become unable to inflict any harm. All opposition is utterly defeated. Those with reference points are
                        left without reference. The sacred Dharma also remains for a long time. The Thus-gone One will also
                        rejoice in this and approve of it.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-21"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Blessed One knew that the god Lord of Peace and Calm would make this request, and sent out a
                        beam of light from the ūrṇā hair on his brow. That ray of light illuminated the great trichiliocosm with
                        its intense luminescence <ref cRef="F.245.b"/> and, passing through those 18,000 other buddha realms, its
                        intense radiance spread throughout the Jewel World, the buddha realm of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect Buddha Ratnaketu. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-22"/>
                    <p tid="23">Witnessing this radiance, some bodhisattva great beings asked the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect Buddha Ratnaketu who resided there, “Blessed One, there was such a bright light just now; who
                        caused that sign?” </p>
                    <p tid="24">“Son of noble family,” replied the Blessed Ratnaketu, “to the west of this buddha realm, past
                        18,000 buddha realms, is the Sahā world. There, the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni
                        currently lives and teaches the Dharma. The Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni sent out
                        a beam of light from the ūrṇā hair on his brow, and the luminescence of that beam of light passed through
                        18,000 buddha realms and illuminated this world with its intense radiance.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-23"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Blessed One,” asked those bodhisattva great beings, “why did that blessed, thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect buddha emit this beam of light?” </p>
                    <p tid="26">The Blessed Ratnaketu replied, “He did so in order to summon Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta. And why? To
                        make him return there. In that buddha’s retinue there are numerous bodhisattva great beings as well as
                        many gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, and so forth. They all want to behold Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta and <ref cRef="F.246.a"/> hear him teach the Dharma.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-24"/>
                    <p tid="27">The Thus-gone Ratnaketu then said to Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, “Mañjuśrī, since the Blessed, Thus-gone
                        Śākyamuni and all those in his retinue would like to see you, you should go to that Sahā world.” </p>
                    <p tid="28">“Yes, Blessed One,” replied Mañjuśrī. “I had also noticed that sign.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-25"/>
                    <p tid="29">So Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, along with ten thousand bodhisattvas, bowed at the feet of the Thus-gone
                        Ratnaketu. They circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu three times, and
                        then instantaneously traveled to this Sahā world, arriving as quickly as it takes a strong person to
                        extend and retract his arm. Remaining in midair with their bodies invisible, they sent down a great shower
                        of fragrant, colorful, and delightful flowers, such as had never been seen or heard of before, in order to
                        honor the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni. This great shower of flowers filled the
                        whole great trichiliocosm to knee height. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-26"/>
                    <p tid="30">Seeing these flowers, everyone assembled there was amazed and asked, “Blessed One, who caused this
                        great shower of blossoms, so pleasant to behold, to fall?” </p>
                    <p tid="31">The Blessed One replied, “Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, accompanied by ten thousand bodhisattvas, has come
                        from the Jewel World to this Sahā world. With their bodies invisible, <ref cRef="F.246.b"/> they all sent
                        down this great shower of flowers to honor the Thus-gone One.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-27"/>
                    <p tid="32">Those in the retinue said, “Blessed One, we would like to see Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta and those
                        bodhisattva great beings.” </p>
                    <p tid="33">At that point, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta and the ten thousand bodhisattvas descended from the sky.
                        Having prostrated at the Blessed One’s feet, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta and the bodhisattva great beings each
                        sat down on their own miraculously emanated seat. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-28"/>
                    <p tid="34">Then the god Lord of Peace and Calm bowed to the Blessed One and said, with joined palms, “Blessed
                        One, all of us would like to listen, so please ask Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta to teach.” </p>
                    <p tid="35">The Blessed One replied, “Divine son, you yourself should make that request.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-29"/>
                    <p tid="36"> So the god said, “Mañjuśrī, it would be wonderful if you could give us a Dharma teaching similar
                        to what is taught in the buddha realm of the Blessed, Thus-gone Ratnaketu.” </p>
                    <p tid="37"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Ultimately, the Dharma is not about generating attachment; nor is it about
                        bringing attachment to an end. Ultimately, it is not about generating anger; nor is it about bringing
                        anger to an end. Ultimately, it is not about generating delusion; nor is it about bringing delusion to an
                        end. Ultimately, it is not about generating wisdom; nor is it about bringing wisdom to an end.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-30"/>
                    <p tid="38">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how is that?” </p>
                    <p tid="39"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine son, in the unborn, there is no birth or ending whatsoever. Ultimately,
                        divine son, the bodhisattva <ref cRef="F.247.a"/> great beings have no thoughts at all, none that have
                        arisen, none that are arising, and none that will arise. And why is that? Because ultimately all phenomena
                        are inherently unborn.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-31"/>
                    <p tid="40">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, so what does that Thus-gone One wish to see abandoned through his
                        teaching the Dharma?” </p>
                    <p tid="41"> Mañjuśrī said, “That Thus-gone One teaches the Dharma because ultimately things are neither
                        inherently born, nor do they inherently end. And why? Because bodhisattva great beings apply themselves
                        assiduously to the ultimate truth. However, they do not apply themselves diligently to the relative
                        truth.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-32"/>
                    <p tid="42">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is the ultimate truth?” </p>
                    <p tid="43"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, if, on the ultimate level, ultimate truth becomes an object of body,
                        speech, or mind, that is not ‘ultimate truth’ but relative truth itself. Rather, divine son, on the
                        ultimate level, ultimate truth transcends all conventions. It is without specific instances; it does not
                        arise, does not cease, and is free from something to be expressed, an expression, something to be known,
                        and knowledge. Divine son, the ultimate truth transcends everything up through the domain of omniscient
                        wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects. Divine son, it has no engagement with, nor any
                        turning back of, concepts and thoughts. Ultimately, there is no ‘far shore,’ there is no ‘this shore,’ nor
                        is there a middle. Divine son, although one indeed makes the exaggerated claim, ‘This is ultimate truth,’
                        that is not the same as saying, ‘Ultimate truth is like this.’ Divine son, ultimately, reality is unborn;
                        thus, no conventions apply to it. That to which, on the ultimate level, no conventions apply, divine son,
                        is ultimate truth. Thus, that is not like saying, ‘Ultimate truth is like this.’ <ref cRef="F.247.b"/>
                        Divine son, the Thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha also says that ultimately all phenomena and all terms
                        are false and deceptive phenomena.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-33"/>
                    <p tid="44"> The god said, “How is it then, Mañjuśrī, that the Dharma taught by the Thus-gone One is not
                        false?” </p>
                    <p tid="45"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, on the ultimate level, the Thus-gone One does not speak falsely. Nor
                        does he speak truly. And why is that? Ultimately, divine son, the Thus-gone One has not arisen. And so,
                        ultimately he speaks neither falsely nor truly. Divine son, what do you think? Are explanations given by
                        magical creations of the Thus-gone One true or false?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-34"/>
                    <p tid="46">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, explanations given by magical creations of the Thus-gone One are not
                        true, nor are they false. Why is that? Mañjuśrī, ultimately there is nothing truly established in that
                        which is emanated by the Thus-gone One.”</p>
                    <p tid="47"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, so it is. The Thus-gone One knows that all phenomena are
                        unestablished in the ultimate sense. Whatever is unestablished in the ultimate sense should not be called
                        true nor should it be called false in the context of the ultimate. Why is that? Because ultimately all
                        phenomena are unborn.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-35"/>
                    <p tid="48">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how does the Thus-gone One teach the ultimate truth?”</p>
                    <p tid="49"> Mañjuśrī said, “The ultimate truth, divine son, cannot be taught. And why? Because the topic, the
                        teacher, the method of teaching, the student, and the reason for teaching are all ultimately utterly
                        unborn. Phenomena that are utterly unborn cannot themselves express utterly unborn phenomena.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-36"/>
                    <p tid="50">When Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta had given this teaching on the ultimate truth without teaching, the
                        minds of five hundred monks were freed from defilements without further clinging. <ref cRef="F.248.a"/>
                        Countless bodhisattva great beings developed, without developing it, the acceptance that phenomena are
                        unborn. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-37"/>
                    <p tid="51">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, it is difficult to feel conviction in the ultimate truth.” </p>
                    <p tid="52"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, it is difficult for anyone who relies on reference points to feel
                        conviction in the ultimate truth.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-38"/>
                    <p tid="53">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, it is difficult to understand the ultimate truth.”</p>
                    <p tid="54"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, it is difficult for those who do not exert themselves to understand
                        the ultimate truth.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-39"/>
                    <p tid="55">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how do monks exert themselves?”</p>
                    <p tid="56"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately, when they are without exertion that aims to understand,
                        relinquish, cultivate, or actualize, that is how monks exert themselves without exerting themselves. And
                        why? Because one might think, ‘Ultimately, this is to be understood, this is to be relinquished, this is
                        to be cultivated, and this is to be actualized.’ However, such thinking involves conceptual marks and
                        elaborations. It involves reference points and disturbing emotions. It involves tumult and fear. It
                        involves illness and suffering. It involves pain and poison. Thus, engagement of that type is not
                        authentic.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-40"/>
                    <p tid="57">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is authentic engagement?”</p>
                    <p tid="58"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the
                        utterly unborn on the ultimate level is also the same as the five acts with immediate consequence on the
                        ultimate level.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-41"/>
                    <p tid="59">“Whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn on the ultimate
                        level is also ultimately the same as views. <ref cRef="F.248.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="60">“Whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn on the ultimate
                        level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of ordinary beings. </p>
                    <p tid="61">“Whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn on the ultimate
                        level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of those who are training. </p>
                    <p tid="62">“Whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn on the ultimate
                        level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of those who are no longer training. </p>
                    <p tid="63">“Whatever is the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn on the ultimate
                        level is also ultimately the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-42"/>
                    <p tid="64">“Whatever is the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha on the ultimate level is
                        also ultimately the same as suchness, the sphere of reality, and the utterly unborn. </p>
                    <p tid="65">“Whatever is the same as the dharmas of the completely perfect Buddha on the ultimate level is
                        also ultimately the same as nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <p tid="66">“Whatever is the same as nirvāṇa on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as saṃsāra. </p>
                    <p tid="67">“Whatever is the same as saṃsāra on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as affliction. </p>
                    <p tid="68">“Whatever is the same as affliction on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as
                        purification. </p>
                    <p tid="69">“Whatever is the same as purification on the ultimate level is also ultimately the same as all
                        phenomena. </p>
                    <p tid="70">“A monk who genuinely engages in the equality of all phenomena on the ultimate level in this way,
                        divine son, is called one with <distinct>authentic engagement</distinct> on the ultimate level. However,
                        it is not like the way it is expressed.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-43"/>
                    <p tid="71">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is the sameness by which everything up to purification is said to be
                        ultimately the same, and also to be ultimately the same as all phenomena?” </p>
                    <p tid="72"> Mañjuśrī said, “Ultimately, all phenomena are the same in that they are unarisen. <ref cRef="F.249.a"/> Ultimately, all phenomena are the same in that they are unborn. Ultimately, all
                        phenomena are the same in that they are unreal. Therefore, divine son, ultimately all phenomena are the
                        same. And why is that? Since ultimately, divine son, all phenomena are unarisen, they cannot be
                        distinguished. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-44"/>
                    <p tid="73">“Divine son, it is like this analogy. The space within a clay vessel and the space within a
                        precious vessel are both the element of space; ultimately, not the slightest distinction can be made
                        between them. Divine son, in the very same way, disturbing emotions are themselves unarisen on the
                        ultimate level. Purification itself is also unarisen on the ultimate level. Ultimately, saṃsāra itself is
                        also unarisen. Ultimately, all phenomena up through nirvāṇa itself are unarisen. Ultimately, not even a
                        slight distinction can be made with respect to these. And why? Because ultimately all phenomena are
                        unarisen.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-45"/>
                    <p tid="74">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how should bodhisattva great beings exert themselves with respect to the
                        truths of the noble ones?”</p>
                    <p tid="75"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, if bodhisattva great beings did not apply themselves to the truths of
                        the noble ones, how could they teach, without teaching, the Dharma to the hearers? Yet, divine son,
                        although indeed that is the case, the bodhisattva great beings’ meditation on the truths involves
                        consideration, while the hearers’ meditation on the truths does not involve consideration. Why is that?
                        Divine son, on the relative level the bodhisattva great beings consider all sentient beings. Although they
                        do meditate on the truths without meditating, they do not actualize the limit of reality by focusing on
                        lack of substance. On the relative level, in order to acquire skill in means, the bodhisattva great beings
                            <ref cRef="F.249.b"/> meditate on the truths without meditating. On the relative level they do not
                        discard the truths of saṃsāra, nor of nirvāṇa. On the relative level, in order to individually
                        discriminate the wisdoms of the buddhas, the bodhisattva great beings meditate on the truths without
                        meditating. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-46"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Divine son, it is as in the following analogy. A person who had been caught by many
                            strangers<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-238">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dron pa</foreign>.</note> flees. He escapes from among those many strangers and enters a jungle.
                        But he becomes frightened, panics, and leaves the jungle, never to return. Divine son, in the same way the
                        hearers are frightened of saṃsāra and flee in panic. They do not return to this world but meditate
                        one-pointedly on the truths in solitude. Thus, since they lack the intelligence of various methods, they
                        do not consider all sentient beings, and so forth up to not considering the wisdom of omniscience. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-47"/>
                    <p tid="77"> “Divine son, it is like the following analogy. A leader acquires many servants and all necessary
                        provisions. Thinking that he should set out to gather many goods, he rounds up many people and, without
                        fear or panic, he leaves the wild forest. Similarly, divine son, the bodhisattva great beings resemble
                        that great leader as they engage in worldly conduct on the relative level. Thereby, they provide for all
                        sentient beings and engage with great compassion, which can be likened to the many servants. They acquire
                        all the roots of virtue, which are the provisions. They possess the great profit that is comprised of the
                        six perfections, the means of attracting disciples, and unsurpassed merit and wisdom. They act for the
                        welfare of all realms of sentient beings and proceed from buddha realm to buddha realm. Thus, they provide
                        for sentient beings and meditate on the truths through being skilled in means. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-48"/>
                    <p tid="78"> “Divine son, consider this analogy. If one infuses a hempen cloth with campaka and vārṣika
                        flowers, their scent fades quickly. <ref cRef="F.250.a"/> Divine son, similarly, the hearers’ meditation
                        on the truths is observed for just a short period of time. Passing quickly into nirvāṇa, they do not bring
                        forth the fragrance of the buddhas’ discipline, hearing, absorption, knowledge, and wisdom. Furthermore,
                        they are unable to relinquish the disturbing emotions that are conjoined with the habitual tendencies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-49"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Divine son, now consider another analogy. If one were to infuse a cloth of precious Benares silk
                        for hundreds of thousands of great aeons with the scent of perfume and flowers from the human and divine
                        realms, its divine fragrance would be experienced in perpetuity, and that pure aroma would overwhelm both
                        gods and men. Divine son, similarly, the bodhisattva great beings without meditating meditate on the
                        truths for incalculably many hundreds of thousands of eons. They do not relinquish doing so until they
                        have attained omniscient wisdom endowed with the supreme of all aspects and pass into complete nirvāṇa.
                        And so, without reference points, they become exceedingly fragrant with the scent of omniscient wisdom
                        endowed with the supreme of all aspects. In terms of worldly conventions, they abandon all their habitual
                        tendencies toward the disturbing emotions and attract the worlds of gods, men, and demigods.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-50"/>
                    <p tid="80">Then the god Lord of Peace and Calm asked Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, “Mañjuśrī, how is the spiritual
                        community of hearers that belong to the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu?” </p>
                    <p tid="81"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Ultimately, they are not devoted followers, but they are also not devotedly
                        turning to someone else. Ultimately, they are not followers of the family, but neither do they ultimately
                        abandon the family of the Thus-gone One. Ultimately, they are not following the Dharma; indeed, ultimately
                        they do not observe any Dharma at all. Ultimately, they do not possess the eight mistaken dharmas, but
                        neither are they relatively free from them. <ref cRef="F.250.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-51"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Ultimately they are not stream-enterers, yet in terms of the conventional truth of the world,
                        they are beyond all the lower realms. Ultimately they are not once-returners, yet relatively they do
                        return in order to ripen beings. Ultimately they are not non-returners, yet relatively from all phenomena
                        there is no return. Ultimately they are not worthy ones, yet according to worldly conventions they are
                        supremely worthy of veneration by the world along with its gods. Ultimately they are not hearers, yet,
                        without conceptually apprehending them, they do listen to all the blessed buddhas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-52"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Ultimately they are not without attachment, yet relatively they are unharmed by the torments of
                        attachment. Ultimately they are not without anger, yet relatively they are unharmed by the torments of
                        anger. Ultimately they are not without delusion, yet relatively all phenomena are free from darkness.
                        Ultimately they are not without disturbing emotions, yet relatively they endeavor to tame the disturbing
                        emotions of all beings. Ultimately they have abided definitively in non-origination from the very
                        beginning, yet relatively they consciously take up existence. Relatively they embrace cyclic existence,
                        yet ultimately there is no grasping to or abandoning of any phenomenon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-53"/>
                    <p tid="84"> “Ultimately, without intense mindfulness regarding all phenomena, they see without seeing.
                        Relatively, however, they train in the foundations of mindfulness. Ultimately, without knowing, they know
                        that all phenomena are unborn and unceasing. In terms of worldly experience, however, they train in the
                        thorough relinquishments. Ultimately, they have neither body nor mind yet, in the relative truth of the
                        world, they have accomplished the bases of miraculous power. <ref cRef="F.251.a"/> Ultimately they are
                        without any faculties, yet relatively they have accomplished all the faculties. Ultimately, without
                        seeing, they see that all phenomena are unreal. However, in order to eradicate the conceit and conceptual
                        apprehension of everyone who is conceited and engages in conceptual apprehension, they train, without
                        training, in the <term>powers</term>. Ultimately, in order to make it understood that all phenomena are
                        unreal, they train, without training, in the branches of awakening. Although ultimately utterly unreal,
                        relatively they train in the path by means of not training. Ultimately, they accomplish tranquillity
                        within the limit of reality. Ultimately, by not training, they see insight to be utterly unarisen.
                        Ultimately, their knowledge is born through not apprehending ignorance as something to be exhausted.
                        Ultimately, neither exhaustion nor arising is observed. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-54"/>
                    <p tid="85">“Although they see all beings and all buddha realms with their physical eye, ultimately they see
                        nothing whatsoever. Although they see all the deaths, transmigrations, and rebirths of all beings so
                        clearly with their divine eye, ultimately they see nothing whatsoever. Although they know all the
                        experiences and movements of the minds of all beings with their eye of wisdom, ultimately they know
                        nothing whatsoever. Although they see all dharmas with their dharma eye, ultimately they see nothing
                        whatsoever. Although they perform all the acts of a buddha with their buddha eye, ultimately they perform
                        nothing whatsoever. Although with their divine ear they hear the teachings of all the blessed buddhas,
                        ultimately they hear nothing whatsoever. Although with their single mind they view the minds of all
                        beings, ultimately they view nothing whatsoever. Although with their wisdom of recollection they surely
                        recollect the very dawn of time, ultimately they recollect nothing whatsoever. Although they visit the
                        inconceivable buddha realms by means of their miraculous powers, ultimately there is no coming or going.
                        Although their defilements are exhausted, <ref cRef="F.251.b"/> ultimately there is nothing to be
                        exhausted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-55"/>
                    <p tid="86">“Although they appear as beings, ultimately their bodies are devoid of true existence. Although
                        they speak, ultimately their speech is not pronounced in the form of syllables. Although they think,
                        ultimately thought is not something that can be expressed as mind or mental phenomena. Ultimately they do
                        not appear as form, but relatively they are adorned with the thirty-two marks and ornamented with the
                        excellent signs of great beings. They are adorned with the accumulations of merit and wisdom. Their
                        splendor is dazzling. Their speech resounds. They have been anointed with the unguent of discipline. Words
                        spoken with ill intent cause them no disturbing emotions. They sport in clairvoyant powers. Their learning
                        sets them free.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-239">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par shigs</foreign>.</note> With their eloquence they make declarations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-56"/>
                    <p tid="87"> “Relatively, they produce emanations by means of wisdom; with the light of wisdom they dispel all
                        darkness; with knowledge they illuminate; their teaching knows no limit, and is assimilated as
                        realization. Relatively, for all beings they are the refuge, and because of their awakening they
                        constantly consider beings—who are continuously beheld by the blessed buddhas, but who are not considered
                        by the hearers, solitary buddhas, and the extremists with reference points— so that, relatively, their
                        teaching knows no exhaustion, their mindfulness is like the ocean, their absorption is comparable to the
                        central mountain, and their patience is like the earth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-57"/>
                    <p tid="88">“Relatively, they are courageous when it comes to clearing away all thoughts; they shine like the
                        sun to dispel the deep darkness of ignorance; they shine like the moon in order to illuminate the world.
                        Relatively, they are like a ruler in order to attract others. Relatively, they are like Brahmā in order to
                        master the mind. Relatively, they are incomparable in order to master space. Relatively they have
                        followed, but ultimately there is no one who goes, comes, or remains. Why is that? Because ultimately all
                        phenomena are utterly unarisen. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-58"/>
                    <p tid="89">“Divine son, such is the spiritual community of hearers belonging to the Blessed, thus-gone, <ref cRef="F.252.a"/> worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu. Moreover, the dharma that they possess is even more
                        inconceivable than that.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-59"/>
                    <p tid="90"> When Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta delivered this teaching in a manner beyond reference points, five
                        hundred monks, five hundred laypeople, and five thousand gods who held reference points all made this
                        supplication: “Blessed One, may we also become hearers belonging to the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect Buddha Ratnaketu.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-60"/>
                    <p tid="91"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Well, my friends, in that buddha realm no-one with reference points is born!
                        My friends, only bodhisattva great beings who are free from reference points are born there without being
                        born. My friends, if you aspire to that realm, you must strive in the perfection of knowledge in a manner
                        free from reference points. My friends, when you strive in the perfection of knowledge in a manner that is
                        free from reference points, then, my friends, it will not be difficult to discover omniscient wisdom that
                        is endowed with the supreme of all aspects. So what need is there to mention that you will also be born in
                        the pure buddha realms!”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-61"/>
                    <p tid="92">The god Lord of Peace and Calm then asked Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, “Mañjuśrī, what is the vinaya of
                        the hearers like? And how is the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings?”</p>
                    <p tid="93"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine son, the vinaya that is well known in the three worlds is the vinaya of
                        the hearers. However, on the relative level, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings gathers all
                        accumulations of roots of virtue, comforts all beings, and tames them by taking birth in the three realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-62"/>
                    <p tid="94">“The vinaya of the hearers opposes all disturbing emotions. <ref cRef="F.252.b"/> However,
                        relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings goes further in order to eliminate the disturbing
                        emotions of all beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-63"/>
                    <p tid="95"> “The vinaya of the hearers is aware of just one place. However, relatively, the vinaya of the
                        bodhisattva great beings is aware of all the limitless and boundless worlds in the ten directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-64"/>
                    <p tid="96">“The vinaya of the hearers maintains equanimity with regard to all demons. However, relatively,
                        the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings disturbs all classes of demons in all the limitless and
                        boundless worlds in the ten directions, and conquers all hostile forces. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-65"/>
                    <p tid="97">“The vinaya of the hearers clarifies one’s own mind stream. However, relatively, the vinaya of the
                        bodhisattva great beings clarifies the mind streams of all beings, causes the wisdom of omniscience to
                        manifest, and causes the vision of stainless wisdom with regard to all phenomena to manifest. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-66"/>
                    <p tid="98">“The vinaya of the hearers is contemplated by individual minds. However, relatively, the vinaya of
                        the bodhisattva great beings is the intent of all the buddhas in the past, the present, and the future. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-67"/>
                    <p tid="99">“The vinaya of the hearers is like a stone that cannot be repaired when broken. However,
                        relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is like gold and silver, which can be mended when
                        broken. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-68"/>
                    <p tid="100">“The vinaya of the hearers does not contain all the teachings of the Buddha, and it also lacks
                        skillful means. However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings has great skillful means
                        and comprises all the teachings of the Buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-69"/>
                    <p tid="101">“The vinaya of the hearers does not embody the ten strengths, the various types of fearlessness,
                        the unique qualities, or omniscient wisdom. However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great
                        beings contains the ten powers, the various types of fearlessness, the unique qualities, and omniscient
                        wisdom. <ref cRef="F.253.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-70"/>
                    <p tid="102"> “The vinaya of the hearers is like escaping from being burned by a fire. However, relatively,
                        the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is to be delighted by the joy of Dharma, just as one would
                        enjoy a park or a palace. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-71"/>
                    <p tid="103">“The vinaya of the hearers does not interrupt the stream of habitual patterns. However,
                        relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings overcomes all habitual patterns. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-72"/>
                    <p tid="104">“Divine son, in short, the vinaya of the hearers is derived from a Dharma that is limited and
                        confined. However, relatively, the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings follows a Dharma that is
                        limitless and beyond measure. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-73"/>
                    <p tid="105">“The vinaya of the hearers brings the attainment of limited discipline, learning, absorption,
                        knowledge, liberation, and vision of the wisdom of liberation. However, relatively, the vinaya of the
                        bodhisattva great beings knows no bounds, possesses limitless qualities, and makes one attain limitless
                        discipline, learning, absorption, knowledge, liberation, and vision of the wisdom of liberation.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-74"/>
                    <p tid="106">At this point, the Blessed One expressed his approval of Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta: “Well said,
                        Mañjuśrī! You have explained the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings well on the relative level. Well
                        done, well done. Now, Mañjuśrī, in order to illustrate the meaning of this, I will give you some examples.
                        Mañjuśrī, imagine two men: one of them praises the hoofprints of an ox, while the other man praises the
                        ocean. Mañjuśrī, what do you think? How extensively would the first man be able to praise the hoofprints
                        of an ox?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-75"/>
                    <p tid="107"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Blessed One, since all ox hoofprints are so small, what is even the use of
                        praising them?”</p>
                    <p tid="108">The Blessed One said, “Just as the ox hoofprints <ref cRef="F.253.b"/> are small, so you should
                        view the vinaya of the hearers. Now, Mañjuśrī, what do you think? Would the other man be able to express a
                        fitting praise of the ocean?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-76"/>
                    <p tid="109"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Blessed One, the praises of the ocean could be incredibly numerous,
                        limitless, and inconceivable.”</p>
                    <p tid="110">The Blessed One said, “Mañjuśrī, just as the praises of the ocean are boundless, so you should
                        view the vinaya of the bodhisattvas on the relative level.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-77"/>
                    <p tid="111">As he delivered this teaching without teaching, 12,000 gods, without ultimately forming anything,
                        formed the wish for unexcelled and completely perfect awakening. They all declared, “Blessed One, without
                        training, we will practice the trainings of the bodhisattvas.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-78"/>
                    <p tid="112">The god Lord of Peace and Calm asked Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta, “Mañjuśrī, do you train in the vinaya
                        of the hearers or in the vinaya of the bodhisattvas?”</p>
                    <p tid="113"> Mañjuśrī answered, “Divine son, what do you think? Is there any water that cannot be contained
                        in the ocean?”</p>
                    <p tid="114">The god replied, “No, Mañjuśrī, there is no water anywhere that cannot be contained in the
                        ocean.”</p>
                    <p tid="115"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, in the same way the vinaya of the bodhisattva great beings is like
                        the ocean.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-79"/>
                    <p tid="116">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, that word <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinaya</foreign>, what
                        does that mean?”</p>
                    <p tid="117"> Mañjuśrī answered, “Divine son, on the relative level vinaya refers to taming the disturbing
                        emotions. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya</foreign> also means understanding disturbing
                        emotions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-80"/>
                    <p tid="118">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how does one tame the disturbing emotions? How does one understand
                        disturbing emotions?” <ref cRef="F.254.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="119"> Mañjuśrī said, “Ultimately, all phenomena are unborn, unarisen, and unreal. Yet this absence is
                        misunderstood on the relative level. Misunderstanding this absence produces concepts and thoughts. Out of
                        concept and thought appears mistaken conceptual activity. Mistaken conceptual activity then gives rise to
                        the superimposition of a self. From the superimposition of a self comes the manifestation of views. Based
                        on the manifestation of views, disturbing emotions appear. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-81"/>
                    <p tid="120"> “Divine son, whoever knows, without knowing, that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn,
                        utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal, is unmistaken in terms of the ultimate. Whoever is unmistaken in
                        terms of the ultimate does not form concepts or thoughts. Whoever does not form concepts or thoughts is
                        applying himself correctly. Whoever applies himself correctly does not ultimately form superimpositions of
                        a self. When superimpositions of a self do not ultimately arise, manifest views also do not arise, and
                        ultimately even the views related to passing beyond suffering do not arise. In that way one comes to
                        experience the unborn, and pacifies disturbing emotions in a manner free from views. Divine son, this is
                        what is meant by taming disturbing emotions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-82"/>
                    <p tid="121">“Divine son, disturbing emotions are ultimately utterly empty, utterly signless and utterly
                        wishless due to the insight and wisdom to which no disturbing emotions ever appear. When one has the
                        insight that ultimately they are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal, then, divine son,
                        one knows disturbing emotions in a manner free from knowing. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-83"/>
                    <p tid="122">“Divine son, consider this analogy. If you chant an incantation against a viper’s venom, it is
                        possible to neutralize the snake’s poison. Divine son, in the same way, whoever understands the types of
                        disturbing emotions <ref cRef="F.254.b"/> will neutralize his disturbing emotions in a manner that is
                        beyond reference points.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-84"/>
                    <p tid="123">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what are the types of disturbing emotions?”</p>
                    <p tid="124"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and
                        utterly unreal. Any conceptualization of that state is a form of disturbing emotion. Ultimately, there are
                        no conceptualizations, so therefore there are also no disturbing emotions whatsoever. Divine son, because
                        there are no disturbing emotions, there is no all-ground.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-240">The Tibetan does not include the word “no” in connection with the
                            disturbing emotions. Given the context, however, this appears to be a scribal error. </note> Because
                        there is no all-ground, there is ultimately no abiding. Because there is no abiding, there is ultimately
                        no scorching. Because there is ultimately no scorching, there is said to be peace. On the ultimate level,
                        things are not as they are expressed in words. Still, divine son, relatively this is how disturbing
                        emotions are tamed.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-85"/>
                    <p tid="125">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how are disturbing emotions tamed? Are they something? Or nothing?”</p>
                    <p tid="126"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, this is how it is. Imagine a man who has a nightmare in which he is
                        bitten by a venomous viper. Although he is suffering, he is treated with an antidote and recovers. As the
                        poison is neutralized, his pain disappears. Divine son, what do you think? Was this man actually bitten or
                        not?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-86"/>
                    <p tid="127">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, ultimately it did not truly happen.”</p>
                    <p tid="128"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, how was the poison neutralized?”</p>
                    <p tid="129">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, just as the bite was not truly real, the neutralization of the poison
                        was also not truly real.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-87"/>
                    <p tid="130"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, in the same way the noble ones view, without viewing, all disturbing
                        emotions on the ultimate level. Divine son, you ask how disturbing emotions are tamed. Well, divine son,
                        just as the ego ultimately is egoless, so, divine son, disturbing emotions are not ultimately disturbing
                        emotions. Divine son, ultimately this self is suchness. Therefore, divine son, disturbing emotions also
                        ultimately become suchness. Divine son, in this way, the self is not ultimately the self. <ref cRef="F.255.a"/> Therefore, divine son, disturbing emotions are also not ultimately disturbing
                        emotions. Divine son, whoever focuses on taming disturbing emotions on the ultimate level is not
                        ultimately focusing on anything. Why? Divine son, because on the ultimate level nothing manifests, and
                        therefore all phenomena are pacified. Divine son, on the ultimate level, there is no grasping, and
                        therefore all phenomena are fully pacified. Divine son, on the ultimate level, all phenomena are free from
                        superimposition, and therefore all phenomena are completely pacified. Divine son, on the ultimate level,
                        all phenomena are utterly unborn, and therefore they are also beyond ceasing. Divine son, the ultimate
                        level is utterly unreal and therefore all phenomena are utterly unborn.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-88"/>
                    <p tid="131">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is the gateway to all dharmas?”</p>
                    <p tid="132"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, the relative truth, which employs all forms of statements, speech,
                        cognition, objects of cognition, activities, conventions, and acts, is a gateway to all dharmas. The
                        ultimate truth, which is so because it is the opposite of all forms of speech, statements, cognition,
                        objects of cognition, activities, conventions, and acts, is a gateway to all dharmas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-89"/>
                    <p tid="133">“Moreover, divine son, on the relative level, the incorrect conceptual workings of the mind are a
                        gateway to saṃsāra. On the relative level, the correct conceptual workings of the mind are a gateway to
                        nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <p tid="134">“On the relative level, doubt is a gateway to obscuration. On the relative level, liberation is a
                        gateway to the absence of obscuration. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-90"/>
                    <p tid="135">“On the relative level, conceptuality is a gateway to disturbing emotions. On the relative level,
                        non-conceptuality is a gateway to the absence of disturbing emotions. </p>
                    <p tid="136">“On the relative level, distraction is a gateway to thought. On the relative level, tranquility
                        is a gateway to peace. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-91"/>
                    <p tid="137">“On the relative level, holding views is a gateway to pride. On the relative level, emptiness is
                        a gateway to the absence of pride. </p>
                    <p tid="138">“On the relative level, relying on evil company is a gateway to all roots of non-virtue. On the
                        relative level, relying on a virtuous spiritual friend is the gateway to all roots of virtue. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-92"/>
                    <p tid="139">“On the relative level, wrong view is a gateway to all suffering. <ref cRef="F.255.b"/> On the
                        relative level, correct view is a gateway to all happiness. </p>
                    <p tid="140">“On the relative level, miserliness is a gateway to poverty. On the relative level, generosity is
                        a gateway to great wealth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-93"/>
                    <p tid="141">“On the relative level, a bad character is a gateway to all lower realms. On the relative level,
                        discipline is a gateway to all human and divine births. </p>
                    <p tid="142">“On the relative level, ill will is a gateway to an ugly appearance. On the relative level,
                        patience is a gateway to a beautiful appearance. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-94"/>
                    <p tid="143">“On the relative level, laziness is a gateway to a lack of realization. On the relative level,
                        diligence is a gateway to realization. </p>
                    <p tid="144">“On the relative level, thought is a gateway to agitation. On the relative level, concentration
                        is a gateway to pliability of mind. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-95"/>
                    <p tid="145">“On the relative level, faulty knowledge is a gateway to a lack of understanding. On the relative
                        level, knowledge is a gateway to the thirty-seven factors of awakening. </p>
                    <p tid="146">“On the relative level, love is a gateway to not becoming angry. On the relative level, great
                        compassion is a gateway to an altruistic mind. On the relative level, an altruistic mind is a gateway to
                        the absence of deceit. On the relative level, joy is a gateway to conviction in the Dharma. On the
                        relative level, equanimity is a gateway to being free from all faults. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-96"/>
                    <p tid="147">“On the relative level, the applications of mindfulness are a gateway to not letting any roots of
                        virtue diminish. On the relative level, the thorough relinquishments are a gateway to genuine
                        perseverance. On the relative level, the bases of miraculous power are a gateway to pliancy of body and
                        mind. On the relative level, the faculties are a gateway to attaining faith. On the relative level, the
                            <term>powers</term> are a gateway to conquering all disturbing emotions. On the relative level, the
                        branches of awakening are a gateway to realizing omniscience. On the relative level, the eightfold path of
                        the noble ones is a gateway to transcending all unwholesome paths. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-97"/>
                    <p tid="148"> “Moreover, divine son, on the relative level, the mind set on awakening is a gateway to all
                        buddha qualities. On the relative level, upholding the sacred Dharma is a gateway to becoming a lord of
                        all dharmas. On the relative level, ripening beings is a gateway to upholding the sacred Dharma. On the
                        relative level, method is a gateway to becoming learned regarding the correct and the incorrect. <ref cRef="F.256.a"/> On the relative level, the perfection of knowledge is a gateway to nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <p tid="149">“On the ultimate level, the unarisen is a gateway to all dharmas.” <ref cRef="B2" type="bampo"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-98"/>
                    <p tid="150">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is the gateway to the utterly unborn?”</p>
                    <p tid="151"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, on the ultimate level, the utterly unarisen is a gateway in every
                        way.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-99"/>
                    <p tid="152">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what is the nature of the utterly unarisen?”</p>
                    <p tid="153"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, on the ultimate level, the utterly unreal is the nature of the
                        utterly unarisen.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-100"/>
                    <p tid="154">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, does the utterly unarisen have any divisions?” </p>
                    <p tid="155"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, what do you think? Does the sky have any divisions?”</p>
                    <p tid="156">The god answered, “No, Mañjuśrī, it does not.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-101"/>
                    <p tid="157"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, in the same way, just as the sky does not have any divisions, so,
                        divine son, does the utterly unborn also not have any divisions.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-102"/>
                    <p tid="158">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, do you comprehend the utterly unarisen on the ultimate level?”</p>
                    <p tid="159"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, the utterly unarisen does not comprehend the utterly unarisen. And
                        why? Because, divine son, all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-103"/>
                    <p tid="160">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, are you this eloquent because you know and understand any phenomenon
                        whatsoever?”</p>
                    <p tid="161"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, what do you think? Does an echo make a sound because it knows
                        phenomena?”</p>
                    <p tid="162">The god replied, “Mañjuśrī, of course an echo does not know any phenomena. Instead, on the
                        relative level, the sound appears from circumstances.”</p>
                    <p tid="163"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, in the same way, based on the circumstance of observing all beings,
                        on the relative level a bodhisattva <ref cRef="F.256.b"/> great being speaks without speaking.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-104"/>
                    <p tid="164">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, on what basis do you teach?”</p>
                    <p tid="165"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, on what type of emanation does the Thus-gone One base himself as he
                        teaches?”</p>
                    <p tid="166">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, the Thus-gone One does not ultimately base himself on any emanation
                        whatsoever.”</p>
                    <p tid="167"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, in the same way, on the ultimate level, without basing myself on any
                        phenomena, I teach without teaching.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-105"/>
                    <p tid="168">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, if, on the ultimate level, without basing yourself on any phenomena, you
                        teach without teaching, on what basis do you awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood?”</p>
                    <p tid="169"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, I base myself on the acts with immediate consequence and, without
                        awakening to completely perfect buddhahood, I awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-106"/>
                    <p tid="170">The god said, “How do you base yourself on the acts with immediate consequence?”</p>
                    <p tid="171"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately the acts with immediate consequence do not truly exist
                        and do not have any substance. It is on them that I base myself without basing myself.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-107"/>
                    <p tid="172">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, the Thus-gone One has explained that beings are born in hell because of
                        committing the acts with immediate consequence.”</p>
                    <p tid="173"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, the Thus-gone One has explained that beings are born in hell because
                        of committing the acts with immediate consequence. In the same way, divine son, the Thus-gone One teaches,
                        without teaching, how to quickly awaken to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood when basing
                        oneself on the acts with immediate consequence, without basing oneself on the acts with immediate
                        consequence.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-108"/>
                    <p tid="174">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what are the acts with immediate consequence?” </p>
                    <p tid="175"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, the acts with immediate consequence are those by which the
                        bodhisattva great beings quickly, without awakening to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood,
                        perfectly awaken. Such are the acts with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings. <ref cRef="F.257.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-109"/>
                    <p tid="176"> “Divine son, you may wonder what the five acts with immediate consequence are. Well, divine son,
                        the first act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings is as follows. When a bodhisattva
                        great being with pure motivation, without developing, has developed the mind set on unexcelled and
                        completely perfect buddhahood, he does not develop the mind-set that aims for the levels of the hearers,
                        solitary buddhas, anyone with reference points, or the extremists. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-110"/>
                    <p tid="177"> “Moreover, divine son, the second act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings
                        is as follows. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without producing, has produced the mind set on
                        giving up all possessions, he will not entertain any feelings of miserliness until he reaches the essence
                        of enlightenment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-111"/>
                    <p tid="178">“Moreover, divine son, the third act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings
                        is as follows. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without producing, has produced the mind-set
                        that thinks, ‘I will protect all beings in any possible way,’ he will not yield from that. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-112"/>
                    <p tid="179">“Moreover, divine son, the fourth act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings
                        is as follows. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without attaining forbearance, has attained the
                        forbearance that understands that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and
                        utterly unreal, he will not engender any clinging to substance, essence, or actuality. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-113"/>
                    <p tid="180">“Moreover, divine son, the fifth act with immediate consequence of the bodhisattva great beings
                        is as follows. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being, without engendering, has engendered the
                        mind-set that thinks, ‘I will fully understand all phenomena by means of momentary knowledge,’ he will not
                        rest under any circumstances until he has obtained, without obtaining, the wisdom of omniscience that is
                        endowed with all supreme features. </p>
                    <p tid="181">“By abiding in this way, without abiding, the bodhisattva great being quickly and perfectly
                        awakens, without ultimately awakening, to unexcelled and completely perfect buddhahood.” <ref cRef="F.257.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-114"/>
                    <p tid="182">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, those acts of immediate consequence that cause ordinary childish beings
                        to be born in hell are the very acts that cause a bodhisattva great being to awaken to unexcelled and
                        completely perfect buddhahood without perfectly awakening. Is that correct?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-115"/>
                    <p tid="183"> Mañjuśrī said, “Yes, divine son, it is. And why? Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter
                        emptiness. Divine son, understanding this utter emptiness is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not
                        the way that it is expressed through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-116"/>
                    <p tid="184">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter signlessness. Divine son, understanding this
                        utter signlessness is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through
                        words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-117"/>
                    <p tid="185">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utter wishlessness. Divine son, understanding this
                        utter wishlessness is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through
                        words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-118"/>
                    <p tid="186"> “Divine son, ultimately all phenomena do not exist as something that can be apprehended
                        whatsoever. Divine son, understanding this state of being beyond something to apprehend whatsoever is
                        awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-119"/>
                    <p tid="187">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly beyond formation. Divine son, understanding
                        this state where phenomena are utterly beyond formation is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not
                        the way that it is expressed through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-120"/>
                    <p tid="188">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unconditioned. Divine son, understanding this
                        utterly unconditioned state is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed
                        through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-121"/>
                    <p tid="189">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unseen. Divine son, understanding this state of
                        being utterly unseen is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through
                        words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-122"/>
                    <p tid="190">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn. <ref cRef="F.258.a"/> Divine son,
                        understanding this utterly unborn state is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is
                        expressed through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-123"/>
                    <p tid="191">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unarisen. Divine son, understanding this
                        utterly unarisen state is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed
                        through words. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-124"/>
                    <p tid="192">“Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are utterly unreal. Divine son, understanding this state of
                        being utterly unreal is awakening. Yet, ultimately, awakening is not the way that it is expressed through
                        words.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-125"/>
                    <p tid="193"> The god then asked, “Mañjuśrī, who will have faith in this Dharma teaching?”</p>
                    <p tid="194"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine son, since ultimately even the Thus-gone One does not have faith,
                        forget about the hearers, solitary buddhas, and all the extremists who rely on reference points.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-126"/>
                    <p tid="195">The god asked him, “Who will gain conviction in it?”</p>
                    <p tid="196"> Mañjuśrī said, “Those who ultimately are not attached to any phenomenon will gain
                        conviction.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-127"/>
                    <p tid="197">The god asked him, “Who will apply it earnestly?”</p>
                    <p tid="198"> Mañjuśrī said, “Those who ultimately do not earnestly apply themselves to any phenomenon.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-128"/>
                    <p tid="199">The god asked him, “Who will become realized?”</p>
                    <p tid="200"> Mañjuśrī said, “Those who ultimately do not realize any phenomenon.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-129"/>
                    <p tid="201">The god asked him, “Mañjuśrī, who are those who ultimately do not realize any phenomenon?”</p>
                    <p tid="202"> Mañjuśrī answered, “Divine son, those who, on the relative level, realize the omniscient wisdom
                        that is endowed with the supreme of all aspects.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-130"/>
                    <p tid="203">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what kind of nature do they have?”</p>
                    <p tid="204"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately they have the utterly unborn nature.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-131"/>
                    <p tid="205">The god asked him, “Mañjuśrī, in whose hands will a sūtra such as this end up?” </p>
                    <p tid="206"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Divine son, relatively, in the hands of those who offer the sacred Dharma to
                        all beings.”<ref cRef="F.258.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-132"/>
                    <p tid="207">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how will they abide?”</p>
                    <p tid="208"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately they will abide in the utterly unborn, the utterly
                        unarisen, and the utterly unreal.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-133"/>
                    <p tid="209">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, in what way will they proceed?”</p>
                    <p tid="210"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately they will proceed within the utterly unborn, the utterly
                        unarisen, and the utterly unreal.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-134"/>
                    <p tid="211">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how will the irreversible bodhisattva great being attain awakening?”</p>
                    <p tid="212"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, whoever is an irreversible bodhisattva great being has no chance and
                        no opportunity not to attain awakening.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-135"/>
                    <p tid="213">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what do the bodhisattva great beings turn back from?” </p>
                    <p tid="214"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, ultimately, bodhisattva great beings turn back from thoughts. They
                        turn back from the levels of all the hearers, solitary buddhas, and the extremists who rely on reference
                        points.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-136"/>
                    <p tid="215">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, what does a bodhisattva great being not turn back from?”</p>
                    <p tid="216"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, bodhisattva great beings do not turn back from all phenomena being
                        the same in being utterly unarisen. If you wonder why, it is because ultimately all phenomena are the same
                        in being utterly unarisen, and the bodhisattva great beings are the same. That is why they do not turn
                        back.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-137"/>
                    <p tid="217">The god asked, “When one speaks of the sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen,
                        Mañjuśrī, what phenomenon is that a designation for?”</p>
                    <p tid="218"> Mañjuśrī said, “The sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen designates that
                        ultimately there is no diversity.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-138"/>
                    <p tid="219">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, how does the sameness of all phenomena in being utterly unarisen
                        manifest as diversity?”</p>
                    <p tid="220"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, <ref cRef="F.259.a"/> whoever conceptualizes the sameness of all
                        phenomena in being utterly unarisen as ultimately having substance, materiality, and essence will
                        ultimately experience diversity. As for ultimately experiencing diversity, it develops into many views
                        involving reference points. Those who hold these many views that involve reference points wander
                        helplessly in all the various forms of existence. Divine son, whoever does not conceptualize the sameness
                        of all phenomena in not occurring as ultimately having substance, materiality, and essence, does
                        ultimately not experience diversity. Since he ultimately does not experience diversity, he ultimately
                        understands the utterly unreal. In this way he comes to understand that all phenomena ultimately are the
                        same in being characterized as utterly unborn.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-139"/>
                    <p tid="221">The god asked, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method that can awaken a bodhisattva great being with
                        disturbing emotions, but not someone <emph>without</emph> disturbing emotions?”</p>
                    <p tid="222"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, there is. Divine son, relatively, all phenomena continuously emerge
                        and disappear. In this way, the awakening of bodhisattva great beings also appears, relatively. And why?
                        Divine son, ultimately, all phenomena are without disturbing emotions, unborn and unceasing. Any
                        phenomenon that is ultimately unborn and unceasing is also ultimately beyond being realized. It will never
                        be realized, nor was it ever realized. And why? Divine son, because ultimately all phenomena are utterly
                        unborn. Therefore, divine son, through such a method a bodhisattva great being with disturbing emotions
                        can awaken, yet someone who is devoid of disturbing emotions cannot.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-140"/>
                    <p tid="223">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is miserly can
                        complete the perfection of generosity, yet those who are generous cannot?”</p>
                    <p tid="224"> Mañjuśrī said, “Yes, divine son, there is a method by which a miserly bodhisattva great being
                            <ref cRef="F.259.b"/> can complete the perfection of generosity, yet those who are generous cannot.
                        And why? Because to never let go of, or cast away, any sentient being, or any of the buddha qualities, on
                        the relative level, is the miserliness of the bodhisattva great beings.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-141"/>
                    <p tid="225">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is ill behaved
                        can complete the perfection of discipline, yet those who are disciplined cannot?”</p>
                    <p tid="226"> Mañjuśrī said, “There is. Divine son, when a bodhisattva great being avoids superficial
                        discipline in order to ripen beings, that is the perfection of discipline of a bodhisattva great being on
                        the relative level.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-142"/>
                    <p tid="227">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method of patience for a bodhisattva great being who has
                        forsaken patience?”</p>
                    <p tid="228"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, there is. Any bodhisattva great being who ultimately has no patience
                        with any phenomena having substance, actuality, or essence is in fact, in an ineffable manner, in
                        possession of the supreme patience. Divine son, in a manner free from reference points, that is the
                        supreme patience of a bodhisattva great being.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-143"/>
                    <p tid="229">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a lazy bodhisattva great being can be
                        diligent?”</p>
                    <p tid="230"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, there is. A lazy bodhisattva great being is unlike those diligent
                        hearers, solitary buddhas, and extremists who employ an easy form of diligence that involves focus.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-144"/>
                    <p tid="231">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who is forgetful
                        can rest in equipoise?”</p>
                    <p tid="232"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, there is. A bodhisattva great being, who, even in his sleep, does
                        not give rise to thoughts of substance, essence, or actuality on the ultimate level, is resting in
                        equipoise in a manner devoid of reference points.” <ref cRef="F.260.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-145"/>
                    <p tid="233">The god said, “Mañjuśrī, is there a method by which a bodhisattva great being who has no
                        knowledge can come to possess great knowledge?”</p>
                    <p tid="234"> Mañjuśrī said, “Divine son, there is. And why? Divine son, ultimately all phenomena are
                        discerned by knowledge. However, when one searches for phenomena, they disappear and cannot be observed.
                        Knowledge is also like that; ultimately it also does not exist and cannot be observed. Therefore,
                        relatively, one speaks of ‘possessing knowledge,’ even though that knowledge is ultimately utterly unborn.
                        Divine son, according to that method, a bodhisattva great being who has no knowledge is called
                            <distinct>one who possesses great knowledge</distinct>, or <distinct>one who possesses especially
                            exalted knowledge</distinct>, or <distinct>one who possesses sacred knowledge</distinct>, or
                            <distinct>one who lays hold of knowledge</distinct>, or <distinct>one who possesses knowledge devoid
                            of a focus.</distinct> Ultimately, things are not as they are described.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-146"/>
                    <p tid="235">The Blessed One now addressed Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta. “Excellent!” he said. “Excellent, excellent!
                        Mañjuśrī, you have spoken well and explained, without explaining, the acts and non-acts of bodhisattva
                        great beings. Mañjuśrī, for a starving person, feeble and thin, it is better to suffer, and thus not to
                        unknowingly eat poisonous food. In the same way, Mañjuśrī, it is better for bodhisattva great beings to
                        engage in nonconceptual miserliness, bad behavior, ill will, laziness, forgetfulness, and lack of
                        knowledge, and thus not engage in the conceptual applications of generosity, discipline, patience,
                        diligence, concentration, and knowledge of the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points.
                        Why? Because the latter give rise to the faults of poisonous reference points, and this must therefore be
                        understood to be a danger on the relative level.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-147"/>
                    <p tid="236">At this point the god Excellent Rule <ref cRef="F.260.b"/> asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One,
                        are bodhisattva great beings not afraid of disturbing emotions?” </p>
                    <p tid="237">The Blessed One replied, “Divine son, relatively, bodhisattva great beings do fear disturbing
                        emotions. But far more, they fear the mind-set of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference
                        points; their fear of the disturbing emotions is not comparable.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-148"/>
                    <p tid="238">The god asked, “Blessed One, why is that?” </p>
                    <p tid="239">The Blessed One answered, “Divine son, that is something you should ask yourself! Why not explain
                        it yourself, as best you can? Divine son, what do you think? If a person wishes to survive, would that
                        person’s greatest fear be having his limbs severed, or having his head cut off?” </p>
                    <p tid="240">The god replied, “Blessed One, someone who loses his limbs could still survive. Thus, if he
                        wanted to acquire merit, he could still take up and follow a meritorious path, which in turn would become
                        a cause for taking birth in the higher realms. However, Blessed One, someone who had his head cut off
                        would be unable to survive. In this way, even if he strove for merit, he would be unable to genuinely
                        follow a meritorious path.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-149"/>
                    <p tid="241"> The Blessed One said, “Divine son, similarly, for bodhisattva great beings it is better to
                        conduct themselves without reference points, even if it involves transgression, and thus not have the
                        qualities and trainings of those who fall into the views of the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on
                        reference points. It is better to be a miserly bodhisattva, and thus not abandon all sentient beings, or
                        even cast away all the qualities of a buddha. It is better to be an ill-behaved bodhisattva great being
                        rather than someone who fails to ripen others. It is better to be a bodhisattva great being who faithfully
                        practices on the level of action with conviction in the absence of focus, yet has disturbing emotions,
                        than to be a hearer or solitary buddha who relies on reference points, who attains certainty and is free
                        from disturbing emotions.” <ref cRef="F.261.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-150"/>
                    <p tid="242"> The god said, “Blessed One, the acts of the bodhisattva great beings, which are non-acts, are at
                        odds with the entire world. Blessed One, when the poisonous faults of reference points have formed, the
                        discipline of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, becomes an unwholesome state
                        for bodhisattva great beings. No matter how diligent the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on
                        reference points, are, the poisonous faults of reference points have been formed, and thus their diligence
                        is inferior to the laziness of bodhisattva great beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-151"/>
                    <p tid="243">The Blessed One said, “Divine son, just as the food of a destitute man is poison for a universal
                        monarch, likewise, divine son, are the discipline and diligence of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who
                        rely on reference points, for ill-behaved and lazy bodhisattva great beings. And why? Because of involving
                        the poisonous faults of reference points. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-152"/>
                    <p tid="244">“Divine son, just as the wealth of a person who is only concerned with his personal achievements
                        is not sufficient to ensure the wellbeing of a whole city, likewise, divine son, the diligence of those
                        who have the impoverished, inferior, and conceptual attitude of the hearers and solitary buddhas is unable
                        to liberate even the beings here in Jambudvīpa, let alone liberate all beings.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-153"/>
                    <p tid="245"> “Divine son, just as a leader who lovingly and compassionately grants great wealth and enjoyment
                        to others may use his wealth to accomplish the happiness of limitless beings in order to give all beings
                        unsurpassed happiness, so likewise, divine son, whoever develops the superior attitude of the bodhisattva
                        great beings and inspires all beings with knowledge, means, great love, and compassion <ref cRef="F.261.b"/> will ripen limitless beings through his diligence beyond focus and the great wealth of the
                        accumulations of merit and wisdom, gathered over limitless trillions of great eons. Without settling them,
                        he will even settle all beings in omniscience.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-154"/>
                    <p tid="246">Venerable Mahākāśyapa now addressed the Blessed One. “Blessed One,” he said, “the hearers
                        actualize all unconditioned phenomena while, Blessed One, bodhisattva great beings are classified under
                        conditioned phenomena. How can that outshine all the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference
                        points, who are included under the unconditioned?”</p>
                    <p tid="247">The Blessed One answered him, “Kāśyapa, I will give you an analogy that illustrates this. Some
                        people need an analogy to understand the meaning expressed by a skilled being. It is like this: imagine
                        that the four great oceans were filled with butter. Then, imagine that someone were to extract a drop of
                        butter from the oceans using the very tip of a hair split into one hundredths. Do you think, Kāśyapa, that
                        the drop of butter extracted with that very tip of a hair split into one hundredths would be able to
                        outshine the four great oceans filled with butter?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-155"/>
                    <p tid="248"> Kāśyapa replied, “No, Blessed One, they would not. Blissful One, they would not.”</p>
                    <p tid="249">The Blessed One asked, “Moreover, Kāśyapa, which one among the two would be largest, best,
                        foremost, and most valuable?”</p>
                    <p tid="250"> Kāśyapa replied, “Blessed One, even one trillionth of a single ocean would be, Blessed One, much
                        larger, better, exalted, and valuable than the single drop. Blessed One, the drop that was extracted using
                        that very tip of a hair split into one hundredths could not compare to that, let alone all four great
                        oceans.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-156"/>
                    <p tid="251">The Blessed One said, “In the same way as in this analogy, <ref cRef="F.262.a"/> the
                        unconditioned wisdom of the hearers and solitary buddhas, who rely on reference points, is as
                        insignificant as the drop of butter that was extracted from that very tip of a hair split into one
                        hundredths, since it involves reference points. </p>
                    <p tid="252">“Kāśyapa, the bodhisattva great beings are similar to the four great oceans filled with butter in
                        this analogy. They are free from reference points. They are endowed with all supreme features of engaging,
                        without engaging, the level of faithful practice. They embody all the accumulations of merit and wisdom.
                        Without viewing, they view conditioned wisdom. Moreover, through the blazing fire of the ultimate, they
                        ripen beings and thereby transform them, without relying on reference points, into the omniscient wisdom
                        that is endowed with all supreme aspects. </p>
                    <p tid="253">“Kāśyapa, this is how the bodhisattva great beings, without relying on reference points, outshine
                        the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points and who have attained the unconditioned. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-157"/>
                    <p tid="254">“Kāśyapa, as another analogy, imagine a city that contains hundreds of thousands of semiprecious
                        trinkets. At the same time, there is a boat on the ocean that easily and effortlessly brings to land
                        precious and valuable gemstones of beryl. Now, what do you think: could the semiprecious stones found in
                        the city outshine the precious gemstones of beryl?”</p>
                    <p tid="255"> Kāśyapa replied, “Blessed One, it could not. Blissful One, it could not.”</p>
                    <p tid="256">The Blessed One said, “Kāśyapa, just like the semiprecious trinkets found in the city, so should
                        you view the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points and their attainment of the
                        unconditioned. Kāśyapa, just like the most valuable gemstones of beryl, which are first discovered in the
                        ocean, then boarded on to the ship, and easily and effortlessly arrive at the trading house, so, Kāśyapa,
                        should you view the bodhisattva great beings who arrive at the trading houses in the city of cyclic
                        existence and, without establishing anyone, establish all beings in unsurpassed and <ref cRef="F.262.b"/>
                        perfectly complete awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-158"/>
                    <p tid="257">“Kāśyapa, consider a further analogy. During the third month of spring, the entire land is filled
                        with crops. If, at that time, a small insect should carry off a single grain to eat, which would be
                        larger, that single grain or all the grains found on the entire land?”</p>
                    <p tid="258"> Kāśyapa answered, “Blessed One, the entire world filled with crops would have an infinitely
                        greater pile of grains, which would be able to nourish uncountable, limitless beings. At the same time,
                        Blessed One, the single grain that the small insect carried off to eat could not even sustain a single
                        being.” </p>
                    <p tid="259">The Blessed One said, “Kāśyapa, you should see the result that is the undefiled liberation of all
                        hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points as being just like the single grain that the
                        small insect carried off to eat. On the other hand, Kāśyapa, it is as being like the entire earth filled
                        with crops that you should see, Kāśyapa, the crops of the bodhisattva great beings’ roots of virtue; they
                        are the accumulations of merit and wisdom that in an unsurpassed manner embody the entire buddhadharma,
                        such as the six perfections, by means of abiding, without abiding, within the relative and ultimate
                        truths. When they have ripened, the bliss of the unsurpassed wisdom that is endowed with the supreme of
                        all aspects becomes, in a manner that is beyond reference points, the sustenance of all beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-159"/>
                    <p tid="260">Venerable Mahākāśyapa exclaimed to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, that is amazing! Blissful One,
                        that is amazing! It is exactly as the Blessed One has explained, without explaining. Blessed One, that is
                        how the bodhisattva great beings, by means of the unsurpassed wisdom beyond focus, which is endowed with
                        the supreme of all aspects, engage in, without engaging in, the level of faithful practice—and thereby
                        outshine the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points.” <ref cRef="F.263.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-160"/>
                    <p tid="261">The bodhisattva great beings from the buddha realm of the Blessed Thus-gone Ratnaketu, who had
                        arrived here in the Sahā world together with noble Mañjuśrī, now addressed the Blessed One. “Blessed One,
                        it is like this. The instructions of the hearers and solitary buddhas who rely on reference points, such
                        as the way to abandon disturbing emotions and determine downfalls, are all conceptual and specific
                        instructions that involve reference points. </p>
                    <p tid="262">“In the buddha realm of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu, there are no
                        such instructions that involve reference points. Such instructions that involve focus do not exist there.
                        Instead, Blessed One, the beings there listen, without listening, to the pure instructions of the
                        bodhisattva great beings. They listen, without listening, to the irreversible instructions. They listen,
                        without listening, to the instructions beyond reference points. They listen, without listening, to the
                        instructions on how all phenomena are ultimately utterly unborn. They listen, without listening, to the
                        instructions on how all phenomena are ultimately utterly unarisen. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-161"/>
                    <p tid="263">“The Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni underwent great hardship. Having
                        patience with so much suffering, and understanding that ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, he
                        taught the higher, middling, and lower Dharma. </p>
                    <p tid="264">“It is like this: ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly
                        unreal. However, from this single identity that all phenomena share on the ultimate level, the Blessed One
                        teaches the Dharma, without teaching, in many ways in order to accommodate the reference points of
                        beings.” </p>
                    <p tid="265">The bodhisattva great beings then began to venerate the Blessed, Thus-gone, Worthy, Perfect
                        Buddha Śākyamuni with exquisite offerings, such as divine flowers, fragrant herbs, incense, <ref cRef="F.263.b"/> flower garlands, unguents, powders, robes, parasols, standards, banners, and canopies
                        with victory banners. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-162"/>
                    <p tid="266"> They addressed Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta.“Mañjuśrī,” they said, “we will now proceed to Jewel World.” </p>
                    <p tid="267"> Mañjuśrī told them, “Children of noble family, if you know that the time has come to leave, then
                        do so.” </p>
                    <p tid="268">The bodhisattva great beings asked him, “Mañjuśrī, are you not coming with us?”</p>
                    <p tid="269"> Mañjuśrī replied, “Children of noble family, all buddha realms are a single buddha realm.
                        Likewise, all buddhas are a single buddha. Likewise, all dharmas are a single dharma. Likewise, all beings
                        are a single being. Since there are no differences between these, children of noble family, I will also go
                        there.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-163"/>
                    <p tid="270">The bodhisattva great beings asked, “Mañjuśrī, in what way are all of the buddha realms a single
                        buddha realm? Mañjuśrī, in what way are all buddhas a single buddha? Mañjuśrī, in what way are all dharmas
                        are a single dharma? Mañjuśrī, in what way are all beings a single being?”</p>
                    <p tid="271"> Mañjuśrī answered, “Children of noble family, none of the buddha realms are realms. Why? Because
                        ultimately they are utterly unborn. Children of noble family, none of the buddhas are buddhas. Why?
                        Because ultimately they are utterly unarisen. Children of noble family, none of the dharmas are dharmas.
                        Why? Because ultimately they are utterly unreal. Children of noble family, no beings are beings. Why?
                        Because ultimately they are all utterly and entirely unarisen.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-164"/>
                    <p tid="272">With these words, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta <ref cRef="F.264.a"/> caused this trichiliocosm to appear
                        precisely, without any difference, like the Jewel World of the Blessed, Thus-gone Ratnaketu. As he had
                        thus fulfilled his intention, he rested evenly in absorption. Then the bodhisattva great beings also saw
                        the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Ratnaketu and the Jewel World. In fact the bodhisattva
                        great beings all thought that they had arrived in the Jewel World. Looking at the Blessed, thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni, they saw him in the precise colors and shape of the Blessed, Thus-gone
                        Ratnaketu. Even the great hearers thought that they had become bodhisattva great beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-165"/>
                    <p tid="273">The bodhisattva great beings, who thought that they were beholding Ratnaketu, asked the Blessed,
                        Thus-gone Śākyamuni, “Blessed One, who has brought us to this Jewel World?”</p>
                    <p tid="274">The Blessed Śākyamuni asked them, “Children of noble family, who has led you?”</p>
                    <p tid="275">The bodhisattva great beings replied, “Blessed One, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta led us.”</p>
                    <p tid="276">The Blessed Śākyamuni said, “Children of noble family, Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta has brought you here
                        without coming and going.”</p>
                    <p tid="277"> Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta told the bodhisattva great beings. “Children of noble family, to find out
                        where you are being led to, and from where you are being led, look with your equipoise!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-166"/>
                    <p tid="278">When the bodhisattva great beings each looked through their meditative absorption, <ref cRef="F.264.b"/> they saw that they had never moved from this Sahā world. Amazed, they were full of
                        astonishment and exclaimed, “Although we never got up from our seats, we thought that we had traveled to
                        the Jewel World. But it was Mañjuśrī who caused it all by means of his inconceivable blessing without
                        blessing!” They then added, “Blessed One, may all beings also attain this blessing in a manner beyond
                        reference point!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-167"/>
                    <p tid="279">Then the Blessed Śākyamuni spoke to the bodhisattva great beings.“Children of noble family,
                        consider this analogy. Space contains the earth, and also wood, zinc, copper, silver, gold, as well gems,
                        pearls, beryl, conch, crystal, coral,<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-241">The list
                            also includes one type of stone (Tib. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a mra gar ba</foreign>)
                            that we have been unable to identify.</note> cat’s eye, conch shells that coil to the right, and red
                        pearls, so that all these are contained within space. Yet at the same time, children of noble family,
                        although relatively there are of course different items contained, space itself remains undifferentiated.
                        And why? Because ultimately space is utterly unreal. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-168"/>
                    <p tid="280">“Likewise, children of noble family, ultimately all phenomena are surely utterly unborn, utterly
                        unarisen, and utterly unreal. And yet, through the relative conventions of the world, they are imputed and
                        designated in a conventional manner: ‘This is form, this is feeling, this is perception, this is
                        formation, this is consciousness. These are the sense fields. These are the elements. This is the Jewel of
                        the Buddha. This is the Jewel of the Dharma. This is the Jewel of the Saṅgha. This is the vehicle of the
                        hearers. This is the vehicle of the solitary buddhas. This is the unexcelled vehicle. These are the paths
                        of the ten virtuous actions. These are the paths of the ten nonvirtuous actions. These are hell beings.
                        These are the animal existences. These are the abodes of the hungry spirits. <ref cRef="F.265.a"/> These
                        are demigods. These are humans. These are gods. These are gods who experience desire. These are gods who
                        experience form. These are gods who experience the formless. This is the desire realm. This is the form
                        realm. This is the formless realm. These are good physical actions. These are good verbal actions. These
                        are good mental actions. This is the perfection of generosity. This is the perfection of discipline. This
                        is the perfection of patience. This is the perfection of diligence. This is the perfection of
                        concentration. This is the perfection of knowledge. This is the perfection of skillful means. This is the
                        perfection of aspirations. This is the perfection of strength. This is the perfection of wisdom. These are
                        the ten levels, the ten powers, the ten strengths of the bodhisattvas, the ten strengths of the thus-gone
                        ones, the fourfold fearlessness, the four genuine discriminations, the five faculties, the five
                            <term>powers</term>, the eighteen unique qualities of a buddha, the omniscient wisdom that is endowed
                        with the supreme of all aspects, the awakening of a buddha, suchness, the limit of reality, emptiness,
                        signlessness, wishlessness, the unconditioned, all conditioned and unconditioned phenomena, saṃsāra and
                        nirvāṇa, all speech and objects of speech, consciousness and objects of consciousness.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-169"/>
                    <p tid="281">“In this way, as conventions are designated and connected, the relative conventions of the world
                        are applied. Ultimately, however, all experiences are nonexistent. And why? Children of noble family,
                        ultimately all phenomena are utterly unborn, utterly unarisen, and utterly unreal.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-170"/>
                    <p tid="282">The bodhisattva great beings were amazed. They rose from their seats and performed a very
                        elaborate and unique worship of the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect <ref cRef="F.265.b"/> Buddha
                        Śākyamuni. They bowed down their heads to the feet of the Blessed One and said, “Blessed One, in a manner
                        beyond reference point, please emit your sound to all beings: a lion’s roar, an especially exalted sound,
                        the sound of the supreme leader, the sound of a great being, a sound of the genuine, the sound of
                        thatness, a sound beyond reference point, the sound of the ultimate.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-171"/>
                    <p tid="283">Those bodhisattva great beings happily and joyfully circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone,
                        worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni several hundred thousand times before finally departing from the presence
                        of the Blessed One. Proceeding into the ten directions, they donned, in the manner of having no armor, the
                        great armor of diligence beyond reference point. In this way they taught, without teaching, this Dharma
                        teaching, which abides within both the ultimate and the relative truths. They taught this very
                        Dharma-vinaya to tame all beings and, without establishing, they established these beings in the teaching. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-172"/>
                    <p tid="284">Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta did not get up, but remained on his seat, resting evenly in absorption. By
                        means of his absorption, a light known as <distinct>eradicating the reference points and ignorance of all
                            beings</distinct> shone forth above his head from his crown protuberance. As the light appeared, it
                        illuminated all the infinite buddha realms within all the worlds in the ten directions. The light rays
                        caused the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni to teach the Dharma so that the teaching
                        on relying on both the relative and ultimate truth was heard, without being heard. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-173"/>
                    <p tid="285">In order to pay homage to all the buddhas and the bodhisattva great beings in all the infinite
                        and limitless worlds in the ten directions, the light produced clouds that rained down divine flowers,
                        clouds that rained down divine fragrant herbs, clouds that rained down divine incense, <ref cRef="F.266.a"/> clouds that rained down divine garlands, clouds that rained down divine unguents, clouds that rained
                        down divine powders, clouds that rained down divine garments, clouds that rained down divine parasols,
                        clouds that rained down divine standards, clouds that rained down divine banners, clouds that rained down
                        divine victory banners, clouds that rained down divine canopies. There were clouds that rained down divine
                        flowers, fragrant herbs, incense, garlands, unguents, powders, garments, parasols, standards, banners,
                        victory banners, and canopies. Thus they sent forth clouds that rained down divine flowers, fragrant
                        herbs, incense, garlands, unguents, powders, garments, parasols, standards, banners, victory banners, and
                        canopies that were all of the finest quality and produced all forms of unexcelled exuberance. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-174"/>
                    <p tid="286">Now Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta emerged from his absorption. In a manner beyond reference points, he
                        circumambulated the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha Śākyamuni several hundred thousand times
                        before he departed from this Sahā world. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-175"/>
                    <p tid="287">The Blessed One now told Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you should uphold and propagate this Dharma
                        teaching, which is the source of all buddhas and bodhisattva great beings.”</p>
                    <p tid="288">Venerable Ānanda answered the Blessed One, “Blessed One, I can indeed uphold this teaching, but I
                        would be unable to propagate it. The reason, Blessed One, is that ultimately there are so many beings who
                        cling to reference points; they also cling to physical matter, and they cling to substance, and it is
                        extremely difficult to break them away from this mistaken grasping.” <ref cRef="F.266.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="289">The Blessed One said to Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, all the blessed buddhas in the past, present,
                        and future have blessed, without blessing, this Dharma teaching. Ānanda, you only need to act as a mere
                        circumstance.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-176"/>
                    <p tid="290">Venerable Ānanda asked him, “Blessed One, what happens if a son or daughter of noble family
                        should hear just a little of this teaching?”</p>
                    <p tid="291">The Blessed One replied, “Ānanda, it is based on this Dharma teaching that the Thus-gone One
                        genuinely teaches, shows reality, shows the absence of reference points, shows the ultimate, and teaches
                        without teaching. This teaching is inconceivable and limitless. Ānanda, whoever hears, without hearing, a
                        little of this Dharma teaching, even if it is just a single syllable, will encounter all the inconceivable
                        and limitless teachings of the Buddha.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-177"/>
                    <p tid="292">Then Venerable Ānanda asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, what is the name of this Dharma
                        teaching? How should one apprehend it?” </p>
                    <p tid="293">The Blessed One said, “Ānanda, you should know this Dharma teaching as <title xml:lang="en">Teaching the Relative and Ultimate Truths</title>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-178"/>
                    <p tid="294">When the Blessed One had spoken, the bodhisattva great beings, the great hearers, Venerable
                        Ānanda, and the entire retinue, as well as the world with all its gods, humans, demigods, and gandharvas,
                        rejoiced and praised the Blessed One’s teachings. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="303">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-179"/>
                    <p tid="295">This completes the Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">Teaching the Relative and
                            Ultimate Truths</title>. </p>
                    <p tid="296">It was translated, proofed, and finalized by the Indian scholars Śākyaprabha and Jinamitra,
                        together with the translator-editor Bhande Dharmatāśīla and others. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="304">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="305">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="306">Tibetan Texts </head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-060-008-180">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa kun rdzob dang don dam pa’i bden pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen
                            po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­saṃvṛti­paramārtha­satya­nirdeśa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 179, Degé Kangyur, vol. 60
                        (mdo sde, ma), folios 244b–266b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-060-008-181">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa kun rdzob dang don dam pa’i bden pa bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen
                            po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur]. krung go’i bod rig
                        pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China
                        Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 60, pp. 653–707. </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="307">Secondary Literature </head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-060-008-182">
                        <author>Vose, Kevin A.</author>
                        <title xml:lang="en">Resurrecting Candrakīrti: Disputes in the Tibetan Creation of Prāsaṅgika</title>.
                        Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2009. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-183">
                            <term>applications of mindfulness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa nye bar bzhag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་བཞག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛtyupasthāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Four contemplations on (1) the body, (2) feelings, (3) mind, and (4)
                                phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-184">
                            <term>bases of miraculous power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Determination, discernment, diligence, and meditative concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-185">
                            <term>bhande</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ban de </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བན་དེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhadanta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The general term from ancient India for any member of the ordained Buddhist
                                saṅgha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-186">
                            <term>Blissful One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sugata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Synonym for a buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-187">
                            <term>thirty-seven factors of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi chos sum cu rtsa bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཆོས་སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sapta­triṃśadbodhyaṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Thirty-seven practices that lead the practitioner to the awakened state: the
                                four applications of mindfulness, the four thorough relinquishments, the four bases of miraculous
                                power, the five faculties, the five power‌s, the eightfold path, and the seven branches of
                                awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-188">
                            <term>elements</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world in terms of eighteen <term type="ignore">elements</term>
                                (eye, form, and eye consciousness; ear, sound, and ear consciousness; nose, odor, and nose
                                consciousness; tongue, taste, and tongue consciousness; body, touch, and body consciousness; mind,
                                mental objects, and mind consciousness).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-189">
                            <term>branches of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mindfulness, discrimination, diligence, joy, pliability, absorption, and
                                equanimity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-190">
                            <term>buddhadharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhadharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Can refer to the teaching of the Buddha as well as the dharmas that constitute
                                an awakened being.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-191">
                            <term>desire realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod pa’i khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་པའི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kamadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three realms of saṃsāra, characterized by a prevalence of
                                desire.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-192">
                            <term>eight mistaken dharmas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">log pa’i chos brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལོག་པའི་ཆོས་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mithyādharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Possibly, this is identical to the eight worldly dharmas: hoping for
                                happiness, fame, praise, and gain, and fearing suffering, slander, blame, and loss.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-193">
                            <term>eighteen unique qualities of a buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi chos ma ’dres pa bco brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་མ་འདྲེས་པ་བཅོ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭā­daśāveṇika­buddha­dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eighteen special features of a buddha’s behavior, realization, activity, and
                                wisdom that are not shared by other beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-194">
                            <term>eightfold path of the noble ones</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa’i lam yan lag brgyad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པའི་ལམ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāṣṭāṅga­mārga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Correct view, intention, speech, actions, livelihood, effort, mindfulness, and
                                concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-195">
                            <term>acts with immediate consequence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañca ānantarya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Describing the result of committing one of five particularly heinous crimes:
                                (1) killing one’s father, (2) killing one’s mother, (3) killing an arhat, (4) maliciously drawing
                                blood from a buddha, and (5) causing a schism in the sangha. In this sūtra, Mañjuśrī describes a
                                corresponding set of five <term type="ignore">acts with immediate consequences</term> that bodhisattvas should, in fact,
                                perform.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-196">
                            <term>faculties</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcendriyāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, dilligence, mindfulness, absorption, and knowledge.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-197">
                            <term>form realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs kyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཀྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three realms of saṃsāra, characterized by coarse materiality
                                similar to the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-198">
                            <term>formless realm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs med pa’i khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་མེད་པའི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ārūpyadhātu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arūpadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three realms of saṃsāra, characterized by having only a subtle
                                mental form.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-199">
                            <term>four genuine discriminations</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so so yang dag par rig pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོ་ཡང་དག་པར་རིག་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catuḥpratisaṃvid</term>
                            <term type="definition">Genuine discrimination with respect to dharmas, meaning, language, and
                                eloquence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-200">
                            <term>fourfold fearlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཇིགས་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturabhaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Fearlessness</term> in declaring that one has (1) awakened, (2) ceased all illusions,
                                (3) taught the obstacles to awakening, and (4) shown the way to liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-201">
                            <term>hearer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A follower of those teachings of the Buddha that <term type="ignore">focus</term> on the monastic
                                lifestyle and liberating oneself from suffering, in contrasted to followers of the bodhisattva
                                vehicle who seek buddhahood for the sake of all beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-202">
                            <term>non-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyir mi ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">The third level of noble ones when practicing the path of the hearers (bound
                                to never be reborn).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-203">
                            <term>once-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lan cig phyir ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sakṛdāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second level of noble ones when practicing the path of the hearers (bound
                                to be born again no more than once).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-204">
                            <term>sense fields</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One way of describing experience and the world in terms of twelve <term type="ignore">sense fields</term>
                                (eye and form, ear and sound, nose and odor, tongue and taste, body and touch, mind and mental
                                objects).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-205">
                            <term>stream-enterer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyun du zhugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">srotāpanna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A person who has entered the “stream” of practice that leads to nirvāṇa. The
                                first of the four attainments of the path of the hearers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-206">
                            <term>ten levels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabhūmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">ten levels</term> of a bodhisattva’s development into a fully enlightened
                                buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-207">
                            <term>ten nonvirtuous actions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dge ba bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དགེ་བ་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśākuśala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, lying, divisive speech, harsh speech,
                                gossip, covetousness, ill will, and wrong views.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-208">
                            <term>ten powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśavaśitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">ten powers</term> gained by bodhisattvas as they progress on the path: life,
                                deeds, necessities, devotion, aspiration, miraculous abilities, birth, doctrine, mind, and
                                wisdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-209" mode="marked">
                            <term>powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcabalāni</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, dilligence, mindfulness, absorption, and knowledge. Although the same
                                as the faculties, they are termed “powers” due to their greater strength.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-210">
                            <term>thorough relinquishments</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag par spong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakprahāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Relinquishing negative acts in the present and the future, and enhancing
                                positive acts in the present and the future.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-211">
                            <term>ūrṇā hair</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdzod spu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཛོད་སྤུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ūrṇākeśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A hair between the eyebrows of a buddha. One of the marks of an awakened
                                being.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-212">
                            <term>unmanifest</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་བྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpanna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-213">
                            <term>focus</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upalabdhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Also translated “reference point” q.v.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-214">
                            <term>reference point</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upalabdhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Conceptual mind. Also translated “focus” q.v.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-215">
                            <term>sphere of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi dbyings </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་དབྱིངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The element, or nature, of ultimate reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-216">
                            <term>non-occurrence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu mi ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-217">
                            <term>non-occurring</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu mi ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་མི་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-218">
                            <term>limit of reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ultimate experience of reality, a close synonym of nirvāṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-219">
                            <term>fearlessness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཇིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “fourfold fearlessness.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-220">
                            <term>unique qualities</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ’dres pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་འདྲེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āveṇika</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “eighteen unique qualities of a buddha.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-221">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The buddha’s cousin and principal attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-222">
                            <term>Dharmatāśīla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dharmatA shIla </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྷརྨཏཱ་ཤཱིལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmatāśīla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-223">
                            <term>Excellent Rule</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་བཟངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Susīma</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-224">
                            <term>Jinamitra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-225">
                            <term>Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Same as Mahākāśyapa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-226">
                            <term>Lord of Peace and Calm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu zhi ba rnam par dul ba’i dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བ་རྣམ་པར་དུལ་བའི་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva god in the assembly receiving Buddha Śākyamuni’s
                                teachings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-227">
                            <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A senior student of Buddha Śākyamuni, famous for his austere lifestyle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-228">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nu gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུ་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī Kumārabhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The bodhisattva Mañjuśrī; literally “Youthful Mañjuśrī.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-229">
                            <term>Ratnaketu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaketu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha who lives in the realm known as Jewel World.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-230">
                            <term>Śākyaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya prabhA </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་པྲབྷཱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyaprabha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-231">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu’i gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The present continent according to Buddhist world descriptions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-232">
                            <term>Jewel World</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che dang ldan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེ་དང་ལྡན་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">The realm of the Buddha Ratnaketu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-233">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital of the ancient kingdom of Magadha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-234">
                            <term>Sahā world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahālokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The present world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-235">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gṛdhra­kūṭa parvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mountain where many Great Vehicle teachings were delivered by Buddha
                                Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-060-008-236">
                            <term>Benares</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsal ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསལ་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāśi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Modern Vārāṇasi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>