<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul pa
                    bstan pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་སྐྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of
                    Attaining the Buddha’s Powers</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­balādhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa­nirdeśa</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་སྐྱེད་པའི་ཆོ་འཕྲུལ་རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul pa
                    bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Sūtra of the Great Vehicle “The Teaching on the Extraordinary
                    Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s Powers”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­buddha­balādhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa­nirdeśa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-7">Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group (Vienna)<lb/> under the patronage
                    and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-27">Gregory Forgues</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-30">Rolf Scheuermann</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-31">Casey Kemp</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-306">Simeon Joffe</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Professor Tom Tillemans</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-239">Khenpo Ngawang Wöser</consultant>
                <!--<author role="translatorEng">Khenpo Ngawang Wöser</author>-->
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.31 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-006"/>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh186" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 186</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 143.b–158.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Unknown</author>
                    <location count-pages="30">
                        <start volume="61" page="288"/>
                        <end volume="61" page="317"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11804" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-18T16:17:34.727Z" user="admin">18/06/2019 16:17:34</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.31" date-time="2019-06-18T16:17:31.913Z" user="celso">v 1.31 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="114">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In this sūtra, the Buddha displays supernatural powers three times. First, he magically transports his
                    entire audience and retinue to Vārāṇasī. Secondly, having incited Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi to use their
                    own miraculous powers to gather there all the beings who must be led to awakening, he makes the whole world
                    appear as a pure realm like Sukhāvatī. He explains that a tathāgata’s various powers are like a doctor’s
                    skills, and teaches, with Mañjuśrī’s help in a series of dialogues with other protagonists, on how the
                    tathāgatas manifest to beings, displaying his supernatural powers a third time by making many other buddhas
                    appear all around him. The meaning of the Tathāgata’s miracles are gradually disclosed to the audience, as
                    well as some other essential points including the merit to be gained by honoring the teachings. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="115">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group. The translation was made by by Gregory Forgues in
                    collaboration with Rolf Scheuermann and the generous assistance of Khenpo Ngawang Wöser. English text edited
                    by Casey Kemp. Special thanks to Professor Tom Tillemans for his comments and advice.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="116">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="117">The Setting</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The sūtra is set at first on the banks of the Nairañjanā River, where the Buddha is dwelling
                        together with a retinue of bodhisattvas including Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, Maitreya, and Mañjuśrī, as
                        well as great hearers like Subhūti, Śāriputra, and Maudgalyāyana. After Śakra and Brahmā pay their
                        respects, the Tathāgata magically transports himself together with his entire assembly to a grove in
                        Vārāṇasī, where he manifests his supernatural powers.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="118">The Story </head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The Buddha, upon entering into the state of state of concentration known as
                            <distinct><!--type="concentration"-->the garlands of the buddhas</distinct>, asks Avalokiteśvara and
                        Vajrapāṇi to summon miraculously all degenerate beings of the Sahā world system who must be led to
                        awakening. Entering into the same state of concentration, Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi manifest light rays
                        and inspirational verses to invite those beings to the mango grove. Once they arrive, the Tathāgata
                        displays his supernatural powers by exerting his sovereign power over the whole world, turning it into a
                        place similar to the pure realm of Sukhāvatī. With Mañjuśrī’s help, he teaches on how the tathāgatas
                        manifest to beings in a series of dialogues with other protagonists. He explains that a tathāgata is like
                        a doctor who knows the various diseases of beings and the methods to cure them. The Buddha finally
                        displays his supernatural powers a third time by making many other buddhas appear all around him. The
                        sūtra ends with a condensed summary of Buddhadharma.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="119">The Main Points of the Subject Matter</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">From a doctrinal perspective, the sūtra explores several important Mahāyāna topics in relation with
                        the notion of miracles (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihārya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cho ’phrul</foreign>), supernatural powers (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhi</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul</foreign>), and extraordinary
                        transformation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvaṇa</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par ’phrul</foreign>):</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <emph>The necessity for miracles</emph>. At the beginning of the text, it is stated that sentient beings
                        who could fall into negative forms of existence should be converted to the path in order to lead them to
                        unsurpassable awakening. This can only occur, though, through the display of miracles. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">
                        <emph>The description of miracles</emph>. In this sūtra, the miracles of the Buddha are presented in three
                        different ways: as magical transformations, as the ability to know another’s mind, and as the capacity to
                        destroy defilements by expounding the Dharma. First the Buddha performs supernatural actions that
                        transform the immediate physical surroundings. Then he explains that beings should be helped according to
                        their dispositions, inclinations, and capacities. Since the Tathāgata is able to know beings’ minds
                        through his supernatural powers, he is able to assist them through various skillful means (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs</foreign>)
                        corresponding to their circumstances. Vasubandhu explains this sequence in great detail in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title>: the Buddha first ravishes the minds of beings he wishes to
                        set on the path through the display of his extraordinary powers. Knowing their dispositions, inclinations,
                        and capacities, he then imparts methods that will ultimately lead them to unsurpassable, truly perfect
                        awakening. The use of such miracles by the Buddha as skillful means is a recurring theme of Mahāyāna
                        sūtras, as can be seen, for example, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgama­samādhi­sūtra</title>
                        (Lamotte 2003: 233) where there is a passage that mirrors the storyline of the present sūtra.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <emph>The “magical show” as an analogy for the nature of reality</emph>. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­balā­dhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa­nirdeśa</title> makes the important point that conditioned
                        phenomena are like a “show” or an illusion, as clearly explained by Mañjuśrī to the gods. Just like a
                        reflection in a mirror, the Tathāgata neither comes nor goes. Things neither arise nor cease. Yet the
                        Tathāgata appears in the world for the sake of beings. For him, however, there is no birth, no old age,
                        and no death. The sūtra explains that since all conditioned phenomena are like illusions, the
                        extraordinary activities of a tathāgata, such as teaching and leading beings to awakening, are not limited
                        by time and space. His teaching remains even if he manifested the extinction of suffering eons ago. As an
                        object of veneration, he is a means to reach awakening by accumulating merit. His purpose and meaning are
                        not constrained by notions of his being present or absent. The same idea occurs in a sūtra found in the
                        Ratnakūṭa, <title xml:lang="en">The Prophecy for the Magician Bhadra</title> (Toh. 65), in which the
                        Tathāgata displays similar miracles (Chang 1983: 4–13) and in which it is stated that the Buddha can
                        perform magic because he knows that all phenomena are illusory. Action (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karma</foreign>) is explained as being the great conjurer that magically creates
                        beings and material objects. Thus, the basis of the Tathāgata’s supernatural powers is considered to be
                        his realization that all phenomena are like magic and illusions. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">
                        <emph>The nature of the cycle of rebirths (saṃsāra) and karma</emph>. In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­balā­dhāna­prātihārya­vikurvā­ṇanirdeśa</title>, the Buddha explains that there is no birth,
                        old age, and death. However, one’s state of life is dependent on the perception conditioned by the body,
                        since beings are fixated on the physical basis of their existence. These perceptions trigger actions. On
                        the basis of these actions, beings will experience suffering again and again throughout all their future
                        rebirths. This endless cycle of arisings and cessations is what is called <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</foreign>. The scales of a balance are used as a metaphor in the text to
                        illustrate this process, and it is worth noting that this simile is also found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharma­samuccaya</title> in the same context (Rahula 2001: 94). </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">
                        <emph>Skillful means and practices</emph>. The sūtra puts forward various methods for venerating the
                        tathāgatas—making offerings, chanting their names, supporting the Dharma, propagating the teachings, and
                        making the Dharma available in any possible way. Of all these methods, those concerning the protection of
                        the Dharma are deemed supreme. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="120">Source Text and Various Versions</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">The source text is extant in Tibetan, Chinese, and (partially) Sanskrit. The Tibetan text is found
                        in the various editions of the Kangyur with no major variations. A glimpse of what might have been the
                        source text for the Tibetan translation of the sūtra is afforded by some Sanskrit fragments in the
                        collection of Gilgit manuscripts. The Gilgit manuscripts are among the oldest manuscripts in the world,
                        dating back to the 5th and 6th centuries A.D., and include famous works from the Buddhist canon such as
                        the <title xml:lang="en">Lotus Sūtra</title>. The language of these manuscripts is a form of Sanskrit with
                        Prakrit vocabulary and inflections. The Gilgit fragments of this sūtra, although far from representing the
                        whole text, show no major variations from their Tibetan counterparts. It is, however, not possible at this
                        stage to establish whether this specific Sanskrit version of the text was the basis for the Tibetan
                        translations. </p>
                    <p tid="13">There is unfortunately no colophon to this sūtra, and therefore no direct mention by name of the
                        Indian and Tibetan translators. We were unable to find any reference to this sūtra elsewhere in the
                        Tibetan canon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">Regarding the relationship between this sūtra and others, it is worth noting that the text belongs
                        to a corpus of sūtras containing passages in which miracles play a significant role: one Vinaya text, the
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya­kṣudraka­vastu</title> (Toh 6); two Prajñā­pāramitā­sūtras, the <title xml:lang="en">Prajñā­pāramitā in 25,000 lines</title> (Toh 9) and <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-031-002.html">Prajñāpāramitā
                            in 10,000 lines</ref>
                        </title> (Toh 11); the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title> (Toh 44); six
                        sūtras from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnakūṭa</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgatācintya­guhya­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 47), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattva­piṭaka</title>
                        (Toh 56), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadra­māyākāra­vyākaraṇa</title> (Toh 65), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­pratihārya­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 66), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­mahā­siṃha­nāda</title>
                        (Toh 67), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Acintya­buddha­viśaya­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 79); and twenty-eight
                        sūtras from the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadra­kalpika</title> (Toh 94), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṃghāṭi­sūtra­dharma­paryāya</title> (Toh
                        102), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karuṇā­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 112), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharma­puṇḍarīka</title> (Toh 113), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­dharma­guṇa­vyūha­rāja</title>
                        (Toh 114), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratna­karaṇḍa</title> (Toh 117), <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-055-001.html">The King of Samādhis Sūtra</ref>
                        </title> (Toh 127), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Praśānta­viniścaya­prātihārya­samādhi</title> (Toh 129), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgama­samādhi</title> (Toh 132), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dāraka­samādhi</title> (Toh 136),
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­samnipāta­ratna­ketu­dhāraṇī</title> (Toh 138), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata­mahā­karuṇā­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 147), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara­mati­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 152), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavatapta­nāga­rāja­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 156), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Druma­kiṃnara­rāja­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 157), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vikurvāṇa­rāja­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 167), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāyānopadeśa</title> (Toh
                        169), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākṣaya­mati­nirdeśa</title> (Toh 175), <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-060-005.html">The Sūtra of the Teaching of Vimalakīrti</ref>
                        </title> (  Toh 176), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­balā­dhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa­nirdeśa</title> (this text, Toh 186), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­bherī­hāraka­parivarta</title> (Toh 222), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśat­parivarta</title> (Toh 223), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­saṅgīti</title> (Toh 228),
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­megha</title> (Toh 232), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramārtha­dharma­vijaya</title> (Toh 246), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saddharma­smṛtyupasthāna</title>
                        (Toh 287), <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdzangs blun</title> (Toh 341), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumāgadhāvadāna</title> (Toh 346). </p>
                    <p tid="15">In addition, the pure realm of Sukhāvatī is mentioned in the text, as are some names of tathāgatas
                        and of a specific samādhi also found in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhāvataṃsaka</title>. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="121">Translation Issues and Academic Research</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-13"/>
                    <p tid="16">To the best of our knowledge, no complete English translation of this sūtra was available prior to
                        the one published here. Schopen, however, edited some Sanskrit fragments of the sūtra, compared them to
                        the Tibetan text, and provided an English translation on the basis of the Sanskrit and Tibetan versions. </p>
                    <p tid="17">The many compounds found in the text remain, unsurprisingly, one of the main issues for
                        translators. Some Tibetan expressions in which terms appear in a different order are apparently used for
                        the same Sanskrit compound, for instance, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bsod nams las skyes pa’i
                            dge ba’i rtsa ba</foreign> (145b.2) instead of <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i rtsa
                            ba las skyes pa’i bsod nams</foreign> (150b.7). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-14"/>
                    <p tid="18">Another good illustration of the difficulty of translating compounds is the title of the sūtra
                        itself, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddha­balādhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa</title>, which Schopen does not
                        translate in his study of the Sanskrit text. Although the Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhāna</foreign> is translated in the Mahāvyutpatti as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs skyed pa</foreign>, different transliterations are found in the various Kangyur
                        editions. For example, the Degé Kangyur reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balavadhana</foreign>, the Stok Palace reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhana</foreign>,
                        the Narthang reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">baladhana</foreign>, and so forth. The Pedurma
                        (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe sdur ma</title>, comparative edition, see <ptr target="#bibliography">bibliography</ptr>) settles for
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balavardhana</foreign>. In the present case, we chose to follow
                        Schopen, who opts for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balādhāna</foreign> (1978: 319). Edgerton, in
                        his <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary</title>, offers a detailed
                        explanation of this term, which he understands as “the attainment of (usually some particular) <term type="ignore">power</term>,” such as the <term type="ignore">powers</term> of a tathāgata (1953:
                        398a). As for the rest of the compound, we have translated <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> as “miracle” and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvāṇa</foreign> as
                        “extraordinary transformation.” In the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgama­samādhi­sūtra</title> (Lamotte
                        2003: 233), <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihāryabala</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vikurvāṇabala</foreign> are often used as synonyms. Lamotte reads them as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign> compounds (in the way of adjective+noun) respectively meaning
                        “wondrous <term type="ignore">powers</term>” and “prodigious <term type="ignore">powers</term>.” Burnouf,
                        on his part, understands <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṛddhi­prātihārya</foreign> as
                        “supernatural transformation” (2010: 189). La Vallée Poussin translates <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> as “magical <term type="ignore">powers</term>” in v. VII.47–48 of the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title> (and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="longTitle">bhāṣya</title>).<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-213">The English translations of
                            these terms are found in the English translations of Lamotte’s, Burnouf’s, and La Vallée Poussin’s
                            respective works. </note> In this context, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign>
                        is used by a buddha to convert beings through the manifestation of miraculous powers, the ability to know
                        others’ minds, and the capacity to teach, all of which correspond very much to the subject matter of our
                        sūtra. In this context, the third <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prātihārya</foreign> is deemed to
                        be superior since it cannot be attained by means of magic formulae (La Vallée Poussin 1988–90: 1166–68 and
                        1209–1210). For these reasons, we have not read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prāti­hārya­vikurvāṇa</foreign> as a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvandva</foreign> in this
                        context, as we were originally tempted to do. It is probably a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign> (noun+noun) and possibly a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tatpuruṣa</foreign>. In the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul
                            pa</foreign>, the two terms stand in apposition, indicating rather a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">karmadhāraya</foreign>. The complete title of the sūtra can therefore be translated as
                        “The Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s Powers,”
                        and indeed the message of the sūtra is that the ultimate miracle is to attain the state of buddhahood.
                        Supernatural powers are only a means to lead beings to awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-15"/>
                    <p tid="19">Another translation issue concerns the mention in the sūtra of a grove (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shing a mra srung ba’i tshal / a mra srung ba mo’i tshal</foreign>) located in Vāraṇasī.
                        Although there is no extant Sanskrit fragment for this passage, Schopen translated the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">a mra srung ba mo’i tshal</foreign> from the Tibetan as “the grove of
                        Āmrapālī” (see Schopen 1978: 323 fragment [1288]), taking it as a reference to the grove offered to the
                        Buddha by the courtesan Āmrapāli in which several events and teachings recorded in the canonical texts
                        took place. This translation is problematic here, however, because Āmrapālī’s grove was located in Vaiśālī
                        and not Vāraṇasī. There are several reasons for thinking that these phrases do not refer to Āmrapālī’s
                        grove. In the narratives of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinaya</title> texts—the only instances in the
                        Kangyur in which Āmrapālī is a protagonist in her own right as opposed to mentions of her grove—her name
                        is rendered in Tibetan as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra skyong ma</foreign>, while the
                        phrase a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mra srung ba</foreign>, which is often taken as an
                        alternative rendering, is in fact only used in the sūtra section of the Kangyur, and only within the
                        phrase a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign>, i.e. referring to a grove.
                        There are, it is true, several sūtras explicitly located in Vaiśālī in which <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> can be reasonably taken as referring to Āmrapālī’s grove.
                        In this text, however, we are faced not only with the anomalous location, but also with the variant
                        phrases <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shing a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba mo’i tshal</foreign>, both of which occur only here and
                        nowhere else in the entire Kangyur. A literal translation of the syntactic construction in this text,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shing a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> (F.143.b) would be
                        “grove of the caretaker of mango trees,” and our understanding is that the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba</foreign> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmrapāla</foreign> / <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmrapālī</foreign>) is
                        simply a generic name with this meaning, not a proper noun. In a word, the translation of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign> as “Āmrapālī’s grove” is technically
                        wrong, although it is semantically correct when the grove is located in Vaiśālī. Other possible hypotheses
                        to explain the anomaly would be that at some point in the transmission of the text a geographical or
                        nominal inaccuracy has been introduced; or else that the translocation of Āmrapālī’s grove to Vāraṇasī is
                        intended to be understood as part of the Buddha’s miraculous display. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="122">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="123">The Noble Sūtra of the Great Vehicle</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="124">The Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the
                    Buddha’s Powers</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-16"/>
                    <p tid="20">
                        <ref cRef="F.143.b"/>
                        <!--modularPassage type=openingHomage-->Homage to the Omniscient One!<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-17"/>
                    <p tid="21"><!--modularPassage type=thusSetting Retinue-->Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was
                        dwelling on the banks of the great Nairañjanā River, together with seven thousand
                        bodhisattvas.<!--/modularPassage--> Among them were the Noble Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, Maitreya, and
                        Mañjuśrī, and all the great śrāvakas like Subhūti, Śāriputra, and Maudgalyāyana. He was circumambulated by
                        Śakra, Brahmā, and all the protectors of the world, as well as all the kings, ministers, brahmins, and
                        householders, and was <ref cRef="F.144.a"/> placed in front of the assembly. After being presented with
                        offerings of almsfood, he pleased his surrounding retinue with a teaching on Dharma, and encouraged,
                        uplifted, and complimented them. By means of his great supernatural power, the Tathāgata and his
                        surrounding retinue were then transported to the city of Vārāṇasī, where they stayed in the grove of the
                        caretaker of mango trees.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-214">The Tibetan reads here
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shing a mra srung ba’i tshal</foreign>. This issue is
                            discussed in detail at the end of the Introduction. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-18"/>
                    <p tid="22">At that time the earth trembled greatly, and a vast lion throne made from the seven kinds of
                        precious substances appeared. Covering about ten miles in height and five miles in breadth, it was well
                            adorned,<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-215">Pd H N S U <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">legs par spras pa</foreign>. D <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">legs par smras
                                pa</foreign>.</note> delightful, and pleasing to the mind. It was tied with hanging silk tassels,
                        clothed with thousands of divine garments, covered with myriad garlands of divine flowers, endowed with a
                        divine fragrance, and colorful. The lion throne had arisen from the Tathāgata’s previously developed roots
                        of virtue. As soon as they saw it, all beings would immediately reach the stage of accepting that
                        phenomena are not produced. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-19"/>
                    <p tid="23"> Then, the Blessed One sat down on this lion throne, settled into the state of concentration known
                        as <distinct>the garlands of the buddhas</distinct>, and addressed the bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara
                        and Vajrapāṇi as follows. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-20"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Avalokiteśvara, go forth. Together with Vajrapāṇi, use your great supernatural powers and state
                        of concentration to assemble around me the beings of this Sahā world system and of the other world systems
                        of the ten directions whom you should tame and who are degenerate, have no faith, practice negative deeds,
                        are obscured because of various types of affliction, have no consideration for their mothers or fathers,
                        do not respect ascetics or brahmins for what they are, and have no faith in the Three Jewels.” <ref cRef="F.144.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-21"/>
                    <p tid="25"> On hearing these words from the Tathāgata, the bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi
                        settled into the state of concentration known as <distinct>watching over and exhorting all
                            beings</distinct>. Through the ­power of their state of concentration, this great earth was
                        tremendously shaken in six ways.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-216">“This great earth
                            teetered, tottered, and tremored in six different ways: it quivered, quavered, and quaked; it shifted,
                            shuddered, and shook. The west rose up and the east sank down. [The east rose up and the west sank
                            down.] The south rose up and the north sank down. The north rose up and the south sank down. The
                            middle rose up and the ends sank down. The ends rose up and the middle sank down.” (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prāti­hārya­sūtra</title>, translated in Rotman 2008: 174).</note> Thousands of
                        light rays shone forth from the bodies of Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi, and as they shone they completely
                        illuminated the world systems of the great trichiliocosm. They illuminated everything from the world of
                        Brahmā on down—that is, the worlds endowed with form and pervaded by form. From these light rays also came
                        these verses of exhortation: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-22"/>
                    <lg tid="26">
                        <l>“Be attentive and without afflictions.</l>
                        <l>Do not fall under the power of distraction!</l>
                        <l>While everywhere is the suffering of birth, old age, and death,</l>
                        <l>Rare is the appearance of the teaching of the Sugata.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-23"/>
                    <lg tid="27">
                        <l>“Those of unwholesome livelihood have no fear,</l>
                        <l>Even though they are bound to circle </l>
                        <l>In saṃsāra’s ocean for countless eons,</l>
                        <l>Always ensnared by afflictions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-24"/>
                    <lg tid="28">
                        <l>“Gain, desires, and women are impermanent.</l>
                        <l>They always possess the nature of an illusory song and dance.</l>
                        <l>Even if one experiences eons of bliss,</l>
                        <l>One will eventually undergo suffering.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-25"/>
                    <lg tid="29">
                        <l>“Behold how tricky things are!</l>
                        <l>One’s mother in this life may be one’s wife in another,</l>
                        <l>And in yet another life fools may eat her flesh,</l>
                        <l>And in their ignorance enjoy it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-26"/>
                    <lg tid="30">
                        <l>“No doubt, human beings take birth in the ocean of saṃsāra’s suffering,</l>
                        <l>Yet they are not afraid. </l>
                        <l>You who desire to honor the Sugata for having explained the noble Dharma to human beings,</l>
                        <l>Go forth!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-27"/>
                    <lg tid="31">
                        <l>“Once you have understood the one who can guide the untamed,</l>
                        <l>You will attain the state of concentration, the cultivation of peace. </l>
                        <l>Thus, all you human beings in the ocean of saṃsāra,</l>
                        <l>Be afraid and long for liberation! <ref cRef="F.145.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-28"/>
                    <lg tid="32">
                        <l> “All you humans, honor this noble one!<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-217">S
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rnams ky ni</foreign>. D <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rnams kyis ni</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Do not take the lives of others,</l>
                        <l>And likewise do not take others’ possessions that have not been offered.</l>
                        <l>Do not violate other people’s wives.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-29"/>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>“Always pay homage to the Buddhadharma!</l>
                        <l>Give up pride, arrogance, and harsh speech,</l>
                        <l> And then set out for the grove of the caretaker of mango trees</l>
                        <l>In the city called Vārāṇasī!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-30"/>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>“Upon arriving, behold the supreme person.</l>
                        <l>Vast and pleasing is his array:</l>
                        <l>The saṅgha of monks who always have supernatural powers,</l>
                        <l>And the bodhisattvas who possess even greater ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-31"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>“He is named Avalokiteśvara</l>
                        <l>Who continuously sends forth light rays</l>
                        <l>So that the ignorant know</l>
                        <l>And the myriad beings are liberated.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-32"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>“Those who are proud, arrogant, and haughty,</l>
                        <l>And those who do not venerate the Buddhadharma,</l>
                        <l>The protector, the supreme Vajrapāṇi, never ceases to illuminate them</l>
                        <l>And leads them to understanding.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-33"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>“Their bodies are vast with great supernatural powers.</l>
                        <l>Eons and eons would not suffice to describe them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-34"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>“There, in the grove of the caretaker of mango trees,</l>
                        <l>Bring perfume, garlands, fine clothes, and ornaments to honor the Sugata.</l>
                        <l>Venerate this guide of humankind,</l>
                        <l>For rare is a buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-35"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“Beings have suffered for myriads of eons</l>
                        <l>And will forever do so due to desire.</l>
                        <l>May the wise always long for liberation</l>
                        <l>And venerate the supreme person, the Buddha!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-36"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“Sons, daughters, relatives,</l>
                        <l>Parents, wives, friends— </l>
                        <l>All are illusory and pointless;</l>
                        <l>They will always be reborn in different ways.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-37"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“So, too, gold and silver are like flashes of lightning.</l>
                        <l>None show any essence.</l>
                        <l>To reach the state of awakening,</l>
                        <l>Venerate the guide of humankind."</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-38"/>
                    <p tid="42">As these inspirational verses arose one after another from the light rays, <ref cRef="F.145.b"/>
                        they filled the world systems of the great trichiliocosm with sound, inspiring all beings. Those who
                        formerly had wrong views were converted to right views. Those who were afflicted with pride, vanity,
                        arrogance, and pretense were freed from pride, vanity, and arrogance. Those who indulged in lust without
                        restraint were freed from lust. All those who engaged in killing, stealing, sexual misconduct on account
                        of desire, or the eight unwholesome factors, were set on the noble eightfold path in all their actions,
                        words, and thoughts. Each and every one of them completely abandoned excitement, joking, pleasure,
                        amusement, desire, anger, envy, and attachment. They felt determined to contemplate, follow, and serve the
                        Tathāgata. They all wished to hear the Dharma. All the gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas,
                        kinnaras, mahoragas, humans, non-humans, kings of the nāgas, royal lords of the citadels, vassals,
                        universal monarchs, monks, nuns, male lay vow holders, and female lay vow holders carried divine flowers,
                        garlands, salves, aromatic powders, garments, umbrellas, royal banners, cymbals, and bundles of silk
                        scarves in order to venerate the Tathāgata. Once they reached the place where he resided, the grove of the
                        caretaker of mango trees in the great city of Vārāṇasī, they worshipped him and his surrounding retinue
                        with the roots of virtue that arose from their own merit. A rain of flowers, a great fragrant rain, fell. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-39"/>
                    <p tid="43">Then, <ref cRef="F.146.a"/> at that moment, the Blessed One exerted his sovereign power<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-218">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin gyi rlabs te</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhyatiṣṭha</foreign>, see Schopen 1978: 322 fragment [1288]). We have translated
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin gyi rlabs</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhāna</foreign>) in this text as ‘sovereign power.’ Conze used the expression
                            ‘sustaining power.’ The term is often translated as ‘blessings.’ However, as explained in Eckel 1994:
                            90–93, Gómez 2011: 539, 541, and Fiordalis 2012: 104, 118, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhiṣṭhāna</foreign> conveys the notions of control (of one’s environment as a result of
                            meditative absorption), authority, or protection (see <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­dharma­kośa</title> VII.51, cf. Poussin 1925: 119ff). As can be seen in the present text,
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhi­ṣṭhāna</foreign> is also used to convey the idea of
                            transformation through exerting one’s control over objects, people, and places. It seems to us that
                            ‘sovereign power’ covers all these shades of meaning as well as the various usages of the Sanskrit
                            term. For example, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satyādhiṣṭhāna</foreign>, ‘the sovereign
                            power of truth,’ and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhi­ṣṭhānādhisthita</foreign>, ‘empowered
                            by the sovereign power (of the Tathāgata)’—which in tantric initiation may also refer to being
                            empowered as a sovereign.</note> on Jambudvīpa and the grove of the caretaker of mango trees so that
                        it extended over several trillions of yojanas. The ground became as smooth as the palm of a hand, divinely
                        pleasing to the mind, colorful, and fragrant. It was ornamented with heavenly flower trees, fruit trees,
                        fragrant trees, jewel trees, wish-fulfilling trees, and trees bearing garments. It supported heavenly lion
                        thrones with hanging garlands of jewels, cloth, and flowers, and was suffused with the sound of divine
                        bells. Thus, just like the world system known as Sukhāvatī, it was ravishing, fulfilling, pleasing, and
                        delightful. It was blessed, being filled by everyone, from bodhisattvas, śrāvakas, pratyekabuddhas, gods,
                        nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kinnaras, and mahoragas, to monks, nuns, male and female lay
                        vow holders, kings, ministers, brahmins, and householders.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-40"/>
                    <p tid="44">Then, the bodhisattvas Noble Avalokiteśvara and Vajrapāṇi emerged from their state of
                        concentration and went to where the Blessed One was staying. They approached, circumambulated him three
                        times, and said to him, “Blessed One, the Tathāgata’s skillful means and methods that bring beings to
                        spiritual maturity are many. Sugata, they are many indeed. Blessed One, the bodhisattva mahāsattvas, the
                        great śrāvakas, gods, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, <ref cRef="F.146.b"/> kinnaras,
                        mahoragas, kings, ministers, brahmins, householders, monks, nuns, and male and female lay vow holders have
                        gathered here in great numbers through the strength of the Tathāgata’s majesty and supernatural powers.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-41"/>
                    <p tid="45">The Blessed One replied, “Sons of a good family, this is excellent, most excellent. Sons of the
                        Victorious One, it is indeed so. Many are the Tathāgata’s skillful means and methods that bring beings to
                        spiritual maturity. He teaches the Dharma knowing their intentions, the way to convert them, and their
                        roots of virtue, as well as their behavior according to their various dispositions. Some beings are to be
                        converted by bodhisattvas. Some are to be converted by śrāvakas. Some are to be converted by
                        pratyekabuddhas. Some are to be converted by gods. Some are to be converted by Śakra. Some are to be
                        converted by Brahmā. Some are to be converted by nāgas. Some are to be converted by great supernatural
                        powers. Some are to be converted by kings. Some are to be converted by states of concentration. Some are
                        to be converted by listening to the Dharma. Some are to be converted by miracles. Some are to be converted
                        by the Tathāgata’s complete nirvāṇa. Some are to be converted by relics. Some to be converted strive for
                        the roots of virtue that arise from commissioning stūpas, monasteries, promenades, and groves. Some to be
                        converted strive for the roots of virtue that arise from commissioning statues, images, and
                        representations of gold, silver, and brass. Some to be converted strive<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-219">In the following sentences, we have chosen to follow the Sanskrit
                            construction. We have thus translated <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">kecid...
                                kuśala­mūlotsukā vaineyāḥ</foreign> as “some to be converted strive for the roots of virtue...”
                            instead of the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha cig... dge ba’i rtsa ba la spro ba
                                bskyed pas ’dul</foreign>, literally, “some are to be converted through striving for the roots of
                            virtue...”</note> for the roots of virtue that arise from worshipping and venerating the saṅgha of
                        monks. Some to be converted strive for the roots of virtue that arise from copying sūtras,<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-220">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dri ba</foreign> in the sense of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yi ger ’dri ba</foreign>. See Schopen 2005: 32ff.</note> having sūtras copied, or
                        reciting sūtras. Some to be converted strive for the roots of virtue that arise from offering lamps,
                        incense, flowers, perfume, garlands, salves, jewel necklaces, and so forth. <ref cRef="F.147.a"/> They do
                        not partake of a Dharma versed in the ultimate nor of a Dharma concerned with nirvāṇa. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-42"/>
                    <p tid="46">“Sons of the Victorious One, there is indeed nothing whatsoever that the tathāgatas do not know,
                        see, hear, or fully comprehend. They know what has happened. They know the future. They know the past.
                        They know the present. They know the activities of all beings. They know their conduct. They know their
                        dispositions. They know their birth. They know their existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-43"/>
                    <p tid="47">“Sons of the Victorious One, it is as follows. Consider the analogy of a well-trained doctor who
                        is very skilled in the eight branches of Āyurveda and expert in all conditions, having extensively studied
                        the use of medicinal substances and instruments, and who knows the condition of the sick beings whose
                        bodies are tormented by various ailments. He knows the phases and the degrees. He knows the cure. He knows
                        the diseases related to the airs, bile, phlegm, or a combination of the three, and those related to blood,
                        indigestion, tumors, edema, heart disease, leprosy, skin eruption, abscesses, and boils, as well as
                        poisoning, inflammation, and so on. Possessing knowledge of all these things, he cures the diseases of all
                        beings and liberates them from the fear of diverse ailments through various medicinal substances,
                        vomitives, purgatives, powders, sternutatory treatments, bleeding, ghee, boiled oil, and tonics.<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-221">The Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">smin par bya ba</foreign>, which literally means “that which raises, that which
                            ripens.” The Sanskrit equivalent is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bālacūrṇa</foreign> (see
                            Schopen 1978: 326 §1291). However, an alternative and possibly better reading would be the Āyurvedic
                            tonic called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">balācūrṇa</foreign>, a powder made with herbs such
                            as <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">sida cordifolia</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-44"/>
                    <p tid="48">“In the same way, noble sons of the Victorious One, the Tathāgata possesses eight branches of
                        Āyurveda with the various states of concentration, the bases of supernatural powers, the powers, the
                        assurances, and divine sight and hearing.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-222">See
                            glossary for lists of these qualities. Divine sight and hearing are qualities that are part of the
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhijñās</foreign> (“superior knowledge”).</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.147.b"/> He is well versed in the various conditions of beings, their intentions, and their
                        conduct. Thus he seeks to free from taking rebirth in hell or as animals, hungry ghosts, or in the world
                        of Yama all those beings who are tormented by the diseases of desire, hatred, and bewilderment and by the
                        sicknesses of the fundamental and secondary defilements, as well as those obscured by pride, vanity, and
                        arrogance or by attachment, suffering, fear, and anger. To this end, by using various skillful means,
                        various practices, various states of concentration, and supernatural powers, he brings beings to all
                        stages of liberation up to and including their unsurpassable, perfect awakening, and thus leads them to
                        the extinction of their suffering in the sphere of remainderless <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">parinirvāṇa</foreign>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-45"/>
                    <p tid="49">“He liberates them from the eight unwholesome factors and sets each of them on the eightfold noble
                        path. Sons of noble family, it is like this. Consider the analogy of the moon which, for the sake of
                        beings to be converted, manifests skillfully to them according to the roots of virtue that constitute
                        their dispositions. It makes itself invisible, or shows itself as a half-moon, or waning, or waxing, or as
                        a full moon. It dispels all obscurity and darkness, and refreshes all the grass, forests, medicinal herbs,
                        and crops. Likewise, sons of the Victorious One, the Tathāgata understands beings who are obscured by
                        various kinds of suffering, as well as the conduct of beings who are to be converted in keeping with their
                        various dispositions. He manifests as being in the state of parinirvāṇa, as being born, as a universal
                        monarch, and also as someone joyful who is entertained by amusements and pleasures such as women’s
                        laughter, play, perfume, and garlands. <ref cRef="F.148.a"/> He also manifests as someone who renounces
                        the household life, goes forth to live as a renunciant and practices asceticism, and eventually as someone
                        who, having tamed Māra and turned the wheel of Dharma, pleases beings by bringing down the rain of the
                        great cloud of Dharma. The tathāgatas have attained parinirvāṇa. Yet they liberate all beings through
                        various practices such as zealously venerating relics; having stūpas, monasteries, and images constructed;
                        giving up the household life for the sake of going forth as a renunciant; and venerating the Saṅgha of
                        monks, as well as copying, reading, and reciting the noble Dharma. They also liberate beings through
                        skillful means such as maintaining the training, the way of life, the monastic vows, fasting,<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-223">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsnyan gnas</foreign> (Tib.) or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upavāsa</foreign> (Skt.) is the fast day during the Poṣadha (Pāli <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn" type="term">uposatha</foreign>), which includes the recitation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prāti­mokṣa­sūtra</title>, the confession of faults, and the restoration of vows (e.g., the eight
                            vows for lay followers). </note> and the lay pledges. They liberate these beings from rebirths as hell
                        beings, animals, and beings born in Yama’s world, and from existences deprived of the eight freedoms, as
                        well as from negative rebirths and negative forms of existence, and so forth, and comfort these beings by
                        having them listen to the Dharma and bringing them to unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-46"/>
                    <p tid="50">At that point, some dim-witted gods thought, “The tathāgatas of earlier times, who were arhats and
                        fully awakened buddhas, accomplished the deeds of a tathāgata. That is to say, after extending their own
                        lifespan through their blessings, they liberated all beings from birth, old age, sickness, death, sorrow,
                        lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and trouble. Likewise, this tathāgata, although he has not yet
                        accomplished all the deeds of a tathāgata, is also extolling and teaching nirvāṇa. And he is displaying
                            <ref cRef="F.148.b"/> supernatural powers and miracles of extraordinary transformations after having
                        assembled a great retinue. So does this tathāgata also seek parinirvāṇa right away?” With this thought,
                        they were depressed and fell silent.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-47"/>
                    <p tid="51">The youthful Mañjuśrī then clairvoyantly understood what those gods were thinking and said to
                        them, “Gods, do not think like that, do not say such things. Do not be depressed. Many are the skillful
                        means of the tathāgatas. They teach the Dharma to beings of diverse inclinations by means of their
                        sovereign power, and the power of their roots of virtue, which consists of various methods, insights, and
                        states of concentration. Gods, since I have seen the supernatural powers and miracles of extraordinary
                        transformations that are the skillful means of the tathāgatas of the past, I know. So surely the Tathāgata
                        will indeed wish to expound and spread the king of sūtras of the great vehicle called <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Extraordinary Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s
                            Powers</title>. Moreover, gods, the tathāgatas do not enter parinirvāṇa, because there is no
                        parinirvāṇa of the tathāgatas, nor are their lives ever exhausted. The tathāgatas remain for immeasurable
                        millions of eons, for utterly inexpressible eons. But through their skillful means they display their
                        parinirvāṇa to beings, as well as the disappearance of the noble Dharma. Just as the Tathāgata sees the
                        various beings of an impure nature who are to be converted by means of parinirvāṇa or by relics, who have
                        no faith in the Tathāgata, and who are irreverent toward the master, so in each such case the Tathāgata
                        displays his parinirvāṇa. But in fact, the Tathāgata neither comes nor goes. When the roots of virtue of
                        beings have fully matured, <ref cRef="F.149.a"/> and they long to look upon the Tathāgata, are worthy of
                        veneration, long to listen to the Dharma, and their longing is like the full moon, at that time, the
                        Tathāgata appears in the world for the benefit and happiness of many beings such as gods and humans, and
                        for the sake of manifesting and propagating the Three Jewels to them.<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-224">Translated on the basis of the Tibetan. The Sanskrit is based on a
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yāvad</foreign> construction: “The Tathāgata appears in the
                            world, for the benefit of many beings, for the happiness of many beings and so on, up to manifesting
                            and propagating the Three Jewels to men and gods.”</note> But in fact, the Tathāgata is not born, nor
                        does he age or die. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-48"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Sons of noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, although many forms might appear and
                        disappear in a well-polished mirror, one never sees the reflected image actually entering the mirror or
                        leaving it.<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-225">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gzugs brnyan</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratibimba</foreign>. The images appearing in the mirror are nothing but reflections. </note>
                        Gods, you should also look upon the body of the Tathāgata in this way. </p>
                    <p tid="53">“Sons of noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, a well-trained conjurer displays various
                        cities, archways, parks, vehicles, physical forms of a universal monarch, amusements, and entertainments.
                        Even if he makes these illusions cease, they do not move anywhere, nor do they come or go. You should
                        regard the appearance of the tathāgatas and their parinirvāṇa in the same way. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-49"/>
                    <p tid="54">“Moreover, gods, the tathāgatas, even though a thousand years, an eon, or ten million eons may
                        have elapsed since their parinirvāṇa, because of their former vows, and on account of the fact that
                        sentient beings worship them, venerate them, construct relic stūpas, create images, recite their names,
                        and preserve and venerate the holy Dharma, liberate beings from all the hells, animal births, the world of
                        Yama, downfalls into inopportune existences, unfortunate destinies, bad rebirths, and all suffering, even
                        though these tathāgatas might belong to different world systems, <ref cRef="F.149.b"/> until beings
                        gradually attain unsurpassable, truly perfect enlightenment.<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-226">This passage was translated from the Sanskrit fragments. As Schopen
                            points out, the Tibetan cannot be followed here since the syntax of the sentence is problematic: “by
                            introducing <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems can</foreign> here as the logical subject of
                            the sentence, [the Tibetan] has completely changed the meaning of the passage” (1978: 333). D reads:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yang lha’i bu dag sngon gyi smon lam gyis de bzhin gshegs
                                pa mya ngan las ’das nas lo stod lon pa’am/ mya ngan las ’das nas bskal par lon pa’am/ mya ngan
                                las ’das nas bskal pa bye bar lon yang sems can rnams kyis mchod par bya ba dang / bkur stir bya
                                ba dang / ring bsrel gyi mchod rten byed du gzhug pa dang / sku gzugs byed du gzhug pa dang /
                                mtshan nas brjod pa dang / dam pa’i chos ’dzin pa dang / mchod pa byed pa’i sems can ’jig rten gyi
                                khams sna tshogs na gnas pa rnams thar par mdzad de sems can dmyal ba dang / dud ’gro'i skye gnas
                                dang / gshin rje’i ’jig rten dang / mi khom pa dang / ngan song dang / ngan ’gro log par ltung ba
                                thams cad dang / sdug <ref cRef="F.149.b"/> bsngal thams cad las yongs su thar par mdzad nas rim
                                gyis bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs pa’i byang chub kyi bar du mngon par rdzogs par ’tshang
                                rgya bar ’gyur na/</foreign> Unfortunately, the other Kangyurs we consulted are not helpful here.
                            Schopen suggests reading the long Sanskrit compound °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇa­pūjanā</foreign> (1978: 332 §1296) as a dative: °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūjanān nānā-</foreign>. This emendation is justified by the fact that the loss of a
                            final dental followed by the same consonant is frequent in the Gilgit manuscripts (1978: 336, n9). We
                            have chosen to follow Schopen’s suggestion. However, it should be added that another problem is
                            involved with Schopen’s reading: the verb <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mokṣayanti</foreign>
                            has no object in the emended Sanskrit sentence. Schopen therefore also has to add the logical object
                            satvān to the sentence on top of his emendation of the compound °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇa­pūjanā</foreign>. An alternative reading based on the principle of
                            lectio difficilior would be to accept Schopen’s emendation °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">saddharmedharaṇa­pūjanān</foreign> but to read it as a bahuvrīhi (accusative plural) instead of a
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tatpuruṣa</foreign> (dative singular). The preceding
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satvānām</foreign> could be read in this case as a
                            partitive genitive: “those who have veneration, etc. (i.e., °<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūjanān</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bahuvrīhi</foreign> acc. plu.) among
                            sentient beings (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satvānām</foreign> = partitive genitive).” The
                            complete sentence would read: “Moreover, gods, although a thousand years, an eon, or ten million eons
                            may have elapsed since the tathāgatas attained parinirvāṇa, on account of their former vows, they
                            liberate from all the hells, animal births, the world of Yama, downfalls into inopportune existences,
                            unfortunate destinies, and bad rebirths those who among beings worship them, venerate them, construct
                            relic stūpas, create images, recite their names, and preserve and venerate the holy Dharma...”</note>
                        Thus, what need is there to mention those who worship the tathāgatas in person by offering them flowers,
                        incense, perfume, garlands, salves, clothes, and aromatic powders? Gods, even though one thousand years,
                        an eon, or even ten million eons may have elapsed since the Bhagavān Buddha entered parinirvāṇa, if some
                        beings throw a flower in the sky, after calling the Tathāgata by his name seven times and saying ‘Homage
                        to the Buddha,’ they will all bring an end to their suffering. But, let alone throwing a flower in the
                        sky, if someone, whoever they might be, faithfully emulating the Tathāgata, strives to maintain even a
                        single precept in order to honor the Tathāgata, or strives to focus on worshipping the Tathāgata even for
                        a single day, or a single night, or a single moment, this person will put an end to suffering and
                        gradually, fully, and completely awaken to unsurpassable, truly perfect enlightenment. If even those who,
                        in order to honor the Tathāgata, laugh, have fun, joke like fools, play games, or make a stūpa from sand
                        will all put an end to suffering and fully and completely awaken to unsurpassable, truly perfect
                        enlightenment, what need is there to mention those who have built relic stūpas or relic images and,
                        understanding that compassion toward all beings is the most important thing, think, ‘I shall liberate all
                        beings from suffering’? And what need is there to mention those who, having produced the thought directed
                        toward unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening, <ref cRef="F.150.a"/> make offerings of divine flowers and
                        incense, garlands, salves, aromatic powders, cymbals, umbrellas, and royal banners? Those who have thus
                        made offerings to all the tathāgatas will be free from birth, old age, sickness, and death, as well as
                        from misery, lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and afflictions. And as long as they have not completely
                        and fully awakened to unsurpassable, truly perfect awakening, they will be reborn in pleasant forms of
                        existence. Gods, thus can one discern the aspiration of the tathāgatas of the past and be in perfect
                        agreement with it.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-50"/>
                    <p tid="55">Then, those gods thought, “Oh, this youthful Mañjuśrī is endowed with great insight. If the
                        tathāgatas possess supreme skillful means, what does it mean when Mañjuśrī says that the tathāgatas remain
                        in the world systems and bring beings to spiritual maturity through various skillful means, even though
                        ten billion eons have passed many times over since the tathāgatas attained nirvāṇa?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-51"/>
                    <p tid="56">The youthful Mañjuśrī, having clairvoyantly understood what those gods were thinking, said, “Gods,
                        excellent! Excellent! Just wait a moment. These thoughts arising in your mind, as well as your earlier
                        question, are also the sovereign power of the Tathāgata.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-52"/>
                    <p tid="57">At this, the Blessed One displayed his supernatural powers and the tathāgatas Śikhin, Viśvabhū,
                        Krakucchanda, Kanakamuni, Vipāśyin, Akṣobhya, and Amitābha appeared in his surrounding retinue, sitting on
                        lion thrones surrounded by the saṅgha of śrāvakas and <ref cRef="F.150.b"/> bodhisattvas, and taught the
                        Dharma to an ocean-like retinue. They too displayed those same types of supernatural powers by manifesting
                        many tathāgatas sitting on their lion thrones, expounding the Dharma throughout the world systems of the
                        east, south, west, and north. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-53"/>
                    <p tid="58">The retinue of all those gathered and the gods rejoiced, jubilated, and were pleased. Having
                        themselves increased the power of the roots of virtue arising from their merit, they worshipped the
                        tathāgatas with flowers, incense, perfume, garlands, salves, garments, and ornaments, and circumambulated
                        them three times, proclaiming the following verses:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-54"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“How wonderful is this gnosis!</l>
                        <l>For this, one should practice the state of concentration and insight!</l>
                        <l>Just like lights illuminating the world, </l>
                        <l>This great hero will remain</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-55"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“For the benefit of beings</l>
                        <l>For many eons after his nirvāṇa.</l>
                        <l>Surrounded by bodhisattvas,</l>
                        <l>He is seated on a lion throne.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-56"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“Seeing the Buddha is excellent.</l>
                        <l>Listening to the Dharma is excellent.</l>
                        <l>Likewise, observing a spiritual friend</l>
                        <l>And listening to him is also excellent.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-57"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“All the precepts of the body</l>
                        <l>That preserve the training are excellent.</l>
                        <l>Those who have diligently perfected them</l>
                        <l>Will all achieve awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-58"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“Those who are skillful in means and insight</l>
                        <l>Will liberate beings in this world.</l>
                        <l>Like the orb of the moon,</l>
                        <l>Like a conjurer,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-59"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“The Tathāgata shows himself</l>
                        <l>To come and go.</l>
                        <l>Because they have stūpas,</l>
                        <l>Drawings, and images made</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-60"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“And they honor and worship him,</l>
                        <l>Those who remember his name</l>
                        <l>And live for the sake of awakening</l>
                        <l>Will all attain liberation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-61"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Since they pay homage to the Tathāgata, <ref cRef="F.151.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Listen to the noble Dharma,</l>
                        <l>And worship and retain it accordingly,</l>
                        <l>They will be free from all suffering.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-62"/>
                    <p tid="67">As the Tathāgata imparted this instruction on the sovereign power and the miracle of the
                        extraordinary transformation of a tathāgata, sixty-four thousand beings reached the stage where they
                        accepted that phenomena are not produced.<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-227">See
                            Sasaki 1986: “[<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</foreign>] represents
                            the fact that emptiness or the absolute experience is beyond the thinkable, and therefore in the
                            failure of the intellect, designation is impossible. One can only refer to being unborn (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anutpattika</foreign>) in the absolute sense. The inclination or
                            willingness to make this absolute statement is called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>... Buddhist <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṣānti</foreign>, however, is
                            a willing acceptance of the unborn” (138–139).</note> Twenty thousand beings completely purified the
                        eye of Dharma that sees all phenomena. Five thousand gods remained without grasping, their minds freed
                        from defilements. They were led to the stage of a non-returner. Seven hundred monks, nuns, and male and
                        female lay vow holders attained various states of concentration.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-63"/>
                    <p tid="68">King Prasenajit said to the youthful Mañjuśrī, “Son of the Victorious One, in your answers to the
                        questions that were asked for the benefit of all beings, what you said was excellent, it was excellent
                        indeed. Yet I still have a few doubts. Therefore, please expound upon and answer my questions, which are
                        about beings applying their minds to what they have heard and thus becoming free from the suffering of
                        saṃsāra, passing into fortunate forms of existence, and never falling back from unsurpassable, truly
                        perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-64"/>
                    <p tid="69">Mañjuśrī replied, “Great king, it is excellent that you have developed your previous roots of
                        merit and that your confidence has increased through the sovereign power of the Tathāgata. Whatever you
                        wish to know, ask and I shall explain it to you.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-65"/>
                    <p tid="70">The king said, “Son of the Victorious One, just by hearing the names of the tathāgatas and
                        honoring and serving them, beings who perform negative actions will be liberated from rebirths as denizens
                        of the hells and animals, as well as from Yama’s world, and will pass into pleasant forms of existence.
                        Who are those beings? In which world system do they abide? How should we honor them?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-66"/>
                    <p tid="71">Mañjuśrī <ref cRef="F.151.b"/> replied, “Son of noble family, listen. I shall elucidate the reason
                        why these beings will not pass into negative forms of existence. I shall state the names of the blessed
                        ones, the tathāgatas, who will liberate them from rebirths in negative forms of existence, from rebirths
                        as denizens of the hells and animals, and from Yama’s world, and I shall state how they are to be
                        worshipped and venerated in their respective world systems. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-67"/>
                    <p tid="72">“In the world system called Vaiḍūrya Light abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect
                        Buddha called Bhaiṣajyaguru Vaidūryaprabharāja,<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-228">
                            In the Tibetan text, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyal po</foreign> (-rāja) is
                            missing.</note> who watches over beings as well as teaches the Dharma. In the world system called
                            <term type="ignore">Śikhin</term> abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called
                        Śikhin. In the world system called Vimalā abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called
                        Stainless Arising. In the world system called Peace abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect
                        Buddha called Established in Peace. In the world system called Sukhāvatī abides the Tathāgata, the Arhat,
                        the truly perfect Buddha called Amitābha. In the world system called Lotus Excellence abides the
                        Tathāgata, the Arhat, the truly perfect Buddha called Lotus Born. In the world system called Vajra abides
                        the Tathāgata called Indestructible Vajra. In the world system called Aśoka abides the Tathāgata called
                        Vigataśoka. In the world system called Fearless abides the Tathāgata called Pacifier of All Fears. In the
                        world system called Endowed with Realization and Intelligence abides the Tathāgata called Purifier of All
                        Rebirths. In the world system called Free from Negative Forms of Existence abides the Tathāgata called
                            <ref cRef="F.152.a"/> Pacifier of All Negative Forms of Existence. In the world system called Vimalā
                        abides the Tathāgata called He Whose Intelligence Has Been Completely Purified. In the world system called
                        Possessed of Power abides the Tathāgata called Powerful Intelligence. By calling them by their names, one
                        will become the lord of the gods. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-68"/>
                    <p tid="73">“In the world system called Moon abides the Tathāgata called Stainless Full Moon. By calling him
                        by his name and worshipping him, one will be completely liberated from all defilements. In the world
                        system called Excellent Attainment abides the Tathāgata called Pacifier of All Negative Forms of
                        Existence. By calling him by his name and worshipping him, one will be liberated from negative forms of
                        existence. In the world system called Perfect Light abides the Tathāgata called He Who Looks at All Beings
                        with Love. By calling him by his name and worshipping him, all worldly beings will be completely
                        delighted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-69"/>
                    <p tid="74">“Son of noble family, in a word, even if a sextillion years or a hundred eons have passed since
                        the tathāgatas Ānandaśrī, Candanaśrī, Hero, Subjugator of All Demon Forces, Śikhin, Viśvabhū,
                        Krakucchanda, Kanakamuni, and Kāśyapa have manifested nirvāṇa, great king, all beings will be liberated
                        from negative rebirths and negative forms of existence by calling the names of these buddhas; by having
                        relic stūpas, drawings, and representations made; by worshipping and honoring them with lamps, incense,
                        flowers, and perfume; and by maintaining the training, way of life, austerities, discipline, <ref cRef="F.152.b"/> and fasting. </p>
                    <p tid="75">“Karmic obscurations that remain for eons, such as those stemming from the five actions with
                        immediate results, will be purified. One will pass to pleasant forms of existence and not to negative
                        ones, and one will gradually, fully, and completely awaken to unsurpassable, complete, and perfect
                        awakening. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-70"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Suppose that sons or daughters of noble family with a feeble recollection of faith and bodhicitta
                        commission drawings or clay statues of those tathāgatas. Suppose they do so to liberate friends and
                        relatives, and for the sake of beings who engage in negative actions, abandon the noble Dharma, denigrate
                        the noble ones, commit the five actions with immediate results, take a life, steal the wealth of the Three
                        Jewels, go to the Avīci hell, or take birth in the three negative forms of existence. And suppose that
                        once they have commissioned the drawings or statues, they focus principally on generating compassion
                        toward all these beings and adopt the noble eightfold path. And then suppose they worship the tathāgatas
                        three times in the night and three times in the day with flowers, incense, perfume, garlands, salves,
                        lamps, cymbals, royal banners, and flags, from the eighth day of the waxing moon until the fifteenth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-71"/>
                    <p tid="77">“Now, in order to liberate beings, the buddhas, the blessed ones, know with their tathāgatas’
                        gnosis, hear with their divine ear, and see with their divine eye, so when sons or daughters of noble
                        family dedicate their merit so that such beings will pass to pleasant forms of existence and accomplish
                        wholesome deeds instead of negative ones, <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> in order to liberate the beings born in
                        negative forms of existence, they should supplicate the tathāgatas. They should dedicate their merit in
                        this way: ‘May negative actions be attenuated through confessing and acknowledging faults! May the names
                        of the tathāgatas be heard! May beings be liberated from all negative forms of existence! Until they fully
                        and perfectly awaken to unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening, may their conduct be in accordance
                        with that of Mañjuśrī himself!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-72"/>
                    <p tid="78">“Moreover, if one copies the different teachings of the Dharma or commissions this activity, keeps
                        them in mind, recites them, and worships them, then due to the power of the aspiration of the past
                        tathāgatas, the names of the buddhas will reach the ears of beings born in Avīci hell and in the three
                        negative forms of existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-73"/>
                    <p tid="79">“In addition, through the power of these different methods of the Dharma, all negative actions
                        will be attenuated. Through the power of the tathāgatas’ majesty and their various Dharma discourses, one
                        will be aware of wholesome and unwholesome actions. Thus one will subsequently not commit negative
                        actions. One will then be liberated from the various kinds of suffering and pass to pleasant rebirths.
                        Until one reaches unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening, the state of truly perfect awakening,
                        one’s actions will be conducive to it. </p>
                    <p tid="80">“Thus, these Dharma discourses are endowed with many positive properties. They are like the great
                        maṇi jewel. Just like the great maṇi jewel, the wish-fulfilling jewel, they accomplish all wishes. All
                        negative actions are subjugated. All gates to the negative forms of existence are closed. All gates to the
                        pleasant forms of existence and the buddhas’ realms are opened. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-74"/>
                    <p tid="81">“So, son of noble family, owing to the tathāgatas’ various skillful means, aspirations,
                        extraordinary transformations, sovereign power, and states of concentration, <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> one
                        will pass to pleasant forms of existence and be liberated from all negative ones by continuously listening
                        to and worshipping those who have remained in the various world systems, even if a hundred eons have
                        passed since the tathāgatas’ nirvāṇa. Therefore, what need is there to mention the importance of keeping
                        in mind the Dharma, reading it, copying it or commissioning this action, or accurately teaching it in a
                        detailed way to others? Suppose a son or daughter of noble family comes to possess this excellent quality.
                        Except for the tathāgatas, no one could easily express the excellent quality of that being’s accumulation
                        of merit and of his or her roots of virtue. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-75"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Great king, you should thus rely on this excellent quality and keep in mind the various Dharma
                        discourses. You should read them. You should explain them. You should worship them. You should make your
                        faith in the Three Jewels integral to you. You should always worship and venerate the tathāgatas and
                        correctly grasp their teachings. Being repulsed by saṃsāra, you should be vigilant and focus your thoughts
                        on its momentariness. Moreover, great king, the pursuit of their desires keeps beings in a state of
                        suffering for sextillions of eons. That is, they will experience the suffering of arising and cessation,
                        the suffering of being in the womb, the suffering of rebirth as a hell being or an animal, or the
                        suffering of the world of Yama, the suffering of poverty, and the suffering of being cut, bruised, beaten,
                        struck, and burnt. Therefore, you should proceed to abandon all conditioned phenomena. Great king, you
                        should give priority to compassion and long for the Dharma and liberation.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-76"/>
                    <p tid="83">King Prasenajit, together with his entire retinue, said to Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, this is excellent,
                        most excellent! By bringing down the rain of the Dharma, <ref cRef="F.154.a"/> you have made us content
                        and happy. As we have set out upon the state of awakening, you have made us vigilant.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-77"/>
                    <p tid="84">An eager bodhisattva then asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, suppose someone adopts the various
                        teachings of the Dharma, reads them, teaches them in detail to others, copies them or commissions their
                        copying, and honors those who copy, adopt, and recite the teachings with flowers, incense, perfume,
                        garlands, salves, garments, and ornaments. How much would the merit of this person increase, Blessed One?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-78"/>
                    <p tid="85">The Blessed One replied, “If sons or daughters of noble family, kings, ministers, monks, nuns,
                        male lay vow holders, or female lay vow holders keep in mind the various teachings of the Dharma with
                        faith in the Tathāgata, worship them, copy them or commission their copying, and teach them correctly,
                        they will attain the eight great qualities. What are those eight great qualities? None of the diseases or
                        harm in the world will affect them at all. All yakṣas, bhūtas, and piśācas who rob people of their
                        radiance will abide in loving-kindness. No harmful influences from kṛtyās, kākhordas, spell-casters, or
                        vetālas will injure their body. Having pleased all the kings, ministers, brahmins, householders, monks,
                        nuns, and male and female lay vow holders, they will accomplish all aims. All the gods will congregate
                        before them. They will pass to pleasant forms of existence. They will be accepted by Vajrapāṇi. They will
                        be born wherever they might wish and will remember the succession of their former lives. In this way those
                        sons or daughters of noble family, and the others, will <ref cRef="F.154.b"/> attain the eight great
                        qualities. Thus, for one hundred thousand years they will venerate these tathāgatas with the divine and
                        manifest offerings meant for a tathāgata. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-79"/>
                    <p tid="86">“Suppose someone were to fill Jambudvīpa with tathāgatas’ relic stūpas made of the seven precious
                        substances, and then venerate, revere, and worship them for one hundred thousand years with divine
                        garlands, salves, flowers, lamps, precious umbrellas, cymbals, royal banners, and flags—compared to such a
                        person, someone who keeps in mind the various teachings of the Dharma with faith in the Tathāgata and who
                        reads them, worships them, copies them or commissions their copying, and teaches them correctly to others
                        will have a vastly greater increase in merit. Son of noble family, suppose someone were to set the beings
                        of Jambudvīpa on the noble eightfold path and, after having done so, venerated and worshipped the
                        Tathāgata for a hundred thousand divine years with all the necessities of life there might be—compared to
                        such a person, someone who listens to just one four-line stanza drawn from the various teachings of the
                        Dharma, keeps it in mind, copies it or commissions it to be copied, and promulgates it to others will have
                        a vastly greater increase in merit.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-80"/>
                    <p tid="87">When the Blessed One had explained in detail the significance of the various teachings of the
                        Dharma, he then spoke the following verses: </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-81"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>“Abiding in one trillion other fields,</l>
                        <l>Ten million skillful buddhas</l>
                        <l>Care for beings</l>
                        <l>And liberate them from negative forms of existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-82"/>
                    <lg tid="89">
                        <l>“After you have performed actions of generosity</l>
                        <l>By engaging in ceaseless activity,</l>
                        <l>You should worship the tathāgatas by longing for the Dharma</l>
                        <l>In order to liberate those who have gone to negative forms of existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-83"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>“Produce drawings, stūpas, and various representations;</l>
                        <l>Have statues made,</l>
                        <l>Some of gold or silver, some of metal or clay;</l>
                        <l>And worship them with various offerings. <ref cRef="F.155.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-84"/>
                    <lg tid="91">
                        <l>“Worship the tathāgatas with flowers, garlands, salves,</l>
                        <l>Lamps, cymbals, perfume, and incense.</l>
                        <l>With superior insight, dedicate merit as well.</l>
                        <l>Explain the teachings of the sūtras, and abide by them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-85"/>
                    <lg tid="92">
                        <l>“The majesty of the Tathāgata and of the collection of sūtras</l>
                        <l>Will liberate beings from negative actions.</l>
                        <l>They will take rebirth in pure abodes</l>
                        <l>Until they reach unsurpassable awakening.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-86"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>“They will remember their former actions, and having done so,</l>
                        <l>Those who understand will not commit negative actions again.</l>
                        <l>By expounding the bodhisattvas’ collection of sūtras for the sake of humans,<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-229"> S (347a.5) <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byang
                                    chub sems dpa’</foreign> instead of D (155a.2) <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byang
                                    chub sems dpas</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>They will obtain great merit.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-87"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>“They will be protected by the gods.</l>
                        <l>In their bodies no disease will occur.</l>
                        <l>Nowhere in their kingdoms will there be strife,</l>
                        <l>And in their homes, villages, and cities there will be peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-88"/>
                    <lg tid="95">
                        <l>“Whoever holds at all times this collection of sutrās</l>
                        <l>Holds at all times the treasury of the buddhas.</l>
                        <l>Whoever worships and venerates it, has it copied, and makes it heard,</l>
                        <l>They, without doing anything else,</l>
                        <l>Will perfectly worship the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>And will quickly attain supreme awakening.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-89"/>
                    <p tid="96">The eager bodhisattva mahāsattva asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One, I have some qualms about
                        this. Having come into possession of a kingdom with this body, will one again experience suffering? Or
                        will there not be any sorrow when one circles in saṃsāra? Or alternatively, as one will experience again
                        birth, old age, sickness, death, misery, despair, lamentation, suffering, and unhappiness, how will one be
                        born, die, live, and gain happiness? How will one experience suffering?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-90"/>
                    <p tid="97">The Blessed One answered the eager bodhisattva mahāsattva, “You who are eager, you should consider
                        that these experiences are conditioned by karma. Now, son of noble family, <ref cRef="F.155.b"/> there is
                        no birth, no death, no life in this world. Son of noble family, although there is no old age and death
                        here, one’s state of life is always dependent on the body consciousness.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-230">D (155b.1) <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tsho ba’i khams ni
                                rtag tu lus kyis par shes pa la gnas so</foreign> does not make sense. We followed the alternative
                            reading found in most other Kangyurs: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’tsho ba’i khams ni rtag
                                tu lus kyi rnam par shes pa la gnas so</foreign>.</note> Furthermore, when one transmigrates to
                        various births due to karmic conditions and karmic circumstances, one will experience happiness and
                        suffering. One has the notion of happiness as happiness and suffering as suffering. One gives rise to the
                        notion that non-happiness is not happiness and that non-suffering is not suffering. Nonetheless, until one
                        possesses the qualities of nirvāṇa in the realm of nirvāṇa without remainder, one will still be subject to
                        sorrow. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-91"/>
                    <p tid="98">“Son of noble family, it is as follows. As an analogy, consider someone who puts on new clothes.
                        Having put them on, this person performs all sorts of actions and experiences happiness and suffering.
                        Later, at another time, this person is finally told that these clothes, being old and moth-eaten, are
                        dirty, upon which he realizes that they should be thrown away, and thus he gets rid of them. Once he is
                        rid of them, he again looks for brand new clothes to wear. When he has put them on, he performs various
                        actions and experiences happiness and suffering. Until this person has put on genuine clothes that are
                        durable and everlasting, indestructible and unbreakable, then though many eons pass, one after another, he
                        will either have to wear such temporary clothes or throw them away. He does not think about this nor
                        reflect upon it; he is under the influence of the body. Likewise, son of noble family, at a certain time,
                        due to one’s state of life, one’s body perishes and is seen to be on the point of collapse. At that time,
                        one discards this body and looks for another that is new and young. Taking it on and performing actions
                        with it, one will experience happiness and suffering. Just as clothes arisen from one’s own merit are
                        soft, hard, or rough, so too one adopts the body that one takes on according to one’s state of life. Just
                        as one is born according to one’s roots of virtue—namely, one’s karmic conditions—one will be born as a
                        god, a king, <ref cRef="F.156.a"/> a hell being, an animal, or a being from the world of Yama. Although
                        this body is also influenced by one’s state of life and is given up according to one’s state of life, one
                        does not think about this, nor reflect upon it. Son of noble family, you should look upon the body just as
                        you look upon these clothes. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-92"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Son of noble family, it is like a snake that, when the time has come on account of karmic
                        conditions, sheds its skin, and then comes and goes in keeping with its physical shape. Although the snake
                        will experience happiness and suffering, it does not think about its skin nor reflect upon it. You should
                        look upon your state of life just as you look upon this snake. </p>
                    <p tid="100">“Son of noble family, it is like a tree that, after it has developed its leaves and foliage, will
                        then, with time, evolve so that finally they wither and fall. And then yet later again, with time, it will
                        grow buds, branches, foliage, flowers, and fruit. Son of noble family, it is in this way that you should
                        look upon arising and cessation due to karmic conditions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-93"/>
                    <p tid="101">“Now, son of noble family, some time in the future beings will experience more greed, attachment,
                        anger, envy, and pride. As they cause the scales and weights of karma to move,<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-231">This metaphor is probably used here to explain the dynamics of cause and
                            effect in relation to karma. Asaṅga uses the same metaphor to explain rebirth (see <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­dharma­samuccaya</title> II.1 trans. in Rahula 2001: 94), and it is found
                            in similar contexts in the Tibetan commentarial literature. </note> their behavior will follow upon
                        pleasure and attachment, so that they will commit more negative actions based upon or caused by their
                        attachment. Committing more negative actions, they will experience suffering. They who construe
                        impermanent things as permanent and the impure as pure will not venerate the Buddha, the Dharma, and the
                        Saṅgha. These infantile people will not seek out a spiritual friend. Instead, they will mock and ridicule
                        those who teach them the Dharma, rather than having faith or trust in them. Such beings will perform
                        negative actions. They will adopt the body that they take on and which they will experience in keeping
                        with karmic conditions and according to their particular state of life. <ref cRef="F.156.b"/> They will
                        then give rise to notions of suffering and pleasure. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-94"/>
                    <p tid="102">“Son of noble family, this is the answer of the Tathāgata. This body should be regarded as
                        karmically conditioned. For this body also there is no death, there is no life; happiness and suffering
                        will not be experienced but they will arise and cease according to karmic causes and conditions. The
                        tathāgatas have undergone sextillions of hardships for the sake of beings. Having completely given up all
                        their possessions, they become perfectly awakened within unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening,
                        and establish all beings, too, in great nirvāṇa.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-95"/>
                    <p tid="103">At that point, the Tathāgata’s sovereign power caused the whole earth to tremble. The assembled
                        retinue said to the Tathāgata, “Excellent!” King Prasenajit and the others, by means of many, great, more
                        and more powerful supernatural powers, made an offering to the Tathāgata of five hundred divine garments.
                        Trembling, they circumambulated the Tathāgata three times. In the presence of all the tathāgatas, each of
                        them confessed that the faults consisting of all their negative actions had indeed been committed, and
                        they promised to adopt the training. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-96"/>
                    <p tid="104">At the same time, the assembled retinue exclaimed, “Tathāgata, we pay homage to those who have
                        turned away from all births, freed all beings from suffering, and attained liberation. Homage to them!
                        Blessed One, in the future, we will not take any delight in the experiences of suffering in saṃsāra.
                        Blessed One, we pray that you liberate us from birth, old age, disease, death, misery, despair,
                        lamentation, suffering, unhappiness, and distress.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-97"/>
                    <p tid="105">The Blessed One replied, “Sons of noble family, with roots of virtue that focus upon diligent
                        application, may you acquire the superior intention directed at the Three Jewels. Know all conditioned
                        phenomena to be impermanent and like illusions. <ref cRef="F.157.a"/> Be filled with joy at upholding the
                        holy Dharma. May you worship, revere, and venerate it more and more. Know it as supreme compassion for all
                        beings. Consider the one who expounds the Dharma as a tathāgata. Consider virtuous friends as gurus. Keep
                        in mind, cultivate, and spread the various Dharma discourses. Sons of noble family, you will be liberated
                        from all sufferings, all births, old age, disease, death, misery, unhappiness, and great distress. You
                        will be liberated from the noose of saṃsāra. Practice the roots of virtue, that is, the noble eightfold
                        path. May you turn away from the state of not being vigilant. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-98"/>
                    <p tid="106">“Sons of noble family, once beings adopt even a single training of the Tathāgata for only a short
                        while, they will be liberated from all suffering, experience pleasant rebirths, and will not experience
                        negative forms of existence. That being so, what need is there to mention those who, after abandoning
                        jokes, amusement, pleasure, and games, through their sublime devotion to the Tathāgata perform rituals to
                        him, live with superior intentions, and practice the restoration and purification of their vows with the
                        eight-branched fasting ritual? What need is there to mention that all those who practice these sorts of
                        conduct will not be born in the three negative forms of existence, but will pass to pleasant ones, and
                        that, having experienced the happiness of gods and humans, their suffering will come to an end so that
                        gradually they will fully and completely awaken to unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-99"/>
                    <p tid="107">“Whoever has the body of a woman tainted by the fundamental and secondary defilements, if they
                        genuinely take refuge in the Three Jewels and adopt the training, whether for one day, half a day, or just
                        a moment, <ref cRef="F.157.b"/> they will all dispel that condition of being a woman, suffering,
                        unhappiness, and afflictions. Having put an end to suffering, they will go to pleasant forms of existence
                        until they become fully and perfectly awakened buddhas within unsurpassable, complete, and perfect
                        awakening. Sons of noble family, the infantile do not recognize that one who genuinely takes up the
                        pledges and the training commitments of body, speech, and mind is endowed with many qualities and great
                        roots of virtue.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-100"/>
                    <p tid="108"><!--modularPassage type=auspiciousSigns-->At that moment, a great noise resounded in the sky. All
                        the retinue marveled, upon which a great rain of flowers and perfume fell.<!--/modularPassage-->
                        <!--modularPassage type=multipleResult-->One hundred thousand beings were all liberated from suffering and
                        established in unsurpassable, complete, and perfect awakening—the spiritual level from which there can be
                        no relapse. Moreover, ten million beings focused upon taking refuge in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, and
                        generated bodhicitta for the first time.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-101"/>
                    <p tid="109">The tathāgatas, too, all disappeared. Then, Vajrapāṇi and the others, all the vajra holders,
                        Śakra, Brahmā, the protectors of the world, and the four kings spoke these words to the Blessed One: </p>
                    <p tid="110">“Thanks to the Tathāgata, we have respite. We have heard the Dharma discourses and the names of
                        the tathāgatas. To the Blessed One, we have dedicated our countries, cities, and temples, as well as our
                        bodies and lives, so that the Dharma will be taught, copied, recited, worshipped, and proclaimed. We will
                        preserve it. We will protect it. We will accomplish all its purposes. We will ensure that wealth and
                        grains are well provided. We will ensure that the Blessed One will be venerated everywhere. We will ensure
                        that people are free from all diseases. We will ensure that we give mindfulness, power, and inspiration.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-102"/>
                    <p tid="111">The Blessed One <ref cRef="F.158.a"/> declared, “Excellent. This is excellent!” And he told them,
                        “At all costs, make sure in this way that these teachings of the Dharma, which are the pledge of the
                        Tathāgata, will not quickly disappear.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-103"/>
                    <p tid="112"><!--modularPassage type=concludingPraise-->When the Blessed One had spoken in this way, all the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattvas, such as Noble Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, and others, as well as the great
                        śrāvakas and the entire retinue, and the world of the gods, human beings, asuras, and gandharvas, rejoiced
                        and praised what the Blessed One had said.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-104"/>
                    <p tid="113"> Here ends the noble Mahāyāna sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Teaching on the Extraordinary
                            Transformation that is the Miracle of Attaining the Buddha’s Powers</title>.</p>
                </div>
                <!--<div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="125">Colophon</head>
                    
                </div>-->
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="126">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="127">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-105">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (sde dge) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-106">
                        <abbr>H</abbr>
                        <expan>Lhasa (zhol) Kangyur </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-107">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang (snar thang) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-108">
                        <abbr>U</abbr>
                        <expan>Urga (khu re) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-109">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stog Palace (stog pho brang)</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-061-006-110">
                        <abbr>Pd</abbr>
                        <expan>Pedurma (dpe bsdur ma) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="128">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="129">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-111">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo
                            (Ārya­buddha­balādhāna­prātihārya­vikurvāṇa­nirdeśa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra).</title> Toh 186, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 61, folios 143b–158a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-112">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 186, Narthang Kangyur vol. 61, folios 228a–251b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-113">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 186, Stok Palace Kangyur vol. 54, folios
                        332a–351b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-114">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sangs rgyas kyi stobs skyed pa’i cho ’phrul rnam par ’phrul ba bstan pa
                            zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo. bka’ ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the
                        Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                        Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
                        skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 61, pp. 387–420.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="130">Sanskrit Fragments</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-115">Schopen, Gregory. “The Five Leaves of the
                        Buddha­balā­dhāna­prāti­hārya­vikurvāna-nirdeśa-sūtra Found at Gilgit.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title>, vol. 5 (no. 4), 1978. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-116">Dutt, Nalinaksha. “Buddha­balā­dhāna­prātihārya-vikurvāna­nirdeśa-sūtra,”
                        in <title xml:lang="en">Gilgit Manuscripts</title>, vol. IV, 173-183. Calcutta, 1959; reprinted
                        Delhi: Sri Satguru Publications, 1984. [Note: an edition of the same fragments as in Schopen (1978) but
                        with numerous passages reconstructed from the Tibetan and inserted without annotation.] </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="131">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-117">Burnouf, Eugène. <title xml:lang="en">Introduction to the History of Indian
                            Buddhism</title>. Chicago &amp; London: University of Chicago Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-118">Chang, Garma C.C. (ed.). <title xml:lang="en">A Treasury of Mahāyāna
                            Sūtras: Selections from the Mahāratnakūṭa Sūtra</title>. New York: Pennsylvania State University,
                        1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-119">Cleary, Thomas (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Flower Ornament Scripture: A
                            Translation of the Avatamsaka Sutra</title>. Boston &amp; London: Shambhala, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-120">Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar
                            and Dictionary</title>. Vol. 2: Dictionary. New Haven: Yale University Press, 1953.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-121">La Vallée Poussin, Louis de (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Abhidharmakośabhāṣya of Vasubandhu</title>. Berkeley: Asian Humanities Press, 1988–90.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-122">Lamotte, Etienne (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra: The
                            Concentration of Heroic Progress</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-123">Rotman, Andy (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Divine Stories:
                            Divyāvadāna</title>, Part 1. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-124">Rahula, Walpola. <title xml:lang="en">Abhidharmasamuccaya: The Compendium
                            of Higher Teaching (philosophy) by Asanga</title>. Fremont: Asian Humanities Press, 2001.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-125">Sasaki, Genjun. <title xml:lang="en">Linguistic Approach to Buddhist
                            Thought</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-126">Schopen, Gregory. <title xml:lang="en">Figments and Fragments of Māhāyana
                            Buddhism in India: More Collected Papers</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-006-127">Vaidya, P.L. (ed.). <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title>. Buddhist
                        Sanskrit Texts No. 20. Darbhanga: Mithila Institute, 1959.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-128">
                            <term>attaining the Buddha’s powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs skyed pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་སྐྱེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">balādhāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-129">
                            <term>Blessed One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-130">
                            <term>karmic circumstances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལས་ཀྱི་གཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmavastu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-131">
                            <term>saṅgha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ’dun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་འདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṅgha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Community.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-132">
                            <term>eon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bskal pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྐལ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-133">
                            <term>Dharma discourse</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi rnam grangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmaparyāya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-134">
                            <term>nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan las ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Extinction of suffering.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-135">
                            <term>assurance</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཇིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśāradya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four kinds of <term type="ignore">assurance</term> of a tathāgata (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">catur­vaiśāraya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’jigs
                                    pa bzhi</foreign>) are: 1) <term type="ignore">assurance</term> concerning complete awakening (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhi­sambodhi­vaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad mkhyen pa la mi ’jigs pa</foreign>); 2) <term type="ignore">assurance</term> concerning the destruction of the
                                impurities (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakṣaya­vaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa zad pa mkhyen pa la mi ’jigs pa</foreign>); 3) <term type="ignore">assurance</term>
                                concerning harmful things (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">antarāyika­dharma­vaiśāradya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bar du gcod
                                    pa’i chos la mi ’jigs pa</foreign>); 4) <term type="ignore">assurance</term> concerning the path that leads to
                                emancipation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nairyāṇika­pratipad­vaiśāradya</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thob par ’gyur bar nges par ’byung ba’i lam la mi ’jigs
                                    pa</foreign>). (See Rahula 2001: 230, in which they are called “perfect
                                self-confidence”).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-136">
                            <term>female lay vow holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བསྙེན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsikā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-137">
                            <term>great trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-138">
                            <term>Mahāyāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Great Vehicle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-139">
                            <term>śrāvaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Hearer.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-140">
                            <term>insight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-141">
                            <term>extraordinary transformation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par ’phrul pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་འཕྲུལ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vikurvāṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-142">
                            <term>male lay vow holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge bsnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བསྙེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāsaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-143">
                            <term>miracle</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">cho ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོ་འཕྲུལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prātihārya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-144">
                            <term>monk</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge’ slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེའ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-145">
                            <term>nun</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge’ slong ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེའ་སློང་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣuṇī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-146">
                            <term>Omniscient One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad mkhyen pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvajñā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-147">
                            <term>bases of supernatural powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipādā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four <term type="ignore">bases of supernatural powers</term> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa
                                    bzhi</foreign>i) are: 1) concentration through will (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">chanda</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dun pa</foreign>); 2) concentration
                                through vigor (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus</foreign>); 3) concentration through the mind (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">citta</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam
                                    pa</foreign>); 4) concentration through investigation (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mīmāṃsā</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpyod pa</foreign>). See Rahula
                                2001: 163.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-148">
                            <term>power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ten <term type="ignore">powers</term> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">daśabala</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bcu</foreign>) of the Tathāgata are 1) the <term type="ignore">power</term>
                                of knowledge of what is possible and what is not possible (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sthānāsthāna­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnas dang gnas ma
                                    yin pa mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 2) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of the individual results of
                                actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karmasvaka­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi rnam smin mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 3) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of
                                knowledge of different practices leading to various destinies (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvatra­gāminī­prati­pajjñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad du ’gro ba’i lam mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 4) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of
                                knowledge of the different dispositions and tendencies of different beings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aneka­dhātu­nānā­dhātu­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khams sna tshogs mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 5) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of
                                the different aspirations of beings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nānādhi­mukti­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mos pa sna tshogs
                                    mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 6) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of the different degrees of
                                development of the faculties and inclinations of beings (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya­parāparya­jñānabala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po mchog
                                    dang mchog ma yin pa mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 7) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of the
                                absorptions, deliverances, concentrations, and attainments (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna­vimokṣa­samādhi­samāpatti­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan dang rnam thar dang ting nge ’dzin dang snyoms par ’jug pa thams cad mkhyen pa’i
                                    stobs</foreign>); 8) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of previous lives (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūrva­nivāsa­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngon gyi gnas rjes su dran pa mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); 9) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of the
                                deaths and births of beings according to their actions (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cyutyu­papāda­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho bo dang
                                    skye ba mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>); and 10) the <term type="ignore">power</term> of knowledge of the destruction of the
                                impurities (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āsravakṣaya­jñāna­bala</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zag pa zad pa mkhyen pa’i stobs</foreign>). (Rahula 2001:
                                229–230, n118).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-149">
                            <term>gnosis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-150">
                            <term>sextillion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bye ba khrag khrig brgya stong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱེ་བ་ཁྲག་ཁྲིག་བརྒྱ་སྟོང་།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-151">
                            <term>pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Solitary awakened one.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-152">
                            <term>state of concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-153">
                            <term>supernatural power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">supernatural powers</term> of a śrāvaka correspond to the first <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhijnā</foreign>: “Being one he becomes many, being many he
                                becomes one; he becomes visible, invisible; goes through walls, ramparts and mountains without
                                being impeded, just as through air; he immerses himself in the earth and emerges from it as if in
                                water; he goes on water without breaking through it, as if on [solid] earth; he travels through
                                the air crosslegged like a winged bird; he takes in his hands and touches the moon and the sun,
                                those two wonderful, mighty beings, and with his body he extends his power as far as the Brahma
                                world” (Lamotte 2003: 20). The great <term type="ignore">supernatural powers</term> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāṛddhi</foreign>) of bodhisattvas are: “causing trembling, blazing, illuminating,
                                rendering invisible, transforming, coming and going across obstacles, reducing or enlarging
                                worlds, inserting any matter into one’s own body, assuming the aspects of those one frequents,
                                appearing and disappearing, submitting everyone to one’s will, dominating the supernormal power of
                                others, giving intellectual clarity to those who lack it, giving mindfulness, bestowing happiness,
                                and finally, emitting beneficial rays.” (Lamotte 2003: 30).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-154">
                            <term>converted</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaineya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-155">
                            <term>yojana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpag tsad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔག་ཙད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-156">
                            <term>garlands of the buddhas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas phal po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཕལ་པོ་ཆེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhāvataṃsaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Here, the name of a particular state of concentration (but also the title of a
                                composite Mahāyāna sūtra or “family” of sūtras, Toh 44).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-157">
                            <term>sovereign power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byin gyi rlabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱིན་གྱི་རླབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhiṣṭhāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-158">
                            <term>eight branches of Āyurveda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe’i rig pa yan lag brgyad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚེའི་རིག་པ་ཡན་ལག་བརྒྱད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭāṅgāyurveda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The eight branches are: 1) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śalya</foreign> (surgery), 2) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śālākya</foreign>
                                (treatment of diseases of the head and neck), 3) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">agada</foreign> (treatment of poisoning), 4) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumāra
                                    bharaṇa</foreign> (pediatrics), 5) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāya
                                    cikitsā</foreign> (treatment of internal diseases), 6) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta kriyā</foreign> (treatment of diseases caused by spirits), 7) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vāji karaṇa</foreign> (aphrodisiacs), and 8) <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rasāyana</foreign> (rejuvenation).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-159">
                            <term>boiled oil</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’bru mar bskol ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྲུ་མར་བསྐོལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">taila</term>
                            <term type="definition">In Āyurvedic medicine, taila can be used both internally and externally. It is
                                produced by boiling herbs in edible oil, such as sesame seed oil.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-160">
                            <term>five actions with immediate results</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcānantarya­karman</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">five actions with immediate results</term> are: killing one’s mother, killing
                                one’s father, killing an arhat, intentionally wounding a buddha, and creating a schism in the
                                Saṅgha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-161">
                            <term>kṛtyā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshed byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤེད་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṛtyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A kind of female evil spirit or sorceress.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-162">
                            <term>kākhorda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kākhorda</term>
                            <term type="definition">A kind of evil spirit, often associated with vetālas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-163">
                            <term>vetāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ro langs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རོ་ལངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vetāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A kind of demon or evil spirit occupying a dead body; a zombie.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-164">
                            <term>Akṣobhya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ’khrugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་འཁྲུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akṣobhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Unmovable One.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-165">
                            <term>Amitābha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag tu med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་ཏུ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amitābha</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Infinite Light.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-166">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāvalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-167">
                            <term>Established in Peace</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu zhi bar bkod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་བཀོད་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-168">
                            <term>hero</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-169">
                            <term>Kanakamuni</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gser thub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསེར་ཐུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kanakamuni</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Golden Sage.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-170">
                            <term>Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāśyapa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-171">
                            <term>Krakucchanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">log par dang sal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལོག་པར་དང་སལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krakucchanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Destroyer of Saṃsāra.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-172">
                            <term>Lotus Born</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མོ་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">padmasaṃbhava</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-173">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maitreya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-174">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-175">
                            <term>Maudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maudgalyāyana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-176">
                            <term>Pacifier of All Fears</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs pa thams cad rab tu zhi bar mdzad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་པ་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་ཞི་བར་མཛད་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-177">
                            <term>Pacifier of All Negative Forms of Existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan song thams cad zhi bar mdzad pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངན་སོང་ཐམས་ཅད་ཞི་བར་མཛད་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-178">
                            <term>Powerful Intelligence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-179">
                            <term>Purifier of All Rebirths</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gro ba thams cad yongs su byong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་བྱོང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-180">
                            <term>Śāriputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-181">
                            <term>Śikhin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug phud can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཙུག་ཕུད་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śikhin</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Crown Ornament Holder.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-182">
                            <term>Ānandaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānandaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-183">
                            <term>Candanaśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsan dan gyi dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཙན་དན་གྱི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">candanaśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-184">
                            <term>Stainless Arising</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med par ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མེད་པར་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-185">
                            <term>Stainless Full Moon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba rgyas pa dri ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བ་རྒྱས་པ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-186">
                            <term>Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་འབྱོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">subhūti</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-187">
                            <term>Subjugator of All Demon Forces</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud thams cad kyi stobs rab tu ’joms pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད་ཐམས་ཅད་ཀྱི་སྟོབས་རབ་ཏུ་འཇོམས་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-188">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajyaguru Vaidūryaprabharāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi bla bai du rya’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་གྱི་བླ་བཻ་དུ་རྱའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhaiṣajya­guru vaidūrya­prabharāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Teacher of Medicine, King of Vaiḍūrya Light.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-189">
                            <term>He Who Looks at All Beings with Love</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sems can thams cad sdug par thong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེམས་ཅན་ཐམས་ཅད་སྡུག་པར་ཐོང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-190">
                            <term>He Whose Intelligence Has Been Completely Purified</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros rnam dag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་རྣམ་དག་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-191">
                            <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajrapāṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-192">
                            <term>Vigataśoka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan bral ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན་བྲལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vigataśoka</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Without Suffering.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-193">
                            <term>Vipāśyin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par gzigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་གཟིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipāśyin</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Discerning One.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-194">
                            <term>Viśvabhū</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad skyob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐམས་ཅད་སྐྱོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viśvabhū</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Protector of All.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-195">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yama</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-196">
                            <term>Prasenajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsal rgyal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསལ་རྒྱལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prasenajit</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-197">
                            <term>Endowed with Realization and Intelligence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtogs pa dang blo gros su ldan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟོགས་པ་དང་བློ་གྲོས་སུ་ལྡན་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-198">
                            <term>Excellent Attainment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khyad par thob pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁྱད་པར་ཐོབ་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-199">
                            <term>Fearless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirbhaya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-200">
                            <term>Free from Negative Forms of Existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan ’gro dang bral ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངན་འགྲོ་དང་བྲལ་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-201">
                            <term>Vaiḍūrya Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bai du rya snang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཻ་དུ་རྱ་སྣང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-202">
                            <term>Lotus Excellence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad mo’i bla ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མོའི་བླ་མ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-203">
                            <term>Moon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-204">
                            <term>Peace</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-205">
                            <term>Perfect Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs par snang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་པར་སྣང་བ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-206">
                            <term>Possessed of Power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-207">
                            <term>Sahā world system</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed kyi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahālokadhātu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-208">
                            <term>Vimalā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimalā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Stainless.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-209">
                            <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sukhāvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Endowed with Happiness.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-210">
                            <term>Vārāṇasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bA rA na sI </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཱ་རཱ་ན་སཱི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vārāṇasī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-211">
                            <term>grove of the caretaker of mango trees</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">a mra srung ba’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨ་མྲ་སྲུང་བའི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmrapālīvana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A phrase usually translated as Āmrapālī’s grove, referring to the grove in
                                Vaiśālī donated to the Buddha by the courtesan Āmrapālī (“Protected by a Mango Tree”), but here
                                possibly to be interpreted as a generic term, as the narrative locates it in Vārāṇasī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-006-212">
                            <term>Aśoka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mya ngan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མྱ་ངན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aśoka</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Without Suffering.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>