<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dāna­pāramitā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྦྱིན་པའི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sbyin pa’i pha rol tu phyin pa
                    zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra “The Perfection
                    of Generosity”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dāna­pāramitā­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee
                    <lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
                    Buddha </author>
            <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-59">Benjamin Collet-Cassart</author>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-57">Anders Bjornback</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-56">Alex Yiannopoulos</consultant>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-255">Chandika Maharjan</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">John Canti</editor>
                <editor role="proofreader" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-283">Dan Hirshberg</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.7 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-002"/>
                <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2018-11-13</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh182" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 182</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios
                        77.a–95.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Prajñāvarman</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="36">
                        <start volume="61" page="77"/><!-- was 47 -->
                        <end volume="61" page="95"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11798" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-01T08:03:04.501Z" user="john">01/06/2019 08:03:04</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.06, 2018" date-time="2019-04-29T13:29:19.807Z" user="mike">v 1.06, 2018 2018-11-14</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2019-04-29T13:29:19.807Z" user="mike">2</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.3" date-time="2019-05-31T08:48:26.556Z" user="john">v 0.3 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.5" date-time="2019-06-01T07:42:46.284Z" user="john">v 0.5 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.5" date-time="2019-06-02T10:29:26.676Z" user="john">v 0.5 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.7" date-time="2019-06-02T10:30:31.462Z" user="john">v 0.7 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="156">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In this sūtra a bodhisattva asks the Buddha how bodhisattvas should exert
                    themselves after having given rise to the mind set on awakening. The Buddha
                    replies by describing the ten virtuous actions and the motivation that
                    bodhisattvas should engender when they engage in those practices. Next, after
                    explaining how they should exert themselves in the ten perfections, the Buddha
                    presents a detailed explanation of the perfection of generosity, focusing on the
                    compassionate motivation that bodhisattvas cultivate while practicing
                    generosity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="157">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This text was translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under
                    the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. Benjamin Collet-Cassart translated the
                    text from Tibetan into English and wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor
                    compared the draft translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text.
                    Anders Bjornback and Alex Yiannopoulos also assisted this project by sharing
                    their draft translation of the first section of this sūtra with the other
                    translators. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="158">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity</title> belongs to the
                        general sūtra section of the Tibetan Kangyur. It does not appear to have been
                        translated into Chinese, and we have not come across any mention of its title
                        in Indian commentarial works. It does not seem, therefore, to have had
                        a particularly influential role in Buddhist India. Until recently, it had
                        also not attracted notable attention in modern scholarship. In 2014,
                        however, Jason McCombs included a full translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity,</title> along with an introduction to the text, in his doctoral dissertation.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-4" index="1"> McCombs (2014), pp. 88–183. His thesis also includes an
                            edited version of the full Tibetan text. Although McCombs’ study and
                            translation of this sūtra only became available to us after we had
                            completed our translation, we subsequently compared our translation
                            to his and as a result were able to improve our rendering in
                            several instances.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-5"/>
                    <p tid="4">As is common with this genre of Buddhist literature, the absence of
                        concrete historical data makes it hard to place the sūtra historically with
                        much certainty. Still, based on particular doctrinal and literary elements,
                        McCombs argues for a tentative date of its being set out in written form somewhere around the
                        fifth or sixth century. To sum up his arguments, the sūtra seems to be
                        fairly developed doctrinally, with various lists of philosophical concepts and
                        practices appearing in their later rather than earlier forms. For example, the
                        text speaks of the ten perfections (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāramitās</foreign>) 
                        rather than the earlier, standard list of six. And perhaps the most significant feature of the
                        sūtra from a historical viewpoint is the mention of three goddesses in attendance at the Buddha’s
                        teaching: Umā (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dka’ bzlog ma</foreign>),
                        Mahāśrīdevī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi lha mo chen
                            mo</foreign>), and Bhairavī (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs byed
                            ma</foreign>). These goddesses generally do not appear in Indian
                        literature until the fifth century, and it is therefore reasonable to accept
                        McCombs’ tentative dating of the sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-6" index="2"> See McCombs, “Mahāyāna and the
                            Gift,” 94–95.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-7"/>
                    <p tid="5">The sūtra is set in Kapilavastu, the city in which the Buddha had lived
                        during his childhood and youth, and to which he returned at times after his awakening. 
                        It is on one of these occasions that we find him residing in
                        the parks of his father, King Śuddhodhana. In the first chapter, after a lengthy introduction, a
                        bodhisattva asks the Buddha about the practices in which bodhisattvas should
                        exert themselves once they have aroused the mind set on awakening. The
                        Buddha first answers by explaining how to engage with the path of the ten
                        virtuous actions and describing the altruistic attitudes that bodhisattvas
                        should cultivate in this regard. Next, in the second
                        chapter of the sūtra, the Buddha explains how bodhisattvas
                        should endeavor in the practices of the ten perfections, using a repetitive formula
                        interspersed with verses. The Buddha provides a detailed explanation of the
                        way bodhisattvas should practice the perfection of generosity in particular,
                        emphasizing the compassionate motivation that must underlie the
                        act of giving, as well as the spiritual attainments and other benefits
                        derived from the practice of giving. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-8"/>
                    <p tid="6">The sūtra was translated into Tibetan by the prolific translator
                        Yeshé Dé sometime during the late eighth or early ninth century, when the
                        majority of sūtras were translated into Tibetan. According to the colophon,
                        Yeshé Dé was assisted in his task by the renowned Indian scholar
                        Prajñāvarman. As further testament to the date of translation, we also find
                        the sūtra included in the ninth century Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</foreign>) Palace 
                        catalog of translated scriptures,
                        where it is grouped under the category of “Mahāyāna, general sūtras of ten or
                            fewer fascicles.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-9" index="3">See Denkarma, 
                                Degé Tengyur vol. 208 (sna tshogs, jo), F.298.a.5–6; also Lalou (1953), p. 322, n.
                                142. In the Denkarma, the sūtra is listed with the title <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags 
                                    pa sbyin pa’i pha rol tu phyin pa bstan pa</title>.</note> Within the Degé Kangyur itself, the sūtra is placed next to
                        another sūtra that likewise includes the term “<term type="ignore">generosity</term>” in its 
                        title.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-10" index="4"> This text (Toh 183, 
                            Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa’i phan yon bstan pa</title>, 
                            Skt. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānānuśaṃsā</title>) is a short, two-page text
                            that presents the benefits associated with the practice of generosity by
                            listing the karmic ripening generated by different types of offering. In
                            the Stok Palace edition and other witnesses of the Thenpangma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">them spangs ma</foreign>) line of
                            Kangyur collections, these two texts are cataloged disjointly, and this
                            title is translated as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyin
                                pa’i legs pa</foreign>, rather than <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyin pa’i 
                                    phan yon bstan pa</foreign>.</note> However,
                        as McCombs points out, <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of
                            Generosity</title> also overlaps significantly in terms of content with
                        larger sections found in other sūtras in the Kangyur.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-11" index="5"> In 
                            particular, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akṣayamati­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> (Toh 175) and
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­sattva­piṭaka­sūtra</title> (Toh 56).
                            See McCombs, “Mahāyāna and the Gift,” 98–99.</note> The
                        organizing principle for the arrangement of the text in the Degé Kangyur (and others 
                        predominantly of Tshalpa lineage) appears to have had more 
                        to do with the title of the sūtra than its content, as is not uncommon when it comes to the structure of
                        the Tibetan Kangyur collections. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-304"/>
                    <p tid="6">The text contains a single chapter colophon (at <ptr target="#UT22084-061-002-309"/>) demarcating the Buddha’s initial 
                        teaching on the ten virtuous actions from the part that follows on the ten perfections. This
                        chapter colophon also makes mention of an alternative title for the sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The 
                            Array That Ornaments, Adorns, and Decorates All Buddha Qualities</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs 
                                rgyas kyi chos thams cad kyi rgyan dang / spud pa dang / lhab lhub bkod pa</title>). To the two chapters thus formed we have added descriptive chapter titles that do not, it should 
                        be noted, appear in the source text.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-310"/>
                    <p tid="6">This English translation is based primarily
                        on the Degé Kangyur version, in consultation with the Comparative Edition
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) and the Stok Palace
                        Manuscript Kangyur.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="159"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="160">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="161">The Perfection of Generosity</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="1974">How Bodhisattvas Exert Themselves in the Ten Virtuous Actions</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-12"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <ref cRef="F.77.a"/>
                        <ref cRef="B1" type="bampo"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-13"/>
                    <p tid="8">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One, in order to benefit his
                        kinsmen and the local people, was residing in the parks of King Śuddhodhana in the city
                        of Kapilavastu, parks adorned with many hundreds of thousands of trees of
                        different types, such as sāla, palmyra, tamāla, karṇikāra, juniper,
                        walnut, kharjūra, śipan, nīpa, mango, pear, āmalakī, wood apple,
                        pomegranate, elephant apple plantain, banyan fig, goolar fig, myrobalan,
                        aśvattha, vārśika, nutmeg, dhanuṣkarī, rosewood, magnolia, aśoka, taraṇi,
                        pāṭalā, śiriṣa, and arjun trees. The parks were beautified by cascading
                        streams, waterfalls, lakes, pools, ponds, and springs of fragrant water
                        filled with purple, pink, red, and white lotus flowers. There one could hear
                        the calls of geese, peacocks, cranes, ducks, cuckoos, ospreys, parrots,
                        grouse, pheasants, partridges, nightingales, and wild ducks. Countless
                        honeybees buzzed in the air. The water in the parks possessed eight special
                            qualities<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-15" index="6">The
                            eight qualities of the best kind of water (a set frequently mentioned 
                            in the literature) are that it is cool, sweet, light, soft, clear, clean, pure, does not
                            upset the stomach, and does not irritate the throat.</note> and was
                        limpid, flavorful, cool, pristine, and pure. The grass was green, soft and
                        tender, and as pleasing to the touch as silk, wool, cotton, raw silk,
                        kācilindika cloth, and linen. Those fine parks were beautiful, clean, and
                        free of any stones, pebbles, gravel, dirt, mud, or refuse. They were also
                        home to various wild animals, such as śarabha, spotted deer, monkeys, cats,
                        brown bears, rabbits, black bears, <ref cRef="F.77.b"/> hyenas, and a number
                        of different birds. Hundreds of thousands of other beings were also present,
                        such as gods and goddesses of the night, guardians of the world, Varuṇa,
                        Śiva, Yama, Virūḍhaka, Kubera, Śakra, Virūpākṣa, and Dhṛtarāṣṭra, as well as
                        asuras, garuḍas, gandharvas, kiṃnaras, and mahoragas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-16"/>
                    <p tid="10">A large saṅgha of seventy-seven thousand monks was also residing
                        there, including venerable Śāradvatīputra, venerable Mahāmaudgalyāyana,
                        venerable Subhūti, venerable Kapphiṇa, venerable Gavāṃpati, venerable
                        Mahākauṣṭhila, venerable Bharadvāja, venerable Ājñātakauṇḍinya, venerable
                        Bhadrika, venerable Pūrṇa, venerable Suśubha, venerable Cūḍāpanthaka,
                        venerable Bakkula, venerable Rāhula, venerable Upananda, venerable Nanda,
                        and venerable Ānanda. With the exception of one person—namely, venerable
                        Ānanda—they were all worthy ones who had exhausted the defilements and were
                        without afflictions. They were endowed with <term type="ignore">powers</term>, and had liberated minds and 
                        liberated <term type="ignore">insight</term>. They were of noble origin and
                        like great elephants. Their work was done, their deeds were done, they had
                        laid down their burden, they had accomplished their own welfare, and their
                        ties to existence were exhausted. Due to their correct perception, their
                        minds were utterly liberated, and they had perfected the sacred mastery of all
                        mental states.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-17"/>
                    <p tid="11">Also present was a great assembly of trillions of bodhisattvas that
                        included the bodhisattva great beings Maitreya; Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta;
                        Avalokiteśvara; Mahāsthāmaprāpta; Samantabhadra; Ākāśagarbha; Devamukuṭa;
                        Ratnamukuṭa; Ratnapāṇi; Ratnaprabha; <ref cRef="F.78.a"/> Ratnagarbha;
                        Ratnacūḍa; Ratnasiṃha; Ratnajālin; Jālinīprabha; Sūryaprabha; Candraprabha;
                        Stable Strength; Dṛḍhamati; Dṛḍhavīrya; Dṛḍhavikrama; Determined Effort;
                        Mahotsāha; Prāmodyarāja; Bhaiṣajyarāja; Bhaiṣajyasamudgata;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-18" index="7"> At this point the list of
                            bodhisattvas continues and the names increase in length considerably.
                            Although the text is clear that the following lines of this paragraph
                            are indeed to be treated as a list of personal names, their meaning is
                            somewhat unclear, and it is not evident precisely where the individual
                            names begin and end. As such, the rendering of the remainder of the
                            bodhisattva names included in this section should be viewed as
                            tentative.</note> King Precious Moonlight of Pure Virtue;
                        Kamala­dala­vimala­nakṣatra­rāja­saṃkusumitā­bhijña; Hair in a Topknot Shining
                        Dark Like Bees, Ink, Peacocks, and Nightingales; Smiling Face That Brightly Shines
                        Like the Moon and a Lotus Flower; Top Ornament of Precious Qualities
                        With Magnificent Sapphire-like Eyes; Equal and Evenly Set Teeth White like Silver, Conch Shells, the Moon, a White Lotus, and Milk; Tongue Wide as the
                        Leaves of Palm and Plantain Trees and Resembling a Copper Plate; Voice as
                        Delightful as the Songs of Cuckoos, Parrots, Grouse, Pheasants, and
                        Kalaviṅka Birds; Moonlike Body; Rising Sun; Resembling the Karṇikāra Tree,
                        the Mango Tree, and the Blooming Burflower Tree; and the bodhisattva great
                        being Slender, Supple, Firm, Fine, and Smooth Limbs Youthful like Flowers and with Copper-Colored Nails. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-19"/>
                    <p tid="12">Including these bodhisattvas, there were a total of ninety-nine
                        thousand bodhisattvas, all of whom were irreversible in their progress and turned the
                        wheel of the irreversible Dharma. They had subjugated demons and opponents
                        and overcome all the activities of Māra. They were experts in the knowledge
                        that engages with the domain of the thus-gone ones. They had developed the
                            superknowledges,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-20" index="8">
                            S has no <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">shad</foreign> between
                            those two elements, and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mngon par
                                shes pa</foreign> is repeated in what follows: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de bzhin gshegs pa thams cad kyi yul
                                la ’jug pa shes pa la mkhas pa mngon par shes pa / mngon par shes pa
                                dpa’ bar ’gro ba’i ting nge ’dzin gyi mtha’i sgo bsgrub pa’i gzungs
                                thob pa</foreign>.</note> attained the retention that brings about
                        the final gateway of the absorption of bravery, and mastered the <term type="ignore">skillful means</term> related to all the perfections. <ref cRef="F.78.b"/> They revealed different world systems, had donned the
                        great armor, and had no doubts concerning the qualities of the buddhas. By
                        contemplating all the latent tendencies of the primary and secondary
                        afflictions they had conquered pride and its attendant habitual tendencies
                        and predispositions. As such, they were disciplined and gentle. They had
                        perfected the applications of mindfulness, the true relinquishments, the
                        bases of miraculous power, the <term>powers</term>, the strengths, the factors of
                        awakening, and other qualities of the path such as love, compassion, joy,
                        equanimity, patience, and intention, as well as other wholesome propensities.
                        They were free of pride, vanity, haughtiness, aggression, arrogance,
                        miserliness, selfishness, possessiveness, fixation, attachment, grasping,
                        oblivion, craving, and longing. For countless eons they had endeavored to
                        benefit and bring happiness to both themselves and others, and they had
                        thoroughly gathered the roots of virtue and perfected the accumulations.
                        They were free of hypocrisy, deceit, lies, slander, harsh words, killing,
                        harming, bondage, wrong views, threatening, quarrel, strife, fighting,
                        dispute, dueling, and all related afflictions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-21"/>
                    <p tid="13">Also in attendance were the four guardians of the world: the great
                        king Vaiśravaṇa, the great king Dhṛtarāṣṭra, the great king Virūḍhaka, and
                        the great king Virūpākṣa, each surrounded by their respective attendants.
                        There were the yakṣa general Pāñcika accompanied by his sons, the yakṣa
                        general Vajrapāṇi with his retinue of yakṣas, and the great bhūta Hārītī
                        with her retinue of female yakṣas. Śaṅkhinī, Female Spear Holder,
                        Yellow-Robed, <ref cRef="F.79.a"/> Umā, Mahāśrīdevī, Sarasvatī, Bhairavī,
                        Candra,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-22" index="9">S reads:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">zla ba ma</foreign>.</note>
                        Śakra the lord of the gods, the god Maheśvara, and Brahmā, lord of the Sahā
                        world, were also in attendance. All were accompanied by their respective
                        divine retinues. There were also the nāga kings Anavatapta and Sāgara, each
                        with their retinue of nāgas; the garuḍa rulers Mahātejas and Mahākāya, each
                        with their retinue of garuḍas; the asura rulers Bali and Rāhu, each with
                        their retinue; the kiṃnara king Druma with his retinue of kiṃnaras; and the
                        gandharva Pañcaśikha with his own retinue. Countless other majestic gods,
                        nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas, asuras, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, and
                        non-humans were also present. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-23"/>
                    <p tid="14">In this way the Blessed One was surrounded by members of the four
                        castes of priests, warriors, merchants, and commoners; the four retinues of
                        monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen; as well as countless members of the Śakya
                        clan, kings, ministers, townspeople, villagers, householders, officials,
                        members of the royal court, and village elders. These people all attended to
                        the Blessed One and served, honored, and venerated him. They made offerings
                        such that the Blessed One obtained food, beverages, bedding, cushions, and
                        medicine, as well as many other excellent offering articles. In this way the
                        Blessed One’s fame, renown, and praise extended far throughout the
                        immeasurable worlds of the ten directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-24"/>
                    <p tid="15">The ground, of the essence of diamond, was even, <ref cRef="F.79.b"/> pleasant, vast,
                        and open. It had been sprinkled with water, swept clean, made symmetrical,
                        and made fragrant with smoke rising from incense burners. The ground was
                        strewn with purple, pink, red, and white lotus flowers, as well as the
                        flowers of goolar fig, nīpa, vārśika, taraṇi, pāṭalā, aśoka, kuraṇṭaka,
                        nutmeg, and utika<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-25" index="10">We
                            have been unable to identify this tree (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">u thi ka)</foreign>.</note> trees. The site was also
                        adorned with trees made of various precious gems. There the Blessed One sat,
                        on a lion throne made of precious gemstones, upon which hundreds of thousands
                        of precious fabrics had been spread. The throne was sheltered by a precious bejeweled
                        canopy, adorned with a precious web of small jewel bells, and embellished with
                        precious gemstone lattices. It was further decorated with myriad precious
                        materials and gemstones, such as gold, diamond, beryl, pearl, conch shells,
                        moonstone, coral, sapphire, emerald, cat’s eye, and crystal.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-26" index="11">It seems that
                            “emerald” is repeated twice in this list under different names (Tib.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rdo’i snying po</foreign>
                            and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ma rgad</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-27"/>
                    <p tid="16">The Blessed One’s senses were peaceful, his mind was at ease, and
                        he had arrived at a sacred state of composure and tranquility. He had
                        attained, sustained, and mastered perfect composure and calm, and he had
                        brought his passions under control. Like a lake, his mind was pure, clear,
                        and pristine. Like a sacrificial post made of precious substances, he was refined, dazzling, and
                        brilliant. His body was adorned with the thirty-two major marks of a great
                        being and beautified with the excellent minor marks. Like the ocean, he was
                        filled with the water of the sacred Dharma. Like Mount Sumeru, he was
                        unshakable. Like the earth, he sustained all beings. Like water, he gave
                        rise to roots of virtue. Like the administration of justice, he was
                        unbiased. Like the sky, he was immaculate. Like the sun, he dispelled the
                        darkness of ignorance. Like the moon, he had perfected all pure qualities.
                        Like a wish-fulfilling jewel, he fulfilled all <term type="ignore">aspirations</term>. Like the sun, he
                        was lofty. Like the moon, he was cooling and soothing. Like the ocean, <ref cRef="F.80.a"/> he 
                        was a source of wealth, and like the ocean, too, he was
                        deep. Like a fire, he was shining. His body was unshakable; his mind was
                        unwavering, calm, and serene; and his senses were free of delusion,
                        arrogance, and excitement. He observed perfect mindfulness, his conduct was
                        excellent, and he was composed and constantly in equipoise. Over countless
                        billions of eons he had accomplished all the roots of virtue and gathered
                        the entire accumulation of merit; he had become skilled in all the perfections
                        and sported on all the levels of the buddhas and bodhisattvas. He
                        enthusiastically engaged in all the activities of the bodhisattvas, strived for
                        the benefit and happiness of all beings, and taught the
                        Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-28"/>
                    <p tid="17">The Dharma he taught presents pure conduct. It is virtuous in the
                        beginning, virtuous in the middle, and virtuous in the end. This Dharma,
                        with its excellent meanings and excellent words, is unadulterated, complete,
                        pure, refined, stainless, luminous, pleasant, agreeable, fulfilling,
                        elating, inspiring, delightful, and mentally enriching. It is pristine,
                        fearless, gentle, stable, profound, immutable, unchanging, indisputable,
                        beyond the reach of the intellect, inconceivable, marvelous, and utterly
                        inexpressible. Such is the Dharma that he taught, presented, explained, and
                        elucidated. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-29"/>
                    <p tid="18">Present in the assembly at that time was the bodhisattva great being called 
                        Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in 
                        Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows. He had a
                        beautiful physique and was handsome and pleasant to behold. His complexion
                        was attractive. He was well developed and replete with the most delightful
                            features.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-30" index="12">Translated based on S, 
                                which treats these as separate items: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha dog 
                                    bzang po </foreign>/ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgyas 
                                        pa </foreign>/ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mchog dang ldan pa</foreign>. D
                            reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kha dog bzang po
                            </foreign>/ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rgyas pa mchog dang
                                ldan pa</foreign>.</note> He had served victorious ones of the past,
                            <ref cRef="F.80.b"/> created roots of virtue with them, honored myriad
                        buddhas, and now upheld the lineage of the Three Jewels. He was
                        compassionate and his eloquence was unimpeded. He was loving toward all
                        beings, of pure faith, and his attitude was virtuous, steadfast, and
                        profound. He was affectionate, filled with compassion, noble-minded,
                        amicable, learned, wise, clear, intelligent, knowledgeable, devoid of
                        laziness, disciplined, wholesome, honest, straight, soft, gentle, and
                        sincere. As he was free of pride, vanity, haughtiness, strife, hostility,
                        envy, miserliness, selfishness, possessiveness, attachment, suffering,
                        unhappiness, and ignorance, he was endowed with merit. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-31"/>
                    <p tid="19">At one point, the bodhisattva great being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows stood up, draped his shawl over one
                        shoulder, and knelt with his right knee on the calyx of a lotus flower. With
                        his palms joined together he bowed down toward the Blessed One and said,
                        “If the Blessed One would grant me the opportunity, I have a few
                        questions I would like to put to the Blessed One, the thus-gone, worthy, and perfect
                        Buddha.” <ref cRef="F.81.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-32"/>
                    <p tid="20">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva great being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows, “Noble son, all the buddhas
                        and bodhisattvas will always grant you this opportunity. Noble son, ask
                        whatever you wish to the thus-gone, worthy, and perfect Buddha.
                        I will answer your questions and bring satisfaction to your mind.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-33"/>
                    <p tid="21">At these words from the Blessed One, the bodhisattva great
                        being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows asked, “Blessed
                        One, after having first given rise to the mind set on awakening, in what
                        should noble sons and daughters exert themselves?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-34"/>
                    <p tid="22">When he heard this question, the Blessed One expressed his approval
                        to the bodhisattva great being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows, saying, “Excellent, noble son, excellent! Noble son, your wish to
                        investigate this matter is excellent! Noble son, listen carefully and pay
                        attention: I shall now explain this.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-35"/>
                    <p tid="23">The bodhisattva great being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows agreed to this and listened to the Blessed One as
                        instructed. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-306"/>
                    <p tid="23">The Blessed One then said, “Noble son, after having first given
                        rise to the mind set on awakening, bodhisattva great beings should strive
                        diligently on the path of the ten virtuous actions. <ref cRef="F.81.b"/> Noble
                        son, how do bodhisattva great beings strive diligently on the path of the ten
                        virtuous actions? Noble son, bodhisattva great beings do so by abandoning
                        killing and so forth, up until wrong views.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-36" index="13">The abandonments of killing and
                            wrong views are, respectively, the first and the last of the ten
                            virtuous actions.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-37"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Noble son, how do bodhisattva great beings abandon killing? Noble
                        son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even the tiniest of
                        insects, such as an ant, is fond of its life; it cherishes it, likes it, and
                        enjoys it. I, too, am fond of my life; I, too, cherish it, like it, and enjoy
                        it. Therefore, just as I want no one to kill me, order someone to kill me, or
                        rejoice in my killing, I myself will never kill, order someone to kill, or rejoice
                        in the killing of anyone!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings
                        abandon killing. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-38"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>“From the time of being in their mother’s womb,</l>
                        <l>All beings cherish their lives.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, those who hold their lives dear </l>
                        <l>Should not kill any living being.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-39"/>
                    <p tid="26">“How do bodhisattvas abandon taking what is not given? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even the members of low
                        castes and outcasts are fond of wealth; they cherish it, like it, and enjoy
                        it. I am also fond of wealth; I, too, cherish it, like it, and enjoy it. Therefore, just
                        as I want no one to rob me, order someone to rob me, or rejoice in
                        someone robbing me, I myself will never rob, order someone to rob, or rejoice in
                        anyone being robbed!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings
                        abandon taking what is not given. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-40"/>
                    <lg tid="27">
                        <l>“Those who cherish their patrimony</l>
                        <l>Should never steal any wealth, </l>
                        <l>Even mere pieces of wood, clods of dirt,</l>
                        <l>Or what is rejected by others. <ref cRef="F.82.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-41"/>
                    <p tid="27">“How do bodhisattvas abandon sexual misconduct? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even beings born as animals
                        are fond of their mates; they cherish them, like them, and enjoy them. I am
                        also fond of my wife; I, too, cherish her, like her, and enjoy being with
                        her. Therefore, just as I want no one to ravish her, order someone to ravish her,
                        rejoice in someone ravishing her, harass her, or rape her, I myself will never
                        ravish, order someone to ravish, or rejoice in someone ravishing, harassing, or
                        raping anyone’s spouse!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings
                        abandon sexual misconduct. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-42"/>
                    <lg tid="28">
                        <l>“Those who are fond of their own spouse</l>
                        <l>Should not ravage another’s spouse,</l>
                        <l>Not even servants</l>
                        <l>Retained by others.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-43"/>
                    <p tid="29">“How do bodhisattvas abandon lying? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so
                        by reflecting in this way: ‘Even yakṣas, bhūtas, and piśācas are fond of the
                        truth; they cherish it, like it, and enjoy it. I am also fond of the truth;
                        I, too, cherish it, like it, and enjoy it. Therefore, just as I want no one to deceive me, 
                        order someone to deceive me, or rejoice in someone deceiving
                        me by telling lies, I myself will never deceive, order someone to deceive, or
                        rejoice in anyone being deceived by lies!’ Noble son, this is how
                        bodhisattva great beings abandon lying. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-44"/>
                    <lg tid="30">
                        <l>“The wise who are fond of the truth,</l>
                        <l>As even yakṣas and bhūtas are, </l>
                        <l>Should never deceive others </l>
                        <l>By telling lies. <ref cRef="F.82.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-45"/>
                    <p tid="31">“How do bodhisattvas abandon slander? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so
                        by reflecting in this way: ‘Even slanderous people find slander unpleasant;
                        they do not want to hear it, do not like it, and do not enjoy it. I also
                        find slander unpleasant; I do not want to hear it, do not like it, and do
                        not enjoy it. Therefore, just as I want no one to talk about me in a defamatory way, order 
                        someone to talk about me so, or rejoice in someone so talking about me, I
                        myself will never talk about anyone in a defamatory way, order someone to talk so, 
                        or rejoice in anyone being so talked about!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings abandon
                        slander. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-46"/>
                    <p tid="32">“How do bodhisattvas abandon harsh words? Noble son, bodhisattvas
                        do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even those who are used to speaking harsh
                        words find such words unpleasant; they do not want to hear them, do not like
                        them, and do not enjoy them. I, too, find harsh words unpleasant; I do not
                        want to hear them, do not like them, and do not enjoy them. Therefore, just as I want no one 
                        to hurt me, order someone to hurt me, or rejoice in someone
                        hurting me with harsh, cruel, insulting, or defamatory words, I myself will never
                        hurt anyone with harsh, cruel, insulting, or defamatory words, order someone to be so hurt, 
                        or rejoice in anyone being so hurt!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva
                        great beings abandon harsh words. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-47"/>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>“Those who consider slanderous and harsh words</l>
                        <l>To be unpleasant</l>
                        <l>Should not express slander,</l>
                        <l>And should guard against harsh words.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-48"/>
                    <p tid="34">“How do bodhisattvas abandon idle gossip? Noble son, bodhisattva
                            <ref cRef="F.83.a"/> great beings do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even
                        those who engage in idle gossip find meaningless conversations unpleasant;
                        they do not want to hear them, do not like them, and do not enjoy them. I
                        also find meaningless conversations unpleasant; I do not want to hear them,
                        do not like them, and do not enjoy them. Therefore, just as I want no one to talk
                        about me surreptitiously, order someone to talk about me so, or rejoice in someone so talking
                        about me, I myself will never talk about anyone surreptitiously, order someone to
                        talk about anyone so, or rejoice in someone so talking about anyone!’ Noble son, 
                        this is how bodhisattva great beings abandon idle gossip. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-49"/>
                    <p tid="35">“How do bodhisattva great beings abandon covetousness? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even covetous people find
                        covetousness unpleasant; they do not wish for it, do not like it, and do not
                        enjoy it. I, too, find covetousness unpleasant; I do not wish for it, do not
                        like it, and do not enjoy it. Therefore, just as I want no one to talk to me 
                        covetously, order
                        anyone to talk to me so, or rejoice in someone so talking to me, I
                        myself will never talk covetously to anyone, order others to talk so, or rejoice in someone so 
                        talking to anyone!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings abandon
                        covetousness. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-50"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>“All those who dislike</l>
                        <l>Idle gossip and covetousness</l>
                        <l>Should not engage in meaningless conversations,</l>
                        <l>And should guard against covetousness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-51"/>
                    <p tid="37">“How do bodhisattvas abandon ill will? Noble son, bodhisattvas do
                        so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even those who entertain malicious thoughts
                        find ill will unpleasant; they do not wish for it, do not like it, and do
                        not enjoy it. I, too, <ref cRef="F.83.b"/> find ill will unpleasant; I do not
                        wish for it, do not like it, and do not enjoy it. Therefore, just as I want no one 
                        to express malicious words to me, order someone to express them, or rejoice in someone expressing
                        them, I myself will never express malicious words to anyone, order someone to express them, or
                        rejoice in someone expressing them!’ Noble son, this is
                        how bodhisattva great beings abandon ill will. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-52"/>
                    <p tid="38">“How do bodhisattvas abandon wrong views? Noble son, bodhisattvas
                        do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Even those who entertain wrong views find
                        wrong views unpleasant; they do not wish for them, do not like them, and do
                        not enjoy them. I, too, find wrong views unpleasant; I do not wish for them,
                        do not like them, and do not enjoy them. Therefore, just as I want no one to teach
                        me wrong views, order someone to teach me them, or rejoice in someone teaching 
                        me them, I myself will never teach, make someone teach, or rejoice in someone
                        teaching anyone wrong views!’ Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great
                        beings abandon wrong views. Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-53"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“All those who dislike </l>
                        <l>Ill will or wrong views</l>
                        <l>Should not entertain ill will</l>
                        <l>Or wrong views toward anything.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-54"/>
                    <p tid="40">“Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings exert themselves
                        on the path of the ten virtuous actions.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-308"/>
                    <p tid="41">As this teaching on the path of the ten virtuous actions was
                        spoken, countless beings gave rise to the mind set on unsurpassed and
                        perfect awakening. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-309"/>
                    <trailer tid="42">This was the first chapter of the Great Vehicle sūtra called “<title xml:lang="en">The 
                        Array That Ornaments, Adorns, and Decorates All Buddha Qualities</title>.”<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-311">This chapter colophon appears to provide an alternative title for the sūtra. See also <ptr target="#UT22084-061-002-304"/>.</note> </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="1974">How Bodhisattvas Exert Themselves in the Ten Perfections</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-57"/>
                    <p tid="43">“Furthermore, noble son, <ref cRef="F.84.a"/> after having first
                        given rise to the mind set on awakening, bodhisattva great beings should
                        exert themselves in the ten perfections. What are those ten? They are the
                        perfections of generosity, discipline, patience, diligence, concentration,
                        insight, skillful means, aspiration, power, and wisdom. Noble son, how do
                        bodhisattva great beings exert themselves in those ten perfections? Noble
                        son, bodhisattva great beings practice generosity, observe discipline,
                        cultivate patience, engender diligence, rest in concentration, cause insight
                        to blaze, become skilled in means, form aspiration prayers, apply the
                        <term>powers</term>, and embrace wisdom. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-58"/>
                    <p tid="44">“Noble son, how do bodhisattva great beings exert themselves in the
                        perfection of generosity? Noble son, bodhisattva great beings exert
                        themselves in the practice of generosity starting by offering food, beverages,
                        vehicles, clothing, and ornaments, until they are able to offer the marrow of their
                        bones. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-59"/>
                    <p tid="45">“Noble son, how do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by offering food? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in
                        this way: ‘Offering food represents the achievement of longevity, luster,
                        <term type="ignore">power</term>, and happiness. I must therefore exert
                        myself in offering food; I will definitely practice generosity by offering
                        food!’ The generosity practiced by offering food with such thoughts will
                        provide longevity and happiness.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-60"/>
                    <p tid="46">At this point, the Blessed One uttered these verses: <ref cRef="F.84.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-61"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>“Through the generosity practiced by offering food,</l>
                        <l>The wise ones extend a fivefold gift: </l>
                        <l>Longevity, luster, <term type="ignore">power</term>,
                        </l>
                        <l>Happiness, and eloquence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-62"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>“Those who offer food will themselves experience</l>
                        <l>Joy, longevity, strength, and well-being.</l>
                        <l>Such happy persons, supported by such qualities, </l>
                        <l>Will develop unhindered eloquence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-63"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>“They will become wealthy, affluent, </l>
                        <l>Illustrious, noble-minded, intelligent, </l>
                        <l>Meritorious, learned, and calm.</l>
                        <l>Such are the consequences of offering food.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-64"/>
                    <p tid="50"> “How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering beverages? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering beverages represents the elimination of all thirst associated
                        with the afflictions. Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by
                        offering beverages!’ When practicing generosity by offering beverages,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations praised by the buddhas, through this offering of beverages may I
                        dry up the entire ocean of thirst associated with the afflictions of all
                        beings, and may the beverage with the taste of liberation satisfy them!’
                        Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-65"/>
                    <lg tid="51">
                        <l>“Having dried up the ocean of afflicted thirst,</l>
                        <l>Where the sea monsters of old age and death roam,</l>
                        <l>I will satisfy human beings</l>
                        <l>By providing the beverage with the taste of liberation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-66"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“The wise ones who offer beverages</l>
                        <l>Will never be reborn in the dreadful realms of starving spirits</l>
                        <l>Where beings are consumed by the blazing fire of craving,</l>
                        <l>And they will never again be tormented by thirst.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-67"/>
                    <p tid="53">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering vehicles? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering vehicles represents the gathering of all joy and bases of
                        miraculous power. I must therefore practice generosity by offering vehicles;
                        I will definitely offer chariots, palanquins, horses, elephants, and shoes!’
                        Then, when practicing generosity by offering vehicles, <ref cRef="F.85.a"/>
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations praised by the buddhas, through this offering of vehicles may I
                        gather every form of happiness and the bases of miraculous power for all
                        beings!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-68"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“May the offering of vehicles and chariots</l>
                        <l>Forever cause all beings </l>
                        <l>To attain the Great Vehicle</l>
                        <l>And achieve the bases of miraculous power!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-69"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“The wise ones, the great sages who offer vehicles,</l>
                        <l>Will miraculously travel through space</l>
                        <l>From buddha realm to buddha realm,</l>
                        <l>Like birds flying through the sky.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-70"/>
                    <p tid="56">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering clothing? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering clothing represents the perfection of one’s modesty,
                        humility, and appearance. Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity
                        by offering clothing!’ When practicing generosity by offering clothing,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations made by the buddhas, through this offering of clothing may I
                        perfect the modesty, humility, and appearance of all beings!’ Regarding
                        this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-71"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“Through this offering of clothing </l>
                        <l>May I perfect<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-72" index="15">Translated based on S. D reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sbyor ba</foreign>.</note> the modesty and
                            humility</l>
                        <l>Of all beings,</l>
                        <l>And may I also purify their appearance!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-73"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“Those illustrious beings who offer clothing</l>
                        <l>Will always obtain a good caste and beautiful physique.</l>
                        <l>Such persons will be modest </l>
                        <l>And find fame and fortune.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-74"/>
                    <p tid="59"> “How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering ornaments? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering ornaments represents the perfection of the thirty-two major
                        marks and the eighty minor marks of a great being. Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by offering ornaments made of gold, jewels,
                        pearl, beryl, conch shells, moonstone, and coral!’ <ref cRef="F.85.b"/> When
                        practicing generosity by offering ornaments, bodhisattvas make the following
                        aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations expressed by the buddhas,
                        through this offering of ornaments may I witness the bodies of all beings
                        become adorned with the excellent major and minor marks!’ Regarding this,
                        there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-75"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“Through this offering of golden ornaments</l>
                        <l>May I see all beings</l>
                        <l>Become adorned with the excellent marks,</l>
                        <l>And may I also pursue awakening!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-76"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“Those who offer jewels and pearls</l>
                        <l>Will experience a rain of precious gems</l>
                        <l>In all the places </l>
                        <l>Where they are reborn.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-77"/>
                    <p tid="62">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering lamps? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way:
                        ‘Offering lamps represents the purification of the divine eye. Therefore, I
                        will definitely practice generosity by offering lamps!’ When practicing
                        generosity by offering lamps, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations taught by the buddhas, through this
                        offering of lamps may I cause the divine eye of all beings to be purified!’
                        Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-78"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“Through this offering of the lamps </l>
                        <l>Of omniscient <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>
                        </l>
                        <l>May I purify the divine eye</l>
                        <l>Of all beings!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-79"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“Those who offer lamps</l>
                        <l>Will always gradually achieve </l>
                        <l>The five eyes of the buddhas</l>
                        <l>Within the different worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-80"/>
                    <p tid="65">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering music? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way:
                        ‘Offering music represents the perfection of the divine ear. Therefore, I
                        will definitely practice generosity by offering music!’ When practicing
                        generosity by offering music, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations taught by the buddhas, through this
                        offering of music may I cause all beings to perfect the divine ear!’ <ref cRef="F.86.a"/> Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-81"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Through this offering of music </l>
                        <l>May I cause all beings </l>
                        <l>To perfect the divine ear</l>
                        <l>And progress to the awakening of the buddhas!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-82"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“Those who offer the sound of music,</l>
                        <l>Wherever they are born,</l>
                        <l>Will achieve the renown of the perfect buddhas</l>
                        <l>And the divine ear of heroic beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-83"/>
                    <p tid="68">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering perfumes, fragrant powders, and ointments? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Offering perfumes, fragrant
                        powders, and ointments represents the perfumes, fragrant powders, and
                        ointments of discipline, erudition, and absorption. Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by offering perfumes, fragrant powders, and
                        ointments!’ When practicing generosity by offering perfumes, fragrant
                        powders, and ointments, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations of the buddhas, through this offering of
                        perfumes, fragrant powders, and ointments may I anoint all sentient with the
                        fragrances of discipline, erudition, and absorption!’ Regarding this, it is
                        said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-84"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“May this offering of perfumes,</l>
                        <l>Fragrant powders, and ointments</l>
                        <l>Cause all beings to achieve</l>
                        <l>Discipline, erudition, and absorption!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-85"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>“Those who offer perfumes,</l>
                        <l>Fragrant powders, and ointments</l>
                        <l>Will achieve the perfect divine nose of the protectors</l>
                        <l>And the flawless body of the gods.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-86"/>
                    <p tid="71">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering flowers? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering flowers and flower garlands represents the attainment of the
                        precious flowers of retention, eloquence, and the branches of awakening.
                        Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by offering flowers and
                        flower garlands!’ When practicing generosity by offering flowers and flower
                        garlands, bodhisattvas <ref cRef="F.86.b"/> make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations expressed by the buddhas, through this
                        offering of flowers and flower garlands may I adorn the body of all beings
                        with the precious flowers of retention, eloquence, and the branches of
                        awakening!’ Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-87"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>“Through this offering of flowers and flower garlands</l>
                        <l>May all beings be adorned,</l>
                        <l>Swiftly and in all manners,</l>
                        <l>With the flowers of the branches of awakening!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-88"/>
                    <lg tid="73">
                        <l>“Those who offer flowers and flower garlands,</l>
                        <l>Wherever they are born,</l>
                        <l>Will always be worshiped and venerated</l>
                        <l>By kings, ministers, and officials.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-89"/>
                    <p tid="74">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering delicacies? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering delicacies represents the attainment of the mark of a great
                        being who has the finest sense of taste. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by offering the flavors of grape, molasses, honey,
                        butter, oil, and salt!’ When practicing generosity by offering delicacies,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations praised by the buddhas, through this offering of delicacies may
                        I cause all beings to perfect the mark of a great being who has the finest
                        sense of taste!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-90"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>“Through this offering of savory flavors </l>
                        <l>May all beings</l>
                        <l>Experience the essential taste of omniscience,</l>
                        <l>And so perfect the awakened conduct of the perfect buddhas!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-91"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>“Those who offer delicacies develop mental sharpness, </l>
                        <l>Excellent memory, and oceanic intelligence.</l>
                        <l>They will enjoy a variety of tasty flavors</l>
                        <l>And will effortlessly prosper.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-92"/>
                    <p tid="77">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering residences? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering residences represents <ref cRef="F.87.a"/> becoming a
                        shelter, a protector, a support, a refuge, and a helper for all beings.
                        Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by offering residences!’
                        When practicing generosity by offering residences, bodhisattvas make the
                        following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations observed by the
                        buddhas, through this offering of residences may I become a shelter, a
                        protector, a support, a refuge, and a helper for all beings!’ Regarding
                        this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-93"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>“Through the offering of palaces and residences,</l>
                        <l>May I, within all the worlds,</l>
                        <l>Become a protector, a support, a refuge, </l>
                        <l>And a helper for all beings!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-94"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>“Those who offer palaces and residences,</l>
                        <l>Wherever they are born,</l>
                        <l>Will be the owners and leaders</l>
                        <l>Of households, residences, and countries.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-95"/>
                    <p tid="80">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering beds and pillows? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in
                        this way: ‘Offering beds and pillows represents the loftiness of permanently
                        abandoning all obscurations, the divine abodes of Brahmā that are the
                        sleeping chambers of the thus-gone ones, and the gift of elevation.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-96" index="16">Tentative translation
                            (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sgrib pa thams cad gtan
                                spong ba’ ’phags pa dang / lha’i tshangs pa’i gnas de bzhin gshegs
                                pa’i gzims mal dang / ’phangs sbyin pa’i tshigs bla dags yin
                                gyis)</foreign>.</note> Therefore, I will definitely practice
                        generosity by offering beds and pillows!’ When practicing generosity by
                        offering beds and pillows, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations taught by the buddhas, through this offering
                        of beds and pillows may I confer the loftiness of permanently abandoning all
                        obscurations of all beings, the divine abodes of Brahmā that are the
                        sleeping chambers of the thus-gone ones, and the gift of elevation!’
                        Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-97"/>
                    <lg tid="81">
                        <l>“Through whatever merit I have accumulated</l>
                        <l>By offering beds and pillows,</l>
                        <l>May I overcome the obscurations of all beings</l>
                        <l>As well as their distorted, perverted intelligence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-98"/>
                    <lg tid="82">
                        <l>“May I sever the web of their negative views</l>
                        <l>With the sword of insight,</l>
                        <l>And offer them perfect beds worthy of the blissful ones</l>
                        <l>And rested upon<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-99" index="17">K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, and S read: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">bstan</foreign>. J and N read: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">stan</foreign>.</note> in the abodes of Brahmā.
                                <ref cRef="F.87.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-100"/>
                    <lg tid="83">
                        <l>“Those who offer beds and pillows</l>
                        <l>Will be reborn as experts in the treatises.</l>
                        <l>They will achieve tranquility, practice generosity on a vast scale,</l>
                        <l>And become majestic princes born from lotus flowers.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-101"/>
                    <p tid="84"> “How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering seats? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way:
                        ‘Offering seats represents the attainment of the vajra throne at the seat of
                        awakening in all the worlds of the great trichiliocosms. Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by offering seats!’ When practicing
                        generosity by offering seats, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘With aspirations that are in harmony with those of the thus-gone ones,
                        through this offering of seats may I cause all beings to attain the vajra
                        throne at the seat of awakening in all the worlds of the great
                        trichiliocosms!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-102"/>
                    <lg tid="85">
                        <l>“Through this offering of a seat,</l>
                        <l>May the excellent, firm, and stable</l>
                        <l>Vajra throne at the seat of awakening </l>
                        <l>Appear to all beings!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-103"/>
                    <lg tid="86">
                        <l>“It is made of the seven precious substances;</l>
                        <l>Measuring two leagues in height</l>
                        <l>And one in circumference,</l>
                        <l>It is majestic like Mount Sumeru.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-104"/>
                    <lg tid="87">
                        <l>“It is surrounded by hundreds of precious trees,</l>
                        <l>Adorned with celestial palaces,</l>
                        <l>Covered with garlands of small bells,</l>
                        <l>And ornamented with shining jewels.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-105"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>“By offering chairs, seats, and stools </l>
                        <l>To fellow practitioners of pure conduct,</l>
                        <l>One will attain such a seat</l>
                        <l>While turning in cyclic existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-106"/>
                    <p tid="89">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering provisions? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering provisions represents the complete acquisition of the
                        provisions for awakening. Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity
                        by offering provisions!’ When practicing generosity by offering provisions,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with aspirations
                        worthy of the thus-gone ones, <ref cRef="F.88.a"/> through this offering of
                        provisions may I cause all beings to complete the provisions for awakening!’
                        Regarding this, there are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-107"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>“Through this gift of provisions,</l>
                        <l>May I cause beings who seek</l>
                        <l>The provisions for awakening </l>
                        <l>Achieve complete fulfillment!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-108"/>
                    <lg tid="91">
                        <l>“By offering provisions</l>
                        <l>Wherever one is born,</l>
                        <l>One will enjoy excellent limbs</l>
                        <l>That are perfect in all regards.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-109"/>
                    <p tid="92">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by offering medicine? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this
                        way: ‘Offering medicine represents the perfect wellbeing of the ambrosia
                        by which all beings are free from old age and death. Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by offering medicine!’ When practicing
                        generosity by offering medicine, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations blessed by the thus-gone ones, through
                        this offering of medicine may I cause all beings to perfect the wellbeing of the ambrosia
                        by which which all beings are free from old age and death!’ Regarding
                        this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-110"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>“Through this offering of elixir and medicine</l>
                        <l>May all beings attain boundless life,</l>
                        <l>And may they quickly attain</l>
                        <l>The nectar of omniscience.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-111"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>“By offering elixir and medicine,</l>
                        <l>One will be healthy like the full moon. </l>
                        <l>One will enjoy well-being, happiness,</l>
                        <l>Longevity, and little harm.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-112"/>
                    <p tid="95">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by relinquishing male and female slaves, staff, and workers? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘The generosity of
                        relinquishing male and female slaves, staff, and workers represents the
                        perfection of the bodhisattvas’ freedom, independence, and self-arisen <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>. Therefore, I will definitely practice
                        generosity by relinquishing male and female slaves, staff, <ref cRef="F.88.b"/> and workers!’ When practicing generosity by
                        relinquishing male and female slaves, staff, and workers, bodhisattvas make
                        the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations expressed and
                        taught by the thus-gone ones, though this generosity of relinquishing my
                        male and female slaves, staff, and workers may I cause all beings to perfect
                        their freedom, independence, and self-arisen <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-113"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>“In short, by relinquishing my male and female slaves,</l>
                        <l>May all beings </l>
                        <l>Perfect the essence</l>
                        <l>Of their self-arisen <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-114"/>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>“Those who relinquish male and female servants</l>
                        <l>Will never be reborn as servants.</l>
                        <l>They will live with security and independence,</l>
                        <l>Never feeling disheartened or afraid.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-115"/>
                    <p tid="98">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of generosity
                        by giving away gold, silver, jewels, pearls, beryls, conch shells, moonstones,
                        coral, and other precious substances? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away gold, silver, jewels, pearls, beryls,
                        conch shells, moonstones, coral, and other precious substances represents the
                        blue, yellow, red, white, crimson, crystalline, and silvery colors of the
                        bodhisattvas’ light rays that shine within the infinite myriad buddha
                        realms. Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by giving away
                        gold, silver, jewels, pearls, beryls, conch shells, moonstones, coral, and
                        other precious substances!’ When practicing generosity by giving away gold,
                        silver, jewels, pearls, beryls, <ref cRef="F.89.a"/> conch shells, moonstones,
                        coral, and other precious substances, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations that are known, explained, and clarified
                        by the thus-gone ones, may this offering of gold, silver, jewels, pearls,
                        beryls, conch shells, moonstones, coral, and other precious substances enable
                        me to illuminate infinite myriad buddha realms with blue, yellow, red,
                        white, crimson, crystalline, and silvery light rays!’ Regarding this, there
                        are also some concluding verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-116"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>“Through this offering of precious substances</l>
                        <l>May I illuminate all the fields </l>
                        <l>Of the buddhas, the great sages,</l>
                        <l>With the brilliance of various light rays!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-117"/>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>“The noble persons who offer precious substances</l>
                        <l>Wherever they are reborn,</l>
                        <l>Will illuminate with their light rays</l>
                        <l>All worlds down to the Hell of Endless Torment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-118"/>
                    <p tid="101">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away vehicles such as horses, elephants, and chariots?
                        Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away
                        vehicles such as horses, elephants, and chariots represents becoming
                        included within the bodhisattvas’ Great Vehicle—the supreme vehicle, the
                        unequaled vehicle, the unsurpassed buddha vehicle that is the foremost,
                        sublime, and most excellent vehicle. Therefore, I will definitely practice
                        generosity by giving away horses, elephants, and chariots!’ When practicing
                        generosity by giving away horses, elephants, and chariots, bodhisattvas make
                        the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations expressed and
                        practiced by the thus-gone ones, by giving away horses, elephants, and
                        chariots may I include all beings in the Great Vehicle—the supreme vehicle,
                        the unequaled vehicle, <ref cRef="F.89.b"/> the unsurpassed buddha vehicle
                        that is the foremost, sublime, and most excellent vehicle!’ Regarding this,
                        there are also some further verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-119"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>“Through this offering of elephants</l>
                        <l>May I swiftly attract all beings</l>
                        <l>By means of the Great Vehicle of the buddhas—</l>
                        <l>The supreme vehicle!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-120"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“Those who offer elephants and horses</l>
                        <l>Will be bright, learned, and intelligent.</l>
                        <l>Being dedicated to the Great Vehicle,</l>
                        <l>Such beings will be fortunate.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-121"/>
                    <p tid="104">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away parks, forests for ascetic practice, and temples? Noble
                        son, bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away parks,
                        forests for ascetic practice, and temples represents the perfection of the
                        bodhisattvas’ factors of concentration. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by giving away parks, forests for ascetic practice, and
                        temples!’ When practicing generosity by giving away parks, forests for
                        ascetic practice, and temples, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration:
                        ‘In accordance with the aspirations extolled and praised by the buddhas,
                        through this gift of parks, forests for ascetic practice, and temples may I
                        cause all beings to perfect the factors of concentration!’ Regarding this,
                        there are also some further verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-122"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“Through this offering of temples and parks</l>
                        <l>May I cause all beings</l>
                        <l>To gradually perfect</l>
                        <l>The factors of concentration!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-123"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>“The practitioner who offers</l>
                        <l>Temples and parks</l>
                        <l>Will perfect the factors of concentration</l>
                        <l>And practice the spiritual life with great austerity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-124"/>
                    <p tid="107">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away their spouses, sons, and daughters? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: <ref cRef="F.90.a"/> ‘Giving
                        away one’s spouses, sons, and daughters represents the bodhisattvas’ awakening
                        to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood. Therefore, I will definitely practice
                        generosity by giving away my spouses, sons, and daughters!’ When practicing
                        generosity by giving away their spouses, sons, and daughters, bodhisattvas
                        make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations revered
                        by the thus-gone ones, through this gift of my spouses, sons, and daughters
                        may I cause all beings to fully awaken to unsurpassed and perfect
                        buddhahood!’ Regarding this, there are also some further verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-125"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>“For the sake of every single being,</l>
                        <l>May the offering of my sons</l>
                        <l>Cause all to swiftly awaken</l>
                        <l>To unsurpassed and sacred buddhahood!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-126"/>
                    <lg tid="109">
                        <l>“Those who give away their spouses, sons, and daughters</l>
                        <l>Will attain stainless awakening without difficulty.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-127" index="18">Following K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, J, K, N, C,
                                and H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dka’</foreign>. D
                                reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dga’</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Know that such diligent people</l>
                        <l>Will never meet with hardship.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-128"/>
                    <p tid="110">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away wealth, grains, and stores? Noble son,
                        bodhisattvas do so by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away wealth, grains,
                        and stores represents the bodhisattvas’ filling of the treasury of the
                        sacred Dharma. Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by giving
                        away wealth, grains, and stores!’ When practicing generosity by giving away
                        wealth, grains, and stores, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations expressed by the thus-gone ones, through
                        this gift of wealth, grains, and stores may I cause all beings to perfect
                        the treasury of the sacred Dharma!’ Regarding this, it is said: <ref cRef="F.90.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-129"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>“May all the merit, vaster than space,</l>
                        <l>That I have generated by relinquishing wealth and jewels</l>
                        <l>Cause the minds of all beings to swiftly expand, like royal treasuries, </l>
                        <l>By the treasure of the sacred Dharma!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-130"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>“Through whatever merit I have accumulated</l>
                        <l>By giving away wealth, grains, stores, and women,</l>
                        <l>May I swiftly attain awakening</l>
                        <l>And acquire the treasure of the sacred Dharma!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-131"/>
                    <p tid="113">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by relinquishing sovereignty over the four continents,
                        Jambudvīpa, as well as its kingdoms? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Relinquishing sovereignty over the four continents,
                        Jambudvīpa, as well as its kingdoms represents the bodhisattvas’ achievement of
                        sovereignty over the kingdom of the sacred Dharma. Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by relinquishing sovereignty over the four
                        continents, Jambudvīpa, as well as its kingdoms!’ When practicing generosity
                        by relinquishing sovereignty over the four continents, Jambudvīpa, as well
                        as its kingdoms, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance
                        with the aspirations taught by the thus-gone ones, through this gift of
                        relinquishing sovereignty over the four continents, Jambudvīpa, as well as
                        its kingdoms, may I cause all beings to achieve sovereignty over the kingdom
                        of the sacred Dharma!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-132"/>
                    <lg tid="114">
                        <l>“Through whatever merit I have generated</l>
                        <l>By giving away the entirety of the four continents,</l>
                        <l>May all people</l>
                        <l>Obtain the kingdom of the sacred Dharma!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-133"/>
                    <lg tid="115">
                        <l>“Those who offer Jambudvīpa</l>
                        <l>Will become triumphant rulers,</l>
                        <l>Kings who rule the four continents</l>
                        <l>In possession of the seven precious things.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-134"/>
                    <p tid="116">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away crest jewels and crowns? Noble son, bodhisattvas
                        do so <ref cRef="F.91.a"/> by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away crest
                        jewels and crowns represents the bodhisattvas’ achievement of the unseen
                        crown of the head.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-135" index="19">The Buddha’s crown protuberance (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">uṣṇīṣa</foreign>) is described in canonical sources as
                            being invisible, either because the light it emanates is brighter than
                            the light of the sun, or because there is no one above the Buddha, and
                            therefore no one can look down on him.</note> Therefore, I will
                        definitely practice generosity by giving away crest jewels and crowns!’ When
                        practicing generosity by giving away crest jewels and crowns, bodhisattvas
                        make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations expressed
                        by the thus-gone ones, may this gift of crest jewels and crowns cause all
                        beings to achieve the unseen crown of the head!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-136"/>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“Through all the merit I have accumulated</l>
                        <l>By offering crest jewels and crowns,</l>
                        <l>May all beings forever achieve</l>
                        <l>The unseen crown of the head!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-137"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“Through the offering of crest jewels</l>
                        <l>May I achieve the excellent crown protuberance,</l>
                        <l>Which is wide like a fig tree</l>
                        <l>And made of gold and jewels!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-138"/>
                    <p tid="119">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by offering their feet? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Offering one’s feet represents the bodhisattvas’
                        Dharma feet that lead to the seat of awakening. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by offering my feet!’ When practicing generosity by
                        offering their feet, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations accomplished by the thus-gone ones, through
                        this offering of my feet may all humans and other beings quickly renounce
                        their households forever and, in order to pacify the harm associated with
                        birth, old age, sickness, and death, become purposefully restrained and
                        joyful, their senses controlled. Like the gentle moonlight, may their
                        appearance become peaceful and radiant. Like the brilliance of many suns,
                        may the light rays of their compassion illuminate the gloom of helpless
                        humans engulfed in darkness, down to the Hell of Endless Torment, and
                        eliminate the physical sufferings of extreme heat. <ref cRef="F.91.b"/> May
                        they be endowed with lotus-like feet, which are adorned with the marks of
                        thousand-spoked wheels, even, and smooth. May they obtain long toes
                        connected by webbing like the feet of swans, and may they have nails that
                        are beautiful like fine and polished mirrors. May their feet be like jasmine
                        flowers. May they have anklebones that do not protrude, and calf bones
                        similar to reeds or the calves of antelopes. With such features on their
                        feet, may they gently and leisurely proceed to the vajra throne at the seat
                        of awakening. There, on the lion throne of the Dharma, may they thoroughly
                        trample on Māra in order to overcome him!’ Regarding this, there are also
                        some further verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-139"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“Through this offering of my feet</l>
                        <l>May the soles of others’ feet, marked by wheels,</l>
                        <l>Step firmly on the excellent throne</l>
                        <l>At the seat of awakening!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-140"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“Through this offering of my feet</l>
                        <l>May I ascend the supreme throne at the seat of awakening,</l>
                        <l>And defeat the demonic armies, troops,</l>
                        <l>And their vehicles!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-141"/>
                    <p tid="122">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by offering their hands? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Offering one’s hands represents the offering of the
                        bodhisattvas’ Dharma hands to all beings. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by offering my hands!’ When practicing generosity by
                        offering their hands, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations known to the thus-gone ones, through this
                        offering of my hands may I offer the hands of the Dharma to those who have
                        an inferior status: those who are blind, indigent, unprotected, miserable,
                        poor, homeless, defenseless, or helpless; to those who have fallen into the
                        lower realms of hell, the animal realms, or the world of Yama; and to all
                        those who are born in unfree states!’ Regarding this, there are also some
                        further verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-142"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“Through this offering of my hands</l>
                        <l>May I swiftly become an object of worship for the world,</l>
                        <l>A great guide with long hands holding jewels <ref cRef="F.92.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And possessing a golden complexion!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-143"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>“With the lauded hands of the Dharma</l>
                        <l>Pressed together out of compassion,</l>
                        <l>May I forever deliver</l>
                        <l>All beings from all lower realms!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-144"/>
                    <p tid="125">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away their ears and noses? Noble son, bodhisattvas do
                        so by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away one’s ears and nose represents
                        the bodhisattvas’ perfection of unimpaired sense faculties. Therefore, I
                        will definitely practice generosity by giving away my ears and nose!’ When
                        practicing generosity by giving away their ears and noses, bodhisattvas make
                        the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the aspirations made by the
                        thus-gone ones, through this gift of my ears and nose may I cause all
                        beings to be endowed with a full set of unimpaired sense faculties!’
                        Regarding this it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-145"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>“Through this gift of my ears and nose</l>
                        <l>May all beings be endowed </l>
                        <l>With a full set of sense faculties</l>
                        <l>And with unimpaired physical limbs!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-146"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“Those who give away their ears and nose,</l>
                        <l>Wherever they are born,</l>
                        <l>Will always have an attractive appearance</l>
                        <l>And enjoy a pleasant and beautiful physique.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-147"/>
                    <p tid="128">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by offering their eyes? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Offering one’s eyes represents the bodhisattvas’
                        purification of the stainless eye of Dharma. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by offering my eyes!’ When practicing generosity by
                        offering their eyes, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations purified by the thus-gone ones, through this
                        offering of my eyes may I cause all beings to purify the stainless eye of
                        Dharma!’ Regarding this, there are also some additional verses: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-148"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l>“Through this offering of my eyes</l>
                        <l>May I awaken to unsurpassed buddhahood</l>
                        <l>And cause all beings</l>
                        <l>To purify the eye of Dharma! <ref cRef="F.92.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-149"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“Through the excellent practice </l>
                        <l>Of offering one’s eyes,</l>
                        <l>One will attain spotless, immaculate,</l>
                        <l>Pure, wide, magnificent, and peaceful eyes.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-150"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>“That person will have beautiful eyes,</l>
                        <l>Similar to the petals of blue lotus flowers</l>
                        <l>Or the eyes of the kuṇāla bird,</l>
                        <l>With eyelashes like those of a cow.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-151"/>
                    <p tid="132">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away their heads? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away one’s head represents the bodhisattvas’
                        attainment of omniscient <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>, the supreme
                        state that is more exalted than the entirety of the three realms. Therefore,
                        I will definitely practice generosity by giving away my head!’ When
                        practicing generosity by giving away their heads, bodhisattvas make the
                        following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the benevolent aspirations of the
                        thus-gone ones, through this gift of my head, may I cause all beings to
                        attain omniscient <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>, the supreme state that
                        is more exalted than the entirety of the three realms!’ Regarding this,
                        there is also a further verse: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-152"/>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>“Through all the merit that I have accumulated</l>
                        <l>By giving away my head,</l>
                        <l>May all beings attain</l>
                        <l>The unwavering state of omniscience!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-153"/>
                    <p tid="134">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away their skin? Noble son, bodhisattvas do so by
                        reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away one’s skin represents the bodhisattvas’
                        perfection of smooth, fine, and golden skin. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by giving away my skin!’ When practicing generosity by
                        giving away their skin, bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In
                        accordance with the aspirations of the thus-gone ones, through this gift of
                        my skin may I cause all beings to achieve smooth, fine, and golden skin!’
                            <ref cRef="F.93.a"/> Regarding this, there is also a further verse: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-154"/>
                    <lg tid="135">
                        <l>“May this gift of my skin</l>
                        <l>Transform the skin that covers </l>
                        <l>The bodies of all beings</l>
                        <l>Into smooth, fine, and golden skin!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-155"/>
                    <p tid="136">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by giving away their flesh and blood? Noble son, bodhisattvas do
                        so by reflecting in this way: ‘Giving away one’s flesh and blood represents
                        the bodhisattvas’ extraction of substance from all that lacks substance.
                        Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by giving away my flesh and
                        blood!’ When practicing generosity by giving away their flesh and blood,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations made by the thus-gone ones, through the gift of my flesh and
                        blood, may I cause all beings to extract substance from all that lacks
                        substance!’ Regarding this, there is also a further verse: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-156"/>
                    <lg tid="137">
                        <l>“Through the karmic ripening</l>
                        <l>Brought about by offering my flesh and blood,</l>
                        <l>May all beings attain what is substantial</l>
                        <l>From all that lacks substance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-157"/>
                    <p tid="138">“How do bodhisattvas exert themselves in the practice of
                        generosity by offering the marrow of their bones? Noble son, bodhisattvas do
                        so by reflecting in this way: ‘Offering the marrow of one’s bones represents
                        the bodhisattvas’ completion of the indestructible vajra-like body.
                        Therefore, I will definitely practice generosity by offering the marrow of
                        my bones!’ When practicing generosity by offering the marrow of their bones,
                        bodhisattvas make the following aspiration: ‘In accordance with the
                        aspirations formed by the thus-gone ones, through this offering of the
                        marrow of my bones may I cause all beings to achieve the indestructible
                        vajra-like body!’ Regarding this, there is also a further verse: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-158"/>
                    <lg tid="139">
                        <l>“Through this offering of the marrow of my bones</l>
                        <l>May I cause all beings</l>
                        <l>To perfect their bodies, vessels of pus,</l>
                        <l>As indestructible vajra!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-159"/>
                    <p tid="140">“Furthermore, bodhisattvas also think, <ref cRef="F.93.b"/> ‘By
                        offering excellent colors, one will attain a beautiful complexion, so I will
                        definitely offer excellent colors! By offering excellent smells, one will
                        develop the scent of renown. By offering excellent flavors, one will gain
                        excellent provisions. By offering fine textures, one’s limbs will become
                        smooth and tender. By offering one’s hands, one will gain respect. By making
                        offerings with devotion, one will be revered by one’s relatives. By making
                        timely offerings, one will gain wealth and prosper in a timely way. By
                        offering what is suitable and pleasant, one will enjoy pleasant possessions
                        such as beds and clothes. By practicing the generosity that is free of
                        harming others, one will gain stable enjoyments. By practicing the
                        generosity of undertaking what is unpleasant, one’s entourage will be
                        intimate. By offering food, one will become strong. By offering beverages,
                        one will not thirst. By offering clothes, one will gain a beautiful
                        complexion. By offering lamps, one will develop excellent vision. By
                        offering music, one will have good hearing. By offering vehicles, one will
                        be happy. By offering medicine, one will be affected by few illnesses. By
                        offering flowers, one will be worshiped by others. By offering flower
                        garlands, one will be revered by others. By offering praises, one will be
                        endowed with the voice of Brahmā. By offering seats, one will attain
                        important positions. By offering vehicles, one will gain miraculous <term>powers</term>.
                        By offering ointments, one will be free of wounds. By the gift of sweeping,
                        one will be free of dirt. By offering bells, one will be able to recollect
                        former lives. By offering residences, everything will be offered. By
                        offering the Dharma, ambrosia will be offered. Therefore, I will definitely
                        practice generosity by offering the Dharma! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-160"/>
                    <p tid="141">“When bodhisattvas practice generosity by making such offerings,
                        they do not do so out of attachment, aversion, delusion, <ref cRef="F.94.a"/> irritation, contempt, violence, deprecation, disrespect, reproach, pride,
                        or haughtiness. They never offer leftovers or anything rotten or decaying.
                        Instead, they present all their offerings respectfully, always expressing an
                        attitude of respect, reverence, and worship. They offer large quantities of
                        excellent gifts with delight, joy, and elation. What they offer is pure, and
                        they offer it on a vast scale. They make offerings from their own hands with
                        respect and reverence, and their motivation is pure, wholesome, and
                        virtuous. They make offerings without any sense of miserliness, greed,
                        discouragement, or fear, and their offerings are vast and extensive. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-161"/>
                    <p tid="142">“When they practice generosity by making such offerings, they
                        never discriminate by thinking, ‘This person is disciplined, so I will be
                        generous to them—but that one has flawed <term type="ignore">discipline</term>. This person is virtuous, but that one is not. Being
                        generous to this person will generate great results, great benefits, and
                        great profits, but being generous to that one will not.’ Furthermore, since
                        their attitude is correct and free of mistakes, when bodhisattvas practice
                        generosity they never think, ‘Through this gift, these roots of virtue, and
                        this offering of the Dharma may I become a king, a ruler, a minister, a god,
                        a nāga, a divine son, or any other type of divine being!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-162"/>
                    <p tid="143">“Instead, what do bodhisattvas wish for? They dedicate their merit
                        to unsurpassed and perfect <ref cRef="F.94.b"/> awakening. They think,
                        ‘Through these roots of virtue and this offering of the Dharma, may I free
                        all beings who have not crossed over to the other shore, and may I liberate
                        all those who are not yet liberated. May I provide relief to all those who
                        have not found relief. May I lead beyond suffering all those who have not
                        transcended suffering, and may I be a guide, a leader, a liberator, a
                        refuge, a shelter, a support, and an assistant for those worldly beings who
                        are blind and lack a guide, a protector, refuge, shelter, support, and
                        assistance!’ Regarding this, it is said: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-163"/>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“Through this offering of the Dharma</l>
                        <l>May I liberate all beings</l>
                        <l>From the ocean of cyclic existence</l>
                        <l>Through the sole path of the Great Vehicle!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-164"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“May I release all beings </l>
                        <l>From the fetters of their afflictions!</l>
                        <l>May I provide relief to those who have not found relief</l>
                        <l>And guide them on the path to the transcendence of suffering!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-165"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“May I be a leader for those worldly beings</l>
                        <l>Who are blind and have no guide!</l>
                        <l>May I be a protector, an assistant, </l>
                        <l>A support, and a refuge for all beings!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-166"/>
                    <p tid="147"> “Noble son, this is how bodhisattva great beings exert themselves
                        in the perfection of generosity.” </p>
                    <p tid="148">When the bodhisattva great being Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows heard the Blessed One’s detailed exposition on
                        the perfection of generosity, he felt satisfied, delighted, and elated.
                        Thrilled, happy, and ecstatic, he stood up, draped his shawl over one
                        shoulder, and knelt with his right knee on the calyx of a lotus flower. With
                        his palms joined together, he bowed down toward the Blessed One and
                        applauded him by chanting these verses: <ref cRef="F.95.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-168"/>
                    <lg tid="149">
                        <l>“Benefactor, this is excellent! You who are always like a father, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>Benefactor, this is excellent! Blissful One, your words<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-169" index="20">Following KY, K, N, C, and
                                H: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gsung</foreign>. D reads
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gsang</foreign>.</note>
                            are excellent!</l>
                        <l>Friend, this is excellent! Beloved teacher, this is excellent!</l>
                        <l>Sole protector of hell beings, this is excellent! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-170"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“Excellent leader, this is excellent! Chief of gods and humans, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>Venerable One, this is excellent! Hero among humans, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>Your words are excellent! Great being, this is utterly excellent!</l>
                        <l>King of healers who dispels the poison of humans’ afflictions, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-171"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“Liberated being, this is excellent! One freed from the three existences,
                            this is excellent!</l>
                        <l>Physician, this is excellent! Generous and sublime aide, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>Glorious being, this is excellent! Auspicious and impartial one, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>Fortunate One with a pure face like the sun and moon, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-172"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“Wise One with long and wide sapphire eyes, this is excellent!</l>
                        <l>Glorious One with a beautiful and marvelous nose, this is excellent!</l>
                        <l>Eloquent One with earlobes like golden plumb lines, this is
                            excellent!</l>
                        <l>You with teeth white like snow or conch shells, this is excellent! Homage
                            to you!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-173"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“O chief protector, this detailed exposition on generosity, </l>
                        <l>Which you have expounded so well to these people today, is excellent!</l>
                        <l>Now we wish to hear more about discipline, patience, power,</l>
                        <l>Wisdom, methods, concentration, miracles, and aspiration.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-174"/>
                    <p tid="153">When the Blessed One had spoken, the bodhisattvas
                        Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta, Avalokiteśvara, Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows, and the other bodhisattvas, along with the gods,
                        the four great kings, and the world with all its gods, humans, demigods, and
                        gandharvas, rejoiced and praised the words of the Blessed One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-175"/>
                    <p tid="154">This concludes the noble Great Vehicle sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity</title>. <ref cRef="F.95.b"/>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="162">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-176"/>
                    <p tid="155">This was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholar
                        Prajñāvarman, the translator-editor venerable Yeshé Dé, and others.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="163">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="707">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-989">
                        <abbr>C</abbr>
                        <expan>Coné (co ne) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-990">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (sde dge) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-991">
                        <abbr>H</abbr>
                        <expan>Lhasa (zhol) Kangyur </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-992">
                        <abbr>J</abbr>
                        <expan>Lithang (’jang sa tham) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-993">
                        <abbr>K</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking (pe cin) Kangxi Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-994">
                        <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Yongle (g.yung lo) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-995">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang (snar thang) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-064-001-996">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace (stog pho brang) Manuscript Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="164">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-177">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sbyin pa’i pha rol tu phyin pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dāna­pāramitā­sūtra</title>). Toh 182, Degé Kangyur vol. 61 (mdo
                        sde, tsa), folios 77.a.1–95.b.1.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-178">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sbyin pa’i pha rol tu phyin pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>.<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> bka’
                            ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung
                        go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The
                        Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center).
                        108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China
                        Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 61, pp. 203–247. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-179">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sbyin pa’i pha rol tu phyin pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dāna­pāramitā­sūtra</title>). Stok 222, Stok Palace Manuscript
                        Kangyur vol. 73 (mdo sde, za), folios 240b.1–266b.6.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-180">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sbyin pa’i phan yon bstan pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dānānuśaṃsā­nirdeśa­sūtra</title>). Toh 183, Degé Kangyur vol. 61
                        (mdo sde, tsa), folios 95b.2–96b.6. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-181">Lalou, Marcelle. “Les textes bouddhiques au
                        temps du roi Khri-sroṅ-lde-bcan.” <title xml:lang="fr">Journal
                            asiatique</title> 241 (1953): 313–52.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-002-182">McCombs, Jason Matthew. “Mahāyāna and the
                        Gift: Theories and Practices.” PhD diss., University of California, Los
                        Angeles, 2014.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-183">
                            <term>aspiration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon lam </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨོན་ལམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">praṇidhāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-184">
                            <term>concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསམ་གཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-185">
                            <term>diligence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-186">
                            <term>discipline</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-187">
                            <term>generosity</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-305">
                            <term>kācilindika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ka tsa lin di </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀ་ཙ་ལིན་དི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kācilindika, kācalindika</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet for softness, usually applied 
                                to cloth, and probably in reference, directly or metaphorically, to the
                                down of the <term type="ignore">kācilindika</term> bird. See Lamotte, 
                                Etienne. <title xml:lang="fr">La Concentration de la
                                    Marche Héroïque</title>. Bruxelles: Peeters (1975), p. 261, n. 321. 
                                The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> includes the term using the variant 
                                spelling <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kācalindika</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-188">
                            <term>insight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-189">
                            <term>kuṇāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku na la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུ་ན་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kuṇāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bird with beautiful eyes that lives on Mount
                                Sumeru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-190">
                            <term>patience</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the six or ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-191">
                            <term>power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-307">
                            <term>sacrificial post</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod sdong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་སྡོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A post set up as a marker to which offerings may be presented. Described in
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreyāvadāna</title> (“The Story of Maitreya”), which in the
                                Kangyur is found within the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajya­vastu</title> (in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1, Degé Kangyur vol. kha, folios 29a-32b); a
                                matching passage from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Divyāvadāna</title> is translated in Rotman,
                                Andy, <title xml:lang="en">Divine Stories</title> Part I (Somerville: Wisdom Publications, 2008), pp. 121–124.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-192">
                            <term>śarabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldang sko ska </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྡང་སྐོ་སྐ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śarabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical eight-legged lion.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-193">
                            <term>skillful means</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-194">
                            <term>applications of mindfulness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa nye bar gzhag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">smṛtyupasthāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Four contemplations on: the body, feelings,
                                mind, and phenomena. These are part of the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of awakening</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-195">
                            <term>bases of miraculous power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzu ’phrul gyi rkang pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫུ་འཕྲུལ་གྱི་རྐང་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛddhipāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Determination, discernment, diligence, and
                                absorption. These are part of the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of awakening</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-196">
                            <term>branches of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi yan lag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་ཡན་ལག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhyaṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Recollection, analysis of the dharmas,
                                diligence, joy, pliancy, absorption, equanimity. These are part of
                                the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of
                                awakening</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-197" mode="marked">
                            <term>powers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indriya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and
                                knowledge. These are part of the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of awakening</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-198">
                            <term>strengths</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Faith, diligence, mindfulness, absorption, and
                                knowledge. These are part of the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of awakening</term>. Although the same as the <term>powers</term>,
                                they are termed strengths due to their greater strength.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-199">
                            <term>true relinquishments</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag par spong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པར་སྤོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samyakprahāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Relinquishing negative acts in the present and
                                future and enhancing positive acts in the present and future. These
                                are part of the thirty-seven <term type="ignore">factors of
                                    awakening</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-200">
                            <term>wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the ten perfections.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-201">
                            <term>piśāca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piśāca</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of demons. Literally
                                “flesh eaters.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-202">
                            <term>Hell of Endless Torment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avīci</term>
                            <term type="definition">The most severe among the eight hot hell realms,
                                characterized as endless not only in terms of torment, but also in
                                terms of the ceaseless chain of actions and effects experienced
                                there, the long lifespan of its denizens, and its excessive
                                crowdedness, in which there is no physical space between its
                                denizens.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-203">
                            <term>bhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A general term for spirit, ghost, or
                                demon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-204">
                            <term>seven precious things</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen sna bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་སྣ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saptaratna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The seven precious things comprise the seven
                                precious metals and stones, namely, gold, silver, turquoise, coral,
                                pearl, emerald, and sapphire. More generally‌, they may also
                                comprise the symbols of royal dominion, namely, the wheel, gem,
                                queen, minister, elephant, general, and horse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-205">
                            <term>Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun shes kauN Di nya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎཌིནྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five ascetics who later became
                                the first five disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-206">
                            <term>Ākāśagarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśagarbha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight main bodhisattvas, the heart
                                sons of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-207">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s cousin and principal
                                attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-208">
                            <term>Anavatapta </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma dros pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་དྲོས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anavatapta </term>
                            <term type="definition">A king of the nāgas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-209">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight main bodhisattvas, the heart
                                sons of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-210">
                            <term>Bakkula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ba ku la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བ་ཀུ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bakkula </term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the sixteen elders.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-211">
                            <term>Bali</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bali</term>
                            <term type="definition">A ruler of the asuras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-212">
                            <term>Bhadrika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟང་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadrika</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the first five disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-213">
                            <term>Bhairavī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs byed ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་བྱེད་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhairavī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Fierce and terrifying Hindu goddess identified
                                as the consort of Bhairava.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-214">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-215">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajyasamudgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman yang dag ’phags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་ཡང་དག་འཕགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajya­samudgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-216">
                            <term>Bharadvāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bha ra dva dza </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྷ་ར་དབ༹་ཛ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bharadvāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha. One of the
                                first ten to be ordained.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-217">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the Sahā world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-218">
                            <term>Candra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lunar deity in Hindu mythology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-219">
                            <term>Candraprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-220">
                            <term>Crown Jewel of the Lord of Men Resembling a Sublime Lion Sporting and Roaring in Mountain Caves, Peaks, Clefts, Valleys, and Meadows</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri’i phug dang zom dang ri sul dang gseb dang
                                sman ljongs na seng ge’i mchog rnam par bsgyings shing nga ro rnam
                                par sgrogs pa lta bu’i mi’i dbang po’i gtsug gi nor bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིའི་ཕུག་དང་ཟོམ་དང་རི་སུལ་དང་གསེབ་དང་སྨན་ལྗོངས་ན་སེང་གེའི་མཆོག་རྣམ་པར་བསྒྱིངས་ཤིང་ང་རོ་རྣམ་པར་སྒྲོགས་པ་ལྟ་བུའི་མིའི་དབང་པོའི་གཙུག་གི་ནོར་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva great being, interlocutor of the
                                Buddha in <title xml:lang="en">The Perfection of Generosity.</title>
                            </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-221">
                            <term>Cūḍāpanthaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lam phran bstan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལམ་ཕྲན་བསྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cūḍāpanthaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-222">
                            <term>Determined Effort</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spro ba brtan pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྲོ་བ་བརྟན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-223">
                            <term>Devamukuṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha’i cod pan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་ཅོད་པན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Devamukuṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-224">
                            <term>Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul ’khor srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great kings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-225">
                            <term>Dṛḍhamati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo gros brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་གྲོས་བརྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dṛḍhamati</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-226">
                            <term>Dṛḍhavikrama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu rtsal brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་རྩལ་བརྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dṛḍhavikrama</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-227">
                            <term>Dṛḍhavīrya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྩོན་འགྲུས་བརྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dṛḍhavīrya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-228">
                            <term>Druma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ljon pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྗོན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Druma</term>
                            <term type="definition">A king of the kiṃnaras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-229">
                            <term>Equal and Evenly Set Teeth White like Silver, Conch Shells, the Moon, a White Lotus, and Milk</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so mnyam zhing thags bzang la dkar ba dngul dang
                                dung dang zla ba dang ku mud dang ’o ma ltar dkar ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་མཉམ་ཞིང་ཐགས་བཟང་ལ་དཀར་བ་དངུལ་དང་དུང་དང་ཟླ་བ་དང་ཀུ་མུད་དང་འོ་མ་ལྟར་དཀར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-230">
                            <term>Female Spear Holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdung thogs ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མདུང་ཐོགས་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A Hindu goddess, unidentified. McCombs (p. 128)
                                suggests that the Sanskrit name for this goddess might be Śūlinī
                                (one of the names for Durgā) or Śaktidhārī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-231">
                            <term>Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ba lang bdag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བ་ལང་བདག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gavāṃpati</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha. One of the
                                first ten to be ordained.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-232">
                            <term>Hair in a Topknot Shining Dark Like Bees, Ink, Peacocks, and
                                Nightingales</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bung ba dang snag sa dang rma bya dang ’jon mo
                                dang mugs gsal ral pa’i thor tshugs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བུང་བ་དང་སྣག་ས་དང་རྨ་བྱ་དང་འཇོན་མོ་དང་མུགས་གསལ་རལ་པའི་ཐོར་ཚུགས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-233">
                            <term>Hārītī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phrog ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕྲོག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hārītī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A female yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-234">
                            <term>Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dra ba can gyi ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲ་བ་ཅན་གྱི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-235">
                            <term>Kamala­dala­vimala­nakṣatra­rāja­saṃkusumitā­bhijña</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad ma’i ’dab ma ltar dri ma med pa rgyu skar
                                rgyal po mngon par shes pa’i me tog shin tu rgyas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མའི་འདབ་མ་ལྟར་དྲི་མ་མེད་པ་རྒྱུ་སྐར་རྒྱལ་པོ་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པའི་མེ་ཏོག་ཤིན་ཏུ་རྒྱས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kamala­dala­vimala­nakṣatra­rāja­saṃkusumitā­bhijña</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-236">
                            <term>Kapphiṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ka pi na </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀ་པི་ན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kapphiṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-237">
                            <term>Mahākauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsus po che </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསུས་པོ་ཆེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākauṣṭhila</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-238">
                            <term>King Precious Moonlight of Pure Virtue</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba dri ma med pa rnam dag rin chen zla ’od
                                rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བ་དྲི་མ་མེད་པ་རྣམ་དག་རིན་ཆེན་ཟླ་འོད་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-239">
                            <term>Kubera</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus ngan po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་ངན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kubera</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great kings, also known as
                                Vaiśravaṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-240">
                            <term>Mahākāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་ཆེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A ruler of the garuḍas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-241">
                            <term>Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­maudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the two closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his miraculous abilities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-242">
                            <term>Mahāśrīdevī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi lha mo chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་ལྷ་མོ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśrīdevī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Lakṣmī, Hindu goddess of wealth and
                                prosperity and consort of Viṣṇu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-243">
                            <term>Mahāsthāmaprāpta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu chen thob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་ཆེན་ཐོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sthāmaprāpta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva great being who represents the <term type="ignore">power</term> of <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-244">
                            <term>Mahātejas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་ཆེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahātejas</term>
                            <term type="definition">A ruler of the garuḍas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-245">
                            <term>Maheśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maheśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Śiva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-246">
                            <term>Mahotsāha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spro ba che ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྲོ་བ་ཆེ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahotsāha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-247">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight main bodhisattvas, the heart
                                sons of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-248">
                            <term>Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight main bodhisattvas, the heart
                                sons of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-249">
                            <term>Moonlike Body</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-250">
                            <term>Nanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha's half-brother and disciple.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-251">
                            <term>Pañcaśikha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zur phud lnga pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟུར་ཕུད་ལྔ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pañcaśikha</term>
                            <term type="definition">An eminent gandharva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-252">
                            <term>Pāñcika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lngas rtsen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྔས་རྩེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pāñcika</term>
                            <term type="definition">A leader of the yakṣas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-253">
                            <term>Yellow-Robed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ser mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A Hindu goddess, unidentified. McCombs (p. 128)
                                suggests that the Sanskrit name for this goddess might be Pītā or
                                Vāruṇī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-254">
                            <term>Stable Strength</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthu brtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐུ་བརྟན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-255">
                            <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pra dz+nyA bar ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲ་ཛྙཱ་བར་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian Bengali paṇḍita resident in Tibet
                                during the late eighth/early ninth centuries. Arriving in Tibet on
                                an invitation from the Tibetan king, he assisted in the translation
                                of numerous canonical scriptures. He is also the author of a few
                                philosophical commentaries contained in the Tibetan Tengyur
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</foreign>)
                                collection.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-256">
                            <term>Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog tu dga’ ba’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོག་ཏུ་དགའ་བའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prāmodyarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-257">
                            <term>Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">At least five different disciples of the Buddha in 
                                the canonical texts have this name, but the Pūrṇa in this text  is likely to 
                                be the eminent disciple of the Buddha from Kapilavastu, nephew of 
                                Ājñātakauṇḍinya who ordained him, and described as the foremost disciple in explaining the doctrine.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-258">
                            <term>Rāhu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A ruler of the asuras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-259">
                            <term>Rāhula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན་ཟིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha's son and disciple.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-260">
                            <term>Ratnacūḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen gtsug phud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་གཙུག་ཕུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnacūḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-261">
                            <term>Ratnagarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnagarbha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-262">
                            <term>Ratnajālin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dra ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་དྲ་བ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnajālin</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-267">
                            <term>Ratnamukuṭa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen cod pan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཅོད་པན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnamukuṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-268">
                            <term>Ratnapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rin chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་ན་རིན་ཆེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnapāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-269">
                            <term>Ratnaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-270">
                            <term>Ratnasiṃha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen seng ge </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་སེང་གེ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnasiṃha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-271">
                            <term>Resembling the Karṇikāra Tree, the Mango Tree, and the Blooming
                                Burflower Tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dong ka’i shing dang sa ha ka ra dang me tog
                                ’byung ba’i ka dam pa lta bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དོང་ཀའི་ཤིང་དང་ས་ཧ་ཀ་ར་དང་མེ་ཏོག་འབྱུང་བའི་ཀ་དམ་པ་ལྟ་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> </term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-272">
                            <term>Rising Sun</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ma’i ’char ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་མའི་འཆར་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> </term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-273">
                            <term>Sāgara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya mtsho </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ་མཚོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sāgara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A king of the nāgas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-274">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-275">
                            <term>Samantabhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samantabhadra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight main bodhisattvas, the heart
                                sons of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-276">
                            <term>Śaṅkhinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dung can ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དུང་ཅན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śaṅkhinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">A Hindu goddess.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-277">
                            <term>Śiva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śiva</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the main Hindu gods.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-278">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ra dva ti’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ར་དབ༹་ཏིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the two closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                known for his pure observance of discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-279">
                            <term>Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbyangs can ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབྱངས་ཅན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Hindu goddess of art and <term type="ignore">wisdom</term>, consort of Brahmā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-280">
                            <term>Slender, Supple, Firm, Fine, and Smooth Limbs Youthful like Flowers and with Copper-Colored Nails</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rka lag phra zhing mnyen la gzhon sha chags
                                shing sra ba la ’jam zhing me tog ltar shin tu gzhon la rka lag gi
                                sen mo zangs kyi mdog ’dra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྐ་ལག་ཕྲ་ཞིང་མཉེན་ལ་གཞོན་ཤ་ཆགས་ཤིང་སྲ་བ་ལ་འཇམ་ཞིང་མེ་ཏོག་ལྟར་ཤིན་ཏུ་གཞོན་ལ་རྐ་ལག་གི་སེན་མོ་ཟངས་ཀྱི་མདོག་འདྲ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-281">
                            <term>Smiling Face That Brightly Shines Like the Moon and a Lotus
                                Flower</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pad ma dang zla ba ltar bzhin ’dzum zhing brjid
                                la mdangs gsal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པད་མ་དང་ཟླ་བ་ལྟར་བཞིན་འཛུམ་ཞིང་བརྗིད་ལ་མདངས་གསལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-282">
                            <term>Subhūti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་འབྱོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhūti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-283">
                            <term>Śuddhodhana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zas gtsang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟས་གཙང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śuddhodhana</term>
                            <term type="definition">King of Kapilavastu and father of the
                                Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-284">
                            <term>Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sūryaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-285">
                            <term>Suśubha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suśubha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-286">
                            <term>Tongue Wide as the Leaves of Palm and Plantain Trees and
                                Resembling a Copper Plate</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lce chu shing gi lo ma dang ta la’i ’dab ma ltar
                                yangs shing zangs kyi glegs ma lta bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྕེ་ཆུ་ཤིང་གི་ལོ་མ་དང་ཏ་ལའི་འདབ་མ་ལྟར་ཡངས་ཤིང་ཟངས་ཀྱི་གླེགས་མ་ལྟ་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-287">
                            <term>Top Ornament of Precious Qualities with Magnificent Sapphire-like
                                Eyes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che mthon ka ltar mig shin tu mdzes pa
                                yon tan rin po che’i tog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེ་མཐོན་ཀ་ལྟར་མིག་ཤིན་ཏུ་མཛེས་པ་ཡོན་ཏན་རིན་པོ་ཆེའི་ཏོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-288">
                            <term>Umā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dka’ zlog ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཀའ་ཟློག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Umā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Pārvatī, consort of Śiva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-289">
                            <term>Upananda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upananda</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the disciples of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-290">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam thos kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great kings, also known as
                                Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-291">
                            <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A leader of the yakṣas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-292">
                            <term>Varuṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chu lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆུ་ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Varuṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the guardian deities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-293">
                            <term>Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags skyes po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་སྐྱེས་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great kings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-294">
                            <term>Virūpākṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig mi bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་མི་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virūpākṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four great kings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-295">
                            <term>Voice as Delightful as the Songs of Cuckoos, Parrots, Grouse,
                                Pheasants, and Kalaviṅka Birds</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khu byug dang ne tso dang ri skegs dang ku na la
                                dang ka la ping ka skad ’byin pa lta bur yid du ’ong ba’i nga ro’i
                                gdangs nges par sgrogs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁུ་བྱུག་དང་ནེ་ཙོ་དང་རི་སྐེགས་དང་ཀུ་ན་ལ་དང་ཀ་ལ་པིང་ཀ་སྐད་འབྱིན་པ་ལྟ་བུར་ཡིད་དུ་འོང་བའི་ང་རོའི་གདངས་ངེས་པར་སྒྲོགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> </term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the bodhisattva great beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-296">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of death.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-297">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the
                                late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-298">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Personification of everything that functions as
                                a hindrance to awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-300">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu’i gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུའི་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The continent (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvīpa</foreign>) on which we live, shaped like a rose-apple
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jambū</foreign>) according to ancient
                                South Asian cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-301">
                            <term>Kapilavastu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ser skya’i gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་སྐྱའི་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kapilavastu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital city of the Śākya kingdom, where the
                                Buddha grew up.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-302">
                            <term>Mount Sumeru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sumeru</term>
                            <term type="definition">Center of the universe according to Buddhist and
                                Hindu cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-061-002-303">
                            <term>Sahā world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sahā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indian Buddhist name for the universe in which
                                we live. It means “endurance,” as beings there have to endure
                                suffering. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>