<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud rtsi brjod pa/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛtavyāharaṇa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Nectar of Speech</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bdud rtsi brjod pa zhes bya ba
                    theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Nectar of
                    Speech”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryāmṛtavyāharaṇanāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">Ambrosial Speech</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛtavyāharaṇa</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-10">Translated by The
                    Dharmasāgara Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-80">Rebecca Hufen</author>
                <author role="translatorTib" ref="contributors.xml#person-79">Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche (Pema Dorjee)</author>

                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Dr. Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">John Canti</editor>


            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.9.2 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>

            <publicationStmt status="1.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                    non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages,
                    and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-061-017"/>
                <date>2020-02-04</date>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh197" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 197</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa), folios 271.b–274.b</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="7">
                        <volume number="61" start-page="542" end-page="548"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11823" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-02-29T11:28:52.204Z" user="admin">29/02/2020 11:28:52</note>

                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.0.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2020-01-23T15:47:53.829Z" user="andreas">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-01-27T13:15:59.698Z" user="mike">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-01-29T10:44:35.699Z" user="andreas">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-01-30T11:49:29.402Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
            
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.0" date-time="2020-02-06T11:23:19.619Z" user="andre">v 1.0</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.2" date-time="2020-02-07T06:10:27.77Z" user="mike">v 0.1.2</note>
<note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2" date-time="2020-02-07T06:10:27.77Z" user="mike">2</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.3" date-time="2020-02-07T11:39:51.884Z" user="andre">v 0.1.3</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.9.1" date-time="2020-02-29T11:20:05.269Z" user="john">Reviewed and edited, ready for release.</note>
<note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1.a" date-time="2020-02-29T11:20:05.269Z" user="john">Reviewed and edited, ready for release.</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.9.2" date-time="2020-02-29T11:28:49.504Z" user="john">Contributor edit</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-57"/>
                <p tid="41">In this sūtra, Buddha Śākyamuni teaches, at the request of Maitreya, five qualities that bodhisattvas should have: (1) giving the Dharma, (2) giving freedom from fear, (3) practicing great loving kindness, great compassion, great joy, and great equanimity, (4) repairing dilapidated stūpas, and (5) causing all beings to aspire to the mind of awakening. Maitreya praises the benefits of this teaching and vows to teach it himself in future degenerate times. Both Maitreya and the Buddha emphasize the positive effects on beings and the environment that upholding, preserving, and teaching <title xml:lang="en">The Nectar of Speech</title> will bring about.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="2">Acknowledgements</head>
                <p tid="42">This text was translated from the Tibetan, introduced, and edited by the Dharmasāgara Translation Group: Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche, Rebecca Hufen, Shanshan Jia, Jason Sanche, and Arne Schelling. Prof. Harunaga Isaacson (University of Hamburg) kindly assisted the translators with help and advice. The final version was also lightly edited by the 84000 editorial team. The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="3">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-1"/>
                    <p tid="5">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Nectar of Speech</title> is a Mahāyāna sūtra in
                        which the Buddha Śākyamuni, at the request of the bodhisattva Maitreya,
                        teaches a great assembly of monks and bodhisattvas. The setting for the
                        teaching is the famous Veṇuvana forest
                        monastery. This monastery was located outside Rājagṛha, the capital city
                        of Magadha, which at the time was one of the great kingdoms of ancient India
                        (located in the modern-day state of Bihar). The teaching provides an outline
                        of the following five qualities of bodhisattvas that will ensure they
                        avert obstacles, live long, and attain awakening: Bodhisattvas
                        should (1) give the Dharma; (2) give freedom from fear; (3) practice great
                        loving kindness, great compassion, great joy, and great equanimity; (4)
                        repair dilapidated stūpas; and (5) cause all beings to aspire to the mind of
                        awakening. When the Buddha delivers this brief teaching, a large number of
                        the monks, bodhisattvas, and celestial beings in attendance attain different
                        stages of realization. Maitreya is inspired to give a discourse on the
                        benefits of this sūtra and vows to teach it himself in the future during the
                        time of degeneration. His exposition of its benefits and commitment to teach it himself are welcomed and
                        endorsed by the Buddha. At the end, the Buddha emphasizes the importance of
                        this teaching and instructs Ānanda to uphold and preserve it. The Buddha
                        names the teaching <title xml:lang="en">The Nectar of Speech</title> and
                        also gives it an alternative title, <title xml:lang="en">The Question of
                            Maitreya</title>.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-59">It should be noted that 
                                there are three sūtras elsewhere in the Kangyur whose main titles are <title xml:lang="en">The Question of
                                    Maitreya</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya­paripṛcchā</title>, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pas zhus pa</title>): <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh85.html">Toh 85</ref>, <ref target="https://read.84000.co/translation/toh85.html">Toh 86</ref>, and Toh 149.</note> In the standard ending formula, the
                        entire assembly rejoices and praises the words of the Buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-2"/>
                    <p tid="6">At present we are not aware of any surviving Sanskrit version, Chinese translation, or
                        rendering of the text in any other language. The Sanskrit titles are rendered differently 
                        in the versions in different Kangyurs: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛtavyāharaṇa</title> (Degé), <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛtadāna</title> (Narthang), and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛtavarṇa</title> (Stok Palace). According to the colophon,
                        the Tibetan translation was produced by the Indian scholar Prajñāvarman
                        and the Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé. It can therefore be dated to the 
                        late eighth or early ninth century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> in central Tibet. The text was cited by the
                        Tibetan translator Kawa Paltsek, who was a contemporary of the translators<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-60">In his <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung rab rin po che’i gtam rgyud dang shAkya’i rabs rgyud</title>, (Toh
                            4357)<!--Reference Toh 4357-->, a treatise in the Tengyur; see <ptr target="#UT22084-061-017-14"/>.</note> and is listed in the Denkarma catalogue,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-3" index="3">
                            Denkarma, F.299.b. See also
                                Hermann-Pfandt (2008), p. 114, no. 215.</note> which confirms
                        that the translation of this sūtra into Tibetan must have been completed
                        before 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-61"/>
                    <p tid="6">This English translation has
                        been produced based on the Tibetan rendering that is found in the Degé
                        Kangyur as well as the Comparative Edition (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) and the Stok Palace manuscript.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="7"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="8">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="9">The Nectar of Speech</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-6"/>
                    <p tid="13">
                        <ref cRef="F.271.b" type="folio"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-7"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-8"/>
                    <p tid="15">Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was residing in Rājagṛha, at 
                        the Kalandaka­nivāsa in Veṇuvana, with a great saṅgha of five 
                        hundred bhikṣus and a great saṅgha of seventy-two thousand
                        bodhisattvas. At that time the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya was also
                        seated in the assembly.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-62"/>
                    <p tid="16">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya rose from his
                        seat, draped his upper robe over one shoulder, knelt on his right knee, and
                        with palms joined bowed to the Bhagavān and said, “With permission, I would
                        like to ask the Blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect Buddha some questions.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-9"/>
                    <p tid="16">The Bhagavān replied, “Maitreya, the Tathāgata will always grant you
                        permission. Maitreya, ask the Thus-Gone, worthy, perfect Buddha whatever you
                        wish, and I shall ease your mind by answering each of your questions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-10"/>
                    <p tid="17">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya then asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān,
                        <ref cRef="F.272.a" type="folio"/> what are the qualities that bodhisattva 
                        mahāsattvas need to have so
                        that none of Māra’s hordes will cause them obstacles, so that none of 
                        Māra’s retinue will transgress against them, so that out of love for sentient beings 
                        they will live for a long time, and so that they will soon
                        fully awaken to unexcelled and perfect awakening?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-11"/>
                    <p tid="18">The Bhagavān replied to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya,
                        excellent, excellent! Maitreya, your intention in asking the Thus-Gone,
                        worthy, perfect Buddha about this matter is excellent, since you act for the
                        benefit of many beings, aim for the happiness of many beings, have
                        compassion for the world, and seek the welfare, benefit, and well-being of
                        gods and humans. Hence, Maitreya, listen very well and keep it in mind! I
                        will explain it.”</p>
                    <p tid="19">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya replied, “I will do so,” and he 
                        listened accordingly as the Bhagavān taught as follows.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-13"/>
                    <p tid="20">“Maitreya, there are five qualities that bodhisattva mahāsattvas should have  
                        so that none of Māra’s hordes will cause them obstacles, so that none of 
                        Māra’s retinue will transgress against them, so that out of love
                        for sentient beings they will live for a long time, and so that they will soon fully awaken to unexcelled and
                        perfect awakening. What are those five qualities? They are the unceasing giving of
                        the Dharma; the unceasing giving of freedom from fear; the unceasing practice
                        of great love, great compassion, great joy, and great equanimity; the
                        unceasing repair of dilapidated stūpas; <ref cRef="F.272.b" type="folio"/> and the unceasing inspiring of
                        all beings to set their minds on awakening.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-14" index="4"> Kawa Paltsek (folio 283.b) quotes this
                                passage as follows: “When bodhisattvas are endowed with five
                                qualities, they will not be harmed by Māra, they will live long, and
                                they will soon attain awakening. These five are (1) always giving
                                sentient beings the Dharma, (2) giving sentient beings freedom 
                                from fear, (3) practicing the four immeasurable qualities, (4)
                                repairing old stūpas, and (5) causing all beings to aspire to the
                                mind of awakening.”</note> Maitreya, if bodhisattva mahāsattvas
                        have those five qualities, none of Māra’s hordes will cause them obstacles, none of 
                        Māra’s retinue will transgress against them, out of love
                        for sentient beings they will live for a long time, and they
                        they will soon fully awaken to unexcelled and perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-15"/>
                    <p tid="21">When the Bhagavān taught this discourse on the five qualities, the minds of
                        five thousand bhikṣus became free of all defilements with no further appropriation.
                        Seventy-two thousand bodhisattvas attained the acceptance that phenomena do
                        not arise. The Dharma eye of eighty-four thousand gods regarding phenomena became 
                        purified, free from dust and stains, and without defilements. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-16"/>
                    <p tid="22">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya then said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, I
                        feel inspired to speak. Blissful One, I feel inspired to speak.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-63"/>
                    <p tid="23">The Bhagavān said, “Noble son, speak if you know the time has come.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-18"/>
                    <p tid="24">Having thus received the Bhagavān’s permission, the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Maitreya rose from his seat, draped his upper robe over one shoulder, knelt
                        on his right knee, and with palms joined bowed to the Bhagavān and said,
                        “Bhagavān, how marvelous that this Dharma discourse has been taught by the Bhagavān
                        in order that all beings—sick because of desire, anger, and ignorance, obscured
                        by the darkness of the cataracts and visual aberrations of all views—may have their illnesses 
                        of the afflictions cured, and have their unexcelled Dharma eye purified! Bhagavān, this Dharma
                        discourse you have taught is a great nectar! <ref cRef="F.273.a" type="folio"/> Bhagavān, this Dharma discourse 
                        you have taught is a great panacea! Even for beings born as animals, those 
                        who happen to hear this Dharma discourse will have gathered thereby an accumulation of great roots of virtue and
                        will be superior to all beings. They will behold all buddhas. They will be
                        of great service to many beings. They will bring about roots of virtue. They
                            will purify their karmic obscurations,
                            be freed from the animal realm, and attain human bodies. Then,
                            remembering their previous lifetimes and gaining faith in the teachings
                            of the Tathāgata, they will be reborn in any buddha realm they wish. So if
                            that is the case even for them, what need is there to mention those who hear this teaching 
                            as human beings?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-19"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Bhagavān, hearing this Dharma discourse is
                        of great benefit to beings. Bhagavān, beings who hear this Dharma discourse
                        belong to the assembly of those who are certain to awaken fully to
                        unexcelled and perfect awakening. Respected Bhagavān, because they will be
                        embraced by the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddhas, they will soon fully
                        awaken to unexcelled and perfect awakening.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-20"/>
                    <p tid="26">The Bhagavān said, “Excellent, Maitreya, excellent! Maitreya, it is just as
                        you have said. It is the truth. It is that alone. It is unmistaken. Even
                        those who listen to this Dharma discourse doubtingly will have no small roots of
                        virtue; so what need is there to mention those who listen to, retain,
                        hold, read, master, and <ref cRef="F.273.b" type="folio"/> teach it extensively and properly without
                        any doubts? Such holders of the sūtra will not encounter the works of Māra. They
                        will not be harmed by desire, anger, ignorance, pride, avarice, rage, or
                        malevolence. Their bodies will not be stricken by plague or disease. In
                        whatever region such a sūtra as this is kept, wherever such a Dharma teacher dwells,
                        or wherever this Dharma discourse is written down as a scripture—in such
                        places all diseases, epidemics, harm, contagions, and conflicts will be
                        quelled.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-21"/>
                    <p tid="27">Then the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān,
                        later, in the future, during the final five hundred years when the time of 
                        destruction has come, the true Dharma is disappearing, and there is a great
                        danger that the Buddha’s awakening will vanish, I shall teach this Dharma
                        discourse to those noble beings. I shall invigorate them. In places where a
                        holder of this sūtra resides, I shall quell all untimely cold winds, winter
                        rains, famine, diseases, plagues, epidemics, infectious disease, harm, and
                        conflict. In a place where this Dharma discourse is kept and written down as
                        a scripture or tied at the top of a banner and worshiped—in such a place,
                        all the terrors of hostile armies, thieves, rākṣasas, and ḍākinīs will be
                        quelled through my blessing. I shall bless those places where such Dharma
                        teachers reside and where this sūtra is kept, so that all harvests, riches,
                        grains, flowers, leaves, and fruits may be abundant, and all kinds of joy
                        may arise.” <ref cRef="F.274.a" type="folio"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-22"/>
                    <p tid="28">The Bhagavān said, “Excellent, Maitreya! It is excellent indeed that you have
                        donned the great armor and proclaimed the lion’s roar for the benefit of all
                        beings in order to uphold the true Dharma of the Tathāgata and to sustain<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-23" index="5"> Translated based on S:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bskyang</foreign>. D:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bskyed</foreign>.</note> the Dharma way of the Tathāgata. I
                        entrust this Dharma discourse to you. Thereby, later, in the future, during
                        the final five hundred years when the time of 
                        destruction has come, the true Dharma is disappearing, and there is a great
                        danger that the Buddha’s awakening will vanish, you should teach this Dharma discourse to all beings. You
                        should proclaim it. You should inspire those noble beings. You should
                        proclaim that they must do nothing else but persevere in taking ultimate
                        reality as their authority. You should teach them only according to 
                        ultimate reality. You should be sure to teach them in such a way that those
                        noble beings understand this Dharma discourse unmistakably as it is.”</p>
                    <p tid="29">The bodhisattva Maitreya said, “Bhagavān, I will do so.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-25"/>
                    <p tid="30">Thereupon Indra and his retinue of gods, Brahmā and his retinue of gods,
                        Prajāpati, and others, realizing that this Dharma discourse was coming
                        to an end, offered heavenly flowers, fragrant smoke, incense, flower
                        garlands, ointments, powders, garments, parasols, banners, and flags to the
                        Bhagavān and the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-64"/>
                    <p tid="31">They then exclaimed,
                        “Bhagavān, this Dharma discourse that benefits innumerable beings is indeed
                        a marvelous nectar of speech!” <ref cRef="F.274.b" type="folio"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-26"/>
                    <p tid="31">The Bhagavān now said to Venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, such a Dharma discourse
                        is rarely heard. Therefore, you must retain this Dharma discourse. You must
                        write it down, hold it, read it aloud, and master it!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-27"/>
                    <p tid="32">Ānanda said, “Bhagavān, I will retain this Dharma discourse. Bhagavān, what
                        is the name of this Dharma discourse? How should it be remembered?”</p>
                    <p tid="33">The Bhagavan said, “Ānanda, you should remember this Dharma discourse as
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Nectar of Speech</title>. You should also refer
                        to it as <title xml:lang="en">The Question of Maitreya</title>.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-29"/>
                    <p tid="34">After the Bhagavān had thus spoken, the entire assembly—Venerable Ānanda, the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, the bhikṣus, the bodhisattvas, and also the
                        gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas—all rejoiced and praised the words of the
                        Bhagavān.</p>
                    <trailer tid="35">This concludes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra “The Nectar of Speech.”
                    </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="36">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-30"/>
                    <p tid="37">Translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian abbot Prajñāvarman and
                        the chief editor-translator venerable Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="38">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="40">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-31">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bdud rtsi brjod pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                        chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryāmṛta­vyāharaṇa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">)</title>. Toh 197, Degé Kangyur vol. 61 (mdo sde, tsa),
                        folios 271.b–274.b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-32">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bdud rtsi brjod pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of
                        the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe
                        sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                        Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 61, pp.
                        740–750.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-33">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa bdud rtsi brjod pa zhes bya ba theg pa
                        chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amṛta­varṇa­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Stok Palace Kangyur (stog pho brang bris ma bka’
                        ’gyur) vol. 62 (mdo sde, da), folios 370.b–375.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-34">Kawa Paltsek (ska ba dpal brtsegs). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung rab rin
                            po che’i gtam rgyud dang shAkya’i rab rgyud</title>. Toh 4357, Degé
                        Tengyur vol. 204 (mdo ’grel, co), folios 239.a–377.a.<!--Reference Toh
                        4357-->
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-35">Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pho brang stod thang ldan dkar gyi chos
                            ’gyur ro cog gi dkar chag</title>). Degé Tengyur, vol. 206 (sna tshogs,
                        jo), folios 294.b–310.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-061-017-36">Hermann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte: kritische Neuausgabe mit Einleitung und Materialien</title>. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.
                    </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-37">
                            <term>acceptance that phenomena do not arise</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattikadharmakṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The particular realization that all phenomena
                                are beyond birth.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-38">
                            <term>Bhagavān</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavān</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha. In Sanskrit usually
                                defined as someone who is the possessor of six specific qualities as
                                well as the conqueror of māras. The usual definition of the Tibetan
                                term is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bcom</foreign>
                                (“subdue”), referring to the subduing of the four māras; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ldan</foreign> (“to possess”),
                                referring to the possession of the great qualities of buddhahood;
                                and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’das</foreign> (“beyond,”
                                “transcended”), meaning that such a person has gone beyond saṃsāra
                                and nirvāṇa.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-39">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-40">
                            <term>Blissful One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sugata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-41"><!-- introduce dual type=person/term, functionality appears -->
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Originally the name of Indra’s principal enemy among the asuras. In early Buddhism he appears as a drought-causing demon and eventually his name becomes that of <term type="ignore">Māra</term>, the principal opponent of the Buddha's teaching. The name also applies to the deities ruled over by <term type="ignore">Māra</term> who attempted to prevent the Buddha’s awakening and who do not wish any being to escape from saṃsāra.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-43">
                            <term>mind of awakening</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The wish, resolve, and practice to attain
                                complete awakening for the sake of all sentient beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-44">
                            <term>Tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha. Also rendered here as “Thus-Gone.” </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-58">
                            <term>Thus-Gone</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha. Also rendered here as “Tathāgata.” </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-45">
                            <term>worthy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">Depending on the etymological interpretation,
                                “<term type="ignore">worthy</term> one” or “a person who has defeated the enemy of the
                                afflictions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśa</foreign>).” </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-46">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a first cousin, close student, and
                                attendant of the Buddha.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-47">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a god. </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-48">
                            <term>Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Indra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a god. </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-49">
                            <term>Kawa Paltsek</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ska ba dpal brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐ་བ་དཔལ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A famous Tibetan translator and monk of the
                                8th–9th centuries.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-50">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva who, it is believed, will be
                                the future buddha after Śākyamuni, becoming the fifth buddha of this
                                eon.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-51">
                            <term>Prajāpati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye dgu’i bdag po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་དགུའི་བདག་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajāpati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a god. </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-52">
                            <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pradza+nyA barma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲཛྙཱ་བརྨ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian scholar and translator of the 8th–9th
                                centuries who translated, in collaboration with other Indian and
                                Tibetan scholars, about eighty texts of the Kangyur into Tibetan. He
                                also composed commentaries that are preserved in the Tengyur. </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item> 
                    <!-- Check Wylie here. The most likely version from other glossaries is pra dza+nyA bar ma.For markup: this
                                spelling is correct. But if it does not display properly in Wylie,
                                then please use Laura’s suggestion: pra dza+nyA bar ma.  -->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-53">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A famous Tibetan translator and monk of the
                                8th–9th centuries, who translated and revised in collaboration with
                                various Indian scholars more than 250 texts of the Kangyur and
                                Tengyur into Tibetan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-54">
                            <term>Kalandaka­nivāsa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ka lan da ka gnas pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་ཀ་ལན་ད་ཀ་གནས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalandaka­nivāsa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalandakanivāpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “the dwelling place of kalandaka (birds).” A location within the Veṇuvana where the Buddha stayed. The place was given its name by King Bimbisāra after he had been saved from a snake attack there by the squawking of many <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kalandaka</foreign>—flying squirrels, Sanskrit and Pali sources suggest, but Tibetan translations understand the
                                Sanskrit term to refer to a kind of bird. The alternative Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalandakanivāpa</foreign> means “where food-offerings are made to kalandakas.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-55">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Situated in the modern Indian state of Bihar,
                                <term type="ignore">Rājagṛha</term> was the capital of Magadha, one of the great kingdoms of
                                ancient India. </term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-061-017-56">
                            <term>Veṇuvana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ma’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་མའི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Veṇuvana</term>
                            <term type="definition">King Bimbisāra’s park (lit. “Bamboo Grove”) near
                                Rājagṛha. Here the Buddha dwelled regularly and gave many
                                teachings.</term>
                            </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>