<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ལས་ཀྱི་སྒྲིབ་པ་རྣམ་པར་དག་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic Obscurations</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmāvaraṇa­viśuddhi</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ལས་ཀྱི་སྒྲིབ་པ་རྣམ་པར་དག་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                    mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Purification of Karmic Obscurations”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­karmāvaraṇa­viśuddhi­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-15">Translated by the Garchen Buddhist Institute Translation Group<lb/> under the
                    patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-111">Ina Bieler</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-102"/>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Dr. Tom Tillemans</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.1 <date>2013 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-062-018"/>
                <date>2013-01-23</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh218" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 218</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 284.a–297.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Prajñāvarman</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="28">
                        <start volume="62" page="569"/>
                        <end volume="62" page="596"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11858" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:27:23 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="184">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-1"/>
                <p tid="1">The Buddha is residing at Āmrapālī’s Grove in Vaiśālī, when Mañjuśrī brings before him the monk
                    Stainless Light, who had been seduced by a prostitute and feels strong remorse for having violated his vows.
                    After the monk confesses his wrongdoing, the Buddha explains the lack of inherent nature of all phenomena and
                    the luminous nature of mind, and the monk Stainless Light gives rise to the mind of enlightenment. At
                    Mañjuśrī’s request, the Buddha then explains how bodhisattvas purify obscurations by generating an altruistic
                    mind and realizing the empty nature of all phenomena. He asks Mañjuśrī about his own attainment of patient
                    forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising and recounts the tale of the monk Vīradatta, who, many eons
                    in the past, had engaged in a sexual affair with a girl and even killed a jealous rival before feeling strong
                    remorse. Despite these negative actions, once the empty, non-existent nature of all phenomena had been
                    explained to him by the bodhisattva Liberator from Fear, he was able to generate bodhicitta and attain patient
                    forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising. The Buddha explains that even a person who had enjoyed
                    pleasures and murdered someone would be able to attain patient forbearance in seeing all phenomena as
                    non-arising through practicing this sūtra, which he calls “the Dharma mirror of all phenomena.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="185">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Garchen Buddhist Institute Translation Group. The translation was prepared under the
                    supervision of H.E. Garchen Rinpoche by Ina Bieler, who would like to acknowledge the support and help of Dr.
                    Tom Tillemans with the introduction to this text and research on certain technical terms. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="186">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The setting for this sūtra is Āmrapālī’s Grove in Vaiśālī, where Buddha Śākyamuni taught and
                        performed miracles. The Lord Buddha visited Vaiśālī several times; first, in the fifth year after his
                        enlightenment, he spent the rainy season there, and later, he laid down various rules of the Vinaya at
                        Vaiśālī, as well as giving other important discourses. On his last visit he announced his approaching
                        parinirvāṇa. In addition, one hundred years after the Buddha’s parinirvāṇa, it was the site of the second
                        Buddhist Council.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">This sūtra relates the story of a monk who has been seduced by a prostitute and is deeply
                        remorseful for his actions. Mañjuśrī takes him to seek the counsel of the Buddha. What is interesting is
                        the way in which the Buddha deals with monastic discipline and the ethical impairment of the monk’s vows,
                        contrasting the view of emptiness, or the lack of intrinsic nature of phenomena, and morality. Here, the
                        view of emptiness trumps the code of monastic discipline as explained in the Vinaya. From the point of
                        view of the monk’s vows, sleeping with a woman is a disaster; however, this moral discourse takes the
                        point of view of emptiness. This is an example of how the codes of monastic discipline are sometimes
                        subordinated to the ultimate view of emptiness. Although the Vinaya is practiced in all vehicles,
                        including the Vajrayāna, it is given different priorities. For example, in the Mahāyāna, if a monk holds
                        the bodhisattva vows, certain exceptions can be made to his monastic vows, such as the one that prohibits
                        touching a woman, when he is employing skillful means. Here in this text, however (although it is a
                        Mahāyāna sūtra), the emphasis is not on any such skillful means, but on the metaphysical view of
                        emptiness.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The Degé Kangyur version of this sūtra was compared to those in the Stok Palace Kangyur and Lhasa
                        Kangyur; discrepancies and remarks are indicated in the endnotes. This text was translated solely on the
                        basis of the Tibetan versions, as a Sanskrit original has not been found. When the names of individuals
                        are generally known in Sanskrit, e.g. Mañjuśrī, they are presented here in Sanskrit. In the case of many
                        other personal names, however, it is difficult to establish from the Tibetan translation an unquestionable
                        rendering back into Sanskrit; these names are therefore translated into English instead.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The Sanskrit title of the work, as transcribed in the Degé and most other recensions of the
                        Kangyur, is—shorn of its honorific elements—<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmāvaraṇa­viśuddha­sūtra</foreign>, which could be translated as “purified of karmic obscurations.”
                        However, the sūtra is mentioned in Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣā­samuccaya</title> with the
                        title <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karmāvaraṇa­viśuddhi­sūtra</foreign> (which is also the spelling given in
                        the Narthang Kangyur), and we have followed most modern cataloguers of the Kangyur in taking this spelling
                        as the probable original version, rendering it as <title xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic
                            Obscurations</title>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-7"/>
                    <p tid="8"> According to the colophon, the sūtra was originally translated from Sanskrit into Tibetan by the
                        Indian paṇḍitas Jinamitra and Prajñāvarman, and by the principal editor-translator (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lo tsā ba</foreign>), the monk Yeshé Dé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes
                            sde</foreign>), and others. Jinamitra was a Kaśmīri of around the late eighth to early ninth century
                        who travelled to Samyé Monastery in Tibet during the reign of the Dharma king Trisong Detsen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khri srong lde btsan</foreign>) to engage in translation; he and Yeshé Dé
                        collaborated on the translation of many hundreds of works. The translation of this text is listed in the
                        Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</foreign>) catalogue, compiled in 824, and was thus most
                        likely prepared in the early ninth century. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="187">THE TRANSLATION </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="188">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="189">Purification of Karmic Obscurations </head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <ref cRef="F.284.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas! <!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-9"/>
                    <p tid="10"><!--<modularPassage type="thusDid">-->Thus have I heard at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling at
                        Āmrapālī’s Grove in Vaiśālī, in the company of a great monastic assembly of about five hundred monks and
                        thirty-two thousand great bodhisattva mahāsattvas, such as the bodhisattva mahāsattvas Destroyer of Pride,
                        Sublime Knowledge Displayed with Luminosity, Like a Lotus Flower,<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-181">Both D (F.284.a.5) and H (F.438.b.4) read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me
                                tog dam pa lta bu</foreign>, but S (F.216.a.1) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog padma lta
                                bu</foreign>. The translation follows the latter reading. </note> King of Light Diffusion,
                        Embodiment Always Appearing Like an Honorable Image, All Doubts Diminished, He whose Intelligence is Like
                        an Ocean of Arrayed Jewels, Abode of Myriad Flowers, King of Utterly Clear Melody, Lamp of the Light King,
                        Golden Light of the Glorious Essence, Mighty One, Subjugator of All Places, King of Openly Proclaiming
                        Melody, Embodiment of Enchanting Splendor, the great bodhisattva mahāsattva Youthful Mañjuśrī, and
                        others.<!--</modularPassage>--> In all he was accompanied by thirty-two-thousand great bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">At that time, the monk called Stainless Light came to the great city of Vaiśālī to beg for alms.
                            <ref cRef="F.284.b"/> As he made his alms round, he arrived at a prostitute’s home, not knowing whose
                        it was.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">The moment the monk went into her home, lustful intentions were aroused in the prostitute, who
                        thought, “I will not let this monk go without sleeping with him. If I fail, I will die.” Once the monk had
                        come inside, she immediately shut the door and told him, “It would be wrong for you not to sleep with me.
                        Unless you sleep with me, I will die.” </p>
                    <p tid="13">The monk Stainless Light protested to the prostitute, “Auntie! I must train in the great precepts
                        prescribed by the Buddha. I dare not engage in sexual activity. Please let me go! I would rather die than
                        engage in sexual activity.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">At this the prostitute thought, “If I use a certain secret mantra and drug to seduce<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-182">D (F.284.b.4) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdag
                                gis gsang sngags dang / sman gang gis dge slong ’di ’dug nas</foreign> which would be translated
                            as “by... this monk will stay.” While H (F.437.a.7) also uses <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dug
                                nas</foreign>, S (F.216.b.3) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gug nas</foreign> which translates
                            as “seduce” and thus seems more fitting in this case.</note> this monk, he will surely engage in
                        blissful acts with me; I shall definitely use that secret mantra and drug on this monk.” But she said to
                        him, “I, too, have no desire to destroy or impair the Buddha’s prescribed precepts. Most graciously accept
                        my alms.”</p>
                    <p tid="15">With these words she went inside, bewitched the food with magic spells and secret mantras, and
                        poured it into the monk’s begging bowl. As soon as she had poured out his food, the monk suddenly gave
                        rise to immoral thoughts. Fantasizing, he gave rise to enormous longing. When the prostitute noticed the
                        change in the monk’s expression, she grabbed him with her right hand, led him to the bed, and they slept
                        with each other. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-13"/>
                    <p tid="16">After the monk had had his pleasure from dallying with the prostitute, he collected his alms, went
                        to the main temple, and thought, “Oh, woe is me! I have just violated all that is contained in the
                        Buddha’s great teaching of moral conduct! <ref cRef="F.285.a"/> As I have violated my moral conduct, I am
                        no longer worthy to partake of faithful people’s offerings. I shall fall into the great hell realms.”</p>
                    <p tid="17">He approached his monastic companions and said, “I have neglected my moral conduct. As I am no
                        longer an ordained devotee, I shall fall into the great hell realms.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-14"/>
                    <p tid="18">His monastic companions asked, “Why did you neglect your moral conduct?” So he recounted to them
                        exactly how it had happened. </p>
                    <p tid="19"> “Venerable Stainless Light,” his monastic companions said, “the bodhisattva mahāsattva called
                        Youthful Mañjuśrī is expert in expunging all wrong-doings. He is expert in dispelling all obscurations. He
                        has attained patient forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-183">On <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</foreign>, see
                            Lamotte (1981), chapter XXV “La patience à l'endroit du Dharma,” p. 902 <foreign xml:lang="fr">et
                                seq</foreign>. See <foreign xml:lang="la">ibid</foreign>. p. 970, n. 2 (our translation): “...It
                            is on the 8th level that the bodhisattva obtains the forbearance to accept and understand the
                            non-arising of the elements, the certainty to become enlightened and the assurance that he will not
                            fall back; he exchanges the body that he has had from birth, or the body of flesh, for the
                            dharmakāya.” See also <foreign xml:lang="la">ibid</foreign>. p. 903 n. 1; and Edgerton (1953) p. 27
                            s.v. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</foreign>: “intellectual
                            receptivity to the truth that states of existence have no origination.” </note> Even the Bhagavān
                        speaks well of him, praising and extolling him. So, venerable one, please come. We shall go to meet
                        Youthful Mañjuśrī. He will be able to dispel your distress.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-15"/>
                    <p tid="20">Then, without eating his food, the monk Stainless Light, together with his monastic companions,
                        left for the abode of Youthful Mañjuśrī. When they entered the presence of Youthful Mañjuśrī, they
                        exchanged some joyful and delightful conversation, and then recounted to Youthful Mañjuśrī what had
                        happened.</p>
                    <p tid="21">After these explanations, Youthful Mañjuśrī told the monk Stainless Light, “Monk, eat some of this
                        food. Once you have eaten, tell the Bhagavān about this and follow the Bhagavān’s instructions.”</p>
                    <p tid="22">As soon as the monk Stainless Light had eaten, he and his monastic companions, together with
                        Youthful Mañjuśrī, left for the abode of the Bhagavān. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-16"/>
                    <p tid="23">Upon entering his presence, they touched their heads to the feet of the Bhagavān, and after
                        circumambulating the Bhagavān three times, they sat down to one side of him. <ref cRef="F.285.b"/> The
                        monk Stainless Light was too ashamed to be able to speak to the Bhagavān, so Youthful Mañjuśrī rose from
                        his seat, draped his outer robe over one shoulder, knelt on his right knee, joined his palms before the
                        Bhagavān, and relayed to the Bhagavān everything that had happened. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-17"/>
                    <p tid="24">When he had been told what had happened, the Bhagavān asked the monk Stainless Light, “Monk, is it
                        true that you did thus?” </p>
                    <p tid="25">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, yes, it is true.” </p>
                    <p tid="26">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, did you have a prior intention to engage in lustful conduct?” </p>
                    <p tid="27">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, no, I did not.” </p>
                    <p tid="28">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, if lustful thoughts did not arise, how did you come to engage in
                        lustful conduct?” </p>
                    <p tid="29">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, my lustful mind arose later on.” </p>
                    <p tid="30">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, did you engage in your passionate act with that mind?” </p>
                    <p tid="31">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, no, I did not.” </p>
                    <p tid="32">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, when their minds are afflicted, sentient beings become controlled by
                        their afflictions; when their minds are purified, they become pure. Is this not the Dharma I taught?” </p>
                    <p tid="33">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, yes, it is.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-18"/>
                    <p tid="34">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? In your sleep, when dreaming, did you ever engage in
                        passionate acts?” </p>
                    <p tid="35">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, yes, I did.” </p>
                    <p tid="36">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, do you not know that it is your mind that engaged in passionate
                        conduct?” </p>
                    <p tid="37">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, I do know that.”<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-184">D (F.285.b.6) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khyod kyis mi shod
                                dam</foreign>; this reading accords with H (F.441.a.6), and would translate as “Are you not now
                            telling me that it is your mind that engaged in passionate conduct?” In response the monk negates it
                            by saying, “No, it is not so.” However, S (F.218.b.2) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khyod kyis mi
                                shes sam</foreign> which would be rendered as “Do you not know that it is your mind that engaged
                            in passionate conduct?” and in response the monk affirms it by saying, “Yes I do.” The translation
                            follows this reading, which makes more sense in the context. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="38">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, do you think that there is a difference such that your dreaming mind
                        and your waking mind are separate and distinct?”<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-185">D
                            (F.285.b.7) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyid ma log pa’i sems ’di la bye brag dang tha dad du
                                bya ba zhig yod par mthong ngam</foreign>, which accords with H (F.441.b.1) and would translate as
                            “Do you think the activities engaged in by your dreaming mind and your waking mind are separate and
                            distinct?” However, S (F.218.b.3) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyid ma log pa’i sems’di la bye
                                brag dang tha dad du dbye ba zhig yod par mthong ngam</foreign>. The context and grammar seem to
                            favor this latter reading. </note>
                        <ref cRef="F.286.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="39">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, I do not see the slightest distinction between the dreaming
                        mind and the waking mind.” </p>
                    <p tid="40">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Have I not taught that all phenomena are like
                        dreams?” </p>
                    <p tid="41">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, yes, you have.” </p>
                    <p tid="42">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Are dreams true?” </p>
                    <p tid="43">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, no, they are not.” </p>
                    <p tid="44">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Are not the dreaming mind and the waking mind
                        non-existent?” </p>
                    <p tid="45">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, they are indeed non-existent. Sugata, they are indeed
                        non-existent.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-19"/>
                    <p tid="46">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Could something non-existent exist anywhere?” </p>
                    <p tid="47">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, no, it could not.” </p>
                    <p tid="48">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Could something non-existent arise?” Stainless Light
                        replied, “Bhagavān, no, it could not.” </p>
                    <p tid="49">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Could something non-arising arise or cease? Could it
                        become controlled by afflictions, or cleansed?” </p>
                    <p tid="50">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, no, it could not.” </p>
                    <p tid="51">The Bhagavān asked, “Monk, what do you think? Could non-arising phenomena go to the hell realms,
                        or to the birthplace of an animal, or to the realm of the Lord of Death?” </p>
                    <p tid="52">Stainless Light replied, “Bhagavān, since things that are non-arising do not exist, it would be
                        impossible for them to go to the lower realms.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-20"/>
                    <p tid="53">The Bhagavān continued, “Monk, while all phenomena are luminous in this way, childish ordinary
                        beings construct unreal phenomena, construct erroneous qualities, and have constructed all phenomena,
                        which are in fact insignificant and worthless. And thus they will go to hell, animal states of birth, and
                        to the realm of the Lord of Death. <ref cRef="F.286.b"/> Monk, furthermore, all phenomena are untrue; they
                        have the characteristic that once created they do not remain.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-186">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par bsgrubs nas nye par gnas pa’i mtshan nyid do</foreign>. The
                            meaning is unclear but it would fit the context to assume that a negative particle is missing.</note>
                        Monk, all phenomena are compounded; childish ordinary beings have given rise to attachment, hatred, and
                        delusion. Monk, all phenomena arise from distorted perceptions. Monk, all phenomena lack existence, their
                        very essence is like a mirage. Monk, all phenomena lack a core, they are like space. Monk, as all
                        phenomena are devoid of reality, they are not real entities. Monk, as all phenomena are deep like space,
                        they are deep. Monk, as all phenomena are unperceived, they are wide open. Monk, as all phenomena are
                        utterly void, they are non-abiding. Monk, as all phenomena have no worth for anything at all, they are
                        unreliable. Monk, as all phenomena are without worth whatsover, they are baseless. Monk, as all phenomena
                        are devoid of afflicted concepts, they are unfettered. Monk, as all phenomena are non-arising by nature,
                        they are entirely free from pain. Monk, as all phenomena are void, they are unobscured. Monk, as all
                        phenomena are free of hatred by nature,<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-187">D
                            (F.286.b.5) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos thams cad ni rang bzhin gyis ldang ba med pa’i
                                phyir</foreign>; this reading accords with H (F.442.b.6) and would translate as “as all phenomena
                            are non-arising by nature.” However, S (F.220.a.7) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos thams cad ni
                                rang bzhin gyis sdang ba med pa’i phyir</foreign>, “as all phenomena are free of hatred by
                            nature,” and once again this reading seems to fit the context better. </note> there is no hatred.
                        Monk, as all phenomena are luminous by nature, there is no delusion. Monk, as all phenomena are like
                        hallucinations, there is no karmic maturation. Monk, as all phenomena appear mistakenly, they are like
                        illusions. Monk, as all phenomena are constructed falsely, they are non-abiding.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-21"/>
                    <p tid="54">"Monk, as childish ordinary beings project existence on to non-existent phenomena, they act
                        completely blindly. Monk, as all phenomena are mutually contradictory conditions, they are non-arising.
                        Monk, as all phenomena are without path, they are unattached. Monk, as all phenomena are not truly
                        afflicted, they are free from afflictions. <ref cRef="F.287.a"/> Monk, as all phenomena are as immaculate
                        as space, they are stainless. Monk, as phenomena are nothing but void, they are nothing whatsoever. Monk,
                        as all phenomena are inherently non-arising, they are tamed. Monk, as all phenomena are devoid of an
                        earlier limit, a later limit, and a middle, they are untrue. Monk, as no phenomenon is the cause of
                        another, phenomena are liberated. Monk, as all phenomena are like grass, wood, walls, and clods of dirt,
                        they are material substance. Monk, as all phenomena are like space, they are essenceless. Monk, as no
                        phenomenon is anything to be attached to, phenomena are equal. Monk, as all phenomena are like a body of
                            space<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-188">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’i lus</foreign>, i.e., “insubstantial.”</note> and an empty hand,
                        they cannot be grasped. Monk, as all phenomena have been the objects of thorough searches by those endowed
                        with exalted wisdom, they are unobtained. Monk, as all phenomena are free of the three times, they are
                        timeless. Monk, as all phenomena are nothing to be benightedly attached to, they are not to be engaged
                        with. Monk, as all phenomena are devoid of obscurations, they are free of pain. Monk, as all phenomena are
                        like nirvāṇa, they are blissful. Monk, as all phenomena are without fearsomeness, they are not to be
                        feared. Monk, as all phenomena are unobserved on this side, there is no other side. Monk, as all phenomena
                        are incalculable, they are beyond measure. Monk, as the signs of all phenomena are insignificant, they are
                        signless. Monk, as all phenomena lack wishes, they are wishless. Monk, as all phenomena have the nature of
                        false formations, they are without actual formation. <ref cRef="F.287.b"/> Monk, as all phenomena are
                        undisturbed by discursive thought, they are unelaborated. Monk, as all phenomena are free of abiding, they
                        are non-abiding. Monk, as all phenomena are always clear, they are unsullied. Monk, as the arising of all
                        phenomena is unperceived, as their arising is insignificant, as their arising is worthless, as their
                        arising is empty, and as their arising is peaceful, they are final nirvāṇa. Monk, for these reasons, these
                        phenomena are exactly as I have taught. Monk, dwelling within the essence of enlightenment, I have not
                        perceived even the slightest phenomenon that arises, that perishes, that is afflicted, cleansed, obscured,
                        fettered, regretful, or miserable. Why is that so? Monk, as all phenomena are at all times unafflicted,
                        they are perfectly pure by nature.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-22"/>
                    <p tid="55">When the monk Stainless Light heard this of the nature of phenomena, he felt satisfied, and
                        rejoiced. He was very happy, and felt joy and relief. Delighted to have no obscurations, he joined his
                        palms before the Bhagavān, bowed, and spoke these verses to the Bhagavān: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-23"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Ah! Ah! Buddha powerful,</l>
                        <l>Refuge of the world including gods,</l>
                        <l>Even though you needed no training,</l>
                        <l>Your good qualities rise above all.</l>
                        <l>Homage to you, who sets free all pain!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-24"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“You grant refuge to the protectorless,</l>
                        <l>And give counsel to those without guide.</l>
                        <l>You dwell in the peaceful path of bliss.</l>
                        <l>Homage to you, Buddha powerful!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-25"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>“You are the lamp for the blind of this world;</l>
                        <l>Granting sight to those who could not see,</l>
                        <l>You free those beings who had no freedom.</l>
                        <l>Homage to you, hero powerful!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-26"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“You are free from clinging and dislike,<ref cRef="F.288.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And teach lustful ones suffering;</l>
                        <l>You have seen the lie of saṃsāra’s circle.</l>
                        <l>Homage to you, wisdom’s might supreme!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-27"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“Never attached because of discursive thoughts,</l>
                        <l>Freeing with inconceivable wisdom</l>
                        <l>Supreme in the three worlds, you are unstained and free of passions.</l>
                        <l>Homage to you, who are unstained and clean! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-28"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“I, too, shall enter awakening,</l>
                        <l>Shall end helpless beings’ misery.</l>
                        <l>Having attained such wisdom</l>
                        <l>I shall not be tainted by the lesser paths.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-29"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“I shall suffer for inconceivable myriads of eons,</l>
                        <l>But shall not forsake the bodhi mind.</l>
                        <l>Like the moon within a field of stars</l>
                        <l>Is how you appear, world’s guardian.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-30"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“Some with inferior minds,</l>
                        <l>Though they travel on the vast extensive sea,</l>
                        <l>Fail to collect many gems,</l>
                        <l>But only bring back worthless trinkets.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-31"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“Likewise, some, although they hear of the buddhas’ manifestations</l>
                        <l>And his strengths, awakened intent does not arise in them.</l>
                        <l>They turn away from awakening, and strive on the hearers’ path.</l>
                        <l>They will not pierce wisdom’s vast expanse—</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-32"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>“Just as someone with childish character,</l>
                        <l>Although he sees the king surrounded by his court,</l>
                        <l>Finds inspiration only in the ministers’ skill</l>
                        <l>And will not fully pierce the knowledge of the king.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-33"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Likewise, there are those who, </l>
                        <l>Although they hear of great buddha attributes,</l>
                        <l>And of his wisdom’s magical display,</l>
                        <l>Decide upon the lower mind.</l>
                        <l>They are lazy and their minds are weak.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-34"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“The non-attachment to the world of those of the inferior vehicle</l>
                        <l>Gives as much light as fireflies in the night.</l>
                        <l>But those who work with the sun in all its splendor,</l>
                        <l>Will, when they obtain that illumination, be divest of darkness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-35"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“The Buddha’s voice reaches the highest realms.</l>
                        <l>The Buddha’s voice reaches the noble-born.</l>
                        <l>The Buddha, supreme lamp for this world,</l>
                        <l>Illuminates all the world and the realms of the gods.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-36"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“Just as, when a lion is seen amongst foxes,</l>
                        <l>Some may take interest in fox talk <ref cRef="F.288.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>And, ignoring the lion’s display,</l>
                        <l>Find delight in fox affairs,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-37"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>“So, too, when those who, among the hearers</l>
                        <l>See the Supreme Lion of Man’s display,</l>
                        <l>But take delight in the lower vehicle,</l>
                        <l>Their powers will be one-sided indeed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-38"/>
                    <lg tid="71">
                        <l>“May people who seek wisdom always expound</l>
                        <l>On suffering, to help the worldly ones;<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-189">D
                                (F.288.b.2) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten kun tu sdug bsngal mang ’grel ba</foreign>,
                                which accords with H (F.445.b.1) and would translate as “explaining suffering at length in all the
                                worlds.” However, S (F.222.a.6) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten don du sdug bsngal mang
                                    ’grel ba</foreign>, “explaining suffering for the sake of worldly ones;” the translation
                                follows the latter reading. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>May they seek the wisdom, true and sublime</l>
                        <l>Which is not the ground of common hearers.” </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-39"/>
                    <p tid="72">Hearing these verses of faith spoken by the monk Stainless Light, forty-two thousand sons of gods
                        gave rise to the mind set on unsurpassed, perfectly complete enlightenment. Tossing mandārava blossoms
                        toward the Bhagavān, Youthful Mañjuśrī, and the monk Stainless Light, they proclaimed, “Monk, very good,
                        very good. To thus pursue the enlightenment of a buddha is to reciprocate the Tathāgata’s kindness.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-40"/>
                    <p tid="73">At that moment the Bhagavān smiled. An attribute of bhagavān buddhas is that whenever they smile,
                        light radiates from their mouths in myriad colors such as blue, yellow, red, white, vermillion,
                        crystalline, and silver. Diverse colors emerged, permeated infinite limitless world systems with light,
                        and extended up to the brahmā worlds. Outshining even the light of the sun and moon, the light then
                        returned, circled around the Bhagavān three times, and vanished into the crown of the Bhagavān’s head. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-41"/>
                    <p tid="74">Then the venerable Ānanda rose from his seat. Draping his Dharma robe over one shoulder, he placed
                        his right knee on the ground, faced the Bhagavān, joined his palms, and asked him, <ref cRef="F.289.a"/>
                        “As the bhagavats, tathāgatas, arhats, perfectly enlightened buddhas do not smile without causes and
                        conditions, what is the cause of your smile, and what are the conditions for it?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-42"/>
                    <p tid="75">The Bhagavān replied, “Ānanda, the monk Stainless Light has given rise to the mind set on
                        enlightenment with noble intent. I therefore predict that the monk Stainless Light shall attain
                        unsurpassed perfectly complete enlightenment. Ānanda, in the future, after ten eons have passed, the monk
                        Stainless Light will make offerings to two hundred and twenty million buddhas and attain patient
                        forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising, in the presence of the tathāgata, arhat, perfectly
                        complete Buddha Maitreya. He will also make offerings to all the bhagavān buddhas of the Fortunate Eon.
                        Thereafter, having fully matured, he will become the Tathāgata He Who Proclaims the Lion’s Roar of Conduct
                        That is Renowned to be the Lotus of Good Qualities. Ānanda, the buddhafield of that tathāgata, arhat,
                        perfectly complete Buddha He Who Proclaims the Lion’s Roar of Conduct That is Renowned to be the Lotus of
                        Good Qualities, will be made with seven precious attributes. There will be no hearers or solitary
                        realizers, only bodhisattvas will gather there. Furthermore, in this buddhafield he will teach them the
                        Dharma called ‘The Wheel of No Return.’ Also, those bodhisattvas will swiftly awaken truly and completely
                        into unsurpassed, perfectly complete enlightenment. Thus their buddhafield will become utterly
                            purified<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-190">D (F.289.a.6) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su sbyang bar ’gyur ro</foreign>, as does S (F.223.b.1). H (F.446.b.5)
                            reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su spyad par ’gyur ro</foreign>, which would translate as
                            “entirely consumed,” or “completely enjoy” or other equivalents. The translation follows D. </note> by
                        the excellence of exalted wisdom, and this world system will then be called ‘Endowed with Infinite
                            Discourses.’ ”<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-191">D (F.289.a.6) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam grags mtha’ yas ldan zhes bya bar</foreign>, which is an unusual
                            combination and would translate as “Endowed with Infinite Full Renown.” Both S (F.223.b.1) and H
                            (F.446.b.7) instead read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam grangs mtha’ yas ldan zhes bya bar</foreign>,
                            “Endowed with Infinite Discourses,” which seems more fitting. </note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-43"/>
                    <p tid="76">The Bhagavān then said to the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, it is like this. In the same way that all
                        darkness disappears when the sun rises, Ānanda, so, likewise, whoever hears this Dharma discourse will
                        attain full illumination, and will also attain non-obscuration with regard to all phenomena.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-44"/>
                    <p tid="77">At this, the venerable Ānanda asked the Bhagavān, <ref cRef="F.289.b"/> “Bhagavān, how does one
                        become obscured, and how non-obscured?” </p>
                    <p tid="78">But the Bhagavān told him, “Never mind, Ānanda! What use is it for you to ask questions on that
                        point? Ānanda, if the tathāgata explained everything about obscuration and non-obscuration, the world and
                        its gods would become confused.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-45"/>
                    <p tid="79">Youthful Mañjuśrī, however, made this plea to the Bhagavān: “Bhagavān, by hearing about
                        obscuration and non-obscuration, the bodhisattvas of the final five hundred years will no longer give rise
                        to desire for worldly affairs. Therefore, please do explain them!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-46"/>
                    <p tid="80">The Bhagavān said, “Mañjuśrī, as for ‘obscuration,’ attachment is an obscuration, hatred is an
                        obscuration, ignorance is an obscuration, generosity is an obscuration, moral conduct is an obscuration,
                        patience is an obscuration, diligence is an obscuration, meditation is an obscuration, transcendent
                        awareness is an obscuration, perceiving the Buddha is an obscuration, perceiving the Dharma is an
                        obscuration, perceiving the Saṅgha is an obscuration, perceiving emptiness is an obscuration, perceiving
                        signlessness is an obscuration, perceiving wishlessness is an obscuration, perceiving the actual absence
                        of formations is an obscuration, perceiving non-arising is an obscuration, and perceiving enlightenment is
                        an obscuration. Mañjuśrī, in brief, whether they are viewed as totally afflicted or fully cleansed, you
                        should regard them all as obscurations.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-47"/>
                    <p tid="81">Mañjuśrī asked, “Bhagavān, how is generosity an obscuration? How are moral conduct, patience,
                        diligence, meditation, and transcendent awareness obscurations?” </p>
                    <p tid="82">The Bhagavān replied, “Mañjuśrī, in all phenomena there is indeed no obscuration. Nevertheless,
                        conditioned by their thoughts, childish ordinary beings engage in obscured activity with regard to
                        generosity, and they engage in obscured activity with regard to moral conduct, patience, diligence,
                        meditation, and transcendent awareness. How is this so? <ref cRef="F.290.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-48"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Mañjuśrī, when childish ordinary beings practice generosity, they do it with disrespect toward
                        miserly sentient beings. Due to their disrespect, those who practice giving get angry and give rise to the
                        fault of resentfulness. The faults of anger and resentfulness plunge them into the hell realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-49"/>
                    <p tid="84">“When childish ordinary beings observe moral conduct they speak ill of those neglecting moral
                        conduct, disparaging and treating them contemptuously. When these disparaging remarks are repeated to
                        others it causes disrespect in many ordinary beings, who will go to the lower realms due to their
                        disrespect. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-50"/>
                    <p tid="85">“When they practice patience, they declare, ‘We have patience, while those others bear harmful
                        thoughts.’ Intoxicated with the arrogance of patience, they create all the suffering that results from
                        fundamental heedlessness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-51"/>
                    <p tid="86">“When they exert themselves in diligence, they extol themselves and think, ‘Those other monks are
                        lazy and lack diligence, yet they enjoy the offerings of the faithful. They are not worthy of even
                        enjoying water from a water container.’ As they exert themselves in diligence, they praise themselves and
                        disparage others. I say that they are childish beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-52"/>
                    <p tid="87">“When they spend their time in the equilibrium of meditation, they give rise to attachment to the
                        joyful bliss of meditation and think, ‘We spend our time in equipoise. Those other monks spend their time
                        in mental distraction. They spend their time enjoying frivolous entertainments. As they enjoy frivolous
                        entertainments, how will they ever become buddhas? They are far from the enlightenment of a buddha.’ Those
                        who take attitudes like these, as long as they think such contemptuous thoughts, will cling tightly to
                        saṃsāra for eons. Later, if they engage in enlightenment, even if they have great learning, they will
                        imagine that, amongst all letterless phenomena,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-192">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi ge med pa</foreign>, “letterless,” refers to the emptiness of all
                            phenomena and their transcendence of all conventions; phenomena are nameless, inexpressible, and
                            ineffable. </note> the mind is existent. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-53"/>
                    <p tid="88">“When they observe transcendent awareness they disdain others. I say that they have no knowledge,
                        I say that they talk even though they do not know, <ref cRef="F.290.b"/> I say that they are not sublime
                        beings, I say that as they conceptualize, they are corrupted. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-54"/>
                    <p tid="89">“If they enter the Mahāyāna, again they will think, ‘We are foremost in this world, we are the
                        best in this world, we are supreme in this world.’ When they see followers of the Hearers’ Vehicle they
                        give rise to disrespect, disparage them, denigrate them, and speak ill of them. Due to these evil thoughts
                        and condemnations they will be reborn in the lower realms.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-55"/>
                    <p tid="90">Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, are the bodhisattvas not praised because of the
                        Buddha’s teachings?” </p>
                    <p tid="91">The Bhagavān replied, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? Do the bodhisattvas not regard all sentient
                        beings affectionately, do they not naturally give rise to altruism?” </p>
                    <p tid="92">Mañjuśrī answered, “Bhagavān, yes, they do.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-56"/>
                    <p tid="93">The Bhagavān continued, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? Would bodhisattvas forsake even a few
                        sentient beings, whether of the Hearer’s Vehicle, the Solitary Realizers’ Vehicle, or the Mahāyāna?” </p>
                    <p tid="94"> Mañjuśrī answered, “Bhagavān, they would not. As bodhisattvas regard all sentient beings equally,
                        bodhisattvas would not dismiss even a few sentient beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-57"/>
                    <p tid="95">The Bhagavān continued, “Mañjuśrī, it is like this. Just as a physician does not forsake even a
                        few sentient beings, whether they are a king, a merchant, a householder, or a mendicant, but attends to
                        all with equanimity and thinks of what he can do to free these sentient beings from their illnesses,
                        Mañjuśrī, likewise, the bodhisattva mahāsattvas suffuse all sentient beings with compassion and attend to
                        them with equanimity. <ref cRef="F.291.a"/> They think, ‘How can I cause all these sentient beings to find
                        definite release through the Buddha’s teachings?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-58"/>
                    <p tid="96">“Mañjuśrī, it is like this: just as when the lineage of medical cure remains unbroken, the
                        physician is pleased and rejoices, likewise, Mañjuśrī, the bodhisattva mahāsattvas are pleased and rejoice
                        when the lineage of the Buddha remains unbroken. Mañjuśrī, not all sentient beings are like physicians.
                        Mañjuśrī, a physician who has the ability to heal is rare. Likewise, Mañjuśrī, not all sentient beings are
                        like the Buddha; bodhicitta is rare. Not all sentient beings can bear to put on such armor for the purpose
                        of enlightenment. Just as lazy people might think, ‘I shall be a physician,’ and yet do not seriously
                        observe the practices of physicians, so, likewise, not all beings are able to give rise to the mind set on
                        enlightenment. Laziness makes them fall ill. Mañjuśrī, naturally occurring bodhicitta is rare.
                        Self-arising exalted wisdom is rare. A vast mind is rare. To seriously observe the teachings of the Buddha
                        is rare.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-59"/>
                    <p tid="97">Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, how can bodhisattvas become unobscured and
                        purified with respect to all phenomena?” </p>
                    <p tid="98">At this question the Bhagavān replied to Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who see all
                        phenomena as objects of desire will attain purification from karmic obscurations. Those who see all
                        phenomena as objects of hatred will attain purification from karmic obscurations. Those who see all
                        phenomena as objects of delusion will attain purification from karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-60"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who openly delight in the pleasures of the five senses
                        without renouncing or abandoning them, <ref cRef="F.291.b"/> and those who see the Buddha’s teachings as
                        essentially desire will attain purification of karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-61"/>
                    <p tid="100">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who pursue enlightenment through the five obscurations, who
                        do not pursue and attain enlightenment, and who do not have obscurations either, will attain purification
                        of all karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-62"/>
                    <p tid="101"> “Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, bodhisattvas who have purified the nine grounds of hostility will attain
                        loving kindness. Those who genuinely discern the development of the ground of their hostility to a
                        particular person, yet do not apprehend a self, or others, or even loving kindness, being free of
                        apprehending all phenomena in this way have supreme loving kindness. Thus, bodhisattvas endowed with
                        patience will attain freedom from obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-63"/>
                    <p tid="102">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who sees downfalls as non-downfalls, who sees discipline as
                        non-discipline, who sees affliction as purity, and who sees saṃsāric realms as the sphere of nirvāṇa, will
                        attain purification of karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-64"/>
                    <p tid="103">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who sees the realm of desire as the sphere of nirvāṇa, who
                        sees the realm of hatred as the sphere of nirvāṇa, and who sees the realm of delusion as the sphere of
                        nirvāṇa, will attain purification from karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-65"/>
                    <p tid="104">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva mahāsattva who truly sees all phenomena as the teachings of
                        the Buddha will attain purification of karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-66"/>
                    <p tid="105">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who sees all phenomena as arising from the ground of space
                        will attain purification of karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-67"/>
                    <p tid="106">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who does not distinguish between the phenomena of avarice
                        and the phenomena of generosity, <ref cRef="F.292.a"/> who does not distinguish between the phenomena of
                        immoral conduct and the phenomena of moral conduct, who does not distinguish between the phenomena of
                        malice and the phenomena of patience, who does not distinguish between the phenomena of laziness and the
                        phenomena of diligence, who does not distinguish between the phenomena of distraction and the phenomena of
                        meditation, and who does not distinguish between the phenomena of misconstrued wisdom and the phenomena of
                        wisdom will attain purification from karmic obscurations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-68"/>
                    <p tid="107">“Furthermore, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who is convinced that all afflictions are the Buddhadharma
                        will attain purification of karmic obscurations.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-69"/>
                    <p tid="108">Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, how do the bodhisattvas integrate the teachings
                        of the Buddha into all afflictions?” </p>
                    <p tid="109">The Bhagavān answered, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? Does a phenomenon engage in afflicted acts
                        with respect to another phenomenon?” </p>
                    <p tid="110">Mañjuśrī replied, “Bhagavān, no, it does not.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-70"/>
                    <p tid="111">The Bhagavān asked, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? Does a phenomenon engage in pure acts with
                        respect to another phenomenon?” </p>
                    <p tid="112">Mañjuśrī replied, “Bhagavān, no, it does not.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-71"/>
                    <p tid="113">The Bhagavān spoke, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? How did you attain patient forbearance in
                        seeing all phenomena as non-arising?” </p>
                    <p tid="114">Mañjuśrī replied, “Bhagavān, it is with respect to all afflictions that I have attained patient
                        forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising. Why? Bhagavān, since all afflictions arise from the
                        ground of space, I neither seek, nor abandon, nor meditate on, nor manifest, any phenomenon. Bhagavān,
                        childish ordinary beings are neither separate from the teachings of the Buddha, <ref cRef="F.292.b"/> nor
                        have they realized them; and so, Bhagavān, in order to abandon afflictions, I have abandoned these
                        apprehensions of the Buddha’s teachings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-72"/>
                    <p tid="115">Then the Bhagavān praised Youthful Mañjuśrī, “Very well done. Mañjuśrī, very well done.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="116">“Mañjuśrī, a long time in the past, incalculable, immeasurable, measureless, inconceivable,
                        unfathomable eons ago, in a world system called Most Fragrant, the tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete
                        buddha, endowed with perfect knowledge and virtue, sugata, knower of the world, unsurpassed guide who
                        tames beings, teacher of gods and men, the buddha Bhagavān <term>Stainless Light, the Essence of the
                            Sun</term>, appeared in the world. Mañjuśrī, this tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete buddha
                            <term>Stainless Light, the Essence of the Sun</term>, was able to live for nine thousand eons. The
                        sentient beings of that world system took an interest in the lesser paths. Interest in the great paths
                        decreased. After this tathāgata passed into parinirvāṇa, his sacred Dharma endured for a thousand years.
                        His bodily relics proliferated in the same way that my bodily relics will proliferate.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-73"/>
                    <p tid="117">“Mañjuśrī, at that time there appeared a monk called Vīradatta. He practiced all that is
                        contained in the Buddha’s teaching of moral conduct. He was modest, inclined to the higher trainings, and
                        learned. That monk was handsome and lovely to behold. He was of fine color and complexion. One morning he
                        put on his lower garment, took his begging bowl and robes, and went to the great city of Vijaya in order
                        to beg for alms. As he walked around the city begging for alms, he came to a merchant’s home. In that
                        merchant’s home <ref cRef="F.293.a"/> was the merchant’s daughter. Her body was shapely; she was
                        beautiful, lovely to behold, and she had not yet been bestowed upon a husband.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-74"/>
                    <p tid="118">“When the merchant’s daughter saw the monk Vīradatta, lustful intentions were aroused in her and
                        she thought, ‘If I do not gain the monk Vīradatta as my husband, I will die.’ Being unable to talk about
                        this to anyone and deeply distressed by her desire, she became ill. After the monk Vīradatta had made his
                        rounds begging for alms, he went to the main temple. The girl’s father had died, too.</p>
                    <p tid="119">“The girl’s mother asked her, ‘Why have you fallen so ill?’ But the girl did not respond and
                        continued to fast.</p>
                    <p tid="120">“Then the girl’s friends of the same age who had experienced the same joys and pains asked her,
                        ‘Why have you fallen so ill?’</p>
                    <p tid="121">“The girl replied, ‘When I saw a certain monk, I gave rise to longing desire. If I have sex with
                        this monk, I will be cured from my illness, but if I do not have sex with him, I will die.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-75"/>
                    <p tid="122">“The other girls told her mother what she had said, whereupon her mother thought, ‘If she does
                        not have sex with the monk Vīradatta there is nothing that can be done to keep this girl from dying.’ And
                        then she thought, ‘I must have my daughter receive instruction from the monk Vīradatta. Then the monk
                        Vīradatta will come to our home regularly.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-76"/>
                    <p tid="123">“Subsequently the monk Vīradatta returned to the city of Vijaya in order to beg for alms, and
                        again he went to the merchant’s home in order to beg for alms. He went inside, and when he saw that the
                        merchant’s daughter had become so weak he asked, ‘Why has this girl become so weak and ill?’</p>
                    <p tid="124">“The girl’s mother replied, ‘The girl wanted to listen to the Dharma but I prevented her. This is
                        why she fell ill.’</p>
                    <p tid="125">“The monk Vīradatta therefore said to the girl’s mother, <ref cRef="F.293.b"/> ‘Do not prevent
                        this girl from listening to the Dharma.’</p>
                    <p tid="126">“The mother said, ‘If you, master, will impart instruction to her, I shall not prevent this girl
                        from listening to the Dharma.’ </p>
                    <p tid="127">“The monk Vīradatta said, ‘I shall impart instruction to this girl.’ </p>
                    <p tid="128">“The girl’s mother said, ‘Master, please come to our home regularly.’ </p>
                    <p tid="129">“ ‘I shall come,’ Vīradatta replied. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-77"/>
                    <p tid="130">“When she heard the monk’s words, the girl’s improper thoughts became less overpowering than they
                        had been, and she thought, ‘Now I shall by all means make him act according to my desire; I shall seduce
                        him.’ She said to the monk, ‘Master, please do me the favor of coming to our home.’</p>
                    <p tid="131">“The monk Vīradatta wordlessly indicated his agreement, took his alms, and went to the main
                        temple.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-78"/>
                    <p tid="132">“Then the girl’s mother told her, ‘Daughter, from now on adorn yourself with jewels, anoint your
                        body with sandalwood, dress yourself in colorful robes. You must make an effort to be sure that he falls
                        under your power!’ Accordingly, the girl applied herself with effort.</p>
                    <p tid="133">“Thereafter, the monk Vīradatta visited her home repeatedly and they became friends. From seeing
                        her all the time, he gave rise to lustful intentions toward the girl. Preoccupied by desire and being in
                        her company, he became fettered by desire. He came together with the girl, and had full sexual intercourse
                        with her. Becoming intimate with her,<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-193">D
                            (F.293.b.6) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de ’dres shing mngon par dga’ nas</foreign>, which
                            translates as “joining and truly adoring;” this accords with H (F.454.a.4). However, S (F.230.a.5)
                            reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">der ’dris shing mgnon par dga’ nas</foreign>, which translates as
                            “becoming intimate and truly adoring,” which seems more fitting. </note> and adoring her, he had
                        intercourse with her again and again. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-79"/>
                    <p tid="134">“The suitor who had previously asked for her hand heard that Vīradatta had been sleeping with the
                        girl; thinking about how the monk Vīradatta had been with the girl again and again, he decided to seize
                        him and kill him. </p>
                    <p tid="135"> “When the monk Vīradatta heard that the girl’s suitor intended to kill him he thought, <ref cRef="F.294.a"/> ‘I must send some poison with the girl to bring death to that merchant’s son.’ So the
                        monk Vīradatta passed some poison to the girl and said to her, ‘If you love me, kill your suitor with this
                        poison.’ </p>
                    <p tid="136">“The girl took the poison from the monk, mixed it with food, and sent it with the maid, telling
                        her, ‘Go and offer this to my suitor.’ The maid offered the food mixed with poison to the girl’s suitor;
                        the merchant’s son ate the food mixed with poison, and he died.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-80"/>
                    <p tid="137">“As soon as the monk Vīradatta learned that the merchant’s son had died, he felt deep distress,
                        thinking, ‘I have committed a horrific deed. I have committed an inexpiable deed. I have indulged in
                        pleasure, and moreover I have caused a man to die. What kind of creature am I? What will I become in a
                        future life? I will fall into the hell realms.’ He felt great physical pain, and he thought, ‘It is
                        certain that when I die I will go to the hell realms.’ Reflecting thus, he wondered, ‘Is there anyone who
                        can liberate me from this misery?’ He wandered from temple to temple, and would collapse to the ground
                        like a felled tree, weeping, ‘Oh no! Oh no! I have become a sentient being of the hell realms.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-81"/>
                    <p tid="138">“At that time, there was a temple called Snow Temple. The monk went to that temple and when he
                        reached the entrance, he fell to the ground and wept, ‘Oh no! Oh no! I have become a sentient being of the
                        hell realms.’ </p>
                    <p tid="139"> “The bodhisattva mahāsattva Liberator from Fear came into the temple, and when he saw the monk
                        crumpled on the ground, he asked him, ‘Monk, why have you fallen to the ground?’</p>
                    <p tid="140">“The monk replied, ‘I have become a sentient being of the hell realms. I have committed a
                        horrific deed. <ref cRef="F.294.b"/> I have engaged in sexual intercourse, and also killed a person.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-82"/>
                    <p tid="141">“But the bodhisattva Liberator from Fear said to the monk Vīradatta, ‘Monk, do not be afraid. I
                        shall bring an end to your fear.’ </p>
                    <p tid="142">“When the monk Vīradatta heard these words of reassurance he was overjoyed and happy. The
                        bodhisattva Liberator from Fear helped the monk Vīradatta up from the ground, took him by his right hand,
                        and they went into a thick forest, where they remained.</p>
                    <p tid="143">“The bodhisattva mahāsattva Liberator from Fear then hovered in space at the height of a palm
                        tree, and asked the monk, ‘Monk, do you trust me?’ </p>
                    <p tid="144">“The monk joined his palms and said these words, ‘I have met the Bhagavān. I have met the Sugata.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-83"/>
                    <p tid="145">“At that moment, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Liberator from Fear entered the samādhi called
                            <distinct>the exalted wisdom mudrā of the tathāgatas, the entrance gate to the domain of all
                            buddhas</distinct>. No sooner had he entered that samādhi than golden forms of tathāgatas endowed with
                        the thirty-two marks of a buddha emerged from his body. The forms of those tathāgatas pervaded the entire
                        forest. Those tathāgatas spoke these verses that accord with<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-194">D (F.294.b.5) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’thun</foreign>; this
                            seems to be a spelling mistake as both S (F.231.b.5) and H (F.455.b.5) read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mthun</foreign>, which translates as “accord with.”</note> enlightened speech: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-84"/>
                    <lg tid="146">
                        <l>“ ‘All these phenomena are like reflections,</l>
                        <l>Just as the moon appears in water, yet is not there.</l>
                        <l>Immature minds have become dim and afraid,</l>
                        <l>Thus creating toxic thoughts of lust and hate.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-85"/>
                    <lg tid="147">
                        <l>“ ‘All phenomena are like space, ever pure and clear,</l>
                        <l>Beyond suffering, non-dwelling, and peaceful.</l>
                        <l>There is no one who feels or performs actions.</l>
                        <l>All things are peace, unreal, and without essence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-86"/>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“ ‘When examined from within, lust cannot be found,</l>
                        <l>Nor has anyone ever discovered hate.</l>
                        <l>Immature ones believe that they are attached,</l>
                        <l>Yet there is no one who has ever been so.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-87"/>
                    <lg tid="149">
                        <l>“ ‘In dreams they believe in the forms that they see; <ref cRef="F.295.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>With liking and disliking their minds grow dull.</l>
                        <l>Wielding weapons and striving to kill,<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-195">D
                                (F.295.a.1) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshon cha thogs shing gsad par gsol ba na,</foreign>
                                which accords with H (F.456.a.3) and could be translated as “wielding weapons and speaking of
                                killing / requesting to kill.” However, the reading in S (F.232.a.2), <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshon cha thogs shing gsad par rtsol ba na</foreign>, seems more fitting. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>When in fact the weapon and killer do not exist;</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-88"/>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l>“ ‘In this way, immature ones engage in lust,</l>
                        <l>Combat, resistance, and also butchery.</l>
                        <l>Their minds deluded, they are frightened and dull,</l>
                        <l>With thoughts of “I must have this” they grasp at joy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-89"/>
                    <lg tid="151">
                        <l>“ ‘These worldly preoccupations are like dreams,</l>
                        <l>Such phenomena are worthless, void, of no essence;</l>
                        <l>Like a mirage and similar to a cloud,</l>
                        <l>Lust is without sign and delusion is peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-90"/>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“ ‘Phenomena resemble grass straws and walls.</l>
                        <l>Mind can be found neither inside nor outside.</l>
                        <l>Lust is no living creature, nor sentient person;</l>
                        <l>Hate is neither an individual nor a thing.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-91"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“ ‘Causes and conditions form phenomena;</l>
                        <l>Illusions<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-196">D (F.295.a.3) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu de la ni rmongs shing byed pa med</foreign>, which accords with H
                                (F.456.a.6). However, S (F.232.a.5) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyu rkyen de la rmongs shing
                                    byed pa med</foreign>, which could be translated “causes and conditions neither confuse nor
                                act.”</note> neither confuse nor act;</l>
                        <l>Like a moon in a pool of water, they are unproduced.</l>
                        <l>The body, too, is not there; attachment to it is worthless.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-92"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“ ‘It stems from illusion and is emptiness;</l>
                        <l>Grasping at matter, immature ones dissect and construct.</l>
                        <l>Illusions are worthless, absent, empty;</l>
                        <l>There is no lust, hatred, and ignorance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-93"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“ ‘All phenomena are void of attributes;</l>
                        <l>With no root seen, they are at peace from the first;</l>
                        <l>Without end, they are void and lack all essence.</l>
                        <l>Lust is clear light, ignorance is perfect peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-94"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l>“ ‘When childish ones see reflected images,</l>
                        <l>They believe in their identity as truth;</l>
                        <l>Of no worth and ungraspable, things do not exist,</l>
                        <l>Yet beings wrongly view what is without essence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-95"/>
                    <lg tid="157">
                        <l>“ ‘These phenomena, optical illusions:</l>
                        <l>Lust, delusion, and hatred, all ungraspable,</l>
                        <l>Like mirages, dreams, and the moon in a pool of water,</l>
                        <l>No-one should crave or hate them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-96"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>“ ‘They are harmless and empty.</l>
                        <l>No perception of anything can be found;</l>
                        <l>None of these constructions exist.</l>
                        <l>Things are unobservable and perfectly at peace.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-97"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“ ‘Delusion, lust, and hatred do not exist.</l>
                        <l>These illusions will never be real.</l>
                        <l>All phenomena, like illusions or dreams,</l>
                        <l>With no apparent origin, none exist.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-98"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“ ‘Likewise, though it is seen in a pool,</l>
                        <l>The moon never enters any water.</l>
                        <l>Just so, though the infantile hate and lust,</l>
                        <l>Their desire and hatred are never real.<ref cRef="F.295.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-99"/>
                    <lg tid="161">
                        <l>“ ‘Lust cannot be grasped and hate does not exist.</l>
                        <l>Ignorance is clear light, conditions are empty.</l>
                        <l>Beings are not perceived and there is no life.</l>
                        <l>All things are of no import, peaceful, and without essence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-100"/>
                    <lg tid="162">
                        <l>“ ‘There are no eyes, nor are there ears.</l>
                        <l>The nose cannot be found and nor can the tongue;</l>
                        <l>Nothing material has any essence.</l>
                        <l>Intoxicated, childish ones are confused.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-101"/>
                    <lg tid="163">
                        <l>“ ‘Space is boundless, limitless, endless,</l>
                        <l>Inexhaustible, and unproduced.</l>
                        <l>So, too, are all phenomena:</l>
                        <l>They are like rain in the sky, pristine and crystal clear.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-102"/>
                    <lg tid="164">
                        <l>“ ‘Manifold phenomena are all fabricated,</l>
                        <l>But none of those fabrications are ever real.</l>
                        <l>The infantile grasp at the skandhas like that, too;</l>
                        <l>But none of them, either, are ever real.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-103"/>
                    <lg tid="165">
                        <l>“ ‘The wise do not think of real and unreal,</l>
                        <l>But see the true nature of all things as peace,</l>
                        <l>Unarisen and ungraspable.</l>
                        <l>Nor have their own bodies ever existed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-104"/>
                    <lg tid="166">
                        <l>“ ‘All things are luminous, unfettered and free,</l>
                        <l>Peaceful, non-abiding, beyond misery;</l>
                        <l>None of them can be seized.</l>
                        <l>When they know this, the wise will be free.’ </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-105"/>
                    <p tid="167">“In order to hear the teaching of the bodhisattva Liberator from Fear, forty-two thousand sons of
                        gods assembled in the forest, and upon hearing these verses of teachings, they attained patient
                        forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising. The monk Vīradatta also became completely free of
                        fetters, and seeing with a genuine mind of enlightenment the array of the tathāgata’s emanations, he fully
                        recognized the nature of this teaching and attained patient forbearance in seeing all phenomena as
                        non-arising. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-106"/>
                    <p tid="168">“Mañjuśrī, should you wonder whether at that time the bodhisattva Liberator from Fear was someone
                        else, you will not find it so. Why? Because the bodhisattva Maitreya was the bodhisattva Liberator from
                        Fear at that time. Mañjuśrī, should you wonder whether at that time the monk Vīradatta was someone else,
                        you will not find it so. Why? Because the Tathāgata Jewel Moon Performing Enlightened Actions was the monk
                        Vīradatta at that time. <ref cRef="F.296.a"/>.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-107"/>
                    <p tid="169">At this, Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, did the monk Vīradatta attain manifest
                        complete enlightenment?” </p>
                    <p tid="170">The Bhagavān replied, “Mañjuśrī, he attained manifest complete enlightenment and became the
                        Tathāgata Jewel Moon in the West, as many buddhafields beyond this buddhafield as there are sand grains in
                        the River Ganges, in a world system called Eternal Light. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-108"/>
                    <p tid="171">“Mañjuśrī, consider how someone who practiced this Dharma teaching<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-197">D (F.296.a.3) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos ’di dag gi sgrub pa
                                byed pa dag</foreign>, which accords with H. S (F.233.b.5) reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos
                                ’di dag gi sgrib pa med pa dag</foreign> which translates “those who are free of obscurations
                            regarding these teachings.” Since it seems that the benefits of the practice of this sūtra are being
                            explained, the version in D seemed preferable here. </note> attained patient forbearance in seeing all
                        phenomena as non-arising despite having partaken of all that he desired and even having interrupted
                        another’s life. How could that be? It was because he understood that everything in the three realms is
                        untrue, and that all sentient beings are like optical illusions. Mañjuśrī, when one abides in the
                        illusion-like mind there is no obscuration with respect to any phenomenon. Further, Mañjuśrī, childish
                        ordinary beings fall into the hell realms, or into birth as an animal, or into the realm of the Lord of
                        Death, due to their own discursive thoughts. Imagining nonexistent phenomena, they experience infinite
                        suffering.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-109"/>
                    <p tid="172"> Youthful Mañjuśrī asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, what qualities will a bodhisattva who
                        comprehends, upholds, perfectly masters, and honors this Dharma discourse, obtain in this very life?” </p>
                    <p tid="173">The Bhagavān replied, “Mañjuśrī, what do you think? How beneficial is it to the men of Jambudvīpa
                        when the sun rises?” </p>
                    <p tid="174">Mañjuśrī answered, “Bhagavān, the benefit is inconceivable; there is boundless light. It allows
                        people to engage in activities.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-110"/>
                    <p tid="175">The Bhagavān continued, “Mañjuśrī, likewise, through this Dharma discourse, <ref cRef="F.296.b"/>
                        all the bodhisattva’s afflictions will be dispelled and the boundless light of exalted wisdom will arise.
                        He will then attain freedom from obscurations with regard to all phenomena. He will become free of misery,
                        and all fetters will also vanish. He will also swiftly actualize unattached confidence. No māra or
                        adversary will be able to overcome him. He will also teach the Dharma, and moreover he will teach the
                        Dharma with limitless confidence.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-198">Limitless
                            confidence, free of all doubts because one has realized the ultimate truth, is a quality that only a
                            fully enlightened buddha possesses. This passage thus implies that one will become a buddha. </note>
                        Mañjuśrī, it is like this: just as when a fire takes hold, it burns away all grass and wood, likewise,
                        Mañjuśrī, this Dharma discourse burns away all afflictions. Mañjuśrī, it is like this: just as the
                        majestic snow mountain outshines all the black mountains, likewise, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who is skilled
                        in this Dharma discourse subjugates and outshines in virtue all opponents. Mañjuśrī, it is like this: just
                        as the wheel-turning emperor outshines all regional kings, likewise, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who abides by
                        this Dharma discourse outshines those who are skilled in language and composition. Mañjuśrī, it is like
                        this: just as a monk who holds to the rules of the Vinaya is skilled in controlling all downfalls,
                        likewise, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who is skilled in this Dharma discourse dispels the regret of all
                        sentient beings of the ten directions. Mañjuśrī, it is like this: just as the rising sun makes all gloomy
                        darkness disappear, likewise, Mañjuśrī, a bodhisattva who is skilled in this Dharma discourse dispels the
                        afflictions of all sentient beings and thus causes the light of exalted wisdom to manifest. Mañjuśrī, this
                        is because whoever trains in this Dharma discourse trains in the higher training of transcendent
                        awareness.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-111"/>
                    <p tid="176">Then the evil Māra came to the Bhagavān and said to the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, you are
                        compassionate. <ref cRef="F.297.a"/> You are the physician of all sentient beings and endowed with a
                        loving heart. If that is so, Bhagavān, all the abodes of Māra are shaken, and I too am stricken with
                        painful suffering. Bhagavān, please do not expound this Dharma discourse. Bhagavān, I will do anything so
                        that this Dharma discourse is not practiced in Jambudvīpa. I will do anything so that no one comprehends,
                        holds, and masters this Dharma discourse. I will do anything to make beings perceive this Dharma discourse
                        as a wrong path. I will make them perceive the elaborate sūtras with corrupt views. I will employ all
                        means to make various fetters arise so the monks abandon this Dharma discourse.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-112"/>
                    <p tid="177">At that moment, by the Buddha’s miraculous powers, Indra, the chief of gods, appeared before the
                        Bhagavān. He prostrated with his head to the Bhagavān’s feet, cast mandārava flowers toward the Bhagavān,
                        and said to him, “Bhagavān, if the evil Māra deliberately tries to make this Dharma discourse decline,
                        Bhagavān, then I shall comprehend this Dharma discourse, I shall hold it, and perfectly master it. And
                        after you, the Bhagavān, and the venerable Ānanda have passed into parinirvāṇa, I shall cause this Dharma
                        discourse to be practiced in Jambudvīpa. I shall command the Four Great Kings and the host of yakṣas,
                        together with their retinues, to guard, protect, and shield this teaching. I, too, shall guard, protect,
                        and shield those who comprehend, hold, read, and perfectly master this Dharma discourse.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-113"/>
                    <p tid="178">Thereupon the Bhagavān said to the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, comprehend this Dharma discourse,
                        establish it, assemble it, perfectly master it, and teach it widely to others. <ref cRef="F.297.b"/>
                        Because, Ānanda, it is the Dharma mirror of all phenomena.”<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-199">This teaching is said to be a “Dharma mirror” because it clearly reflects
                            the nature of all phenomena. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="179"> Ānanda said, “Bhagavān, just as the Tathāgata commands, I shall comprehend this Dharma
                        discourse. Bhagavān, what is the name of this Dharma discourse? How shall it be retained?” </p>
                    <p tid="180">The Bhagavān answered, “Ānanda, for all these reasons, retain this Dharma discourse with the name
                        ‘Purification of Karmic Obscurations.’ Also retain it with the name ‘Entering the Unobscured Exalted
                        Wisdom.’ ” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-114"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="181">When this Dharma discourse was expounded, the minds of sixty monks were liberated from all
                        defilements, without remainder.<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-200">This is a loose
                            translation of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">len pa med par</foreign>. Of the two types of arhat, with
                            and without remainder, the latter state is attained when all afflictive emotions have been purified.
                            An arhat with remainder continues to assume the five skandhas, while one without abandons the five
                            skandhas altogether. The monks referred to here became arhats without remainder because “their minds
                            were liberated from all defilements.” </note> Eighty bodhisattvas attained patient forbearance in
                        seeing all phenomena as non-arising. When the Bhagavān had thus spoken, the Youthful Mañjuśrī, the
                        venerable Ānanda, the monks, and the worlds of gods, humans, demi-gods, and gandharvas rejoiced, and
                        highly praised the Bhagavān’s words. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="190">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-115"/>
                    <p tid="182"> This concludes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra, <foreign xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic
                            Obscurations</foreign>.</p>
                    <p tid="183">The sūtra was translated and edited by the Indian paṇḍitas Jinamitra and Prajñāvarman, and by the
                        principal editor-translator, the monk Yeshé Dé, along with others. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="191">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="192">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-062-018-116">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-062-018-117">
                        <abbr>H</abbr>
                        <expan>Lhasa Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-062-018-118">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="193">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-119">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­karmāvaraṇa­viśuddhi­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh.
                        218, Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 284a-297b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-120">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo.</title> Lhasa number 222, Lhasa Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, ma), folios 438a-461a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-121">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo.</title> Stog number 128, Stok Palace (stog pho brang) Kangyur, vol. 65 (mdo sde, pha), folios
                        215b-236a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-122">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa las kyi sgrib pa rnam par dag pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo.</title> bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa
                        zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China
                        Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006-2009, vol. 62, pp 780-814. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-123">Lamotte, Etienne. <title xml:lang="fr">Le Traité de la Grande Vertu de
                            Sagesse de Nāgārjuna (Mahāprajñāpāramitāśāstra),</title> Tome II, Chapitres XVI-XXX. Louvain:
                        Publications de l’Institut Orientaliste de Louvain, 1981. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-018-124">Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar
                            and Dictionary</title> (2 vols). New Haven: Yale University Press, 1953. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-125">
                            <term>construct</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྟག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-126">
                            <term>definite release</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nges par ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངེས་པར་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">niryāṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-127">
                            <term>distorted</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyin ci log pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-128">
                            <term>essenceless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngo bo med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངོ་བོ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">niḥsvabhāva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asvabhāva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-129">
                            <term>worthless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསོག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rikta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-130">
                            <term>insignificant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསོབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tuccha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-131">
                            <term>formation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃskāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five aggregates; formative forces concomitant with the production
                                of karmic seeds causing future samsaric existence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-132">
                            <term>fully cleansed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par byang ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་བྱང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyavadāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The opposite of ‘totally afflicted.’</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-133">
                            <term>miserable</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid la gcags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་ལ་གཅགས་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-134">
                            <term>patient forbearance in seeing all phenomena as non-arising</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The forbearance to accept and understand the non-arising of phenomena,
                                attained by a bodhisattva on the 8th level (see note <ptr target="#UT22084-062-018-183"/><!--3-->).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-135">
                            <term>perception</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālambana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-136">
                            <term>project</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgro btags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲོ་བཏགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samāropa</term>
                            <term type="definition">To superimpose existence upon something which does not exist; adherents of
                                eternalist views superimpose existence upon something which does not exist. They grasp at a
                                concrete reality. The opposite is the view of nihilists which denies the existence of
                                phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-137">
                            <term>totally afflicted</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas nyon mongs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་ཉོན་མོངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃkleśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Saṃsāra, in being nothing but afflicted; its opposite is ‘fully cleansed,’
                                ‘complete purification.’</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-138">NOT in text as such - AAR
                            <term>totally fettered</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas dkris pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་དཀྲིས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paryavasthāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-139">
                            <term>transcendent awareness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-140">
                            <term>unelaborated</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spros pa med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྲོས་པ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">niṣprapañca</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-141">
                            <term>unperceived</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dmigs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དམིགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anupalambha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-142">
                            <term>void</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Equivalent to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">med pa</foreign> (non-existent) or
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong pa</foreign> (empty), with a sense of ‘being devoid
                                of.’</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-143">
                            <term>Stok Palace Kangyur</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོག་ཕོ་བྲང་བྲིས་མ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A manuscript Kangyur copied from a Bhutanese original in 1729 and kept at the
                                Stok Palace near Leh, Ladakh. It is among the Kangyurs derived mostly from the Thempangma
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">them spangs ma</foreign>) tradition.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-144">
                            <term>Lhasa Kangyur</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha sa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་ས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhol </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞོལ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A xylograph Kangyur printed in 1934. Based mainly on the Narthang (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar thang</foreign>) Kangyur but with some texts following the Degé
                                Kangyur, it is among several Kangyurs of “mixed” lineage, including elements from the Thempangma
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">them spangs ma</foreign>) in addition to the predominating Tshalpa
                                    (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshal pa</foreign>) traditions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-145">
                            <term>Abode of Myriad Flowers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog sna tshogs gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་སྣ་ཚོགས་གནས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-146">
                            <term>All Doubts Diminished</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">som nyi thams cad mgu byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོམ་ཉི་ཐམས་ཅད་མགུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-147">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">Śrāvaka arhat and attendant of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-148">
                            <term>Destroyer of Pride</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nga rgyal rnam par ’joms </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ང་རྒྱལ་རྣམ་པར་འཇོམས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-149">
                            <term>Vīradatta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpas byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔས་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vīradatta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name, in his previous lifetime as a monk, of the buddha named Jewel Moon
                                Performing Enlightened Actions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-150">
                            <term>Embodiment Always Appearing Like an Honorable Image</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtag tu bu don ltar bris pa’i lus can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟག་ཏུ་བུ་དོན་ལྟར་བྲིས་པའི་ལུས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-151">
                            <term>Embodiment of Enchanting Splendor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid yid ’ong kun bsdus </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་བརྗིད་ཡིད་འོང་ཀུན་བསྡུས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-152">
                            <term>Golden Light of the Glorious Essence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal gyi snying po’i gser ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་གྱི་སྙིང་པོའི་གསེར་འོད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-153">
                            <term>He whose Intelligence is Like an Ocean of Arrayed Jewels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen bkod pa’i rgya mtsho blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་བཀོད་པའི་རྒྱ་མཚོ་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-154">
                            <term>Indra, the chief of gods</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha’i dbang po rgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷའི་དབང་པོ་རྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-155">
                            <term>Jewel Moon Performing Enlightened Actions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen zla ba byang chub kyi spyad pa spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་ཟླ་བ་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-156">
                            <term>Jinamitra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indian paṇḍit who translated and edited (among many others) the sūtra <title xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic Obscurations</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-157">
                            <term>King of Light Diffusion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer rab tu ’gyed pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་རབ་ཏུ་འགྱེད་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-158">
                            <term>King of Openly Proclaiming Melody</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra dbyangs mngon par sgrogs pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་དབྱངས་མངོན་པར་སྒྲོགས་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-159">
                            <term>King of Utterly Clear Melody</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra dbyangs rnam par dag pa’i rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་དབྱངས་རྣམ་པར་དག་པའི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-160">
                            <term>Lamp of the Light King</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer rgyal po’i sgron ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་རྒྱལ་པོའི་སྒྲོན་མ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-161">
                            <term>Liberator from Fear</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">jigs sgrol </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཇིགས་སྒྲོལ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of Maitreya in a previous lifetime as a bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-162">
                            <term>Like a Lotus Flower</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog pad+ma lta bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་པདྨ་ལྟ་བུ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-163">
                            <term>He Who Proclaims the Lion’s Roar of Conduct That is Renowned to be the Lotus of Good
                                Qualities</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yon tan pad+ma rnam par grags spyod seng ge’i sgra sgrogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོན་ཏན་པདྨ་རྣམ་པར་གྲགས་སྤྱོད་སེང་གེའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-164">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha to follow Śākyamuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-165">
                            <term>Mighty One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་པོ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-166">
                            <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pra dznya’ barma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">པྲ་ཛཉའ་བརྨ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indian paṇḍit who translated and edited (among others) the sūtra <title xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic Obscurations</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-167">
                            <term>Stainless Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dri med ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདྲི་མེད་འོད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A monk, main character of the sūtra <title xml:lang="en">Purification of
                                    Karmic Obscurations</title>. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-168">
                            <term>Subjugator of All Places</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul thams cad rab tu ’dul ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་ཐམས་ཅད་རབ་ཏུ་འདུལ་བ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-169">
                            <term>Sublime Knowledge Displayed with Luminosity</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od kyis rnam par rtse ba mngon par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཀྱིས་རྣམ་པར་རྩེ་བ་མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-170" mode="marked">
                            <term>Stainless Light, the Essence of the Sun</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyi ma’i snying po 'od zer dri ma med pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉི་མའི་སྙིང་པོ་འོད་ཟེར་དྲི་མ་མེད་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-171">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">Prolific translator and editor of a large number of sūtras, including <title xml:lang="en">Purification of Karmic Obscurations</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-172">
                            <term>Youthful Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur ’gyur pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་འགྱུར་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī­kumāra­bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of wisdom and one of the Buddha's principal interlocutors in many
                                sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-173">
                            <term>Eternal Light</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer rtag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་རྟག་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A world system.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-174">
                            <term>Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu gling </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུ་གླིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambudvīpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-175">
                            <term>Āmrapālī’s Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">A mras bsrungs ba’i tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨཱ་མྲས་བསྲུངས་བའི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āmrapālīvana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The site in Vaiśālī where Buddha Śākyamuni taught and performed
                                miracles.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-176">
                            <term>Most Fragrant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shin tu dri ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིན་ཏུ་དྲི་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A world system.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-177">
                            <term>Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yangs pa can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡངས་པ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The site where Buddha Śākyamuni laid down various rules of the Vinaya, gave
                                other teachings, and, on his last visit, announced his approaching parinirvāṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-178">
                            <term>Vijaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vijaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A great city in the world system Most Fragant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-179">
                            <term>Endowed with Infinite Discourses</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam grangs mtha’ yas ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་གྲངས་མཐའ་ཡས་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A world system.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-018-180">
                            <term>Snow Temple</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtsug lag khang gangs zhes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཙུག་ལག་ཁང་གངས་ཞེས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>