<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sA lu’i ljang pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སཱ་ལུའི་ལྗང་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སཱ་ལུའི་ལྗང་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sA lu’i ljang pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Rice Seedling”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­śāli­stamba­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-10">Translated by the Dharmasāgara Translation Group<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-79">Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-80">Rebecca Hufen</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-81">Jason Sanche</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-83">Arne Schelling</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-244">Sonam Spitz</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.14 <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-062-010"/>
                <date>2018-01-01</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh210" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 210</ref>, <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 116.a–123.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib"/>
                    <location count-pages="16">
                        <start volume="62" page="233"/>
                        <end volume="62" page="248"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11845" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-26T22:10:42.92Z" user="laura">26/02/2019 22:10:42</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="79">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In this sūtra, at the request of venerable Śāriputra, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya elucidates a
                    very brief teaching on dependent arising that the Buddha had given earlier that day while gazing at a rice
                    seedling. The text discusses outer and inner causation and its conditions, describes in detail the twelvefold
                    cycle by which inner dependent arising gives rise to successive lives, and explains how understanding the very
                    nature of that process can lead to freedom from it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="80">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-2"/>
                <p tid="2"> This text was translated from the Tibetan, with comparison to Sanskrit editions, introduced, and
                    edited by the <term type="ignore">Dharmasāgara</term> Translation Group: Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche,
                    Rebecca Hufen, Jason Sanche, Arne Schelling and Sonam Spitz. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="81">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>
                        <note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-4">Edgerton, Gokale, Reat, and Sastri all record the
                            spelling of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stamba</foreign> (seedling) in the title <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śālistamba</title>, rather than the more common <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stambha</foreign>. Monier-Williams lists <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stamba</foreign> as “prob. a phonetic variation of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stambha</foreign>.” Among the versions of the Tibetan translation consulted, all read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stambha</foreign> with the exception of Peking Yongle and Peking Kangxi, which
                            read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stamba</foreign>. The Tibetan translations of the three
                            Indian commentaries read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">stamba</foreign>.</note>) is one of
                        the most important sūtras on the topic of dependent arising. In this sūtra Śāriputra approaches Maitreya
                        and requests him to explain the meaning of the following statement of the Buddha, which he had made
                        earlier that same day while gazing at a rice seedling: “Whoever sees dependent arising sees the Dharma.
                        Whoever sees the Dharma sees the Buddha.” What follows is an explanation of dependent arising through the
                        twelve links, the eightfold path of the noble ones, and their relation to outer and inner causes and
                        conditions. Crucially, it is by understanding the very nature of dependent arising that one can be free
                        from it and attain enlightenment.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-5"/>
                    <p tid="4">We are not aware of any extant complete Sanskrit text of <title xml:lang="en">The Rice
                            Seedling</title>. However, it is quoted extensively in surviving Sanskrit treatises like Yaśomitra’s
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­dharma­kośa­vyākhyā</title>, Candrakīrti’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>, Prajñākaramati’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title>,
                        Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣasamuccaya</title>, and also a critical non-Buddhist treatise,
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāmatī</title> by Vācaspatimiśra. Mainly based on these, several Sanskrit
                        reconstructions have been carried out which are claimed to include about ninety percent of <title xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title>. The first reconstructed edition was prepared by Louis de La
                        Vallée Poussin (1913). Without having access to this, N. Ayaswami Sastri (1950) produced another
                        reconstruction. Another one was produced by V.V. Gokhale (1961). Finally, a thorough comparative study and
                        new reconstructed edition was carried out by N. Ross Reat (1993), taking into account Sanskrit, Tibetan,
                        Pāli, and Chinese sources; Reat also provides a complete English translation. This work also illustrates
                        the many parallel and similar passages in Pāli suttas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-6"/>
                    <p tid="5">There are three Indian commentaries on <title xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title> which have
                        been preserved in Tibetan and Mongolian translations, namely the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title> by
                        Kamalaśīla, as well as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāyana­sūtra­ṭīkā</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāli­stambaka­kārikā</title>, both attributed to Nāgarjuna. These works have been thoroughly studied
                        and translated by Jeffrey D. Schoening (1995). He also gives a chronological account of both partial and
                        complete Western language translations of <title xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title>, the first <term type="ignore">being</term> a translation from the Chinese into Italian in 1908; and he mentions a
                        Japanese translation from the Chinese of Taishō 709. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-7"/>
                    <p tid="6">Most of the information given in this introduction can be found in more detail in the sources
                        mentioned above, especially Reat and Schoening. <term type="ignore">Being</term> of such significance,
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Rice Seedling</title> has also been discussed in the context of multiple
                        other studies, the details of which would go beyond the scope of this brief introduction. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-8"/>
                    <p tid="7">There are four Chinese translations (Taishō 709–712), the first and earliest having been carried
                        out during the Eastern Jin Dynasty (317–420 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>). A very similar sūtra (Taishō 708) had already been
                        translated by Chih-ch’ien in the Wu Dynasty (222–280 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>). As Martin (2014, p. 283) has noted, the <title xml:lang="en">Testament of Wa / Ba</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dba’</title> / <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sba bzhed</title>) mentions that a Chinese version was translated into Tibetan
                        before the completion of the first monastery of Tibet, Samye, toward the end of the eighth century. The
                        Tibetan translation is also mentioned in the Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>)
                        catalogue compiled by Kawa Paltseg et al., probably in the year 812. The colophons in two of the oldest
                        surviving Tibetan manuscripts identified so far (the Dunhuang manuscripts PT 551 and PT 552), credit Yeshé
                        Dé, a famous Tibetan translator of the eighth to ninth centuries, as the translator. This information is
                        absent in the later editions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-9"/>
                    <p tid="8">There are considerable differences and variant readings across the many versions, editions, and
                        translations of this sūtra that are not recorded in detail here. Variant readings as well as references to
                        the commentaries are only given for passages that were crucial for essential decisions made with regard to
                        the translation. Thus this translation does not aim to improve on the studies mentioned above. Readers who
                        are interested in academic and philological research on the available textual sources may refer to them.
                        What is intended here is a translation that is mainly based on the Tibetan version in the Degé Kangyur
                            <term type="ignore">collection</term> and the Pedurma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>)
                        comparative edition of the Kangyur, with reference to available Sanskrit materials, particularly Reat’s
                        edition. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="82">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="83">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="84">The Rice Seedling</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-10"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <ref cRef="F.116.a"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-11"/>
                    <p tid="10">Thus have I heard at one time. The Bhagavān was residing on Vulture Peak mountain in Rājagṛha with
                        a large saṅgha of 1,250 bhikṣus and with a great many bodhisattva mahāsattvas. At that time, venerable
                        Śāriputra went to the place frequented by the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya and, after they had
                        exchanged courtesies upon meeting each other, they both sat down on a flat rock. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-12"/>
                    <p tid="11">Venerable Śāriputra then said to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, “Maitreya, here today, the
                        Bhagavān, gazing at a rice seedling, spoke this aphorism<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-13">The term translated here is <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sūtra</foreign> (Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mdo</foreign>). In Indian
                            literature a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sūtra</foreign> generally refers to the statement
                            of a short rule or universal truth, e.g. an axiom, dictum, formula, or thread. A <term type="ignore">collection</term> of such statements can also be called a sūtra. While, generally speaking,
                            Buddhist sūtras present a complete speech of the Buddha including introductory and concluding
                            statements, here we have a complete teaching of the Buddha in very few words but still resembling the
                            general usage of the term.</note> to the bhikṣus: ‘Bhikṣus, whoever sees dependent arising sees the
                            Dharma.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-14"> Owing to the multivalence of the term
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> and the play between these different senses witnessed in this text, we have chosen
                            to leave it untranslated as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Dharma</foreign> in certain passages. Where we do render it into
                            English, explanatory notes are provided.</note> Whoever sees the Dharma sees the Buddha.’ Having said
                        this, the Bhagavān fell silent. Maitreya, what is the meaning of this aphorism spoken by the Sugata?<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-15">The Sanskrit reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bhagavatā</foreign> (Reat 1993, p. 27).</note> What is dependent arising? What is the
                        Dharma? What is the Buddha? How does one see the Dharma by seeing dependent arising? How does one see the
                        Buddha by seeing the Dharma?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-16"/>
                    <p tid="12">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya then replied to the venerable Śāradvatīputra,<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-17"> A common name variant of Śāriputra. However, the Sanskrit
                            (Reat, p. 28) and the Stok Palace version of the Tibetan (F.282b.6) both read Śāriputra. </note>
                        “Venerable Śāriputra, you want to know what dependent arising is in the statement made by the Bhagavān,
                        the Lord of Dharma, the Omniscient One: ‘Bhikṣus, whoever sees dependent arising sees the Dharma. Whoever
                        sees the Dharma sees the Buddha’? Well, the phrase <distinct>dependent arising</distinct> means that
                        something arises because something else already exists; something is born because something else was
                        already born.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-18"> This entire sentence is missing from
                            the available Sanskrit materials and the Chinese translation (Reat, pp. 28–29). </note> That is to
                        say, ignorance causes formations. Formations <ref cRef="F.116.b"/> cause consciousness. Consciousness
                        causes name and form. Name and form cause the six sense sources. The six sense sources cause contact.
                        Contact causes sensation. Sensation causes craving. Craving causes appropriation. Appropriation causes
                        becoming. Becoming causes birth. And birth causes aging and death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering,
                        despair, and anxiety. Thus does this entire great heap of suffering arise.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-19"/>
                    <p tid="13">“When ignorance ceases, formations cease. When formations cease, consciousness ceases. When
                        consciousness ceases, name and form cease. When name and form cease, the six sense sources cease. When the
                        six sense sources cease, contact ceases. When contact ceases, sensation ceases. When sensation ceases,
                        craving ceases. When craving ceases, appropriation ceases. When appropriation ceases, becoming ceases.
                        When becoming ceases, birth ceases. And when birth ceases, aging and death, sorrow, lamentation,
                        suffering, despair, and anxiety cease. Thus does this entire great heap of suffering cease. This is what
                        the Bhagavān has called dependent arising.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-20"/>
                    <p tid="14">“What is the Dharma? The Dharma is the eightfold path of the noble ones: right view, right
                        intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, and right
                        concentration. This eightfold path of the noble ones, combined with the attainment of its results and
                        nirvāṇa, is what the Bhagavān has called the Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-21"/>
                    <p tid="15">“Who is the Bhagavān Buddha? A <distinct>buddha</distinct>, so-called because of comprehending all
                            dharmas,<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-22"> “All dharmas” here has the sense of
                            “all phenomena.” We leave the term untranslated here and throughout this passage to help convey the
                            chain of associations communicated in the Sanskrit and Tibetan source texts through these uses of the
                            multivalent term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>. See the following note, and note 12 for more on this multivalence.
                            </note> is endowed with the wisdom eye of the noble ones and the body <ref cRef="F.117.a"/> of Dharma,<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-23"> “Body of Dharma” here renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi sku</foreign>. This section of the sūtra is not attested in the available
                            Sanskrit material, so the available Sanskrit editions have actually been reconstructed from the
                            Tibetan translation. Louis de La Vallée Poussin (1913, p. 72) and Sastri (1950, p. 3) reconstruct
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi sku</foreign> here with <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmakāya</foreign>, but we prefer—with Reat (p. 30)—the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmaśarīra</foreign> because it is attested as a possible
                            underlying Sanskrit term for the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi sku</foreign>
                            in the next paragraph (cf. Reat, p. 32 n5). Kamalaśīla interprets the term as the pristine wisdom, or
                            suchness, that serves as a basis for the dharmas (i.e., awakened qualities) of a buddha. He states:
                            “ ‘body of Dharma’ demonstrates the cause: that which serves as the cause of the dharmas (i.e.,
                            awakened qualities) of a buddha is pristine wisdom or pristine suchness—the body which is the body of
                            Dharma” (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 473). Reat (ibid.) translates this term as “Dharma-body,” whereas
                            Schoening (vol. 1, p. 237) renders it as “the body consisting of dharma(s).” As indicated by these
                            different interpretations, the semantic range of the term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmaśarīra</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos kyi sku</foreign>) can
                            include the interlinked notions of the “corpus” of the Buddha’s “teachings” or “doctrine” (Dharma),
                            the “<term type="ignore">collection</term>” of undefiled “qualities” (dharmas) that make a buddha a
                            buddha, the physical body of the Buddha as an “embodiment” of “ultimate reality” (Dharma) and
                            attendant “awakened qualities,” and, by extension, as Kamalaśīla’s interpretation suggests, the
                            ethereal “body” of pristine wisdom that characterizes the Buddha’s awakening experience. The mutual
                            implications of dharma as “doctrine,” “qualities,” and “reality” (and “phenomena” in general) is an
                            important facet of the term’s multivalence in Buddhist literary sources. For more on the shifting
                            semantic range of the terms <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmaśarīra</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmakāya</foreign>, see Paul Harrison (1992). We have partially followed Reat in rendering this
                            term with the slightly ambiguous “body of Dharma,” with the hope of not overly constraining the broad
                            semantic range of the term and its possible commentarial interpretations.</note> and thus perceives
                        the dharmas<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-24"> Dharmas (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos rnams</foreign>) here seems to have the dual sense of “trainings” on the path and
                            their associated “attainments” or “qualities” of attainment. Reat (p. 31) interprets dharmas here to
                            mean only “rules, practices,” but this would not apply to “those beyond training.” </note> of those
                        still in training and those beyond training.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-25"/>
                    <p tid="16">“How does one see dependent arising? On this point the Bhagavān said, ‘One who sees dependent
                        arising as constant,<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-26"> We opted to interpret this
                            passage according to Kamalaśīla’s commentary: “It is constant because it has been taught as a dharma
                            that is thus unborn in all times. This shows that since the three times too are ultimately of one
                            taste, it is unchanging (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title>, p. 395: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dus thams cad du ’di ltar skye ba med pa’i chos gsungs pa dang ldan pas na rtag pa’o/ /’dis ni
                                dus gsum yang don dam par ro gcig pas ’gyur ba med par bstan to/</foreign>).” However, the
                            Sanskrit versions also allow another interpretation by which “permanent / always / constant” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">satatasamitam</foreign>) qualifies “without life force” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ajīvam</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nirjīvam</foreign>), thus meaning, “always without life force.” This is also supported by the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistambaṭīkā</title> ascribed to Nāgarjuna (p. 805). Reat (pp. 32–33)
                            translates this passage with “always and ever devoid of soul,” and he translates from the Chinese
                            (Taishō 709) with “eternal, continuously arising without soul.” Note also the very similar passage at
                            1.59.</note> without life force, devoid of life force, true, unmistaken, unborn, not arisen,
                        uncreated, uncompounded, unobstructed, imperceptible, tranquil,<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-27"> The Sanskrit (Reat, p. 32) has <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śiva</foreign>, “glorious,” “auspicious,” “propitious,” suggesting that the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhi ba</foreign> might have been a transliteration of the Sanskrit.
                            However, Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, pp. 479–480) interprets it to mean “tranquil,” “peaceful.”
                        </note> fearless, incontrovertible, inexhaustible, and by nature never stilled,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-28"> In Tibetan “by nature” could also refer to all aspects listed
                            above; however, in Sanskrit, and according to Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, pp. 481–482), it only
                            modifies “never stilled” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">avyupaśama­svabhāva</foreign>).</note> and who likewise sees the Dharma to also be constant, without
                        life force, devoid of life force, true, unmistaken, unborn, not arisen, uncreated, uncompounded,
                        unobstructed, imperceptible, tranquil, fearless, incontrovertible, inexhaustible, and never stilled,
                        clearly understands the Dharma of the nobles ones, and by thus acquiring such right knowledge, sees the
                        Buddha, the body of the unsurpassable Dharma.’<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-29">
                            The available Sanskrit (Reat, p. 32) for this passage reads: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">anuttara­dharma­śarīraṃ buddhaṃ paśyati| ārya­dharmābhisamaye samyag-jñānād
                                upanayenaiva|</foreign>. The corresponding section in the Tibetan Degé and other versions recorded
                            in the Pedurma comparative edition read: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">’phags pa’i chos
                                mngon par rtogs te/ yang dag pa’i ye shes dang ldan pas bla na med pa’i chos kyi skur sangs rgyas
                                mthong ngo gsungs so/</foreign>. The Stok Palace version of the Tibetan differs from the Degé and
                            all other versions recorded in the Pedurma comparative edition; it also more closely reflects the
                            Sanskrit. The Stok Palace (F.284a.4-5) reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">yang dag pa’i ye
                                shes thob pas/ ’phags pa’i chos mngon par rtogs pas bla na med pa’i chos kyi skur sangs rgyas
                                mthong ngo gsungs so/</foreign> (“By attaining right knowledge and thereby realizing the Dharma of
                            the noble ones, he sees the Buddha, the body of the unsurpassable Dharma”). The Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">thob pa</foreign>, “to attain,” is a conceivable rendering of the
                            Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upanaya</foreign>, which Reat renders as “exertion.”
                            Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, pp. 483–484) interprets this phrase to mean, “Whoever sees dependent
                            arising in this manner sees the Dharma of accomplishment and the Dharma of fruition, because
                            ultimately everything is the same taste, and because the Buddha Bhagavān too is the nature of the body
                            of the ultimate Dharma which was thus taught. Therefore, it is taught that whoever sees the Dharma
                            thus taught sees the Buddha… Whoever comprehends dependent arising thus taught realizes the Dharma of
                            the noble ones; this means ‘comprehending the Dharma of the ultimate meaning.’ Whoever comprehends the
                            Dharma of the ultimate meaning is endowed with perfect wisdom. Whoever is endowed with perfect wisdom
                            abides in the wisdom of equanimity and thus does not perceive any difference between dependent
                            arising, the Dharma, and the Buddha.” The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]-<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title> attributed to Nāgārjuna
                            (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 393) interprets the phrase as: “ ‘Unsurpassable’ means that that there is no
                            special dharma whatsoever that is superior to this, hence it is ‘unsurpassable.’ ‘Body of Dharma’
                            means the Dharma-body itself. … ‘Buddha’ is so-called because of comprehending dharma(s). Thus, one
                            who sees dependent arising sees the nature of one who awakens to the unexcelled Dharma, beyond further
                            training.” Akin to the reconstruction presented above in note 7, this phrase on its own carries the
                            semantic range of the Buddha as an embodiment of the unsurpassable nature of “reality” (Dharma), the
                            unsurpassable “doctrine” (Dharma) that teaches it, and the unsurpassable “qualities” of awakening
                            (dharmas) incumbent upon becoming an awakened one (Buddha). Reat (p. 32) translates the phrase as “he
                            sees the unsurpassable Dharma-body, the Buddha, by exertion based on right knowledge in clear
                            understanding of the noble Dharma.” Schoening (vol. 1, p. 241) translates the final section as, “sees
                            the Buddha, the body consisting of unsurpassable dharma(s).” In interpreting “unsurpassable” to modify
                            “dharma,” and not the whole phrase “body of dharma,” we attempt to follow the interpretations of the
                            commentaries and Schoening. We also leave “dharma” untranslated here in an attempt to capture
                            something of the multiple entendre of the term. See Harrison (1992) for observations about possibly
                            earlier, non-metaphysical senses of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmakāya</foreign> and
                            the associated term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmaśarīra</foreign> in Mahāyāna
                            literature. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-30"/>
                    <p tid="17">“Why is it called <distinct>dependent arising</distinct>? It is called dependent arising because
                        it is causal and conditional, not non-causal and non-conditional. In this connection, the Bhagavān
                        concisely taught the characteristics of dependent arising as follows: ‘Results come from their own
                        specific conditions. Whether tathāgatas appear or not, this true nature of things<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-31"> “Things” here renders <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign>. Note the associations
                            the source text is making in this and the next passage between <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> as “phenomena,”
                            “reality,” and “doctrine.” </note> will remain. It is the true nature; the constancy of Dharma;<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-32"> The sense of “Dharma” here seems to be both
                            “doctrine” and “reality,” i.e., the “doctrine” as “law” (Dharma), which describes the “true nature”
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmatā</foreign>) of “reality” (Dharma). According to
                            Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 487), the phrase functions as a synonym for “true nature” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmatā</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos
                                nyid</foreign>). We leave it untranslated here so as not to constrain this double entendre.
                        </note> the immutability of Dharma,<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-33"> The available
                            Sanskrit (Reat, p. 33) reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niyāmatā</foreign>. Edgerton
                            describes this term, as rendered into Tibetan with the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos mi ’gyur ba nyid</foreign>, as “the doctrine’s <term type="ignore">being</term> unchangeably
                            the same.” Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 487) has the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nges par ’gyur ba</foreign>, and interprets it as, “purely immutable, meaning, one
                            should know that things are dependent on certain specific causes.” Once again, “Dharma” here seems to
                            refer both to the nature of reality and to the doctrine that describes this reality. </note>
                        consistent with dependent arising, suchness, unmistaken suchness, unchanging suchness, actuality, and
                        truth; unmistaken; and unerring.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-34"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Moreover, dependent arising emerges from two principles. <ref cRef="F.117.b"/> From what two
                        principles? From a causal relation and a conditional relation. Furthermore, it should be understood as
                        twofold: outer and inner. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-35"/>
                    <p tid="19">“What is the causal relation in outer dependent arising? It is as follows. From a seed comes a
                        sprout, from a sprout a leaf, from a leaf a stem, from a stem a pedicel, from a pedicel a pistil, from a
                        pistil a flower, and from a flower comes a fruit. If there is no seed, the sprout cannot arise and so on,
                        until finally, without the flower, the fruit cannot arise. If there is a seed, the sprout will form and so
                        on, until finally, if there is a flower, then the fruit will form.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-36"/>
                    <p tid="20">“In that process, the seed does not think, ‘I form the sprout.’ Nor does the sprout think, ‘I am
                        formed by the seed.’ Likewise, the flower does not think, ‘I form the fruit.’ Nor does the fruit think, ‘I
                        am formed by the flower.’ Yet, if there is a seed, the sprout will take form and arise, and so on, until
                        finally, likewise, if there is a flower, the fruit will take form and arise. Thus is the causal relation
                        in outer dependent arising to be seen.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-37"/>
                    <p tid="21">“So how is the conditional relation in outer dependent arising to be seen? As due to the coming
                        together of six elements. As due to the coming together of what six elements? Namely, conditional
                        dependent arising is to be seen as due to the coming together of the elements of earth, water, fire, wind,
                        space, and season.<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-38"> Although the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dus</foreign> is most often rendered with the general term “time,”
                            the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṛtu</foreign> suggests a specific time span. Also
                            compare with Kamalaśīla’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title>, (p. 405): “As for ‘season,’ the division by
                            specific momentary conditions of the earth, etc., is considered a specific aspect of time (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dus kyang sa la sogs pa’i gnas skabs kyi bye brag gis rab tu phye
                                ba nyid dus kyi bye brag tu dgongs pa’o//</foreign>).”</note> The earth element functions as the
                        support for the seed. The water element moistens the seed. The fire element ripens the seed. The wind
                        element opens the seed. The space element performs the function of not obstructing the seed. And season
                        transforms the seed. Without these conditions a sprout cannot form from a seed. <ref cRef="F.118.a"/> But
                        when the outer element of earth is not deficient, and likewise water, fire, wind, space, and season are
                        not deficient, then from the coming together of all these factors, a sprout forms as the seed is
                        ceasing.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-39"/>
                    <p tid="22">“The earth element does not think, ‘I support the seed.’ Nor does the water element think, ‘I
                        moisten the seed.’ Nor does the fire element think, ‘I ripen the seed.’ Nor does the wind element think,
                        ‘I open the seed.’ Nor does the space element think, ‘I make sure the seed is not obstructed.’ Nor does
                        the season think, ‘I transform the seed.’ Nor does the seed think, ‘I form the sprout.’ Nor does the
                        sprout think, ‘I am formed by these conditions.’ Yet when these conditions are present and the seed is
                        ceasing, the sprout forms. Likewise, when finally there is a flower, the fruit forms.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-40"/>
                    <p tid="23">“The sprout is not created by itself, not created by another, not created by both, not created by
                        Īśvara, not transformed by time,<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-41"> Here, “time” as
                            an agent is rejected, not change in time. (cf. Reat, p. 39 n4). </note> not derived from <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prakṛti</foreign>, and not born without any cause. Nevertheless, through
                        the coming together of the elements of earth, water, fire, wind, space, and season, the sprout forms as
                        the seed is ceasing. </p>
                    <p tid="24">“Thus is the conditional relation in outer dependent arising to be seen.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-42"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Here, outer dependent arising is to be seen in terms of five aspects. What five aspects? As not
                        permanent, as not discontinuous, as not involving transmigration, as the production of a large result from
                        a small cause, and as a continuity of similar type.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-43"/>
                    <p tid="26">“How is it not permanent? It is not permanent because the sprout and the seed are different. The
                        sprout is not the seed. <ref cRef="F.118.b"/> The sprout does not come from the seed after it has ceased,
                        nor does it come from the seed while it has not yet ceased.<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-44"> The sentence, “The sprout…has not ceased,” is not found in the known
                            Sanskrit sources. Reat thus assumes it might be displaced from the similar sentence in the next
                            paragraph (Reat, p. 40 n2).</note> Rather, the sprout is born precisely as the seed ceases.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-45"/>
                    <p tid="27">“How is it not discontinuous? It is not discontinuous because a sprout is not born from a seed
                        that has already ceased, nor from a seed that has not yet ceased. Rather, like the beam of a scale tilting
                        from up to down, a sprout is born precisely when the seed has ceased. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-46"/>
                    <p tid="28">“How does it not involve transmigration? It does not involve transmigration because the sprout and
                        the seed are different; that which is the sprout is not the seed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-47"/>
                    <p tid="29">“How does it entail the producing of a large result from a small cause? A large fruit is produced from
                        the planting of a small seed. Therefore, it entails the producing of a large result from a small cause. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-48"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Lastly, fruit is produced precisely according to the type of seed planted. Therefore, it involves a
                        continuity of similar type. </p>
                    <p tid="31">“Thus is outer dependent arising to be seen in terms of five aspects.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-49"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="32">“Similarly, inner dependent arising also arises from two principles. From what two principles?
                        From a causal relation and a conditional relation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-50"/>
                    <p tid="33">“What, then, is the causal relation in inner dependent arising? It starts with ignorance causing
                        formations and so on, until finally, birth causes aging and death. If ignorance does not arise, then
                        formations do not manifest and so on, until finally, if birth does not arise, then aging and death do not
                        manifest. Likewise, from the existence of ignorance, formations occur and so on, until finally, from the
                        existence of birth, comes aging and death. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-51"/>
                    <p tid="34">“Ignorance does not think, ‘I produce formations.’ Nor do formations think, ‘We are produced by
                        ignorance,’ and so on. Finally, birth does not think, ‘I produce aging and death.’ Nor do aging and death
                        think, ‘I am produced by birth.’ Nevertheless, <ref cRef="F.119.a"/> formations take form and arise
                        through the existence of ignorance and so on, until finally aging and death take form and arise through
                        the existence of birth. </p>
                    <p tid="35">“Thus is the causal relation in inner dependent arising to be seen. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-52"/>
                    <p tid="36">“How is the conditional relation in inner dependent arising to be seen? As due to the coming
                        together of six elements. As due to the coming together of what six elements? Namely, the conditional
                        relation in inner dependent arising is to be seen as due to the coming together of the elements of earth,
                        water, fire, wind, space, and consciousness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-53"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Here, what is the earth element in inner dependent arising? That which assembles to form the
                        solidity of the body is called the earth element. That which provides cohesion in the body is called the
                        water element. That which digests whatever the body eats, drinks, chews, and tastes is called the fire
                        element. That which performs the function of the body’s inhalation and exhalation is called the wind
                        element. That which allows the body to have hollow spaces inside is called the space element. That which
                        produces the sprouts<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-54">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">myu gu</foreign>. This term is missing from the available
                            Sanskrit materials (Reat, p. 47 n16).</note> of name and form like reeds in a sheaf—the combination of
                        the five collections of consciousness, together with the defiled mental consciousness—is called the
                        consciousness element. Without these conditions the body cannot be born. But when the inner earth element
                        is not deficient, and likewise the elements of water, fire, wind, space, and consciousness are not
                        deficient, then from the coming together of all these factors, the body forms.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-55"/>
                    <p tid="38">“In this process, the earth element does not think, ‘I provide the solidity of the body by
                        assembling.’ Nor does the water element think, ‘I provide cohesion for the body.’ Nor does the fire
                        element think, ‘I digest whatever the body eats, drinks, chews, or tastes.’ <ref cRef="F.119.b"/> Nor does
                        the wind element think, ‘I perform the function of the body’s inhalation and exhalation.’ Nor does the
                        space element think, ‘I create hollow spaces inside the body.’ Nor does the element of consciousness
                        think, ‘I produce the name and form of the body.’ Nor does the body think, ‘I am produced by these
                        conditions.’ Yet, when these conditions are present, the body is born.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-56"/>
                    <p tid="39">“The earth element is not a self, not a being, not a life force, not a creature, not a human, not
                        a person, not female, not male, not neuter, not me, not mine, and not anybody else’s.</p>
                    <p tid="40">“Similarly, the water element, the fire element, the wind element, the space element, and the
                        consciousness element are also not a self, not a being, not a life force, not a creature, not a human, not
                        a person, not female, not male, not neuter, not me, not mine, and not anybody else’s.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-57"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Here, what is <distinct>ignorance</distinct>? That which perceives these same six elements to be
                        unitary, whole, permanent, constant, eternal, pleasurable, a self, a being, a life force, a creature, a
                            soul,<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-58"> The Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gso ba</foreign>, literally “nourishment,” but here translated as “soul,” is not found
                            in the Sanskrit sources (Reat, p. 50). Also compare with Schoening (vol. 1, p. 296 n2). Generally,
                            however, the list of items in the Tibetan translation featuring <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gso ba</foreign> appears in several Sanskrit Buddhist texts. Sastri (p. 9 n45) refers to such an
                            occurrence in Prajñākaramati's <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title> (where it
                            is, however, marked as a quote from a Prajnāpāramitā text) and inserts <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">poṣa</foreign> based on that. De La Vallée Poussin (p. 79) also inserts <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">poṣa</foreign>, but does not reference a source. Edgerton, under his
                            entry for <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">poṣa</foreign> (which he defines as, “<term type="ignore">person</term>, individuality, soul, spirit”), mentions <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gso ba</foreign> as a common Tibetan rendering. He surmises that the Tibetan
                            translation comes from the notion that the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">poṣa</foreign> derives from <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">puṣ</foreign>, “to thrive,
                            nourish,” when it more likely derives from <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">puruṣa</foreign>.
                        </note> a man, an individual, a human, a person, me, and mine, along with the many other such variations
                        of misapprehension, is called <distinct>ignorance</distinct>. The presence of such ignorance brings
                        desire, aversion, and delusion toward objects. Such desire, aversion, and delusion toward objects are the
                            <distinct>formations</distinct> caused by ignorance. <ref cRef="F.120.a"/> That which distinguishes
                        between individual objects is <distinct>consciousness</distinct>. The four aggregates for appropriation
                        that emerge in conjunction with consciousness, [along with the aggregate of material form], are
                            <distinct>name and form</distinct>.<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-59"> In all
                            the Śālistamba sources that are not from the Kangyur, i.e. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra­pañjikā</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhāmatī</title> (cf. Reat, pp. 49–50), the passage on name and form is more
                            explicit; in all of these sources an additional passage clarifies that “name and form” includes all
                            five aggregates: the four immaterial aggregates that emerge together with consciousness are subsumed
                            under “name,” while physical form is subsumed under the aggregate of “form.” This point is also
                            clarified later in the sūtra. </note> The faculties based on name and form are the <distinct>six sense
                            sources</distinct>. The conjunction of the three factors<note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-60"> The “three factors” here, in which “factor” renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>), are object, sense faculty, and consciousness (Reat, p. 52 n19). </note> is
                            <distinct>contact</distinct>. The experience of contact is <distinct>sensation</distinct>. Attachment
                        to sensation is <distinct>craving</distinct>. The intensification of craving is
                            <distinct>appropriation</distinct>. Action that comes from appropriation and causes rebirth is
                            <distinct>becoming</distinct>. The emergence of the aggregates from such a cause is
                            <distinct>birth</distinct>. The maturation of the aggregates after birth is
                        <distinct>aging</distinct>. The perishing of the decrepit aggregates is <distinct>death</distinct>. The
                        inner torment of the deluded, attached, dying person is <distinct>sorrow</distinct>. The utterance that
                        comes from sorrow is <distinct>lamentation</distinct>. The experience of discomfort associated with the
                        collection of the five consciousnesses is <distinct>suffering</distinct>. The mental suffering accompanied
                        by attention<note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-61"> The Tibetan here, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yid la byed pa dang ldan pa</foreign>, reflects a rendering of the
                            Sanskrit phrase <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">manasi­kāra­yukta</foreign>, partially attested
                            in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāyāna­sūtra­saṁgraha</title> as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">manasi­kāra­saṁprayukta</foreign> (Reat, p. 52 n32). </note> is <distinct>despair</distinct>.
                        Moreover, any other subtle defilements of this kind are called <distinct>anxiety</distinct>.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-62"/>
                    <p tid="42">“They are called <distinct>ignorance</distinct> in the sense of obscuring,
                            <distinct>formations</distinct> in the sense of forming, <distinct>consciousness</distinct> in the
                        sense of causing to know, <distinct>name and form</distinct> in the sense of mutual support,<note place="end" index="25" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-63"> Sanskrit sources read <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">anyo anyopa­stambhana</foreign>, here appearing in the Tibetan translation as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rten pa</foreign> / <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">brten
                                pa</foreign>. </note> the six sense sources in the sense of entryways,<note place="end" index="26" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-64"> The Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āyadvāra</foreign>
                            (Reat, p. 53) here includes the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āya</foreign> part of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āyatana</foreign>, and is defined by Edgerton as “cause or means
                            (lit. door) of arrival or origin.” The Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">skye ba’i
                                sgo</foreign> gives the sense of “door of arising.” </note>
                        <distinct>contact</distinct> in the sense of contact, <distinct>sensation</distinct> in the sense of
                        experience, <distinct>craving</distinct> in the sense of thirst, <distinct>appropriation</distinct> in the
                        sense of appropriating, <distinct>becoming</distinct> in the sense of giving birth to repeated becoming,
                            <distinct>birth</distinct> in the sense of the emergence of the aggregates, <distinct>aging</distinct>
                        in the sense of the maturation of the aggregates, <distinct>death</distinct> in the sense of perishing,
                            <distinct>sorrow</distinct> in the sense of grieving, <distinct>lamentation</distinct> in the sense of
                        wailing, <distinct>suffering</distinct> in the sense of bodily torment, <distinct>despair</distinct> in
                        the sense of mental torment, and <distinct>anxiety</distinct> in the sense of subtle defilement.<note place="end" index="27" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-65"> The Sanskrit reads <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upakleśa</foreign> here (Reat, p. 53), whereas the Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nyon mongs</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kleśa</foreign>). However, since <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">nye ba’i nyon
                                mongs</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upakleśa</foreign>) appears in the
                            previous discussion of “anxiety,” we have opted for the Sanskrit. </note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="43">“Furthermore, not knowing reality, in the sense of not apprehending it and misapprehending it, is
                        ignorance.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-66"/>
                    <p tid="44">“If such an ignorance is present, three types of formations develop: those that lead to
                        meritorious states, those that lead to unmeritorious states, and those that lead to immovable states. This
                        is what is meant by ‘ignorance causes formations.’ <ref cRef="F.120.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-67"/>
                    <p tid="45">“From formations that lead to meritorious states comes consciousness that leads to meritorious
                        states. From formations that lead to unmeritorious states comes consciousness that leads to unmeritorious
                        states. And from formations that lead to immovable states comes consciousness that leads to immovable
                        states. This is what is meant by ‘formations cause consciousness.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-68"/>
                    <p tid="46">“The four immaterial aggregates emerging together with consciousness, along with physical form, is
                        what is meant by ‘consciousness causes name and form.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-69"/>
                    <p tid="47">“Due to the development of name and form, the performance of actions through the entryways of the
                        six sense sources occurs. This is what is meant by ‘name and form cause the six sense sources.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-70"/>
                    <p tid="48">“From the six sense sources arise the six collections of contact. This is what is meant by ‘the
                        six sense sources cause contact.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-71"/>
                    <p tid="49">“Sensations occur precisely according to the type of contact that occurs. This is what is meant by
                        ‘contact causes sensation.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-72"/>
                    <p tid="50">“Relishing those different kinds of sensations, taking delight in them, clinging to them, and
                        having that clinging remain is what is meant by ‘sensation causes craving.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-73"/>
                    <p tid="51">“From relishing, taking delight, clinging, and having that clinging remain comes an unwillingness
                        to let go, with the repeated wish: ‘May I never part from these dear and delightful forms!’<note place="end" index="28" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-74">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Ngo bo</foreign> here in the Tibetan phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdug pa’i ngo bo dang</foreign>/ <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bde ba’i ngo bo</foreign> is a conceivable rendering of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">rūpa</foreign>, “form” (Negi, vol. 3, p. 977), in the corresponding Sanskrit phrase
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">priya­rūpa­śāta­rūpa</foreign> (Reat, p. 55). </note> This
                        is what is meant by ‘craving causes appropriation.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-75"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Such wishing gives rise to rebirth-producing actions by means of body, speech, and mind. This is
                        what is meant by ‘appropriation causes becoming.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-76"/>
                    <p tid="53">“The formation of the five<note place="end" index="29" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-77"> Khu is missing
                            “five” here; this is reflected in the Sanskrit (Reat, pp. 54–55).</note> aggregates born from such
                        actions is what is meant by ‘becoming causes birth.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-78"/>
                    <p tid="54">“The maturation of the development of the aggregates formed from birth, and their disintegration,
                        is what is meant by ‘birth causes aging and death.’</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-79"/>
                    <p tid="55">“Thus, this twelvefold dependent arising<note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-80">
                            The Sanskrit resources depict this phrase in the masculine singular nominitive <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvādaśāṅgaḥ pratītya­samutpādo</foreign>; all the qualifyiers in the
                            passage follow suit.</note>—which comes from several different causes and from several different
                        conditions, is neither permanent nor impermanent, <ref cRef="F.121.a"/> is neither compounded nor
                        uncompounded, is not without any cause or condition, is not an experiencer,<note place="end" index="31" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-81"> This is following Reat (p. 57), with <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vedayitā</foreign> (masculine singular nominitive of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vedayitṛ</foreign>), and Kamalaśīla’s commentary (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 509), with
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">myong ba po</foreign>. </note> and is not something<note place="end" index="32" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-82"> “Something” here (and in the following two
                            instances) renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>). </note> exhaustible, something destructible, or something that
                        ceases—has proceeded from time immemorial, without interruption, like the flow of a river.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-83"/>
                    <p tid="56">“This twelvefold dependent arising—which comes from several different causes and from several
                        different conditions, is neither permanent nor impermanent, is neither compounded nor uncompounded, is not
                        without any cause or condition, is not an experiencer, and is not something<note place="end" index="33" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-84"> “Something” here, again (and in the following two instances), renders
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharma</foreign>). </note> exhaustible, something destructible, or something that ceases—has
                        indeed proceeded from time immemorial, without interruption, like the flow of a river. Nevertheless, there
                        are four links that serve as the cause for assembling this twelvefold dependent arising. What four links?
                        Namely, ignorance, craving, karma, and consciousness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-85"/>
                    <p tid="57">“Consciousness functions as a cause by having the nature of a seed. Karma functions as a cause by
                        having the nature of a field. Ignorance and craving function as causes by having the nature of
                        afflictions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-86"/>
                    <p tid="58">“Karma and afflictions cause the seed of consciousness to grow. Here, karma functions as the field
                        for the seed of consciousness. Craving moistens the seed of consciousness. Ignorance sows the seed of
                        consciousness. Without these conditions, the seed of consciousness does not develop.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-87"/>
                    <p tid="59">“In this process, karma does not think, ‘I function as the field for the seed of consciousness.’
                        Nor does craving think, ‘I moisten the seed of consciousness.’ Nor does ignorance think, ‘I sow the seed
                        of consciousness.’ Nor does the seed of consciousness think, ‘I am produced by these conditions.’ Yet when
                        the seed of consciousness grows, planted in the field of karma, moistened by the water of craving, and
                        strewn with the manure of ignorance, <ref cRef="F.121.b"/> the sprout of name and form manifests within
                        whichever mother’s womb one will take rebirth through. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-88"/>
                    <p tid="60">“And this sprout of name and form is not created by itself, not created by another, not created by
                        both, not created by Īśvara, not transformed by time, not derived from <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prakṛti</foreign>, not dependent on a single factor, and not born without any cause.
                        Nonetheless, from the combination of the union of the parents, the period of ovulation, and other
                        conditions, the seed of consciousness, filled with appetite,<note place="end" index="34" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-89"> Although the Tibetan here has the rather ambiguous <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">myong ba dang ldan pa</foreign>, the available Sanskrit reads
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">āsvāda-anuviddhaṁ</foreign> (Reat, p. 60). </note>
                        produces the sprout of name and form within whichever mother’s womb one will take rebirth through. For
                        although things<note place="end" index="35" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-90"> “Things” here renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos rnams</foreign> (dharma). </note> are devoid of owner, devoid
                        of ownership, ungraspable, space-like, and their nature is the mark of illusion, there is no deficiency of
                        requisite causes and conditions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-91"/>
                    <p tid="61">“For instance, the eye consciousness arises by way of five principles. What five principles? Namely, the eye
                        consciousness arises based on the eye on which it depends, form, light, space, and the appropriate
                        attention. Here, the eye functions as the basis for the eye consciousness. Form functions as the object of
                        perception for the eye consciousness. Light functions as visibility. Space functions by not obstructing.
                        Appropriate attention functions as mental reflection. Without these conditions, the eye consciousness
                        cannot arise. But when the inner <term>sense source</term>, the eye, is not deficient, and likewise, when
                        form, light, space, and appropriate attention are not deficient, then from the coming together of all
                        these factors, the eye consciousness arises.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-92"/>
                    <p tid="62">“The eye does not think, ‘I serve as the basis for the eye consciousness.’ Nor does form think, ‘I
                        serve as the object of perception for the eye consciousness.’ Nor does light think, ‘I function as the
                        visibility for the eye consciousness.’ Nor does space think, ‘I do not obstruct the eye consciousness.’
                        Nor does appropriate attention think, <ref cRef="F.122.a"/> ‘I provide mental reflection for the eye
                        consciousness.’ Nor does the eye consciousness think, ‘I am produced by these conditions.’ Yet, the eye
                        consciousness is born from the presence of these conditions. Similarly, a corresponding analysis should be
                        applied to the rest of the faculties.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-93"/>
                    <p tid="63">“Here, there is nothing<note place="end" index="36" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-94"> “Thing” here in
                            “nothing” renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (dharma). </note> whatsoever
                        that transmigrates from this existence to the next. And yet, because there is no deficiency of requisite
                        causes and conditions, the result of karma nonetheless manifests. It is like the appearance of the
                        reflection of a face on the surface of a well-polished mirror. The face has not shifted onto the surface
                        of the mirror, but because there is no deficiency of requisite causes and conditions, the face nonetheless
                        appears there. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-95"/>
                    <p tid="64">“Similarly, there is nobody at all who transmigrates from here after death and is born elsewhere.
                        And yet, because there is no deficiency of requisite causes and conditions, the result of karma
                        nonetheless manifests. It is like how the orb of the moon travels at a distance of forty-two thousand
                        yojanas above earth, and yet its reflection nonetheless appears in small vessels filled with water. It is
                        not that the moon moves from its position and enters the small vessels filled with water. Yet, because
                        there is no deficiency of requisite causes and conditions, the orb of the moon nonetheless appears
                        there.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-96"/>
                    <p tid="65">“Likewise, that there is nobody at all who transmigrates from here after death and is born
                        elsewhere, and yet, because there is no deficiency of requisite causes and conditions, the result of karma
                        nonetheless manifests, is like how a fire ignites from the assemblage of its requisite causes and
                        conditions, and not when deficient of its requisite causes and conditions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-97"/>
                    <p tid="66">“In the same way, although things<note place="end" index="37" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-98"> “Thing”
                            here renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">chos</foreign> (dharma).</note> are devoid of
                        owner, devoid of ownership, ungraspable, space-like, and their nature is the mark of illusion, because
                        there is no deficiency of requisite causes and conditions, the seed of consciousness born of karma and
                        afflictions will nonetheless produce the sprout of name and form within whichever mother’s womb one will
                        take rebirth through. </p>
                    <p tid="67">“Thus is the conditional relation in inner dependent arising to be seen.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-99"/>
                    <p tid="68">“Here, inner dependent arising is to be seen in terms of five aspects. What five aspects? <ref cRef="F.122.b"/> As not permanent, as not discontinuous, as not involving transmigration, as the
                        production of a large result from a small cause, and as a continuity of similar type.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-100"/>
                    <p tid="69">“How is it not permanent? It is not permanent because the final aggregates at death are one thing
                        and those at birth are another; that is, the final aggregates at death are not the ones at birth. And yet,
                        only when the final aggregates at death cease do the aggregates at birth arise. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-101"/>
                    <p tid="70">“How is it not discontinuous? It is not discontinuous because the aggregates at birth do not arise
                        from the final aggregates at death either when they have already ceased, or when they have not yet ceased.
                        Like the beam of a scale tilting from up to down, the aggregates at birth arise precisely when the final
                        aggregates at death have ceased. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-102"/>
                    <p tid="71">“How does it not involve transmigration? It does not involve transmigration because beings from
                        different classes of existence bring about their rebirth in a common form of birth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-103"/>
                    <p tid="72">“How does it entail the production of a large result from a small cause? The ripening of a large
                        result is experienced from having performed a minor action. Thus, it entails the production of a large
                        result from a small cause. </p>
                    <p tid="73">“It involves a continuity of similar type because the ripening of an action is experienced
                        precisely according to the action performed. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-104"/>
                    <p tid="74">“Venerable Śāriputra, whoever sees with perfect wisdom this dependent arising, perfectly taught by
                        the Bhagavān, as it actually is—as always and forever<note place="end" index="38" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-105"> Kamalaśīla’s commentary (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 517) interprets the
                            Tibetan phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rtag par rgyun du</foreign> not to modify the
                            adjacent <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srog med pa</foreign>, as suggested by the available
                            Sanskrit and Tibetan, but as the “constant and uninterrupted” quality of dependent arising itself.
                        </note> without life force, devoid of life force, true, unmistaken, unborn, not arisen, uncreated,
                        uncompounded, unobstructed, imperceptible, tranquil, fearless, incontrovertible, inexhaustible, and by
                        nature never stilled—whoever fully and truly sees it as unreal, vain, hollow, unsubstantial, as a
                        sickness, <ref cRef="F.123.a"/> a boil, a thorn, as miserable, impermanent, painful, empty, and self-less,
                        such a person does not reflect on the past thinking, ‘Did I exist in the past, or not? What was I in the
                        past? How was I in the past?’ Nor does such a person reflect on the future thinking, ‘Will I exist in the
                        future, or not? What will I be in the future? How will I be in the future?’ Nor does such a person reflect
                        on the present thinking, ‘What is this? How is this? <term type="ignore">Being</term> what, what will we
                        become? Where does this being<note place="end" index="39" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-106"> The singular
                            number here is according to the Sanskrit and Tibetan of the Stok Palace version; the Degé and other
                            versions recorded in the Pedurma comparative edition all read plural <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’di dag</foreign>.</note> come from? Where will it go when transmigrating from here at
                        death?’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-107"/>
                    <p tid="75">“Whichever dogmas mendicants and brahmins hold throughout the world, whether they involve belief
                        in a self, belief in a being, belief in a life force, belief in a person, or belief in ceremonies and
                            festivities,<note place="end" index="40" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-108"> This renders <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dge mtshan dang bkra shis</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kautukamaṇgala</foreign>). Reat (p. 72) translates this as, “rites and rituals”;
                            Schoening (vol. 1, p. 329) translates it as, “festive and salutary.” Monier-Williams understands the
                            term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kautukamaṇgala</foreign> not as a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dvandva</foreign> compound, but as “an auspicious ceremony (esp. the
                            ceremony with the marriage-thread preceding a marriage).” Kamalaśīla (Schoening, vol. 2, p. 520)
                            presents only the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dge mtshan dang ldan pa</foreign>,
                            “endowed with <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kautuku</foreign> (‘interest or curiosity’),”
                            which he interprets as follows: “This refers to things like riddles, tales, legends, song, dance and
                            the like that bring one enjoyment, because one becomes infatuated.” </note> such dogmas, prone to
                        agitation and dullness,<note place="end" index="41" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-109"> The passage, “prone to
                            agitation or dullness,” is missing in the available Sanskrit sources and has been reconstructed from
                            the Tibetan by de La Vallée Poussin and Sastri as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vā
                                unmiñjita­nimiñjitāni</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">unmiñjitāni
                                nimiñjitāni ca</foreign>, respectively (Reat, p. 72). However, Kamalaśīla seems to have had a
                            version similar to the Tibetan, since he states in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title> (p.
                            422): “ ‘Agitation or dullness’ means the mind is either distracted or withdrawn. These are features
                            of dogma.” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">lhag par g.yo ba dang bral bar g.yo ba zhes bya ba
                                ni/ sems rgyas pa dang zhum par gyur pa ste/ de dag ni lta bar song ba’i bye brag
                            go/</foreign>).</note> are all abandoned at that time. Fully understood as false, these dogmas are
                        severed at the root and wither like the head of a palm tree,<note place="end" index="42" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-110"> Unlike other trees, the palm tree does not produce cambium—the layer
                            that closes a wound and protects the trunk from rotting. As a result a palm tree dies when its head is
                            cut off. </note> never to arise or cease in the future. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-111"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Venerable Śāriputra, whoever is endowed with such acceptance of the Dharma and thus perfectly
                        understands dependent arising is prophesied for unexcelled, perfect, and complete awakening by the
                        Tathāgata, the Arhat, the perfectly and completely awakened one, the one with perfect knowledge and
                        conduct, the Sugata, the knower of the world, the incomparable charioteer of those who need taming, the
                        teacher of gods and humans, the Bhagavān, the Buddha, in this way: ‘Such a person will become a perfect
                        and complete buddha!’ ”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-112"/>
                    <p tid="77">After the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya had thus spoken, venerable Śāriputra, together with the
                        world of gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas, <ref cRef="F.123.b"/> rejoiced and praised what the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya had taught. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-113"/>
                    <p tid="78">This concludes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra, The Rice Seedling.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="85">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="86">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="87">Tibetan Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-114">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu’i ljang pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh 210,
                        Degé Kangyur, vol. 62 (mdo sde, tsha), folios 116a–123b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-115">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu’i ljang pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok 191,
                        Stok Palace Kangyur (stog pho brang bris ma), vol. 72 (mdo sde, zha), folios 282r–292r. Leh: sman rtsis
                        shes rig dpe mdzod, 1975–1980.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-116">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu’i ljang pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Pedurma Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi
                        bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research
                        Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006–2009, vol. 62, pp. 314–335.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-117">Kamalaśīla. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu’i ljang pa rgya cher
                            ’grel pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śālistamba</title>[<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ka</title>]<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭīkā</title>). bstan ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of
                        the Tengyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 120 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod
                        rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 1994–2008, vol. 67, pp. 380–426.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-118">Nāgārjuna. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu’i ljang pa zhes bya ba
                            theg pa chen po’i mdo’i rgya cher bshad pa</title>. (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāli­stambaka­ṭīkā</title>). bstan ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Tengyur], krung
                        go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau
                        of the China Tibetology Research Center). 120 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang
                        (China Tibetology Publishing House), 1994–2008, vol. 65, pp. 783–881.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-119">____ <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sā lu ljang pa’i tshig le’ur byas
                            pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāli­stambaka­kārikā</title>). Ibid. pp. 774–782.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="88">Sanskrit and Western Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-126">de la Vallée Poussin, Louis. <title xml:lang="fr">Théorie des douze causes:
                            Bouddhisme, études et matériaux</title>. Gand: Van Goethem, 1913.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-127">Gokhale, Vasudev. “Madhyamaka-śālistamba-sūtram”, in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāyāna-sūtra-saṁgraha</title>, ed. by Paraśurāma Lakṣmaṇa Vaidya, Vol. 1.
                        Darbhanga: Mithila Institute of Post-graduate Studies and Research in Sanskrit Learning, 1961,
                        107–116.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-128">Harrison, Paul. “Is the Dharma-kāya the Real ‘Phantom Body’ of the Buddha?”
                        in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title> 1992, vol.
                        15.1: 44–94. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-129">Martin, Dan. <title xml:lang="en">Tibskrit Philology: A Bio-Bibliographical
                            Resource Work</title>. Edited by Alexander Cherniak. Tibskrit Philology: April 21, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-130">Reat, N. Ross. <title xml:lang="en">The Śālistamba Sūtra: Tibetan Original,
                            Sanskrit Reconstruction, English Translation, Critical Notes</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass
                        Publishers Private Limited, 1993.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-131">Sastri, N. Ayaswami. <title xml:lang="en">Ārya-śālistamba-sūtra: With
                            Tibetan Versions, Notes and Introduction</title>. Adyar, Madras: Adyar Library, 1950.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-062-010-132">Schoening, Jeffrey D. <title xml:lang="en">The Śālistamba Sūtra and its
                            Indian Commentaries</title>. 2 volumes. Wien: Arbeitskreis für Tibetische und Buddhistische Studien
                        Universität Wien, 1995.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-133">
                            <term>dependent arising</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rten cing ’brel bar ’byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟེན་ཅིང་འབྲེལ་བར་འབྱུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratītya­samutpāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The central Buddhist doctrine that teaches how things are empty of self-nature
                                and thus lack independent existence, yet exist provisionally insofar as they are created through
                                the interaction of various causal <term type="ignore">factors</term>.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">interdependent origination</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-134">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                            <term type="alternative">demi-god</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-135">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-136">
                            <term>body of Dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmaśarīra</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Dharma body, Truth body</term>
                            <term type="definition">See <ptr target="#UT22084-062-010-23"/>.</term>
                          </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-137">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of ethereal beings, living on scents.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">scent-eater</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-138">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Thus-gone one, the Thus-gone</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-139">
                            <term>being</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyes bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེས་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puruṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-140">
                            <term>person</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang zag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་ཟག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pudgala</term>
                            <term type="alternative">individual</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-141">
                            <term>prakṛti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang bzhin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་བཞིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prakṛti</term>
                            <term type="definition">“According to Sāṁkhya, the prime substance, from which the material universe
                                evolves, as opposed to <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">puruṣa</foreign>, pure
                                consciousness.” (Reat, 39 n5).</term>
                            <term type="alternative">primal matter </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-142">
                            <term>neuter</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ning </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ནིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">napuṃsakam</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Tibetan term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma ning</foreign> is
                                broader than any existing English term and refers not only to those whose sexual characteristics
                                are not clearly defined as male or female (intersexual), but also to those who do not have any
                                proper gender organs, those who may have both, and those who are <term type="ignore">neuter</term>, infertile, or who simply
                                have physical or non-physical characteristics of a <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma
                                    ning</foreign>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-143">
                            <term>yojana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpag tshad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔག་ཚད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A measure of distance, often translated with “league.” The exact value is
                                disputed and varies in different sources from 1 to 40km.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-144">
                            <term>sugata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde bar gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བར་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sugata</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the buddhas, meaning “the blissfully gone one” or “the well gone one.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-145">
                            <term>ignorance</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma rig ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་རིག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avidyā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-146">
                            <term>formation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’du byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṁskāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-147">
                            <term>consciousness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vijñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-148">
                            <term>name and form</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ming dang gzugs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིང་དང་གཟུགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāmarūpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-149">
                            <term>six sense sources</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣadāyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The six sense organs of eyes, ears, nose, tongue, tactile sense, and mind,
                                together with their respective objects of forms, sounds, smells, flavors, tactile objects, and
                                mental objects. See also “<term>sense source</term>.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-167" mode="marked">
                            <term>sense source</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The six “inner” sense organs (eyes, ears, nose, tongue, tactile sense, and
                                mind), and their respective six “outer” objects of forms, sounds, smells, flavors, tactile
                                objects, and mental objects, are sometimes called collectively the “six sense sources” (q.v.), but
                                are also sometimes taken as two separate groups, making twelve.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-150">
                            <term>contact</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">reg pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རེག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sparśa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-151">
                            <term>sensation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshor ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚོར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vedanā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-152">
                            <term>craving</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sred pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲེད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tṛṣṇā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-153">
                            <term>appropriation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">len pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar len pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-154">
                            <term>becoming</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srid pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhava</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-155">
                            <term>birth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jāti</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-156">
                            <term>aging and death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rga shi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒ་ཤི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jarāmaraṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-168">
                            <term>collection</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚོགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">In the context of the psychophysical constituents, refers to the combination
                                of individual sense-consciousnesses related to the five senses, and that of the mind, making five
                                or six constituents depending on the context (and in some texts more) that collectively constitute
                                “consciousness.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-157">
                            <term>dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term has multiple interrelated meanings. In this text, the primary
                                meanings are as follows: (1) the doctrine taught by the Buddha (<term type="ignore">Dharma</term>); (2) the ultimate reality
                                underlying and expressed through the Buddha’s teaching (<term type="ignore">Dharma</term>); (3) the trainings that the
                                Buddha’s teaching stipulates (<term type="ignore">dharmas</term>); (4) the various awakened qualities or attainments acquired
                                through practicing and realizing the Buddha’s teaching (<term type="ignore">dharmas</term>); (5) qualities or aspects more
                                generally, i.e., phenomena or phenomenal attributes (<term type="ignore">dharmas</term>); and (6) mental objects
                                (<term type="ignore">dharmas</term>).</term>
                            <term type="alternative">things</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-169">
                            <term>factor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “dharma.”</term>
                            <term type="alternative">things</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-158">
                            <term>aggregates for appropriation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar len pa’i phung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་ལེན་པའི་ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upādānaskandha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Said of the aggregates individually, but more commonly in terms of all five as
                                a collective, because they are “the basis of clinging to existence”  (Edgerton).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-159">
                            <term>that which leads to meritorious states</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams su nye bar ’gro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསོད་ནམས་སུ་ཉེ་བར་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puṇyopaga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Of formations and modes of consciousness that lead to rebirth in pleasant
                                states within the desire realm.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that leads to meritorious states</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that lead to meritorious states</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-160">
                            <term>that which leads to unmeritorious states</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsod nams ma yin par nye bar ’gro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསོད་ནམས་མ་ཡིན་པར་ཉེ་བར་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apuṇyopaga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Of formations and modes of consciousness that lead to rebirth in the three
                                lower realms of animals, hungry ghosts, and hell beings.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that leads to unmeritorious states</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that lead to unmeritorious states</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-161">
                            <term>that which leads to immovable states</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi g.yo bar nye bar ’gro ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་གཡོ་བར་ཉེ་བར་འགྲོ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āneñjyopaga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aneñjopaga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aniñjyopaga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āniñjyopaga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Of formations and modes of consciousness that lead to rebirth in the form and
                                formless realms.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that leads to immovable states</term>
                            <term type="alternative">that lead to immovable states</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-162">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a bodhisattva, believed to be the future buddha after Śākyamuni, the
                                fifth buddha of this eon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-163">
                            <term>Śāriputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shA ri’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāriputra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Along with Maudgalyāyana, <term type="ignore">Śāriputra</term> was one of the two main disciples of the
                                Buddha. Known as a great arhat, he requested some important teachings such as the Prajnāpāramitā
                                sūtras, and is particularly famous for his discriminating insight (prajñā).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-164">
                            <term>Īśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">īśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “lord,” this term is an epithet for the god Śiva, but functions more
                                generally in Buddhist texts as a generalized “supreme being” to whom the creation of the universe
                                is attributed.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-165">
                            <term>Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rājagṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Situated in the modern Indian state of Bihar, <term type="ignore">Rājagṛha</term> was the capital of
                                Magadha, one of the great kingdoms of ancient India.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-062-010-166">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gṛdhrakūṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A mountain situated in the vicinity of Rājagṛha where the Prajnāpāramitā
                                sūtras were taught and which continues to be a sacred pilgrimage site for Buddhists to this
                                day.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>