<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi phung po</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmaskandha</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་ཕུང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi phung po zhes bya ba
                    theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled: The Sections of Dharma</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryadharmaskandhanāmamahāyānasūtra</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
            <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-206">Professor José Cabezón</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-62">Chloé Cramer</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-60">Ben Ewing</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-67">Lowell Cook</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-72">Oriane Lavole</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-61">Catherine Dalton</consultant>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-206">José I.Cabezón</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-257">Raynald Prévèreau</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-108">André Rodrigues</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.00 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-066-003"/>
                <date>2018-12-28</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh245" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 245</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios
                        27b.5–33a.1</biblScope>
                    <location count-pages="12">
                        <start volume="66" page="56"/>
                        <end volume="66" page="67"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11895" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-13T18:12:20.73Z" user="celso">13/03/2019 18:12:20</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-1"/>
                <p tid="2">In this sūtra some of Buddha Śākyamuni’s senior disciples request a teaching on
                    the nature of <emph>the sections of Dharma</emph>. The Buddha responds by first
                    delivering a teaching on the absence of birth with regard to phenomena as an
                    antidote to the poison of desire. On that basis, the Buddha then presents a
                    longer explanation of the repulsiveness of the human body, and the female body,
                    in particular.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of
                    Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Chloé Cramer, Ben Ewing,
                    Lowell Cook, and Oriane Lavole under the supervision of Catherine Dalton. The
                    translation was then checked against the Tibetan and edited by Andreas Doctor.
                    The translation also benefitted from the contribution of Professor José Cabezón,
                    who generously shared his draft translation of the sūtra with the translators
                    and offered many helpful comments.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-3"/>
                    <p tid="6">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title> sūtra has a long history
                        as part of the Tibetan Buddhist canon. It was among the first texts brought
                        from India to Tibet during the Imperial period (seventh to ninth century)
                        where it was translated by the prolific Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé alongside
                        the Indian scholar Prajñāvarman. Since it appears in both available Imperial
                        catalogues, which are the earliest records of Tibetan scriptural
                            translations,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-4" index="1"> It appears as text no. 193 in
                            the Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ldan dkar
                                ma</foreign>) catalogue and as no. 272 in the Phangthangma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’phang thang ma</foreign>)
                            catalogue. See Halkias (2004), p. 66 and Yoshimura (1950), p. 195.e.
                        </note> its existence in Tibetan translation can be posited as no later than
                        824 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-5" index="2"> The date of
                            the earliest Imperial catalogue, the Denkarma, is debated, but this is
                            the later of the two dates most commonly attributed among scholars, the
                            other being 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> . See Halkias (2004), p.
                            3. </note> Unfortunately, no version of the text is to our knowledge
                        extant in Sanskrit or any other language besides Tibetan (and Mongolian,
                        into which it was translated from the Tibetan), nor does it have any known
                        commentaries. This greatly limits our knowledge of its precise origins and
                        context. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The title of the sūtra refers to the sections of teachings given by the
                        Buddha, which are traditionally said to number 84,000. The sūtra begins with
                        an inquiry by Śāriputra about the nature and number of the sections of the
                        Dharma, to which the Buddha answers with a teaching on the absence of birth
                        with regard to phenomena—a teaching that serves as an antidote to the poison
                        of desire. The beginning of the sūtra thus situates the text explicitly in a
                        Mahāyāna context as it introduces the notion that phenomena do not appear or
                        cease. Indeed, in the manner of the teachings of the second turning,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-7" index="3"> According to later Indian (and even later,
                            Tibetan) doxography that first finds clear expression in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṃdhinirmocanasūtra</title>, the Dharma taught
                            by the Buddha can be classified into three distinct doctrinal groupings
                            called the <distinct>three wheels of doctrine</distinct>. According to
                            this schema, the second wheel focuses primarily on the emptiness of
                            phenomena. </note> the text deconstructs the reality and identity of
                        objects of desire, thereby demonstrating that desires are mere fantasies
                        based on imaginary objects and are not to be indulged in by the wise. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-8"/>
                    <p tid="8">This second-turning introduction to the problem of desire however leads to an
                        extensive discussion of a topic that, due to its emphasis on the elimination
                        of desire as such, would generally be considered a first-turning
                            teaching;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-9" index="4"> The first turning refers mainly to
                            the four noble truths, as well as teachings on the five aggregates.
                            Mahāyāna exegetes considered these to be teachings of the hearers, and
                            therefore classified them as teachings of provisional, as opposed to
                            definitive, meaning. See Powers (2013), p. 103. </note> namely, the
                        repulsiveness of the human body—and the female body, in particular. In its
                        presentation of the female constitution, the sūtra in fact disparages women
                        in a way that most modern readers would find offensive—José Cabezón has
                        aptly described the sūtra as “one of the most misogynistic texts in the
                        Buddhist canon.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-10" index="5">Cabezón (2017), p. 125, no.
                            328.</note> Nonetheless, recent research has shown that the repulsive
                        nature of the female body was in fact a common theme in early Mahāyāna
                        texts. In their studies of texts dating to the beginning of the common era,
                        Ulrich Pagel (1995), Jan Nattier (2003), and Daniel Boucher (2008) have
                        argued that one major strand of early Mahāyāna involved male monastics eager
                        to engage in demanding ascetic practices. The deprecatory descriptions of
                        the repulsiveness of women’s bodies that form the main argument of <title xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title> might have served to
                        support such efforts of male monastics to attain the ideal of renunciation.
                        In this respect, Boucher and Nattier have noted how women were often
                        deprecated and represented as an obstacle to men’s practice in some early
                        Mahāyāna texts, and this very much accords with the tone of our sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-11" index="6"> Boucher (2008), pp. 50–52; Nattier (2003), pp.
                            96–100.</note> In fact, according to these scholars, early Mahāyāna
                        might even have seen a decrease in the participation of women in Buddhist
                        institutions, contrary to a popular modern understanding of the Mahāyāna as
                        a more egalitarian movement than the mainstream tradition.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-12" index="7">Nattier (2003), p. 98. </note> Nevertheless, although this
                        sūtra does in many ways seem to support this analysis, toward the end of the
                        sūtra the Buddha twice describes the intended audience as the four-fold
                        assembly of monks, nuns, laymen, and laywomen. As such, the sūtra itself
                        professes to benefit not only male monastics with its message of the
                        repulsiveness of the human (and, in particular, the female) body, but really
                        anyone, whether male or female, ordained or lay. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-13"/>
                    <p tid="9">In spite of such calls for a broad audience, this approach is likely to have
                        resonated most clearly with male monastics, as it represents a Buddhist
                        perspective that runs right from the institutional androcentrism of early
                        monastic Buddhism to the valorization of ascetic discipline in the early
                            Mahāyāna.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-14" index="8"> Boucher (2008), pp. 51–52. </note>
                        The common theme between our text and those studied by Boucher and Nattier
                        suggests that we might also locate this sūtra among the earlier strata of
                        Mahāyāna sūtras that emerged in the first centuries <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. An interesting difference between these texts, however, is
                            <title xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title>’s explicit usage of
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñāpāramitā</foreign> themes
                        in its discussion of such concepts as the absence of birth and cessation
                        with regard to phenomena; such themes are absent from the texts studied by
                        Boucher and Nattier. <title xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title>
                        therefore seems to belong to a different stream of early Mahāyāna texts, one
                        still centered on monastics, rather than lay bodhisattvas, yet
                        simultaneously inspired by <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñāpāramitā</foreign> themes. This thematic duality is also
                        reflected in the fact that the early imperial catalogues categorized this
                        scripture as a Mahāyāna sūtra, yet the translation colophon in the Stok
                        Palace Kangyur notes that it belongs to the first turning of the wheel of
                        Dharma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bka’ ’khor lo dang por gtogs
                            pa’o</foreign>). Indeed, though it does broach <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">prajñāpāramitā</foreign> concepts, the
                        sūtra is still very much set in the hearers’ monastic context, exemplified
                        by the fact that the Buddha teaches in the presence of worthy ones (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arhants</foreign>), and not
                        bodhisattvas. The sūtra’s concluding verse, which states that the Buddha did
                        not expound this teaching to spiritual practitioners, but only to those who
                        still indulged in desires, moreover suggests that the main body of the text
                        is a teaching of provisional meaning, which is meant for beginners on the
                        path and later to be superseded by more advanced teachings. Teachings of
                        provisional meaning are contextual and adapted to the spiritual capacities
                        of their audience. As such, since they do not literally expound the ultimate
                        view, they require interpretation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-15"/>
                    <p tid="10">One additional theme brought up by this sūtra deserves to be mentioned here.
                        The modern reader may indeed be surprised by several passages describing how
                        various physical and mental ailments that afflict women are caused by
                            <emph>parasites</emph> (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srin
                            bu</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">krimi/kṛmi</foreign>) that subsist in different parts of their bodies.
                        According to this sūtra, such parasites are responsible for a host of
                        (mostly undesirable) physical traits in the female physique. For example,
                        some such parasites are said to live in the urinary tracts of women, where
                        they find nourishment by eating away at their host. The parasites are
                        described to cause women to become mentally disturbed, thus making them
                        engage in uninhibited sexual activity. Other parasites are said to gnaw away
                        at women’s brains, noses, throats, etc. The sūtra apparently describes the
                        presence of these parasites in the female body to account for the unique
                        physical traits that women possess, such as their absence of facial hair,
                        bulging breasts, and smooth throats. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-16"/>
                    <p tid="11">Although the particular descriptions of the parasites that live in the female
                        body may be unique to this sūtra, the belief that parasites are the cause of
                        various unpleasant physical conditions was already a well-established theory
                        in Indian medical literature at the time of composition of this text. This
                        notion, which perhaps developed from the observation of worms in decomposing
                        corpses, was already present in the earliest Indic scripture dealing with
                        cures and healing, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atharvaveda</title>, which
                        was composed sometime between 1200–1000 <hi rend="small-caps">bce</hi>. and
                        offers descriptions of various parasites, or, technically,
                            <emph>worms</emph> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">krimi</foreign>) that invade the human body.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-17" index="9">Zysk (1993), p. 64.</note> Moreover, Jain and Kāmaśāstra literature,
                        which are closer in temporal proximity to our sūtra, both include theories
                        of vaginal worms—in the Jain texts these are said to be killed through
                        sexual intercourse, thus making sex an inherently nonvirtuous act; and in
                        the Kāmaśāstra literature they are described as the cause of a woman’s
                            <emph>itch</emph> of sexual desire.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-18" index="10">Thanks
                            to José Cabezón for bringing this to our attention. See further Cabezón
                            (2017), p. 125, no. 328.</note> As such, the sūtra offers a presentation
                        of the female physique that draws from a theory of parasites that must have
                        been aligned with commonly accepted notions of the human constitution in
                        India at that time. It should also be noted that this presentation is in
                        some ways reminiscent of the radical early Buddhist practice of
                        contemplating the stages of decomposition of corpses that Buddhist ascetics
                        were familiar with. That practice is well described in Buddhaghoṣa’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Visuddhimagga</title> (ch. 6.88), for example, and may
                        have been current in Mahāyāna circles as well, as this sūtra suggests.
                        Buddhaghoṣa’s closing statements on this practice in fact parallel the
                        approach and aim of this sūtra when he addresses men’s unfounded lust for
                        women’s bodies; he writes “… a living body is just as foul as a dead one,
                        only the characteristic of foulness is not evident in a living body, being
                        hidden by adventitious embellishments.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-19" index="11">Cited
                            in Chapple (2013), p. 92.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-20"/>
                    <p tid="12">This English translation is based on the Degé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sde dge</foreign>) version of the sūtra, in consultation
                        with the textual variations recorded in the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>). Additionally,
                        when the readings in the Degé and the Comparative Edition appeared
                        problematic, we consulted the Stok Palace manuscript. These variant
                        readings, when significant, are indicated in the endnotes following the
                        sigla established by the University of Vienna, as based mostly on Harrison
                        and Eimer (1997). These sigla and further abbreviations are indicated in the tables
                        located at the end of the translation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-22"/>
                    <p tid="13">Finally, our translation also benefitted from the contribution of José
                        Cabezón who generously shared his draft translation of the entire sūtra with
                        the committee and offered many helpful comments. Selected parts of Cabezón’s
                        translation of the sūtra have since been published in his groundbreaking
                        study on sexuality in Indian Buddhism, where the interested reader will find
                        further reflections on this sūtra, and the topics of gender and sexuality in
                        Buddhism in general.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-23" index="12">Cabezón (2017).</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="14"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="15">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled:</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="16">The Sections of Dharma</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-24"/>
                    <p tid="18">
                        <ref cRef="F.27.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas! </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-25"/>
                    <p tid="19">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in Kapilavastu at
                        the Nyagrodha Park, together with a great sangha of five hundred monks. At
                        one point venerable Śāriputra, venerable Mahāmaudgalyāyana, venerable
                        Mahākāśyapa, venerable Ānanda, and venerable Rāhula all went to see the
                        Blessed One, prostrated to him, placing their heads at his feet, and sat to
                        one side. Sitting there, venerable Śāriputra asked the Blessed One: <ref cRef="F.28.a"/> “Blessed One, you have spoken of sections of the Dharma.
                        But what is the extent of those sections of the Dharma that the Thus-Gone
                        One refers to with that expression? How many such sections are there? What
                        are the sections of the Dharma?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-26"/>
                    <p tid="20">The Blessed One replied to venerable Śāriputra: “Śāriputra, the Thus-Gone One
                        has taught that there are 84,000 sections of the Dharma. Śāriputra, in this
                        regard, the birthlessness of all phenomena is the primary sense of a section
                        of the Dharma. Śāriputra, I do not claim that there is something called
                        phenomena, or that anything whatsoever is born or ceases. Why is that?
                        Śāriputra, it is because all phenomena are characterized as being unborn and
                        unceasing. For example, Śāriputra, paṇḍakas<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-27" index="13">Tib.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma ning</foreign>; Skt.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">paṇḍaka</foreign>. We have
                            chosen to leave this term untranslated here as no English term seems to
                            cover the full semantic range of the original Sanskrit. Given that we
                            are here in the context of someone who cannot be identified as either a
                            man or a woman, the meaning could perhaps in this context be
                                <emph>neuter</emph>. It seems, however, that in other contexts the
                            term may have a broader range of meaning, or even a somewhat different
                            meaning. Engle (2009, p. 437, note 562) explains the term to refer to a
                            man or a woman who has a functioning but somehow deficient sexual
                            faculty, such as someone who only experiences arousal
                            intermittently.</note> are not called men or women, and should indeed
                        not be said to be men or women. Why is that? Śāriputra, it is because they
                        cannot be designated as men or women. Likewise, Śāriputra, the Thus-Gone One
                        has attained unsurpassed awakening with respect to all phenomena, but one
                        cannot say that he knows phenomena on account of phenomena. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-28"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Śāriputra, for example, paṇḍakas or ṣaṇḍhas<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-29" index="14">Tib.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">za ma</foreign>; Skt.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ṣaṇḍha</foreign>. This term
                            can have a wider range, including those who are, for any number of
                            reasons, sexually impotent. We have chosen to leave this term
                            untranslated here as no English term seems to cover the full semantic
                            range of the original Sanskrit. Engle (2009, p. 437, note 562)
                            translates the term as a “sexually deficient person” and notes that the
                            term refers to a person who lacks a sexual faculty and therefore cannot
                            perform sexually. Engle specifies that this refers to eunuchs, but also
                            those with a congenital abnormality, or who suffer from impotency due to
                            any number of causes.</note> have not abandoned passion, but they cannot
                        act on that passion. Śāriputra, when they see a beautiful woman, arousing
                        desire, most paṇḍakas or ṣaṇḍhas suffer pain in their ducts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-30" index="15">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin
                                pa</foreign>. This term literally means <distinct>calf</distinct>,
                            as in the calf of the leg, which does not make sense in this context.
                            Although all versions of the text consulted read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">byin pa</foreign>, it is possible that
                            a better reading would be <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’byin
                                pa</foreign>. Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’byin
                                pa </foreign>here in the sense of <distinct>gate</distinct> or
                                <distinct>egress</distinct> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">niḥsaraṇa</foreign>; see the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>), we have translated it as <title xml:lang="en">ducts</title>, and understand it to refer to the
                            urethra or other sexual ducts in the case of either a castrate or
                            uncastrated paṇḍaka or ṣaṇḍha. We are grateful to José Cabezón for
                            suggesting this possible alternative reading and its interpretation. See
                            also Cabezón (2017) p. 414, no. 1039.</note> Their ducts drip, their
                        ducts become like metal, and their faces become red. Śāriputra, why do you
                        think this is? These paṇḍakas or ṣaṇḍhas have not fainted to the floor;
                        their bodies have not been struck by weapons. Why do you think their ducts
                        are so painful?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-31"/>
                    <p tid="22">When he spoke thus, venerable Śāriputra replied to the Blessed One with these
                        words: <ref cRef="F.28.b"/> “Blessed One, paṇḍakas or ṣaṇḍhas are the guards
                        of ladies’ quarters. When they see beautiful women, they give rise to
                        desire. Their desirous minds make them boil with affliction, and boiling
                        with affliction, their bodies become engorged with semen. When they
                        are thus tormented by the pang of lust, their ducts burst and their bodies
                        become ruined.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-32"/>
                    <p tid="23">Then the Blessed One said to venerable Śāriputra: “Śāriputra, few among
                        paṇḍakas or ṣaṇḍhas take rebirth in the world of happy destinies of the
                        higher realms. Most of them are reborn as hell beings. Śāriputra, observe
                        the contrast with sons of the Śākya ascetic, none of whom get carried away
                        by desire. Why is that? They know that the sense pleasures are without
                        substance. Knowing that the sense pleasures are impure, they are weary and
                        disenchanted with them. With this deep dislike, they observe celibacy, and
                        their complexions are bright. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-33"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Śāriputra, evil men are unable to feel weary or disenchanted. Why is that?
                        Śāriputra, it is because evil men, due to thinking so much about objects of
                        desire, are full of thoughts. Śāriputra, what are the thoughts of evil men?
                        They think of things that are non-existent. They think of the impure as
                        pure. They think of lack of perception as perception. They think of women as
                        women. They think of being desirous as being desirous. These, Śāriputra, are
                        the thoughts of evil men. Śāriputra, these are the actions of paṇḍakas or
                        ṣaṇḍhas who are gripped by desire; they are not the actions of holy beings.
                        Śāriputra, those paṇḍakas who entertain such conceptions of evil men <ref cRef="F.29.a"/> have the experience, ‘I am touching that,’ and thus
                        perceive the body with its nine orifices, this impure leaking thing, as
                        clean. All these things should not be done. They are not the actions of holy
                        beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-34"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Śāriputra, those ascetics and brahmins who do not recognize the flaws of the
                        sense pleasures for what they really are fantasize about women and cling to
                        certain features of their eyes, perceiving them as beryl. They do not see
                        them as bubbles of water. Śāriputra, compare this to the example of a jenny
                        or a sow that has just given birth. Her body is emptied by giving birth and
                        a filthy excrement-like placenta, unbearable to look at, emerges from her
                        body. Śāriputra, eyes too ought to be described like that. The eyes resemble
                        the placenta of a jenny, of a sow, or of a bitch. The interior of the
                        eyeball is like a water bubble. That is why filth emerges from it, and it is
                        therefore disagreeable. Pus and blood ooze from it—it exudes filth.
                        Śāriputra, the bodily formation that leaks filth, pus, and blood, and that
                        leaks essential fluids, that thing is called the eye. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-35"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Śāriputra, what is the reason for speaking of the eyes? What are the causes
                        and conditions for that? They are the leaders of the body. Looking at form,
                        one is never satisfied—whether at first, in the middle, or in the end—and
                        therefore one physically engages in an ocean of non-virtuous deeds. Because
                        of that we speak of eyes.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-36" index="16"> The Sanskrit word for
                            “eye” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">netra</foreign>), can also
                            mean “leader” or “guide.”</note> Why is that Śāriputra? What are the
                        causes and conditions for speaking of eyes? It is because they are
                        disagreeable. Śāriputra, why are the eyes disagreeable? They see the absence
                        of form as form, the absence of sensations as sensations, the absence of
                        perceptions as perceptions, the absence of formations as formations, and the
                        absence of consciousness as consciousness. Again, what is the reason for
                        this? That is, what are the causes and conditions for speaking of eyes? <ref cRef="F.29.b"/> They cause one’s virtuous conduct to degenerate, and
                        therefore we speak of eyes. They cause monkhood to degenerate, and therefore
                        we speak of eyes. Śāriputra, eyes are impermanent, unstable, and not
                        enduring. That is why they should be known as eyes. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-37"/>
                    <p tid="27">Śāriputra, skilled, well-learned, and dauntless monks relate to the eyes in
                        this way: eyes are not a woman, not a man, not a sentient being, not a life
                        principle, not a living being, and not a person. Likewise, Śāriputra, this
                        applies to the ears, nose, tongue, body, and mind. They are also not a
                        woman, not a man, not a sentient being, not a life principle, not a living
                        being, and not a person. These all arise from being mistaken about the five
                        aggregates. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-38"/>
                    <p tid="28">Śāriputra, those ascetics and brahmins who do not correctly know the
                        shortcomings of the sense pleasures are tormented by lust. Their complexions
                        become poor and pale. Śāriputra, consider this example: when the leaves or
                        the ripe fruits of a big tree fall off, they lose their luster. In the same
                        way, Śāriputra, those among monks and nuns, and male and female lay
                        devotees, who do not correctly know the shortcomings of the sense pleasures
                        are tormented by lust. Their complexions become poor, their thoughts become
                        unclear, and their poor complexions become unpleasant to look at.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-39"/>
                    <p tid="29">“Śāriputra, young monks who are ordained in the prime of their lives will
                        soon correctly know the sense pleasures, understanding that the sense
                        pleasures lack substance. Even if they have thoughts of desire, they quickly
                        pacify them, recognizing them as being non-virtuous. Śāriputra, that being
                        the case, once monks have seen the shortcomings of the sense pleasures, they
                        are disenchanted and free from desire. They then truly rejoice and practice
                        pure conduct. <ref cRef="F.30.a"/> Their complexions become radiant. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-40"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Śāriputra, consider this example: when pus develops in the body of a sick
                        person, 84,000 sores open up on all of that person’s limbs<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-41" index="17"> Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">yan lag dang
                                nying lag</foreign>: the major limbs (head, arms and legs) and minor
                            limbs (fingers, toes, nose, ears, etc.).</note> and each open sore also
                        has 84,000 swarms of parasites.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-42" index="18">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srin bu’i tshogs</foreign>. The term
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srin bu</foreign> (Skt.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">kṛmi</foreign>) refers to any
                            number of types of worms, insects, or bugs. We have chosen to translate
                            it here as <distinct>parasite</distinct> given the context, particularly
                            below in the text, where these <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">srin bu</foreign> are said to inhabit various internal organs in
                            the female body.</note> These parasites have both beaks and mouths. No
                        matter how much they eat, they are never satiated. If that person sits near
                        a heap of embers,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-43" index="19">Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">de mdag ma spungs pa’i drung du ’dug
                                na</foreign>. Note that the Comparative Edition incorrectly reads
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ma dag</foreign>.</note> the
                        more those creatures are tormented by burning, the more they eat. Now, what
                        do you think about that, Śāriputra? As they consume that person, will those
                        creatures eat the person up or not?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-44"/>
                    <p tid="31">Venerable Śāriputra replied to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, if hearing this
                        makes my hair stand on end, it is needless to mention how unpleasant it must
                        be for that person. Blessed One, that person is certainly being eaten up by
                        those varieties of creatures—nothing will be left un-eaten. Those 84,000
                        creatures make the body itch and, in that way, they do not give that person
                        any peace. They bring that person no happiness.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-45"/>
                    <p tid="32">“Śāriputra, what do you think? That person’s body leaks pus and blood—should
                        that state of affair be despised?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-46"/>
                    <p tid="33">“It is indeed something to despise, it is indeed disagreeable, it is indeed
                        not something worthy to look upon.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-47"/>
                    <p tid="34">“Similarly, Śāriputra, skilled monks train correctly by contemplating as
                        follows, ‘The Blessed One has said that women are filthy, foul-smelling,
                        disagreeable, and unsuitable to look upon. Women, boiling with afflictive
                        emotions, should not be kept company with. Desires are foul smelling,
                        disagreeable, and not suitable to be looked upon.’ <ref cRef="F.30.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-48"/>
                    <p tid="35">“Śāriputra, women’s bodies possess an additional five groups of parasites
                        that are different from those on men’s bodies. Śāriputra, these five groups
                        of parasites live in their urinary tracts. Each group of parasites has its
                        own respective eighty parasites that have both beaks and mouths. These
                        parasites constantly eat away at women’s bodies. That is why women, incited
                        by the afflictions, engage in sexual misconduct and yet, when they engage in
                        their passions, they do not find any satisfaction. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-49"/>
                    <p tid="36">“Therefore, Śāriputra, if one sees the sense pleasures as being faulty, one
                        will be disenchanted and free from desire. One will then engage in pure
                        conduct with delight and one’s complexion will glow. Śāriputra, this is the
                        Dharma teaching that begins with a section on the sense pleasures.
                        Śāriputra, one should be disenchanted with indulgence in passion. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-50"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Now Śāriputra, what is defilement? Śāriputra, defilement is one’s own doing.
                        Śāriputra, what are purification and pacification? Śāriputra, purification
                        and pacification are also one’s own doing. Śāriputra, what is defilement and
                        what is one’s own doing? They are the obsession with perceiving things as
                        phenomena. What is the obsession with perceiving things as phenomena? It is
                        to be obsessed with perceiving things as being born and as ceasing,
                        perceiving things as having a self, as not having a self, or as being the
                        self. This is the section of Dharma spoken by the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-51"/>
                    <p tid="38">Śāriputra, childish, ordinary beings are blind and thus conceptualize the
                        form aggregate. They also conceptualize the aggregates of sensation,
                        perception, formation, and consciousness. But conceptualizing is bondage.
                        Not to form concepts is to be liberated. Śāriputra, whoever conceptualizes
                        will take on the form aggregate. <ref cRef="F.31.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-52"/>
                    <p tid="39">“Śāriputra, there are ten misfortunes that befall someone who has lapsed
                        discipline. What are the ten? Lapsed discipline will torment one at the time
                        of death. A monk with lapsed discipline will feel regret. Saying, ‘I am
                        going to go to the hell of unrelenting torment!’ the monk will be afraid to
                        stay among the assembly. The monk will think, ‘I am disparaging the
                        discipline! The buddhas have forsaken me, the hearers have forsaken me, the
                        gods have forsaken me!’ He will be fearful at death, go to the lower realms,
                        and a human body will be difficult to obtain. Śāriputra, these are the
                        misfortunes of a monk’s lapsed discipline—the one who has lapsed discipline
                        will suffer torment at the time of death. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-53"/>
                    <p tid="40">“Śāriputra, since that is the case, you should come to perceive sense
                        pleasures as fault-ridden. Śāriputra, that means that whether a monk dwells
                        in the forest, at the base of a tree, in an abandoned building, or out in
                        the open, he should train himself by thinking, ‘The sense pleasures are foul
                        smelling. The sense pleasures are disagreeable. The sense pleasures are like
                        an open wound. The sense pleasures are not suitable to be looked upon. The
                        sense pleasures are despicable. The sense pleasures are like a corpse filled
                        to the brim with excrement!’ The sense pleasures are the objects of
                        excitement for the childish. Śāriputra, enough of enjoying women sexually
                        and pleasing them!</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-54"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Śāriputra, a woman’s body is completely filled with feces and spit—who would
                        enjoy that? Śāriputra, their bodies are to be despised just like the rotten
                        corpse of an ordinary dog. Indeed Śāriputra, consider the example of a
                        filthy, rotten, and foul-smelling corpse of a dog with repulsive dark
                        bluish-green skin, completely filled with maggots, lying on a roadside. Rain
                        falls on the corpse and the wind tosses it about. Then some people arrive
                        there, circling around the corpse, and catch a whiff of its smell. When that
                        happens, Śāriputra, what do you think? <ref cRef="F.31.b"/> Will they sniff
                        at its stench or not?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-55"/>
                    <p tid="42">“O Blessed One, certainly not!” exclaimed Śāriputra. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-56"/>
                    <p tid="43">The Blessed One then asked venerable Śāriputra, “So what do you think,
                        Śāriputra? If someone touched<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-57" index="20"> Here we follow
                                K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>, K, C and U which read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">reg</foreign>, rather than D which
                            reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rig</foreign>. </note> the
                        corpse of that dog, if he shook it, if he enjoyed himself with it, would he
                        be praised by many people?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-58"/>
                    <p tid="44">Venerable Śāriputra replied, “That person would be difficult even to look
                        at—how could he ever be praised?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-59"/>
                    <p tid="45">The Blessed One then said to venerable Śāriputra, “Śāriputra, the thus-gone
                        ones might praise the person who embraces, shakes, and enjoys himself with
                        that dog’s corpse. However, they would not praise a person who, even with
                        just his toe, touches a woman, whether she is the beauty of the land,
                        sixteen years old, an excellent woman, with a beautiful form, who is lovely
                        to behold, with delightful full breasts, adorned with jewelry, youthful,
                        pleasant to touch, and free of disease. Śāriputra, a person who touches such
                        a beauty of the land with even just his toe is despicable, unlike the one
                        who embraces, shakes, and enjoys himself with that dog’s corpse. Śāriputra,
                        what do you think about this? By embracing or touching a dog’s corpse, will
                        sentient beings end up being born in the hell realms?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-60"/>
                    <p tid="46">“No, Blessed One, they will not.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-61"/>
                    <p tid="47">“Śāriputra, monks must develop the perception of the faults of the sense
                        pleasures in the following way. Śāriputra, how should monks develop the
                        perception of the faults of the body? Śāriputra, this body is very harmful
                        and troublesome. <ref cRef="F.32.a"/> Śāriputra, women’s bodies have
                        twenty-five more groups of parasites that are not like the ones present in
                        men’s bodies. Śāriputra, there are masses of parasites in women’s brains.
                        Known as the <emph>robbers</emph>, they eat the brains of women. Śāriputra,
                        there are masses of parasites in women’s noses. Known as the <emph>mouth
                            terminators</emph>, they eat women’s moustaches, thus preventing them
                        from growing. Śāriputra, there are masses of parasites in women’s ears.
                        Known as the <emph>eaters</emph>, they eat and pierce the ears of women. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-62"/>
                    <p tid="48">Śāriputra, there are masses of parasites on the sides of women’s necks and
                        heads. Known as the <emph>yearners</emph>, they eat and pierce the ears of
                        women and make their eyes sharp. Śāriputra, they don’t prick the ears of men
                        but only those of women. Śāriputra, there are masses of parasites on women’s
                        bodies. Known as the <emph>obstructors</emph>,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-63" index="21">
                            Tentative translation. The Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">a ba re ban</foreign>, which we have been unable to
                            identify. Here we have chosen to read the word as a transcription of
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āvaraṇa</foreign>, meaning
                                <distinct>hindrance</distinct> or <distinct>obstruction</distinct>.
                        </note> they incessantly eat women’s mouths. That is why the throats of
                        women are flat, unlike those of men. As soon as women put food or drink in
                        their mouths, the parasites are the first to eat. They then deposit their
                        waste inside women’s breasts, making their breasts hang down. Whenever women
                        become pregnant, the parasites also become pregnant. That is why there is so
                        much milk in women’s breasts. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-64"/>
                    <p tid="49">“Śāriputra, inside the part of women’s bodies where the womb is, there are
                        destructive parasites known as the <emph>mighty exterminators</emph>. They
                        kill and eat the parasites known as the <emph>lickers</emph>. If they cannot
                        find any of the parasites known as the <emph>lickers</emph>, they too will
                        die. Pregnancy comes about from the death, and thus the absence, of those
                        two types of parasites, in addition to the union of mother and father.
                        Śāriputra, in the birth canal inside women’s bodies, there are four hosts of
                        parasites that are known as the <emph>great lips</emph>, <ref cRef="F.32.b"/> the <emph>lump concealers</emph>, the <emph>wind expellers</emph>, and
                        the <emph>desire catchers</emph>. They incessantly eat at the bodies of
                        women. Because of this, women are completely ablaze with afflictions, yet
                        are never satisfied by indulging in their desires. Consequently, knowing
                        that women have such great faults, the Thus-Gone One added additional rules
                        to the fundamental precepts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-65" index="22">Reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dang bca’ ba</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dang bcas pa</foreign>. When the
                            female renunciate order was established, a number of additional precepts
                            were added that ordained nuns must follow. These precepts, which
                            subordinate female monastics to the supervision of the male ordained
                            community, were most likely added to alleviate opposition in the male
                            ordained community, and Indian society at large, to the inclusion of
                            women in the order.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-66"/>
                    <p tid="50">“Śāriputra, you should teach this Dharma teaching on the sections of Dharma
                        over and over again to the four assemblies.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-67" index="23">
                            This refers to the assemblies of monks, nuns, laymen, and
                            laywomen.</note> Why? So that they will come to know that the body and
                        the sense pleasures are to be despised. Śāriputra, knowing this body to be a
                        fabrication, apart from immature ordinary beings with no education, no one
                        would continue clinging to the sense pleasures—it would be impossible.
                        Śāriputra, that being the case, you should not be fond of this body. In
                        particular, don’t be attached to it.” Thus spoke the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-68"/>
                    <p tid="51">After the Blissful One had uttered those words, the Teacher continued, saying
                        the following:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-69"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“These bodies that arise from filth</l>
                        <l>Are always home to many creatures.</l>
                        <l>Filled to the brim with urine and excrement,</l>
                        <l>It is to these that immature beings cling.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-70"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“Monks and nuns,</l>
                        <l>Laymen and laywomen, </l>
                        <l>Upon hearing this, let go of their desire.</l>
                        <l>Free from desire, they are liberated.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-71"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“To practitioners of the Dharma</l>
                        <l>I did not teach these faults.</l>
                        <l>It is to whomever indulges in desires</l>
                        <l>That I explained these faults.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-72"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“Just as the Buddha has taught,</l>
                        <l>Once those who fantasize upon seeing women</l>
                        <l>Understand this genuine encouragement,</l>
                        <l>Those wise ones will no longer have such thoughts.” </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-73"/>
                    <p tid="56">After the Blessed One had spoken these words, venerable Śāriputra together
                        with the whole world and its gods, humans, and demigods all rejoiced and
                        praised the teaching of the Blessed One.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head tid="57">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-74"/>
                    <p tid="58">This concludes the Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra entitled <title xml:lang="en">The Sections of Dharma</title>. <ref cRef="F.33.a"/> The Indian scholar
                        Prajñāvarman and the chief editor-translator, venerable Yeshé Dé,
                        translated, edited, and finalized this work.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="59">Notes</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <list type="abbreviations">
                        <head type="abbreviations" tid="60">Kangyur Editions:</head>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-75">
                            <abbr>D</abbr>
                            <expan>Degé</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-76">
                            <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                            </abbr>
                            <expan>Yongle</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-77">
                            <abbr>J</abbr>
                            <expan>Lithang</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-78">
                            <abbr>K</abbr>
                            <expan>Kangxi Peking</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-79">
                            <abbr>N</abbr>
                            <expan>Narthang</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-80">
                            <abbr>C</abbr>
                            <expan>Choné </expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-81">
                            <abbr>U</abbr>
                            <expan>Urga</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-82">
                            <abbr>H</abbr>
                            <expan>Lhasa (Zhol)</expan>
                        </item>
                        <item xml:id="UT22084-066-003-83">
                            <abbr>S</abbr>
                            <expan>Stok Palace </expan>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="61">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="62">Main Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-84">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi phung po zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dharma­skandha­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 245, Degé
                        Kangyur vol. 66 (mdo sde, za) , ff. 27b–33a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-85">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi phung po zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dharma­skandha­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>).  bka’ ’gyur
                        (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa
                        zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                        Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
                        House), 2006–2009, vol. 66, pp. 73–85. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-86">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos kyi phung po zhes bya ba theg pa
                            chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dharma­skandha­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Stok Palace Manuscript
                        Kangyur, vol. 64 (mdo sde, pa), ff. 336b.1–344a.7. </bibl>
                    </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="63">Secondary Sources </head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-87"> Boucher, Daniel. <title xml:lang="en">Bodhisattvas of Forest and the
                            Formation of Mahāyāna</title>. Honolulu: University of Hawaii Press,
                        2008. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-88">Cabezón, José. <title xml:lang="en">Sexuality in Classical South Asian
                            Buddhism</title>. Somerville: Wisdom Publications, 2017. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-89">Chapple, Christopher Key. “Abhidharma as Paradigm for Practice.” In
                            <title xml:lang="en">Pāli Buddhism</title>, edited by Frank J. Hoffman
                        and Deegalle Mahinda, 79-101. New York: Routledge, 2013. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-90">Engle, Artemus B. <title xml:lang="en">The Inner Science of Buddhist
                            Practice: Vasubandhu’s Summary of the Five Heaps with Commentary by
                            Sthiramati</title>. Ithaca: Snow Lion, 2009. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-91"> Halkias, Georgios T. “Tibetan Buddhism Registered: A Catalogue from the
                        Imperial Court of ’Phang Thang.” <title xml:lang="en">The Eastern
                            Buddhist</title> 36:1–2 (2004): 46–105. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-92">Harrison, Paul and Helmut Eimer. “Kanjur and Tanjur Sigla: A Proposal for
                        Standardization.” In <title xml:lang="en">Transmission of the Tibetan Canon:
                            Papers Presented at a Panel of the 7th Seminar of the International
                            Association for Tibetan Studies</title>, Graz 1995, edited by Helmut Eimer, xi–xiv. Graz: Verlag der
                        Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1997. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-93">Nattier, Jan. <title xml:lang="en">A Few Good Men</title>. Honolulu:
                        University of Hawaii Press, 2003. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-94">Pad dkar bzang po. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde spyi’i rnam
                            bzhag</title>. Bejing: mi rigs dpe skrun khang (Minorities Publishing
                        House), 2006. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-95">Pagel, Ulrich. <title xml:lang="en">The Bodhisattvapiṭaka</title>.
                        Buddhica Britannica, Series Continua 5, Tring: The Institute of Buddhist
                        Studies, 1995. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-96">Potter, Karl H., Robert E. Buswell, and Padmanabh S. Jaini. <title xml:lang="en">Encyclopedia of Indian Philosophies Vol. VII: Abhidharma
                            Buddhism to 150 A.D</title>.  Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-97">Schopen, Gregory. <title xml:lang="en">Figments and Fragments of Mahāyāna
                            Buddhism in India: More Collected Papers</title>. Honolulu: University
                        of Hawaii Press, 2005. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-98">Yoshimura, Shyuki. <title xml:lang="en">The Denkar-ma: An Oldest
                            Catalogue of the Tibetan Buddhist Canons, with introductory
                            notes</title>. Kyoto: Ryukoku University, 1950. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-003-99">Zysk, Kenneth G. <title xml:lang="en">Religious Medicine: The History and
                            Evolution of Indian Medicine</title>. New Brunswick, New Jersey:
                        Transaction Publishers, 1993.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="glossary">
                    <list type="glossary">
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-100">
                                <term>aggregates</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">skandha</term>
                                <term type="definition">The five <term type="ignore">aggregates</term> of form, sensation,
                                    perception, formations and consciousness. On the individual
                                    level the five <term type="ignore">aggregates</term> refer to the basis of the mistaken
                                    idea of self. On a general level the five <term type="ignore">aggregates</term> constitute
                                    any compounded phenomena.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-101">
                                <term>birthlessness</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye ba med pa </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་བ་མེད་པ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ajātakatvā</term>
                                <term type="definition">Without arising, without beginning,
                                    unborn.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-102">
                                <term>ṣaṇḍha</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">za ma </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཟ་མ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṣaṇḍha</term>
                                <term type="definition">Someone whose sexual organs (or part of
                                    them) have been removed, or who is sexually impotent for some
                                    other reason; sometimes synonym to <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma
                                        ning</foreign> (see entry “paṇḍaka”).</term>
                                <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-066-003-29"/>.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-103">
                                <term>monk</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong</term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                                <term type="definition">A fully ordained male practitioner.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-129">
                                <term>nun</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong ma</term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་མ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣuṇī</term>
                                <term type="definition">A fully ordained female practitioner.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-104">
                                <term>paṇḍaka</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ning </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">མ་ནིང་།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paṇḍaka</term>
                                <term type="definition">A person who either has no sexual organs,
                                    degenerated sexual organs, or the organs of both sexes.</term>
                                <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-066-003-27"/>.</term>ma
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-105">
                                <term>pure conduct</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs par spyad pa spyod pa </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པར་སྤྱད་པ་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmacarya </term>
                                <term type="definition">The practice of celibacy or a chaste sexual
                                    behavior; this lifestyle also entails different spiritual
                                    practices.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-106">
                                <term>lump concealers</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gong bu sped </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">གོང་བུ་སྤེད།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">One of the four parasites inside the birth
                                    canals of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-107">
                                <term>desire catchers</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod len </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་ལེན།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">One of the four parasites inside the birth
                                    canals of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-108">
                                <term>eaters</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">za bar byed </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཟ་བར་བྱེད།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">The parasites that are said to live in the
                                    ears of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-109">
                                <term>great lips</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchu mchog </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">མཆུ་མཆོག</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">One of the four parasites inside the birth
                                    canals of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-110">
                                <term>lickers</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab tu ldag byed </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཏུ་ལྡག་བྱེད།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">Parasites that are said to live inside
                                    women’s wombs.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-111">
                                <term>mighty exterminators</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zad par byed pa dpa’ ba </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཟད་པར་བྱེད་པ་དཔའ་བ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">Parasites that are said to live inside
                                    women’s wombs.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-112">
                                <term>robbers</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phrog byed </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྲོག་བྱེད།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">The parasites that are said to live in the
                                    brains of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-113">
                                <term>mouth terminators</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kha rdzogs </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཁ་རྫོགས།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">Parasites that are said to live in the noses
                                    of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-114">
                                <term>wind expellers</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rlung ’byin </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">རླུང་འབྱིན།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">One of the four parasites inside the birth
                                    canals of women.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-115">
                                <term>yearners</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhen byed </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཞེན་བྱེད།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">Parasites that are said to live on the sides
                                    of women’s neck and head.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-116">
                                <term>Dharma presentation</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi rnam grangs </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་རྣམ་གྲངས།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmaparyāya</term>
                                <term type="definition">A teaching of the Dharma.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-117">
                                <term>hearer</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                                <term type="definition">Someone who practices according to the
                                    Vehicle of the <term type="ignore">Hearers</term> (those who hear the teachings from
                                    others). </term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-118">
                                <term>worthy one</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhant</term>
                                <term type="definition">The fourth of the four results attainable by
                                    a hearer. One who has eliminated all afflictions and personally
                                    ended the cycle of rebirth.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-119">
                                <term>parasite</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin bu </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིན་བུ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krimi</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṛmi</term>
                                <term type="definition">According to classical Indian medical
                                    literature, the human body is filled with various parasitic
                                    beings (literally “worms”) that live off the body.</term>
                                <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-066-003-42"/>.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-120">
                                <term>Ānanda</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                                <term type="definition">Attendant of the Buddha and the one who is
                                    said to have memorized the sūtras.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-121">
                                <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                                <term type="definition">One of the Buddha’s foremost
                                    disciples.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-122">
                                <term>Mahāmaudgalyāyana</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maudgalyāyana</term>
                                <term type="definition">One of the Buddha’s foremost
                                    disciples.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-123">
                                <term>Prajñāvarman</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pra dz+nyA bar ma </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">པྲ་ཛྙཱ་བར་མ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñāvarman </term>
                                <term type="definition">An Indian Bengali paṇḍita resident in Tibet
                                    during the late eighth, early ninth centuries. Arriving in Tibet
                                    on an invitation from the Tibetan king, he assisted in the
                                    translation of numerous canonical scriptures. He is also the
                                    author of a few philosophical commentaries contained in the
                                    Tibetan Tengyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan ’gyur</foreign>)
                                    collection.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-124">
                                <term>Rāhula</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན་ཟིན།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                                <term type="definition">
                                    <term type="ignore">Rāhula</term> is the name of Śākyamuni Buddha’s
                                    physical son. Edgerton reports from different sources that he
                                    miraculously descended from Tuṣita heaven into his mother’s
                                    womb, and insisted on becoming a monk when he found out that the
                                    Buddha was his father. He was ordained by Śāriputra.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-125">
                                <term>Śāriputra</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ri’i bu </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་རིའི་བུ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāriputra</term>
                                <term type="definition">One of the closest disciples of the Buddha,
                                    known for his pure observance of discipline.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-126">
                                <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                                <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during
                                    the late eighth and early ninth centuries.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-127">
                                <term>Kapilavastu</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ser skya gnas </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་སྐྱ་གནས།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kapilavastu</term>
                                <term type="definition">The city in which Śākyamuni Buddha was born,
                                    located in present day southern Nepal.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-003-128">
                                <term>Nyagrodha Park</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing nya gro dha’i kun dga’ ra ba </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ཉ་གྲོ་དྷའི་ཀུན་དགའ་ར་བ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyagrodhārāma</term>
                                <term type="definition">A grove of banyan trees (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nyagrodha</foreign>, Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nya
                                        gro dha</foreign>) near Kapilavastu where
                                        the Buddha sometimes took residence. It was a gift to the
                                        Buddhist community by King Śuddhodana, the father of the
                                        Buddha.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>