<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos dang don rnam par 'byed pa'i
                    mdo/</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་དང་དོན་རྣམ་པར་འབྱེད་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmārtha­vibhaṅga­sūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on How to Distinguish Dharma and
                    Worldly Pursuits</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">'phags pa chos dang don rnam par 'byed pa
                    zhes bya ba theg pa chen po'i mdo</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryadharmārtha­vibhaṃga­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་དང་དོན་རྣམ་པར་འབྱེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་དང་དོན་རྣམ་པར་འབྱེད་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos dang don rnam par 'byed pa/</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="en">Distinguishing Dharma from Worldly
                    Pursuits</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmārtha­vibhaṅga</title>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-75">Timothy Hinkle</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-58">Anna Zilman</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
            <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-165">Robert Miller</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-257">Raynald Prévèreau</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.0 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative that aims to translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-066-005"/>
               <note>An early mistake in the assigning of UT numbers within the 84000 project means
                    that these ids diverge slightly from the standard logic.</note>
                <date>2019-01-29</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh247" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 247</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios 42.b–46.a<!--(pp.84-91)--></biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinamitra </author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Danaśila</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="8">
                        <start volume="66" page="86"/>
                        <end volume="66" page="93"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11898" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
           <notesStmt>
               <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-02-22T16:34:58.293Z" user="celso">22/02/2019 16:34:58</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-1"/>
                <p tid="2">In <title xml:lang="en">Distinguishing Between Phenomena and
                        Reality</title> Buddha Śākyamuni relates a story, which occurred countless
                    eons ago in a world called Flower Origin. He describes how a buddha named Arisen
                    from Flowers gave instructions on the topic of the five aggregates to the royal
                    family and prophesied the awakening of the prince Ratnākara. Buddha Śākyamuni
                    then explains that Arisen from Flowers now has become the present Buddha
                    Amitābha, and Ratnākara, the bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance
                    of Chokyi Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Anna Zilman and
                    Timothy Hinkle. Andreas Doctor compared the translation with the Tibetan and
                    edited the text.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-3"/>
                    <p tid="6">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Distinguishing Between Phenomena and Reality</title> is
                        a scripture that belongs to the general sūtra section of the Degé Kangyur.
                        The sūtra is set in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park at Śrāvastī, where Buddha Śākyamuni
                        resides with a gathering of monks and bodhisattvas. In delivering his
                        teaching, Śākyamuni describes an ancient world known as Flower Origin<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-4"> The Sanskrit name for
                            this world is most likely <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">puṣpākara</foreign>. This is attested in the Negi dictionary for
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">me tog gi ’byung
                                gnas</foreign> and it is found in BHSD as the name of a buddha
                            (Edgerton, 1998, p. 350). We have not, however, found a world by this
                            name, i.e., a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">puṣpākaraloka</foreign> and so have rendered this name in English
                            translation.</note> in which the buddha Arisen from Flowers<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-5"> Although canonical
                            sources list past buddhas known either as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puṣpa</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puṣpita</foreign>,
                            and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puṣpakṛta</foreign>, we have not found
                            an attested Sanskrit for the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog
                                las byung ba</foreign>. We have therefore preferred to use the
                            English translation of this name, rather than attempt a reconstruction,
                            especially because clear lists and equivalents for buddha-names such as
                            these do not as yet seem to be available. For a discussion of the names
                            of buddhas listed in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadra­kalpika­sūtra</title>, see Skilling (2010) and, in
                            particular, Skilling (2014). </note> lived. That world was governed by a
                        ruler known as Attainment of Victory, under whose rule everyone practiced
                        the Great Vehicle. Prompted by the prince Ratnākara, the royal family goes
                        to meet Arisen from Flowers. This buddha then teaches the audience about the
                        insubstantial and unsatisfactory nature of the aggregates, and describes
                        beings’ tendency to perceive the aggregates in a flawed manner: while the
                        aggregates are actually impermanent, repulsive, unclean, and unreal,
                        sentient beings conceive of them as lasting, pleasant, pure, and true.
                        Śākyamuni further explains how beings are themselves a product of their
                        actions, and that the five aggregates (the components that together
                        constitute a sentient being) are not purposely created by anyone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtra thus presents a version of the well–known four errors
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">catvāro viparyāsāḥ</foreign>,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phyin ci log pa bzhi</foreign>)
                        that are often described in Buddhist canonical literature as the main
                        underpinnings of sentient beings’ mistaken view of the world: (1)
                        erroneously perceiving that the impermanent is permanent, (2) the painful is
                        pleasant, (3) the dirty is clean, and (4) that what has no self has a self.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-7"> For a discussion
                            of these four errors, see Lang (2003).</note> The four errors are also
                        discussed <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">in
                            extenso</foreign> in canonical literature—in the Abhidharma, but also in
                        chapters 6–9 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catuḥśataka</title> of Āryadeva
                        (fl. third cent.), where each is treated in a separate chapter.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-8"> Lang (1986).</note>
                        The present sūtra invokes the four errors, but instead of presenting the
                        illusion that the painful is pleasant, it speaks of the illusion that the
                        repulsive (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi sdug pa</foreign>) is
                        beautiful (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdug pa</foreign>). Aside
                        from this minor twist, the context remains that of the four errors
                        traditionally mentioned in Buddhist literature. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-9"/>
                    <p tid="8">Once the buddha Arisen from Flowers has taught the audience, the
                        king, queen, prince, and the entire retinue all take ordination. The
                        Thus-Gone One then prophesies prince Ratnākara’s awakening, revealing his
                        future name, world, lifespan, and the nature of his teachings. Toward the
                        end of the sūtra, Śākyamuni reveals the current identity of the main
                        characters of his narrative. Arisen from Flowers has now become the buddha
                        Amitābha and Ratnākara has become the bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara. In the
                        remainder of the sūtra, Śākyamuni reveals that anyone who faithfully
                        receives this Dharma teaching will be reborn in Sukhāvatī (the buddha realm
                        of Amitābha) and that all women who touch or read this sūtra will be able to
                        exchange their female bodies for male forms and never again take rebirth in
                        a female body. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-10"/>
                    <p tid="9">This notion, that women should prefer (or, in fact, be obliged) to
                        turn into men in order to awaken to buddhahood is a common idea found
                        throughout Mahāyāna literature.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-11"> For more on this theme in Mahāyāna
                            literature see Jan Nattier, “Gender and Enlightenment: Sexual
                            Transformation in Mahāyāna Sūtras” (Unpublished manuscript, University
                            of Indiana, 2002). </note> To a contemporary audience such a denigration
                        of the female body is of course problematic. However, it should be kept in
                        mind that these teachings were given in a society where the status of women
                        was generally low, and women were expected to be subservient to men. It is
                        also important to remember that the Buddha did, although reluctantly,
                        endorse female practitioners by allowing nuns into his order.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-12"/>
                    <p tid="10">There is no extant Sanskrit version of this scripture, and the sūtra
                        does not appear to have been translated into Chinese either. In producing
                        this translation, we have based our work on the Degé xylograph while
                        consulting the Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur
                            ma</title>), as well as the Stok Palace manuscript. The colophon of the
                        sūtra states that it was translated by the Indian scholars Jinamitra and
                        Dānaśīla, as well as the prolific Tibetan translator Yeshé Dé. We can
                        therefore date the Tibetan translation to the late eight to early ninth
                        century, a dating that is also attested by the text’s inclusion in the early
                        ninth century Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>)
                        catalogue.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-13"> The
                            Denkarma catalogue is dated to c. 812 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. In this catalogue, <title xml:lang="en">Distinguishing Between Phenomena and Reality</title>
                            is included among the “Miscellaneous Sūtras” (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde sna tshogs</title>) less than hundred sections (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bam po</foreign>) long. See
                            Herrmann-Pfandt 2008, p. 111, no. 208.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="11"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="12">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra Entitled</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="13">Distinguishing Between Phenomena and Reality</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-16"/>
                    <p tid="17">
                        <ref cRef="F.42.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                <lb/>
                    
                  
                    
                    <p tid="18">Thus did I hear at one time: The Blessed One was staying in the Jeta
                        Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s park, at Śrāvastī. He was there together with a great
                        saṅgha of monks, as well as a great saṅgha of bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-18"/>
                    <p tid="19">At that time, the Blessed One said to the bodhisattva great being
                       <ref cRef="F.43.a"/> Delighted by Victory, “Noble son, countless eons ago in the past,
                        limitless and immeasurable in number, there was a world called Flower
                        Origin. It was abundantly prosperous, happy, had good crops, and was
                        delightful. It was filled with many people and as even as the palm of a
                        hand. Noble son, in the world Flower Origin dwelled the thus-gone, worthy,
                        perfect buddha Arisen from Flowers. He still abides there, alive and well,
                        teaching the Dharma to the fourfold assembly, as well as to gods, nāgas,
                        yakṣas, gandharvas, demigods, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, humans, and
                        non-humans. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-19"/>
                    <p tid="20">“Noble son, in the world Flower Origin lived the ruler Attainment of
                        Victory. He was a universal emperor, who had as his dominion the entire
                        trichiliocosm. Noble son, under the king’s rule<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-20"> Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshig rab</foreign>.
                        </note> beings had found happiness and well-being, followed the path of the
                        ten virtuous deeds, and were satisfied with their wives. Everyone there had
                        entered but a single vehicle: They had entered the Great Vehicle. They had
                        entered the supreme vehicle. They had entered the main vehicle. They had
                        entered the true vehicle. They had entered the foremost vehicle, the best,
                        the finest, and the highest vehicle. The vehicle they had entered was higher
                        than the highest; the unsurpassed vehicle. They had entered the unequalled
                        vehicle. They had entered the matchless vehicle. They had entered the
                        inconceivable vehicle. They had entered the unfathomable vehicle. <ref cRef="F.43.b"/>
                        Noble son, under the rule of the king Attainment of Victory, vehicles other
                        than the Great Vehicle were unheard of. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-21"/>
                    <p tid="21">“Noble son, in his retinue of queens the king Attainment of Victory
                        had ninety-nine thousand wives, none of whom had entered any other vehicle.
                        They all belonged solely to the Great Vehicle, longed for the Dharma day and
                        night, and took delight in the Dharma. Noble son, the king’s primary wife
                        Ratnaśrī, who was a beloved<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-22"> Translated based on Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdug pa</foreign>. Degé reads:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdud pa</foreign>.</note>
                        bodhisattva, followed the Buddha, the Dharma<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-23"> Translated based on Yongle, Lithang,
                            Kangxi, Narthang, Choné, Lhasa, and Stok: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sangs rgyas dang chos</foreign>. Degé reads: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sangs rgyas pa’i
                            chos</foreign>.</note> and the Saṅgha. She belonged to the Great
                        Vehicle, longed for the Dharma at all times, and found delight only in the
                        joy of the Dharma. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-24"/>
                    <p tid="22">“Noble son, once, while Ratnaśrī was seated upon a splendid lion
                        throne, her son Ratnākara got down from her lap where he had been sitting in
                        the cross-legged posture. He was adorned with divine ornaments, attired with
                        divine fabrics, and his body was adorned with the excellent major and minor
                        marks. As soon as he got down, the child asked his mother, ‘Mother, is the
                        thus-gone Arisen from Flowers still alive?’ The queen Ratnaśrī answered the
                        young one: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-25"/>
                    <lg tid="23">
                        <l>‘My only son, the omniscient one,</l>
                        <l>The protector of the world,</l>
                        <l>The unsurpassed one who delights all—</l>
                        <l>He is alive in the world of gods and humans.’ </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-26"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Then, the prince Ratnākara spoke to his parents, ‘Father and
                        mother, come here! We have to go to the thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha
                        Arisen from Flowers in order to behold him, to pay homage and make
                        offerings, to serve him, and to receive Dharma teachings from him. If you
                        wonder why we need to, father and mother, it is because the Thus-Gone One
                        performs hardships in the world of gods and humans.</p>
                    <!--Is this supposed to be verse? check meter in Tibetan.-->
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-27"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>‘He is a protector liberating those who have not been liberated.</l>
                    <l>He grants eyesight to the blind. </l>
                    <l>He is heroic and courageous with regard to the Dharma.<ref cRef="F.44.a"/>
                        </l>
                    <l>He is as unwavering as a great mountain.’ </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-31"/>
                    <p tid="29">“King Attainment of Victory and Queen Ratnaśrī then brought their
                        son and the retinue of queens and servants and went before the Blessed One.
                        They circumambulated the Blessed One seven times and offered him extremely
                        valuable pearl necklaces, after which they all sat down among the assembly.
                        Noble son, the prince then rose up into the sky to the height of seven palm
                        trees by means of his miraculous ability and sprinkled a rain of jewels,
                        flowers, and incense upon the blessed Arisen from Flowers. He then spoke to
                        the Blessed One:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-32"/>
                    <lg tid="30">
                        <l>‘O Teacher, you have crossed </l>
                        <l>The great river of suffering,</l>
                        <l>And ferry beings across it.</l>
                        <l>I have come here to see you, Omniscient One.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-33"/>
                    <lg tid="31">
                        <l>‘As the unsurpassed protector of the world,</l>
                        <l>There is no one who has ever matched you,</l>
                        <l>Or displayed such qualities as yours,</l>
                        <l>In the world of gods and humans.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-34"/>
                    <lg tid="32">
                        <l>‘You establish in the lesser vehicle</l>
                        <l>Beings who have strayed onto negative paths,</l>
                        <l>Those who are under the sway of desire and anger,</l>
                        <l>And then you teach the Great Vehicle.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-35"/>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>‘You are skilled in means and courageous,</l>
                        <l>A master of great compassion.</l>
                        <l>The Dharma is meaningful and you are sated by the Dharma,</l>
                        <l>You set forth the Dharma and are a source of all qualities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-36"/>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>‘Knowing phenomena to be unborn</l>
                        <l>And without substance,</l>
                        <l>You also know their reality.</l>
                        <l>That is how you perform hardships.’ </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-37"/>
                    <p tid="35">“The young prince praised the Blessed One in this manner, then
                        circumambulated him and sat before him. The Blessed One looked in all
                        directions with his broad eyes, which resembled the petals of a lotus
                        flower. Knowing the minds and mental states of the fourfold assembly, he
                        said to King Attainment of Victory, ‘Great King, although the five
                        aggregates are insubstantial, childish ordinary beings think of them as
                        being substantial.<ref cRef="F.44.b"/> Great King, the aggregates look awful, smell
                        terrible, ooze pus and blood, are like wood, clods of dirt or roads, are
                        insubstantial, inert and interlinked with joy and sorrow. They are linked to
                        each other by chains of craving, are full of affliction, and are vile.
                        Still, ordinary beings think that such insubstantial things are substantial;
                        they think that impermanent things are permanent, repulsive things are
                        beautiful, unclean things are clean, and unreal things are real. Great King,
                        the five aggregates are <emph>painted</emph> by one’s own karma. For
                        example, O Great King, there is no painter who paints the peacock’s
                        five-colored tail, nor is there any paint involved either. Rather, it is
                        painted by the peacock’s own karma. Great King, in the same way, childish
                        ordinary beings arise from reciprocal conditions, painted by their own
                        karma.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-38"/>
                    <p tid="36">“At this point the bodhisattva great being Invincible Lord<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-39"> The Tibetan for this
                            bodhisattva’s name is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi pham dbang
                                phyug</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi
                                pham</foreign> translates the Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ajita</foreign>, which is an epithet typically
                            associated with Maitreya. It is therefore possible that the bodhisattva
                            mentioned here could be the well-known Maitreya.</note> stood up among
                        the assembly, circumambulated the Blessed One, draped his shawl over one
                        shoulder, knelt down on his right knee, and bowed with joined palms. Then he
                        spoke to the Blessed One, ‘Blessed One, these aggregates do look awful and
                        smell terrible; they ooze blood and pus; they are like wood, a clod of dirt,
                        a wall, or a road; they lack substance and are inert. Childish ordinary
                        beings think that these things have substance, but these beings are like the
                        mistaken, the blind, and the confused. They have fallen into bewilderment.
                        They are completely enveloped in darkness, obscurity, and veils. They are
                        lost in the dense thicket of all their wrong views. Blessed One, these four
                        collections of the Dharma are all profound; they are like space.  <ref cRef="F.45.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-40"/>
                    <p tid="37">‘Blessed One, will any beings ever come to understand
                        correctly the statements that are spoken in discourses such as this?’ </p>
                    
                    <p tid="38">“The blessed Arisen from Flowers answered the bodhisattva great
                        being, ‘Noble son, whenever bodhisattva great beings manifest, it will be in
                        order to purify beings. They teach them the Dharma in accordance with their
                        inclinations. They cut through the cravings of those who are tormented by
                        craving. They clear away the suffering of those tormented by pain. Knowing
                        all phenomena to be insubstantial and knowing them to be like space, they
                        direct sentient beings to the nature of phenomena. Bodhisattvas are then
                        known as purifiers of beings.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-42"/>
                    <p tid="39">“When the blessed, thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha Arisen from
                        Flowers had delivered this teaching concerning sentient beings, King
                        Attainment of Victory cut off his hair and beard. His son, as well as Queen
                        Ratnaśrī, and the retinue of queens and servants likewise all cut off their
                        hair and they all took ordination with the Blessed One. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-43"/>
                    <p tid="40">The Blessed One now spoke to the assembly, ‘Noble children, look at
                        the young prince. Noble children, this sublime being has produced roots of
                        virtue in the company of ninety nine trillion buddhas. On all of these
                        occasions he has become a Dharma preacher. And this person here has always
                        been the father of that sublime being. This sublime being has always ripened
                        beings to unsurpassed and perfect awakening. Noble children, as soon as I
                        pass into parinirvāṇa, the young prince Ratnākara will become a buddha. He
                        will be seated in front of the tree of awakening, which will be bedecked
                        with various precious stones. When he attains awakening, he will become a
                        thus-gone, worthy, perfect buddha.<ref cRef="F.45.b"/> He will be someone learned and
                        virtuous, a blissful one, a knower of the world, a charioteer who guides
                        beings, an unsurpassed being, a teacher of gods and humans, a blessed
                        buddha, known as Splendorous King of Shining Light. His world will be known
                        as Painted with Many Jewels. He will have an immeasurable saṅgha of hearers.
                        He will have a lifespan of ninety six trillion eons. The appearance of his
                        sacred Dharma will remain for seven million five hundred thousand
                        years.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-44"/>
                    <p tid="41">“Noble son, at the time when the prophecy concerning this
                        bodhisattva great being was spoken, eighty-four thousand beings gained
                        acceptance that phenomena are unborn. Noble son, should you wonder,
                        question, or have doubts regarding the identity of the Thus-Gone One of that
                        time, there is no need. Why so? Noble son, the thus-gone, worthy, perfect
                        buddha Amitābha was known at that time as the thus-gone Arisen from Flowers
                        and he taught the Dharma in that world. Noble son, should you wonder,
                        question, or have doubts regarding the identity of the prince known as
                        Ratnākara at that time, there is no need. Why so? Noble son, the bodhisattva
                        Avalokiteśvara was at that time the son of King Attainment of Victory. That
                        Thus-Gone One prophesied, ‘He will gain awakening from me.’”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-45"/>
                    <p tid="42">The bodhisattva great being Delighted by Victory, who was among the
                        retinue, now joined his palms and spoke to the Blessed One, “Blessed One,
                        beings who have not produced roots of virtue will never even hear this
                        Dharma teaching.<ref cRef="F.46.a"/> So why even speak about them committing it to
                        writing, commissioning it to be written, retaining it, reciting it, or
                        offering flowers, incense, and incense powder to it?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-46"/>
                    <p tid="43">The Blessed One replied to the bodhisattva great being Delighted by
                        Victory, “Noble son, only those who have served as many buddhas as there are
                        grains of sand in the Ganges river will come across this discourse. Noble
                        son, those sentient beings who hear this Dharma teaching and do not doubt it
                        will be reborn in the realm of Sukhāvatī after they die and pass from this
                        world. Noble son, any place where this discourse is kept will become worthy
                        of homage. Noble son, later, in the future, any woman who holds or reads
                        aloud this Dharma teaching will exchange her female body and be reborn in
                        the realm of Sukhāvatī. That will be her last birth as a female. She will,
                        moreover, behold the thus-gone Amitābha at the moment of death.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-47"/>
                    <p tid="44">Once the Blessed One had spoken, the bodhisattva great being
                        Delighted by Victory, the other bodhisattvas, the monks, and the rest of the
                        assembly, along with the world with its gods, humans, demigods, and
                        gandharvas all rejoiced and praised what the Blessed One had said. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="45">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-48"/>
                    <p tid="46">This concludes <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Vehicle Sūtra
                            entitled Distinguishing Between Phenomena and Reality</title>. </p>
                    
                    <p tid="47">It was translated, edited, and finalized by the Indian scholars
                        Jinamitra and Dānaśila, as well as the chief editor and translator venerable
                        Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="48">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head tid="49" type="abbreviations">Abbreviations</head>
            
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-005-50">
                        <abbr>BHSD</abbr>
                        <expan>Franklin Edgerton, <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid
                            Sanskrit Dictionary</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-005-51">
                        <abbr>Negi</abbr>
                        <expan>J. S. Negi, <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit
                            Dictionary</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="50">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-52">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos dang don rnam par ’byed pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                        (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­dharmārtha­vibhāga­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 247, Degé Kangyur vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios
                        42b5–46a7.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-53">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos dang don rnam par ’byed pa ces bya
                            ba thegs pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Stok no. 116, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</title>, vol. 64 (mdo sde, pa),
                        folios 349a4-354b4.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-54">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos dang don rnam par ’byed pa zhes bya
                            ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative
                        Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’
                        bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China
                        Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe
                        skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 66, pp.
                        117–27.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-55">Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary 2: Dictionary</title>.
                        Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-56">Herrmann-Pfandt, Adelheid. <title xml:lang="de">Die lHan kar ma: ein früher Katalog der ins
                            Tibetische übersetzten buddhistischen Texte</title>. Wien: Verlag der österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-57">Lang, Karen C. (1986). <title xml:lang="en">Āryadeva’s Catuḥśataka: On the Bodhisattva’s Cultivation of Merit and
                            Knowledge</title>. Copenhagen: Akademisk Forlag, 1986.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-58">Lang, Karen C. (2003). <title xml:lang="en">Four Illusions, Candrakīrti’s Advice to Travelers on the Bodhisattva
                            Path</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-59">Nattier, Jan. “Gender and Enlightenment:
                        Sexual Transformation in Mahāyāna Sūtras.” Unpublished manuscript,
                        University of Indiana, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-60">Negi, J. S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit Dictionary</title>. 16 vols. Sarnath, Varanasi:
                        Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies, 1993–2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-005-61">Skilling, Peter. “Notes on the
                        Bhadrakalpika-sūtra.” <title xml:lang="en">Annual Report of the
                            International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology at Soka
                            University</title> XIII (March 2010): 195–229.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-62">
        <term>five aggregates</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phung po lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུང་པོ་ལྔ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcaskandha</term>
        <term type="definition">The constituents of a human being: form, feeling, perception,
            formation, and consciousness.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-63">
        <term>acceptance that phenomena are unborn</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi skye ba’i chos la bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་སྐྱེ་བའི་ཆོས་ལ་བཟོད་པ།</term>
        
          <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anutpattika­dharma­kṣānti</term>
        <term type="definition">The realization that all phenomena are beyond birth.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-64">
        <term>four errors</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyin ci log bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིན་ཅི་ལོག་བཞི།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturo viparyāsā</term>
        <term type="definition">Taking what is impermanent to be permanent, what is painful to be
          delightful, what is unclean to be clean, and what is no self to be a self.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-65">
        <term>nāga</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
        <term type="definition">A semidivine class of beings who live in subterranean aquatic
          environments and who are known to hoard wealth and esoteric teachings. They are associated
          with snakes and serpents.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-66">
        <term>yakṣa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod spyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྤྱིན།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
        <term type="definition">A class of beings belonging to the realm of Kubera, the god of
          wealth.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-67">
        <term>gandharva</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
        <term type="definition">Lower class of divine being, under the control of the Guardian King
          of the East. Capable of flight, they are often described as “celestial musicians.”</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-68">
        <term>demigod</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
        <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the devas (gods) who are frequently
          portrayed in the Brahmanical mythology as having a disruptive effect on cosmological and
          social harmony.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-69">
        <term>garuḍa </term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
        <term type="definition">Lower class of divine being,described as an eagle-type bird with a
          gigantic wing span. They were traditionally enemies of the nāgas. In the Vedas, they were
          thought to have brought nectar from the heavens to earth.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-70">
        <term>kiṃnara</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
        <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings that resemble humans to the degree that
          their very name—which means “Is that a man?”—suggests some confusion as to their divine
          status.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-71">
        <term>mahoraga</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
        <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
        <term type="definition">A class of serpentine non-human beings.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-72">
        <term>trichiliocosm</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum </term>
        <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
        <term type="definition">A universe containing one billion worlds.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-73">
        <term>parinirvāṇa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parinirvāṇa</term>
        <term type="definition">The final stage of passing into nirvāṇa, which occurs when a worthy
          one or a buddha passes away.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-74">
        <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
        <term type="definition">An important benefactor of Buddha Śakyamuni.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-75">
        <term>Delighted by Victory</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bas dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བས་དགའ།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">The bodhisattva to whom this sūtra is spoken.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-76">
        <term>Arisen from Flowers</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog las byung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་ལས་བྱུང་བ།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">A former buddha, who presently is Buddha Amitābha.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-77">
        <term>Attainment of Victory</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal ba thob pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བ་ཐོབ་པ།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">The ruler of the world Flower Origin.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-78">
        <term>Ratnaśrī</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་དཔལ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnaśrī</term>
        <term type="definition">The queen of King Attainment of Victory.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-79">
        <term>Ratnākara</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’byung gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་གནས།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnākara</term>
        <term type="definition">The son of King Attainment of Victory.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-80">
        <term>Invincible Lord </term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi pham dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་ཕམ་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
        
        <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the assembly of the buddha Arisen from
          Flowers.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-81">
        <term>Splendorous King of Shining Light</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od zer kun nas mngon ’phags dpal brtsegs rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་ཟེར་ཀུན་ནས་མངོན་འཕགས་དཔལ་བརྩེགས་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">The name of Prince Ratnākara once he attains awakening.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-82">
        <term>Amitābha</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od dpag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་དཔག་མེད།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amitābha</term>
        <term type="definition">The buddha residing in the western buddha realm Sukhāvatī.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-83">
        <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
        <term type="definition">One of the main bodhisattva disciples of Buddha Śākyamuni, praised
          for his compassion.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-84">
        <term>Jinamitra</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dzi na mi tra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛི་ན་མི་ཏྲ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jinamitra</term>
        <term type="definition">An Indian Kashmiri paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet during the late
          eighth and early ninth centuries. He worked with several Tibetan translators on the
          translation of a number of sūtras.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-85">
        <term>Dānaśīla</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dA na shI la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཱ་ན་ཤཱི་ལ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dānaśīla</term>
        <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍita who was resident in Tibet during the late eighth
          and early ninth centuries.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-86">
        <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
        
        
        <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late eighth and
          early ninth centuries.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-87">
        <term>Śākyamuni </term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya thub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་ཐུབ་པ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyamuni </term>
        <term type="definition">The buddha of this age; the historical buddha.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-88">
        <term>Jeta Grove</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jetavana</term>
        <term type="definition">The park donated to the Buddha by Anāthapiṇḍada.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-89">
        <term>Śrāvastī</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrāvastī</term>
        <term type="definition">The capital of the ancient Kosala kingdom in India during the
          sixth–fifth centuries <hi rend="small-caps">bce</hi>.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-90">
        <term>Painted with Many Jewels</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun nas rin po ches yang dag par bris pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ནས་རིན་པོ་ཆེས་ཡང་དག་པར་བྲིས་པ།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">The buddha realm in which Prince Ratnākara will attain
          awakening.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-91">
        <term>Flower Origin</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me tog gi ’byung gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཏོག་གི་འབྱུང་གནས།</term>
        
        <term type="definition">The buddha realm of the Buddha Arisen from Flowers.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
    <item>
      <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-005-92">
        <term>Sukhāvatī</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bde ba can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདེ་བ་ཅན།</term>
        
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhāvatī</term>
        <term type="definition">The buddha realm, located in the western direction, in which Buddha
          Amitābha resides.</term>
      </gloss>
    </item>
  </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>