<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’i snying po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའི་སྙིང་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Ākāśagarbha Sūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ནམ་མཁའི་སྙིང་པོ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa nam mkha’i snying po zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Ākāśa­garbha Sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryākāśa­garbha­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-27" role="translatorMain">
                    Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division)
                    <lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-179">Jampa Tenzin</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-181">Ngawang Tenzin</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-182"/>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-184"/>
                <editor role="mainEditor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-245"/>
                <editor role="mainEditor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-246"/>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.11 <date>2014 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-066-018"/>
                <date>2014-01-13</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh260" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 260</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol 66 (mdo sde, za), folios 264.a–283.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śākyaprabha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Ratnarakṣita</author>
                    <location count-pages="40">
                        <start volume="66" page="529"/>
                        <end volume="66" page="568"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11912" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 16/01/2019 at 10:34:52 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- COULD NOT FIND THESE TERMS IN THE TEXT: 
        <gloss><term xml:id="UT22084-066-018-te40">maṇḍala</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkyil ’khor</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maṇḍala</term>
        <term type="definition">circle or orb</term>
   </gloss>-->
    <!--<gloss><term xml:id="UT22084-066-018-te60">stūpa</term>
        <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten</term>
        <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
        <term type="definition">A Buddhist monument and reliquary representing the enlightened mind of a buddha.  </term>
   </gloss>-->
    <!-- <gloss><term xml:id="UT22084-066-018-pe11">Maheśvara</term>
        <name xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug chen po </name>
        <name xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maheśvara</name>
        <name type="definition">Literally, “Great Lord.” Name of Śiva </name>
   </gloss>-->
    <!--    Contents
    Summary
    Acknowledgments
    Introduction
    The Translation
    The Ākāśagarbha Sūtra
    Notes
    Bibliography-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="204">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-1"/>
                <p tid="1">While the Buddha is dwelling on Khalatika Mountain with his retinue, an amazing display of light
                    appears, brought about by the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha’s liberating activities. As he joins the gathering,
                    Ākāśagarbha manifests another extraordinary display, and the Buddha, praising his inconceivable
                    accomplishments and activities, explains how to invoke his blessings. He sets out the <term>fundamental
                        transgressions</term> of rulers, ministers, śrāvakas, and beginner bodhisattvas, and, after explaining in
                    detail how to conduct the rituals of purification, encourages those who have committed such transgressions to
                    turn to Ākāśagarbha. When people pray to Ākāśagarbha, Ākāśagarbha adapts his manifestations to suit their
                    needs, appearing to them while they are awake, in their dreams, or at the time of their death. In this way,
                    Ākāśagarbha gradually leads them all along the path, helping them to purify their negative deeds, relieve
                    their sufferings, fulfill their wishes, and eventually attain perfect enlightenment.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="205">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This sūtra was translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group, International Buddhist Academy
                    Division. The text was translated into English by the monastic scholars Jampa Tenzin and Ngawang Tenzin, and
                    by Christian Bernert and Julia C. Stenzel. It was edited by Pamela Gayle White and Vivian Paganuzzi. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="206">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="207">Ākāśagarbha, the Bodhisattva “Essence of Space”</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">Ākāśagarbha features among the so-called Eight Close Sons of the Buddha, who are regarded as the
                        principal bodhisattvas in the Buddha’s retinue, the other seven being Mañjuśrī, Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi,
                        Kṣitigarbha, Sarva­nivaraṇa­viṣkambhin, Maitreya, and Samantabhadra. Each bodhisattva fulfills a
                        particular role for the benefit of beings, Ākāśagarbha’s being that of helping them to purify themselves
                        from the results of their negative actions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The name Ākāśagarbha may be rendered in English as “Essence (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garbha</foreign>)<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-273" index="1">The term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garbha</foreign> can refer to different things, depending on the context. Womb,
                            embryo, heart, and essence are all possible translations. Historically, Tibetans opted for the
                            translation <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snying po</foreign>, which has the connotation of being an
                            essence or the heart of a matter. For a discussion of this term see Zimmermann (2002), p 40-41.
                        </note> of Space (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ākāśa</foreign>).” To understand his name, it is useful to
                        consider the concept of space in Buddhist thought. In early Buddhist theory, space is non-obstruction, the
                        lack of matter allowing for the unhindered movement of the four great elements of earth, water, fire, and
                        air. Space is also non-obstructible due to its omnipresence and its eternal nature. Apart from being the
                        mere absence of obstruction, it is also counted as one of the three unconditioned dharmas or phenomena in
                        this world, the other two being the two types of cessation.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-274" index="2">
                            <abbr>LVP</abbr> (1923), p 7-8. </note> In the Pāli <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Mahāparinibbānasutta</title>,
                        space is presented as the actual foundation for all other elements of existence.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-275" index="3">See <ref target="https://www.accesstoinsight.org/ati/tipitaka/dn/dn.16.1-6.vaji.html">www.accesstoinsight.org</ref>.</note> We can understand, therefore, the prominent position that
                        space holds among the elements of existence, and it is an equally prominent position that the bodhisattva
                        Ākāśagarbha holds among his peers, his presence outshining everything else in the world, everything except
                        the buddhas themselves. Just as space is the unlimited capacity to accommodate the entirety of phenomenal
                        existence, so Ākāśagarbha possesses countless inconceivable qualities to benefit sentient beings. As the
                        embodiment of non-obstruction, he helps beings remove obstacles from the path to awakening, in particular
                        the obstacles caused by their own misdeeds, by making them disclose their transgressions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">Due to his relation to space and the purification of negative deeds, Ākāśagarbha has become closely
                        associated with Buddha Vairocana, one of the principal figures in the Buddhist tantric traditions, whose
                        main function is the purification of negativities in general, and in particular those of the deceased. It
                        is particularly in the tantric traditions of China and Japan that Ākāśagarbha has become an important
                        figure of worship.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-276" index="4">For a discussion of
                            Ākāśagarbha’s role in the Buddhist tantric traditions and his relation to Mahāvairocana, see de Visser
                            (1931), p 11-16. </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="208">The text of the Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">In his work on Ākāśagarbha in China and Japan (unfortunately unfinished), M. W. de Visser gives a
                        comprehensive list of texts related to this bodhisattva.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-277" index="5">de Visser (1931), p 17-18. </note> The first among them to appear in
                        Chinese was the <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra on the Bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha</title>, translated by
                        Buddhayaśas between 403 and 413 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. This is the earliest version of the text we have, for the Sanskrit is
                        no longer extant. </p>
                    <p tid="8">The Chinese version of this text differs significantly from the Tibetan translation found in the
                            Kangyur.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-278" index="6">de Visser (1931), p 18-27, gives an
                            extensive summary of the Chinese version of this sūtra. For a German translation from the Korean and
                            Chinese, see Tarchin and Lindmayer (2010). </note> Although the basic content of both texts is the
                        same, their structures are very different and the Chinese contains numerous passages not found in the
                        Tibetan, and vice versa.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-279" index="7">The Chinese text, for
                            instance, contains a part of the prologue that the Tibetan does not have. Conversely, in the
                            discussion of the eight fundamental trans‌gressions for beginner bodhisattvas, the Tibetan text
                            presents the measures to be taken to purify one’s negative deeds right after the explanation of the
                            first transgression, an explanation we do not find in this place in the Chinese version. </note> It is
                        justifiable, therefore, to speak of two different versions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-7"/>
                    <p tid="9">The Tibetan text was prepared by the Indian paṇḍita Śākyaprabha and the Tibetan monk Ratnarakṣita,
                        probably in the 9th century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-280" index="8">Ratnarakṣita is
                            mentioned in the preamble to the early ninth century translation manual, the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title>, while Śākyaprabha is known to have also worked in
                            collaboration with the translator/editor Yeshé Dé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde</foreign>)
                            who flourished around the turn of the 9th century (see for instance Toh. <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-090-002.html">558</ref>, 559, 562, and <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-090-007.html">563</ref>). </note> But even though
                        the Kangyur contains only one <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>, we do have alternative
                        translations of some of its passages. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> by Śāntideva, of
                        which the Sanskrit has survived as well as its translation into Tibetan, quotes extensively from the
                            sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-281" index="9">For a translation of the relevant
                            passages see Bendall and Rouse (1922), p 61ff. The extensive quotes from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title> found in the Tibetan version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣā­samuccaya</title>, however, are not identical to the corresponding passages from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title> included in the Kangyur. As both translations were
                            produced around the same time, they were either prepared independently from each other, or the former
                            represents some kind of heavily revised edition of the latter. Interestingly, the editor-in-chief of
                            the translation of Śāntideva’s work was Yeshé Dé who, as mentioned above, also worked with
                            Śākyaprabha, one of the translators of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="209">Key points of the Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-8"/>
                    <p tid="10">The sūtra is widely known in the Tibetan Buddhist community, at least by name. This stems from the
                        fact that it is mentioned in Śāntideva’s celebrated and widely studied <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra</title> (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems pa’i spyod pa la ’jug
                            pa</title>). In the fifth chapter on “Guarding Alertness,” Śāntideva advises the reader to study the
                        sūtras, beginning with the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>, in order to learn about
                        the training.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-282" index="10">
                            <abbr>BCA</abbr> V.104. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-9"/>
                    <p tid="11">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title> is a Mahāyāna sūtra that emphasizes
                        spiritual practice. It thus can be said to have a strong affinity with the so-called meditative
                        concentration Mahāyāna sūtras, of which the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgama­samādhi­sūtra</title> is a
                        prominent representative. Our text indeed repeatedly mentions the <term>meditative concentration of brave
                            progression</term> (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūraṃgama­samādhi</foreign>) of the
                        bodhisattvas abiding on the tenth bodhisattva ground.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-283" index="11">Surprisingly, this sūtra is specifically referred to in our text, a
                            reference we do not find in the corresponding portions quoted in Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣā­samuccaya</title>. It is possibly an addition by the translators of our text, who happen to
                            be the same as the ones responsible for the Tibetan rendering of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṅgama­samādhi­sūtra</title>, namely Śākyaprabha and Ratnarakṣita.</note> Furthermore, in the
                        discussion of the transgressions of beginner bodhisattvas, among other corrupt habits the confinement of
                        monks’ practice to the mere recitation of scriptures is criticized. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">The main topic of this sūtra, however, is not <term type="ignore">meditation</term> but faith in
                        and devotion to a bodhisattva as a means of purification. Because the principal activity of Ākāśagarbha,
                        as mentioned above, is the removal of obstructions on the path to awakening, followers are strongly
                        advised to generate pure faith in him. It is this faith, supported by the devotional practices of worship
                        and offering, that will invoke his presence and blessings. Once invoked, the bodhisattva will help
                        devotees according to their capacities and inclinations by first making them disclose their negative
                        actions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">This practice of disclosure or confession of negative deeds is regarded as a fundamental element
                        of Buddhist practice. Essential for the purification of the mind, it forms the third part of the
                        seven-limbed practice, a preliminary practice recited daily by most practitioners in the Tibetan
                            tradition.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-284" index="12">There are many versions of this
                            seven-limbed practice, the most famous being taken from the <title xml:lang="en">Aspirations of
                                Samanta­bhadra</title> (Tib. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang spyod smon lam</title> Toh. 1095 ).</note> The
                        seven limbs are: paying homage to the buddhas, presenting them with offerings, disclosing one’s negative
                        deeds, rejoicing in the positive deeds of all beings, requesting the Dharma, supplicating the enlightened
                        ones to remain with us, and dedicating all virtues to the benefit of sentient beings. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">But what precisely are those negative actions that are to be disclosed by the followers of the
                        Buddha? In this sūtra, the Buddha himself gives the answer to this question: they are the transgressions
                        (Tib. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ltung ba</foreign>; Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āpatti</foreign>), also referred to as <distinct>downfalls</distinct>. The so-called
                            <distinct>downfalls</distinct> are violations of vows or principles of conduct specific to different
                        kinds of Buddhist followers. In Buddhism, vows are forms of spiritual commitment taken to ensure steady
                        progress on the path. They are the “practical applications and outcomes of different Buddhist
                            theories.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-285" index="13">Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé (2003), p
                            22.</note> Thus, transgressions are not actions judged as morally objectionable by some higher
                        authority; rather, they are actions of body, speech, and mind that result in a serious impediment on the
                        spiritual path of the one who commits them. They cause one to ‘fall from’ the path to awakening, so to
                        speak, and in the worst cases fall to the lower realms of existence. These transgressions need to be
                        disclosed and purified at the very outset of the path, and helping people do so is precisely the expertise
                        of Ākāśagarbha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">An individual enters the Mahāyāna when he or she produces bodhicitta, the resolve to attain
                        buddhahood for the sake of all sentient beings.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-286" index="14">For an extensive study of this concept see Wangchuk (2007). </note> Thus, the first step in the
                        training is the production of this intention, called the <distinct>bodhicitta of aspiration </distinct>,
                        which is later followed by active engagement in the path, called <distinct>applied
                            bodhicitta</distinct>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-287" index="15">This distinction is
                            famously attested by Śāntideva in his <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryāvatāra</title>
                            (I.15).</note> In the detailed explanation of the training in <term>applied bodhicitta</term> found in
                        Sakya Paṇḍita’s <title xml:lang="en">Elucidation of the Sage’s Intent</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub pa dgongs gsal</title>), the author explains the cause of its arising, the way to cultivate the
                        conditions conducive to its increase, and the methods for preventing its decline.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-288" index="16">See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub pa’i dgongs pa rab tu gsal
                                ba</title>, F.16.a - F.17.a.</note> It is in the latter section that he mentions the
                            <term>fundamental transgressions</term> listed in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>. They are the transgressions committed by rulers, politicians, and
                        śrāvakas, or disciples, and, in particular, those of beginner bodhisattvas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-289" index="17">The terms used in the sūtra are: kṣatriya, ministers, śrāvakas, and
                            beginner bodhisattvas. For a clear and brief presentation of these vows, see Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé
                            (2003), p 176-179.</note> This entire list, excluding the śrāvakas’ transgressions, became a prominent
                        feature of the Mahāyāna training known as <distinct>the fourteen fundamental
                            trans‌gressions</distinct>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-290" index="18">It should be
                            noted here that the presentation of the fourteen fundamental trans‌gressions may vary depending on the
                            different teaching traditions. According to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>,
                            the complete list comprises five transgressions for kṣatriyas (or kings), five for ministers, and
                            eight for beginner bodhisattvas. Since four of the ministers’ transgressions are the same as four of
                            the kṣatriyas’ transgressions, there is a total of fourteen different fundamental
                            trans‌gressions.</note> As the text is commonly studied in all Tibetan Buddhist schools, authors of
                        all lineages refer to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title> as the source for
                        understanding the bodhisattva transgressions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-291" index="19">See
                            Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé (2003), p 176, and Ngari Panchen (1996), p 84.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">The sūtra mentions the following list of transgressions:</p>
                    <list type="section">
                        <item>
                            <list type="bullet">
                                <head type="list" tid="177">a) For kṣatriya rulers:</head>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="178">1. Stealing from a place of worship or the saṅgha, or inciting others to do so.
                                    </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="182">2. Forcing others to give up the Dharma and creating obstacles for the
                                        teachings.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="183">3. Forcing monastics to give up their monastic robes and abusing them. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="184">4. Committing any of the five heinous deeds.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="185">5. Advocating the philosophy of the non-existence of causality.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <list type="bullet">
                                <head type="list" tid="179">b) For ministers:</head>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="186">1. Stealing from a place of worship or the saṅgha. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="187">2. Destroying a village, district, or town.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="188">3. Forcing others to give up the Dharma and creating obstacles for the
                                        teachings.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="189">4. Harming monastics by taking away their robes, punishing, or even killing them.
                                    </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="190">5. Committing any of the five heinous deeds.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <list type="bullet">
                                <head type="list" tid="180">c) For śrāvakas:</head>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="191">1. Killing.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="192">2. Taking what is not given.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="193">3. Impure conduct.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="194">4. Lying.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="195">5. Harming a buddha.</p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <list type="bullet">
                                <head type="list" tid="181">d) For beginner bodhisattvas:</head>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="196">1. Teaching the profound Dharma of emptiness to spiritually immature people.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="197">2. Discouraging people from practicing the Mahāyāna path.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="198">3. Discouraging people from practicing the vinaya of individual liberation.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="199">4. Disparaging the śrāvaka path, saying it obstructs one from attaining
                                        enlightenment and from eradicating the afflictions.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="200">5. Praising oneself and lying out of jealousy and for the sake of gain and
                                        honor.</p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="201">6. Deceiving others, claiming one has realized the profound teachings on
                                        emptiness when one has not. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="202">7. Causing fines to be imposed on monastics and offering the bribes received to
                                        the kṣatriyas. </p>
                                </item>
                                <item>
                                    <p tid="203">8. Causing monastics to abandon their contemplative training and diverting
                                        offerings intended for contemplative monastics to benefit monastics engaged in mere
                                        recitation practice. </p>
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">A special feature of this sūtra, and quite a unique one, is the mention of dream-inducing
                            practices.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-292" index="20">On the significance of dreams in
                            general in Mahāyāna sūtras see Harrison (2003).</note> Similar practices are known to students of
                        Tibetan Buddhism familiar with the techniques commonly known as dream yoga, but they are fairly rare in
                        non-tantric Mahāyāna contexts.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-293" index="21">The Chinese
                            ‘version’ of our text was produced at the very beginning of the 5th century, which means that the
                            original predates any major influence from the tantric traditions.</note> In this context, the purpose
                        of dream-inducing practice is for those who failed to meet Ākāśagarbha in the waking state to produce a
                        dream encounter with the bodhisattva in order to disclose their transgressions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-16"/>
                    <p tid="18">Finally, another recurring theme throughout this sūtra is the use of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇīs</foreign>. This term has at least two distinct meanings in this text alone:
                        on the one hand, a mystical formula to be repeated with the aim of fulfilling certain worldly and
                        spiritual wishes, whether for oneself or others, and, on the other, a state of unfailing memory that
                        bodhisattvas attain on the higher levels of realization. But the mention of dhāraṇīs does not imply an
                        influence of tantric Buddhism on this text. Dhāraṇīs are used frequently in early Mahāyāna scriptures
                        predating the emergence of tantra in Buddhism.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-294" index="22">On
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</foreign> see Davidson (2009).</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="210">Conclusions</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-17"/>
                    <p tid="19">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra </title>can be understood as a devotional Mahāyāna
                        text, devotion being a skillful means on the path to awakening in Buddhism. The text was eminently
                        important in China and Japan, where the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha became a major figure of veneration, and
                        in the Tibetan tradition, where it served as a primary source for the list of bodhisattva transgressions.
                        The sūtra predates the emergence of the tantric Buddhist movement in India, but nevertheless contains
                        certain elements that gained in importance and were further developed in Vajrayāna Buddhism. </p>
                    <p tid="20">Ākāśagarbha is the essence, the womb of space. Limitless, he provides beings with whatever they
                        need; knowing no obstacles, he removes whatever may hinder them from seeing reality.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="211">The Translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-18"/>
                    <p tid="21">For this work, the translators relied on the version in the Degé Kangyur, supported by those in
                        the Peking and Narthang Kangyurs with the help of the comparative edition of the Kangyur (see <ptr target="#bibliography">bibliography</ptr>). Whenever confronted with problematic or difficult
                        passages, we discussed the variants with the Tibetan scholars we worked with to select the reading most
                        likely to be correct. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-19"/>
                    <p tid="22">The task of translation inevitably coincides with the task of interpretation, and any translation
                        will be only one of the possible readings of the text. In this case, the task was rendered difficult by
                        the many obscure and somewhat esoteric verses the sūtra contains. With the resources at our disposal, we
                        have tried our best to understand and translate those lines; but the clarity we have aimed for in the
                        resulting English verses does not reflect the ambiguous nature of the Tibetan text, cryptic in many
                        places. We apologize for all instances where we did not do it justice. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-20"/>
                    <p tid="23">Specialized terminology, such as the types of beings present in the Buddha’s audience as well as
                        certain technical terms, is given in Sanskrit when we thought that no English rendering would convey the
                        exact meaning. The Tibetan version of the sūtra also contains a number of dhāraṇīs in transliterated
                        Sanskrit, and like the Tibetan translators we have left them as they are. In the process of trying to
                        reconstruct their most correct Sanskrit reading, we faced many problems despite the assistance of a
                        Sanskrit expert. Solving them would entail a separate research project, well beyond the scope of the
                        present translation work.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="212">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="213">The Noble Mahāyāna</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="214">Ākāśagarbha Sūtra</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-21"/>
                    <p tid="24">
                        <ref cRef="F.264.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-22"/>
                    <p tid="25">Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling on the Khalatika Mountain, in the
                            <term>abode of the Sage’s hermits</term>, together with an incalculably large assembly of monks and of
                        great śrāvakas. Great bodhisattva mahāsattvas in numbers as limitless as the sands of the River Ganges,
                        forming an incalculably immense assembly of bodhisattvas, were also staying there. The moment the Bhagavān
                        completed his prophecy on the splendid vows of the tathāgatas, the Indranīla jewel<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-295" index="23">The Indranīla Jewel is also translated as jewel of Indra, or
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cintāmaṇi</foreign>. According to de Visser (1931), p 19,
                            translating from the Sanskrit, the cintāmaṇi is the main jewel appearing on Ākāśagarbha’s head: “At
                            that moment the multitude assembled around Śākyamuni saw the brilliant light of Ākāśagarbha’s
                            cintāmaṇi (nyoi-hōju) surrounded by numberless Śakrābhilagna (shakabiryōga) pearls, appearing in the
                            West and superseding all other lights except that of Śākyamuni.” See also Tharchin and Lindmayer
                            (2010: 51).</note> appeared in the west. Many hundreds of thousands of precious wish-fulfilling jewels
                        spread out and surrounded it. <ref cRef="F.264.b"/> The light of that precious jewel rendered invisible
                        the totality of manifest form in the whole trichiliocosm. Thus, with the exception of the tathāgatas, all
                        gods and humans, śrāvakas, and bodhisattvas, as well as the manifest forms of the great elements of earth,
                        water, fire, and air—however many manifestations there were of the great elements—all without exception
                        were obliterated, and only the precious jewel remained visible. Everything appeared to be limitless,
                        boundless, and ineffable like space. The Bhagavān, too, became most radiant, clear, and brilliant.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-296" index="24">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lham me lhan ne lhang nge</foreign>. This expression refers to the body,
                            speech, and mind of the Buddha. The body is described as radiant; the speech is clear and unconfused;
                            and the mind is brilliant, serene, peaceful, and compassionate.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-23"/>
                    <p tid="26">Indeed, the sentient beings assembled there could not even see themselves, or each other. For
                        them, all visible manifestations of the great elements also ceased and became imperceptible to the eye.
                        They could not perceive their bodies, their features,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-297" index="25">
                            <abbr>Y</abbr> and <abbr>P</abbr> have <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshan ma</foreign>,
                            which has the additional meaning of “gender of a person.”</note> or shape, nor did they have a sense
                        of touch.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-298" index="26">
                            <abbr>D</abbr> reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa</foreign> (mind), <abbr>P</abbr>
                            reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">reg pa</foreign> (touch).</note> Whatever they observed,
                        howsoever they observed it, they saw as empty. They did not even see the orbs of the sun or the moon. The
                        stars and the earth element, water element, fire element, and air element also became invisible to their
                        eyes. Sounds did not resonate in their ears. Odors were not perceived by their noses. They did not take
                        their minds and their mental events as “me,” or take them as “mine,” and the perceptions of the six
                        cognitive bases did not arise. The great elements were also imperceptible.</p>
                    <p tid="27">Instead, in whichever direction they looked, in all those directions they saw everything as the
                        physical marks, colors, shapes, and bodies of the tathāgatas. Only the precious Indranīla encircled by
                        wish-fulfilling jewels appeared from afar; apart from that, nothing at all was visible. <ref cRef="F.265.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-24"/>
                    <p tid="28"> At that place, the bodhisattvas dwelling on the tenth ground, who had achieved the
                            <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>, and who were bound by one more life and in
                        their last existence, looked and saw, yet were not at all frightened, afraid, or terrified, because they
                        realized that all phenomena are by nature endowed with final reality, suchness, and emptiness. Therefore,
                        they were not at all frightened, afraid, or terrified.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-25"/>
                    <p tid="29">The remaining great bodhisattva mahāsattvas, the śrāvakas, devas, nāgas, yakṣas, gandharvas,
                        asuras, garuḍas, kiṃnaras, mahoragas, kumbhāṇḍas, pretas, piśācas, pūtanas, kaṭapūtanas—all of the
                        assembled humans and non-humans—were very frightened and in despair. They were bewildered about what was
                        here and what was there, and in their confusion they were not able to perceive one another. In that state,
                        they asked questions such as “What is this?”, “How did this come about?”, and “What is the nature of
                        this?”, but could find nothing.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-26"/>
                    <p tid="30">At that time, the great bodhisattva mahāsattva known as Great Nail of Brahmā bowed down toward the
                        Bhagavān with folded hands and said:</p>
                    <lg tid="31">
                        <l>“Ordinary beings do not recognize</l>
                        <l>The nature of all phenomena. </l>
                        <l>They live in the form aggregate, </l>
                        <l>And so their six sense faculties become deluded. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="32">
                        <l>There is not a single aggregate to be seen, </l>
                        <l>Yet ordinary beings conceptualize the form aggregate. </l>
                        <l>Consequently, some of these people</l>
                        <l>Develop doubts about the Buddha’s teaching. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-27"/>
                    <lg tid="33">
                        <l>It is for them that the Bhagavān</l>
                        <l>Taught the characteristics of the suchness of phenomena. </l>
                        <l>Thus, here and there </l>
                        <l>They come to know the characteristics of space, which bears everything. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>This indeed is brave equipoise, <ref cRef="F.265.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>A state that cannot be expressed. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-28"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>“A most precious wish-fulfilling jewel</l>
                        <l>Rests on the crown of his head.</l>
                        <l>Those who perceive a precious Indranīla jewel from afar</l>
                        <l>Are very fortunate beings:</l>
                        <l>They will perfect the brave progression.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-29"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>“All who have come to see the Teacher are wise indeed. </l>
                        <l>Today in this place, a profound discourse</l>
                        <l>Will undoubtedly be proclaimed. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-30"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>“O Bhagavān, please give relief</l>
                        <l>To the sentient beings who have come here.</l>
                        <l>Bringing them to full maturation</l>
                        <l>Is the heroes’ sphere of activity.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-31"/>
                    <p tid="38">The Bhagavān replied: </p>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>“It is just as you have said.</l>
                        <l>The place where the all-basis is heard,</l>
                        <l>And where, with wisdom, sentient beings are established, </l>
                        <l>That place is the sphere of activity of meditative concentration.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-32"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“It is the sphere of activity </l>
                        <l>Of the Bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha,</l>
                        <l>Who has demonstrated the meditative concentration free of appearances </l>
                        <l>And free of proliferations.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-33"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“Whoever is attached to the two views</l>
                        <l>Will later be in a realm of delusion. </l>
                        <l>Attachment to eternalism and nihilism </l>
                        <l>Is utter delusion about here and there.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-34"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>“Those who wish to free themselves </l>
                        <l>Completely from both of these views</l>
                        <l>Should meditate on that which is inexpressible,</l>
                        <l>Thereby swiftly attaining the grounds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-35"/>
                    <p tid="43">“Listen well, companions: for bodhisattva mahāsattvas who are beginners one must explain the six
                        perfections with a reference point, with the notion that suchness is expressible. That is to say, they
                        must understand the nature of the great elements to be arising and perishing. Only then should they
                        familiarize themselves with the idea that all phenomena are in essence inexpressible, non-arising,
                        non-ceasing, not perceptible, and not in the slightest way existing.</p>
                    <p tid="44">“Thus will they definitively abandon eternalism and nihilism, and they will not be at all
                        frightened or terrified. Once they have ceased to relate to phenomena with attachment, <ref cRef="F.266.a"/> they will swiftly perfect the six perfections and henceforth not remain in either nihilism or
                        eternalism.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-36"/>
                    <p tid="45">No sooner had the Bhagavān spoken than all those assembled in the retinue saw the manifestations
                        in the same way they had previously seen, heard, understood, and known them. Thereupon, extending his
                        right arm, the Bhagavān proclaimed: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-37"/>
                    <p tid="46">“The bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha’s meditative concentration is like an ocean. This
                        bodhisattva’s training is like Mount Meru, his primordial wisdom like space, his vigor like wind, and his
                        tolerance like a vajra. He is like a supreme victory banner among all bodhisattvas. For voyagers to
                        nirvāṇa, he is like a captain. He is like a treasure of all the roots of virtue. For all who suffer, he is
                        like a wishing vase; for those engulfed in darkness, like the sun; for those who have lost their way, like
                        the moon; for the frightened, like Mount Meru; for those severely tormented by the sickness of
                        afflictions, like a medicinal elixir; for those who have severed the roots of virtue and fallen, like a
                        walking stick. For those who make a living by weaving garlands, he is like a flower; for those who observe
                        vows, like a mirror; for those who have conscientiousness and modesty, like clothing; for travelers to
                        nirvāṇa, like a footbridge; for voyagers to the other shore, like a boat; for travelers to the higher
                        realms, like a staircase. For those suffering from insults and slander, he is like a parasol; for those
                        facing opposition, like a lion; for the rains, like water; for those fighting against Māra, like armor;
                        for those who have mistaken the precepts, like the opening of their eyes; for all harvests of the roots of
                        virtue, like the earth. <ref cRef="F.266.b"/> For the sick he is like a doctor; for the hungry, like
                        grain; for the thirsty, like a water crystal;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-299" index="27">A
                            magical stone endowed with the power to produce water or rain.</note> for the exhausted, like a bed;
                        for those in meditative concentration, like a fire lens;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-300" index="28">A fire lens (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me shel</foreign>)
                            concentrates the sun’s rays in order to produce fire, just like powerful meditative concentration is
                            used to achieve supernatural powers, such as clairvoyance.</note> for those who have entered the path
                        to enlightenment, like a chariot; for those playing in parks, like a pool; for those striving toward
                        enlightenment, like a rosary. Thus does he appear.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-38"/>
                    <p tid="47">“This son of noble family is like the fruition of the perfections, like a wish-fulfilling jewel
                        for those on the tenth ground, like a wish-fulfilling tree for those who have achieved the
                            <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>. For all who are engaged in negative views,
                        he is like a weapon because he severs; for those afflicted beings entangled in latent tendencies, he is
                        like a vajra because he overcomes. The demons cannot conquer him. For those of skillful means, he is the
                        measure of time;<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-301" index="29">This usually refers to the
                            number of lunar days in a month.</note> for primordial wisdom, he is discernment. For the entire
                        Buddhadharma, he is the abode; for pratyekas, like a garland; for all śrāvakas, like the robes; for gods,
                        like an eye; for humans, like a path; for those born in the animal realm, a shelter; for pretas, a
                        support; for hell beings, a protector. For those sentient beings who receive donations, he transforms into
                        a container; for bodhisattvas, into a chariot. For all the tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete buddhas of
                        the three times, this son of noble family is like a minister. He is the gatekeeper of the city of Dharma.
                        This son of noble family possesses the perfect buddhas’ primordial wisdom complete with all adornments,
                        including the eighteen unique qualities of a buddha. This son of noble family is someone whom all sentient
                        beings, with the exception of the tathāgatas, should worship with every supreme offering. Therefore, all
                        of you who have gathered here should now welcome him. <ref cRef="F.267.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-39"/>
                    <p tid="48">“Using every mode of worship and respect, honor him as much as you can with jeweled umbrellas,
                        victory banners, flags, flowers, incense, garlands, ointments, divine garments, ornaments, and vessels of
                        many kinds. Honor, venerate, and revere him. Sweep his path, adorn him with ornaments, and praise him in
                        different ways. All of you will also acquire excellent qualities like his, and before long become vessels
                        like him.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-40"/>
                    <p tid="49">All in the assembly without exception then rose from their seats and turned towards where the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha appeared. With overjoyed hearts, happily smiling faces, and eyes full
                        of admiration, they stood with palms joined and gazed at him. In that assembly were bodhisattva
                        mahāsattvas and śrāvakas, the lord of devas, the lord of nāgas, the lord of yakṣas, the lord of
                        gandharvas, the lord of asuras, the lord of garuḍas, the lord of kiṃnaras, the lord of mahoragas, and
                            <term>hermits</term> in possession of the five kinds of supernatural knowledge.</p>
                    <p tid="50">All of them were thinking the same thought, “What kind of sublime display shall we prepare to
                        honor him with?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-41"/>
                    <p tid="51">At that very moment, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha manifested this buddhafield, the Sahā
                        world, as being made entirely of seven precious materials. It was free of mountains, high lands, rocky
                        landscapes, caves, ravines, abysses, grasses, walls, soil, thorns, unpleasant odors, and so on, and was
                        smooth like the palm of a hand. He manifested melodies sung by the glorious gandharvas; <ref cRef="F.267.b"/> and all the trees, made of seven precious materials, bore delicious fragrances,
                        leaves, flowers, and fruits. He also caused all of the trees, grass, dry wood, and leaves, everything on
                        the <term type="ignore">ground</term>, to appear as if made of the seven precious materials. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-42"/>
                    <p tid="52">Moreover, he completely healed the diseases of the entire Sahā world. He pacified all the
                        sufferings of hell beings, and of those abiding in the animal realms and in the world of Yama, the lord of
                        death. These beings received food, drink, clothing, Dharma robes, and ornaments. At that moment, the
                        wishes of all beings in the realm of the Sahā world were completely fulfilled. They were possessed of good
                        bodies, alluring beauty, sublime excellent complexions, and perfect limbs. The bright radiance of an
                        illuminating orb of light, free of dust and dimness, made them even more beautiful. They were free of
                        mental afflictions, their minds were very calm, inclined to every kind of virtue, and their faith in the
                        Three Jewels deepened. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-43"/>
                    <p tid="53">Next, he manifested precious jewels in the hands of all the beings gathered in this assembly, each
                        jewel radiating its own light rays. The entire realm of the Sahā world was completely pervaded by that
                        great light. Different kinds of melodious sounds also emanated from those jewels as a rain of a multitude
                        of jewels showered down. Rains of various fine garments, of ornaments, of flowers, incense, garlands,
                        parasols, vessels, and of fruit <ref cRef="F.268.a"/> also showered down. He produced manifestations of
                        divine garments, Dharma robes, golden threads, and pearl necklaces; of lotus flowers, utpala flowers,
                        jasmine, and white lotuses; of uragasala trees, snake-heart sandalwood, tamāla tree leaves, and of white
                        sandalwood powder scattered along the path.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-44"/>
                    <p tid="54">On both sides of the road, right and left, he produced manifestations of residences resembling the
                        celestial palace of Indra and divine mansions made of the seven precious materials. In those palaces, he
                        manifested the lord of desire Kāmeśvara’s most sublime consort and her retinue; they were playing pleasant
                        music endowed with the five qualities, and were engaging in joyful play and entertainment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-45"/>
                    <p tid="55">He also produced a manifestation that exquisitely decorated the sky above the Bhagavān’s head.
                        Made of jewel filigrees and garlands of pearl jewelry, vast by some hundred <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojanas</foreign>, it resembled the great Brahmā’s parasol of divine precious
                        jewels. From these ornaments the sound of melodious songs of the five qualities, even more beautiful than
                        divine music, also emerged. The grass, woods, leaves, flowers, fruit, and everything on the <term type="ignore">ground</term>, too, emitted scintillating music of five qualities, even more beautiful
                        than divine music, from which words of praise emerged. No one who heard these sounds would ever turn away
                        from attaining complete and perfect enlightenment. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-46"/>
                    <p tid="56">When the assembly saw the grand display of the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha, the entire
                        gathering had the most wonderful and marvelous experiences. They wondered, “How shall we arrange the seat
                        of this holy being in the presence of the Bhagavān?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-47"/>
                    <p tid="57">At that very moment a lotus flower appeared in front of the Bhagavān. Made of precious substances,
                        it had a stem of silver, leaves of gold, <ref cRef="F.268.b"/> a core of emerald, and flower anthers made
                        of the light of Brahmā’s precious stone. Its width was about one <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krośa</foreign>. Myriad kinds of lotus anther seats emerged in front and around it. On the lotus, the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha appeared, sitting cross-legged. On his crown there was a precious
                        jewel. Similarly, many myriads of bodhisattva mahāsattvas, servants of the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Ākāśagarbha, appeared. Sitting on their respective lotus anther seats, they were absorbed in the
                            <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>. Each was adorned with an Indranīla
                        jewel.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-48"/>
                    <p tid="58">The bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya said to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Bhaiṣajyarāja:</p>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“All bodhisattvas of great renown </l>
                        <l>Respectfully pay homage </l>
                        <l>First, when they arrive,</l>
                        <l>And only then do they take their seats. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>When this great being arrived </l>
                        <l>And made his grand displays,</l>
                        <l>He appeared sitting on his seat </l>
                        <l>Without having prostrated to the Buddha.” </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-49"/>
                    <p tid="61">Bhaiṣajyarāja replied:</p>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“We see that this great being</l>
                        <l>Dwells excellently in the Buddhadharma.</l>
                        <l>Since he does not dwell in discursive thought, </l>
                        <l>We do not see him as a sentient being.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-50"/>
                    <p tid="63">Bodhisattva Maitreya asked: </p>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>“Since he abides in final reality, </l>
                        <l>We do not see him as a sentient being.</l>
                        <l>If that is so, to what purpose has he made this great display?</l>
                        <l>I am afflicted by doubts: please explain further!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-51"/>
                    <p tid="65">At this, Bhaiṣajyarāja replied: </p>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l>“Immature beings do not understand ultimate reality;</l>
                        <l>Their experience is a complete mental construction.</l>
                        <l>This is a hero’s method</l>
                        <l>That brings these sentient beings to maturity.</l>
                        <l>By means of ultimate reality</l>
                        <l>Suffering beings will be completely freed.</l>
                        <l>To this end, <ref cRef="F.269.a"/> by means of relative truth, the skillful ones</l>
                        <l>Manifest displays such as this one here.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-52"/>
                    <p tid="67">The Bhagavān now said to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Bhaiṣajyarāja, “What you say is well spoken,
                        well spoken indeed. It is exactly as you say, holy being! However many immature, ordinary beings there may
                        be, not one of them understands the field of experience, practice, or liberation of a stream-enterer.
                        Imagine that all sentient beings had become stream-enterers. Even then, not one of them would understand
                        the field of experience, practice, or liberation of a single once-returner. Similarly, once-returners
                        would not understand non-returners, non-returners would not understand arhats, and arhats would not
                        understand pratyekabuddhas. Even if all sentient beings had become pratyekabuddhas, who dwell alone like
                        the rhinoceros, none of them would understand the field of experience of a single bodhisattva who has
                        attained acceptance that phenomena are non-arising, nor his liberation, his analysis of ultimate reality,
                        or his practice of bringing sentient beings to complete spiritual maturity. Imagine that all sentient
                        beings had attained acceptance that phenomena are non-arising. Even so, not one of them would understand
                        the field of experience of a single bodhisattva who has realized discriminating awareness and attained the
                            <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>; nor would they fathom his aspirations, or
                        the transformative power of his investigating ultimate reality.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-53"/>
                    <p tid="68">“An uncountable number of eons ago, this son of noble family, the bodhisattva mahāsattva
                        Ākāśagarbha, attained acceptance that phenomena are non-arising, attained discriminating awareness, and
                        attained the <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>. Hence, he knows the mentalities
                        and latent tendencies of the beings now present in my great assembly. <ref cRef="F.269.b"/> Indeed, some
                        of the beings came here for the great display. In order to observe meditative concentration and a great
                        display, one must abide on the level of freedom from attachment. The son of noble family did not appear in
                        this way to those beings, but instead came from the western direction to this place and displayed
                        meditative concentration and the supernatural knowledge of the bases of perception of śrāvakas,
                        pratyekabuddhas, and of the extraordinary beings of the boundless infinity of space.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-54"/>
                    <p tid="69">“Ordinary sentient beings, however, became very disheartened, so he then showed a great display,
                        created on the level of relative truth, in order to bring all sentient beings to complete maturity. He
                        also showed a great display of meditative concentration. If the son of noble family had manifested a
                        display of unborn ultimate reality, the world’s inhabitants, including the gods, would have become
                        confused and defiled. Since even bodhisattvas dwelling on the grounds up to the eighth ground may become
                        defiled, they themselves do not have the capacity to display such a field of experience and the
                        distinguishing qualities of his practice. Thus he abides in the qualities of the profound Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-55"/>
                    <p tid="70">“This son of noble family abides in the understanding of skillful means. He possesses all the
                        ocean-like qualities of a buddha, has no doubt, and is a wise person who does not need to depend on
                        others’ wisdom. He is like the supreme victory banner of all bodhisattvas, suitable for a king. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-56"/>
                    <p tid="71">“This son of noble family, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, shows all beings the way to rebirth in the
                        higher realms and to liberation. He frees them completely of the disease of mental afflictions, and cures
                        the body’s poisons, the diseases derived from the four great elements. Even those sentient beings who,
                        suffering in the desolate place of saṃsāra, have become polluted by their negative views, and do not know
                        the means to reach the higher realms and liberation, may utter the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha,
                        pay homage, <ref cRef="F.270.a"/> and offer perfume and incense of aloe wood. This son of noble family
                        examines their mentalities and latent tendencies, how they are influenced by afflicted views, and how they
                        generated roots of merit in the past, and he understands how their minds have to be trained. He teaches
                        them how to generate roots of virtue toward the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṅgha, or else the
                        meritorious character of the essence of giving, of ethical discipline, or meditation, whichever might be
                        appropriate.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-57"/>
                    <p tid="72">Whether in dreams or during waking hours, in all these ways the skillful one teaches the path
                        directly and with straightforward methods. These methods quickly liberate beings from negative views and
                        actions, from unwholesome intentions, from wrong objects of refuge, and from a mind engaged in negativity. </p>
                    <p tid="73">“It is certain that their actions of body, speech, and mind will become upright, their aspirations
                        will become honest, and they will follow an honest spiritual friend. They will quickly be freed from
                        stains, from mental afflictions, and from negative views. All the unwholesome paths that lead to the lower
                        realms will swiftly be purified by the power of aspirations and the activities of excellent conduct. He
                        also teaches the methods that allow beings to swiftly gain control over their own minds and abide in
                        profound tolerance. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-58"/>
                    <p tid="74">“If those sentient beings who suffer from various physical diseases, whose minds are distracted,
                        who have impaired eyesight, who are inarticulate, or who are physically disabled in any way,
                        wholeheartedly recite the name of the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha in order to pacify their diseases
                        and reach a state free of ills, <ref cRef="F.270.b"/> and if they burn aloe wood and Chinese incense and
                        prostrate to the holy being Ākāśagarbha, then that son of noble family will appear in their dreams in
                        front of them in the guise of a brahmin, Śakra, Śrī, Sarasvatī, a king, minister, hero, doctor, father,
                        mother, boy, or girl. In the dreams he will sit before sick people and manifest whatever appropriate
                        medicine and instruments can pacify their illness. And with one treatment he will heal all illness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-59"/>
                    <p tid="75">“Similarly, the son of noble family teaches the appropriate methods to those who desire good
                        advice or possessions, wish to recite prayers and to study, long for solitude, desire to abide firmly in
                        meditative concentration, gain wisdom, be famous, or learn crafts; those who desire power, a good body,
                        wealth, saintliness, a high caste, a son, or a servant; those who desire good qualities, or giving,
                        ethical discipline, and the other perfections up to wisdom; those who desire soft-spoken words, to be in
                        harmony with other beings, liberation from negativity, or to bring others to the practice of all of the
                        perfections from giving to wisdom; those who desire a long life, or to have property and never lack it;
                        and those who wish to cause the stingy to be generous, the immoral to be ethical, or the lazy to be
                        diligent. <ref cRef="F.271.a"/> Those who are never lacking in great compassion, and who observe
                        themselves and practice equanimity toward all beings, should think, ‘By whatever means necessary, I will
                        place these beings’ minds in unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment, I will familiarize them with
                        skillful means, I will anchor them in all the mental states from the four sublime abodes<!-- removed because it was already a gloss <note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-302">These four are: loving kindness, compassion, sympathetic joy,
                            and equanimity. </note>--> up to great compassion,’ and they should all pay homage to the bodhisattva
                        Akāśagarbha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-60"/>
                    <p tid="76">“In a remote place, or in the open plains, or in an unsheltered place, they should burn incense of
                        aloe wood and Chinese incense at specific times. With palms joined, they should make prostrations with the
                        five limbs<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-303" index="30">In the Buddhist context, the head is
                            considered a limb—the most important limb—as well as the arms and legs.</note> in all the cardinal and
                        secondary directions and recite the words of this mantra: </p>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="173">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> tadyathā | sumriśa | sumriśa | kāruṇika | caracara | vicara |
                            saṃcara | kāruṇika | murmur | vegadhari | maca me | bhujapāda | mahā­kāruṇikā | cinata­maṇi<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-304" index="31">sic. (should probably read <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cintā­maṇi</foreign>).</note> pūrāya | kāruṇika | sarva
                            śamesthapāya | ajñādhāri | sphu guṅ sphu guṅ | ruti viveka guṅ driṣṭi viveka<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-305" index="32">sic. (should probably read <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dṛṣṭiviveka</foreign>).</note> guṅ | pūraya kāruṇika | pūrāyantu mama | aśa
                            sarva antha ca | aśokagati svāhā | </foreign>
                    </ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-61"/>
                    <p tid="78">“They should recite this mantra many times and then go to sleep. The son of noble family will
                        appear to them in the form of a human being, a wild animal, a bird, in his own form, or as a body that
                        corresponds to their fortune of merit. Or he will employ such methods as using words in a similar way.
                        That method alone has the power to bring billions of billions of beings to complete maturity. Whether they
                        do not follow any path, or practice the śrāvaka path, or the pratyekabuddha’s path, in a single brief
                        instant of wisdom and with just a minimum of skillful means he has the power to place them irrevocably on
                        the unsurpassable Mahāyāna path, <ref cRef="F.271.b"/> thereby establishing them in meditative
                        concentration, in the dhāraṇīs, in the various states of tolerance, and up to the tenth ground. This shows
                        that the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha is endowed with inconceivable methods, primordial wisdom, and
                        great compassion. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-62"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Son of noble family, some people can comprehend the extent of space, but no-one can comprehend
                        the extent of this noble son’s methods and primordial wisdom, of his great love and great compassion, the
                        extent to which he has developed the strength of meditative concentration and brings beings to complete
                        maturation. This shows that the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha possesses inconceivable qualities.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-63"/>
                    <p tid="80">“Son of noble family, beings who are without deceit, without pretense, are diligent, endowed with
                        honest views, who do not belittle others and do not praise themselves, who have abandoned jealousy and
                        greed, who are free from hypocrisy, and have altruistic minds—such beings are all deeply loved by this son
                        of noble family. He teaches them skillful means, primordial wisdom, vigor, and how to maintain
                        determination. These means, wisdom, vigor, and determination liberate beings from their sufferings and
                        cause them to generate a mind that strives for unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment. Moreover,
                        since they dedicate all the roots of virtue to enlightenment, they will never turn away from attaining the
                        state of unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment. Their energy, vigor, and great determination
                        will become the great enthusiasm and determination needed to bring the six perfections to complete
                        perfection. They will swiftly awaken entirely and perfectly to unsurpassable, perfectly complete
                        enlightenment. This shows that the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha possesses determination and good
                        qualities that are inconceivable, and that he brings all sentient beings <ref cRef="F.272.a"/> to complete
                        maturation.” </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-64"/>
                    <p tid="81">The bodhisattva Maitreya asked the Bhagavān, “Bhagavān, for what purpose does this son of noble
                        family carry on his head, the holiest part of the body, a precious jewel shining with brilliant bright
                        light, whereas other bodhisattvas do not possess anything like it?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-65"/>
                    <p tid="82">The Bhagavān replied, “The bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha possesses great compassion, he
                        benefits beings, and liberates them from great suffering. Thus, for all beings who have committed a root
                        transgression, who are bound for the lower realms, who have exhausted all roots of virtue—for all these
                        frightened beings, this son of noble family is medicine. For those drowning in the pitch black darkness of
                        ignorance and those tormented by their negative views, he is like the sun. He brings them to disclose
                        their root transgressions; he lifts the doubts from their hearts. For those whose hearts have become like
                        a broken vessel, who have fallen, who have committed a <term>fundamental transgression</term>, who have
                        destroyed all their virtuous qualities, who are bound for the lower realms, who are protectorless, devoid
                        of support, abandoned by all the wise ones—for all of them, this son of noble family is like a crutch. He
                        shows the way, reveals and cleanses all negative actions and all stains. He turns beings away from the
                        paths leading to the lower realms. He is like a chariot. He establishes beings in the higher realms and in
                        the state of liberation. For all beings who have minds entangled in intense desire or intense hatred, who
                        are malevolent, who conceal their faults, whose minds are disturbed by miserliness, who grope in darkness
                        because of extreme dullness, <ref cRef="F.272.b"/> who proclaim the non-existence of causality, who hold
                        the view that one should be fearless concerning the next life, who lack contentment in their accumulation
                        of wealth, and whose minds are constantly involved in all the ten unwholesome actions, this son of noble
                        family performs every role, from closing the door to the lower realms up to serving as a chariot. He
                        establishes those sentient beings in the higher realms and in the state of liberation.</p>
                    <p tid="83">“For these reasons, with the exception of the tathāgata, arhat, completely perfect buddhas, the
                        whole world including the gods should worship this son of noble family.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-66"/>
                    <p tid="84">Bodhisattva Maitreya asked, “Bhagavān, sentient beings stained by a root transgression forfeit
                        their roots of virtue and are bound for the lower realms. They are in a state of transgression and will be
                        deprived of any happiness of the god and human realms. Yet this son of noble family brings about these
                        beings’ fulfillment with the bliss of the higher realms and liberation. What are these particular
                        transgressions?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-67"/>
                    <p tid="85">The Bhagavān answered, “Son of noble family, there are five root transgressions for a kṣatriya on
                        whom royal authority has been bestowed. By committing any of these root transgressions, a kṣatriya upon
                        whom royal authority has been bestowed will forfeit all previously generated roots of virtue, and will be
                        in a state of transgression. Such a kṣatriya will be deprived of all the happiness of the god and human
                        realms, and will go to the lower realms.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-68"/>
                    <p tid="86">“What are these five transgressions? Son of noble family, for a kṣatriya on whom royal authority
                        has been bestowed, stealing from a place of worship, stealing that which has been offered to the local
                        saṅgha or the saṅgha of the four directions, or inciting someone to steal it: these constitute the first
                        root transgression.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-69"/>
                    <p tid="87">"Forcing someone to give up the Dharma, whether it is the instructions on the śrāvakas’ definite
                        deliverance, the instructions on the pratyekabuddhas’ definite deliverance, or the instructions on the
                        Mahāyāna definite deliverance, as well as creating obstacles to the teachings, or concealing them:<ref cRef="F.273.a"/> all of these constitute the second root transgression.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-70"/>
                    <p tid="88">“Taking by force the saffron robes of those who have shaved their heads and beards for my sake and
                        donned the saffron robes—whether they uphold the precepts or not, whether they observe the discipline or
                        not—thus making them householders; inflicting corporal punishment on them, imprisoning or killing them:
                        all of these constitute the third root transgression.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-71"/>
                    <p tid="89">“Furthermore, a kṣatriya commits the fourth root transgression with any one of these five heinous
                        deeds: purposely killing one’s own mother, father, or a śrāvaka, arhat, or the Bhagavān; dividing the
                        saṅgha; or purposely and out of negative intention causing a tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete buddha
                        to bleed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-72"/>
                    <p tid="90">“Furthermore, if a kṣatriya advocates the philosophy of the non-existence of causality, denies the
                        existence of future lives, embraces the ten paths of unwholesome action and engages in them, and also
                        influences many other people to follow the ten paths of unwholesome action, manipulates them, encourages
                        them and brings them to do so: these actions constitute the fifth root transgression.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-73"/>
                    <p tid="91">“Son of noble family, if a kṣatriya on whom royal authority has been bestowed commits any of these
                        five root transgressions, this kṣatriya will forfeit all previously generated roots of virtue. He will be
                        in a state of transgression. Such a kṣatriya will be deprived of any happiness of the god and human
                        realms, and will be bound for the lower realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-74"/>
                    <p tid="92">“When that happens, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will manifest his birth and appear in an
                        uncivilized land or another place, manifesting for some in the form, attire, and conduct of a monastic,
                        for others in the form, attire, and conduct of a brahmin. <ref cRef="F.273.b"/> However and wherever he
                        manifests, he will explain the Dharma to such kṣatriyas. He will explain and teach the hitherto unheard
                        of, the unprecedented, the instructions of the omniscient one, the deep and profound sūtras, the dhāraṇīs,
                        tolerance, and the grounds. And for this reason the kṣatriyas on whom royal authority has been bestowed
                        will be caused to develop shame about their previous negative and unwholesome actions. They will reprimand
                        themselves and disclose, give up, and abandon negative actions. They will develop great enthusiasm for
                        giving, discipline, taking precepts, and determination, and they will reach the higher realms.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-75"/>
                    <p tid="93">“Maitreya, the transgressions of a minister are also five in number. What are these five? Stealing
                        from a place of worship or from the saṅgha of the four directions is considered the first root
                        transgression of a minister. Destroying a village, a district, or a town constitutes the second root
                        transgression. Furthermore, for a minister, forcing somebody to give up the Dharma, whether this entails
                        the instructions on the śrāvakas’ definitive deliverance, the instructions on the pratyekabuddhas’
                        definite deliverance, or the instructions on the definite deliverance of the omniscient one, as well as
                        creating obstacles for the teachings or concealing them: these constitute the third root transgression.
                        Furthermore, for a minister, harming those who have taken ordination with the Bhagavān—whether they uphold
                        the precepts or not, whether they observe the discipline or not, taking by force their saffron robes and
                        making them householders; resorting to corporal punishment, imprisoning them or taking their lives: these
                        all constitute the fourth root transgression. Finally, for a minister to commit one or more of the five
                        heinous deeds <ref cRef="F.274.a"/> constitutes the fifth root transgression. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-76"/>
                    <p tid="94">“Son of noble family, if a minister commits any of the five root transgressions he will forfeit
                        all previously generated roots of virtue, and will be in a state of transgression. Such a minister will be
                        deprived of any happiness of the god and human realms, and will descend to the hell realms. Then, for the
                        sake of such a person, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will be born, live, and teach in the land of the
                        uncivilized or another place. For some beings he will manifest in the form, attire, and conduct of a monk,
                        for others in various other forms and attires, including that of a girl, and he will teach the Dharma.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-77"/>
                    <p tid="95">“Irrespective of where and in which guise he has manifested, he will explain the Dharma to those
                        ministers. He will explain and teach the hitherto unheard of, the unprecedented, the instructions of the
                        omniscient one, the deep and profound sūtras, the dhāraṇīs, tolerance, and the grounds. Then those
                        ministers will be made to develop shame about their previous unwholesome negative actions. They will
                        reprimand themselves and disclose, give up, and relinquish negative actions. And they will eagerly
                        practice giving, discipline, and having determination for the vows; and they will reach the higher realms. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-78"/>
                    <p tid="96">“Son of noble family, there are five root transgressions for śrāvakas. Which are the five? They
                        are killing, taking what was not given, impure conduct, lying, and physically harming or drawing blood
                        from the body of a tathāgata. These are the five.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-306" index="33">The fifth root transgression is twofold: the destruction of representations of a buddha and the
                            drawing of a buddha’s blood.</note> According to how it has always been explained, when my śrāvakas
                        commit any of these root transgressions, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will manifest birth in different
                        places for the benefit of those beings. To some he teaches in the form of a monastic with the appropriate
                        attire and conduct, <ref cRef="F.274.b"/> and so forth, including all forms previously mentioned, and
                        those beings will reach the higher realms.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-79"/>
                    <p tid="97">“There are eight root transgressions for sons of noble family who are beginners and who have
                        correctly embarked on the Mahāyāna path. These root transgressions cause confusion, and beginners who have
                        correctly entered the Mahāyāna will forfeit the entirety of their previously generated roots of virtue,
                        and they will be in a state of transgression. They will be deprived of the happiness of gods, of humans,
                        and of the Mahāyāna, go to the lower realms, be separated from a spiritual friend, and remain in saṃsāra
                        for a very long time. What are the eight? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-80"/>
                    <p tid="98">“There are beings who were born in this worldly realm of afflictions and five impurities because
                        they conducted themselves in evil ways in the past. They rely upon a spiritual friend and listen to the
                        most profound Mahāyāna owing to the tiny root of virtue they possess. Though they do so with little
                        understanding, those sons of noble family give birth to the aspiration to unsurpassable, perfectly
                        complete enlightenment. Some beginner bodhisattvas among them listen to the collection of sūtras that
                        present the most profound emptiness, transmit, and read them. In the presence of other sentient beings who
                        understand as little as those just mentioned, they recall these sūtras in great detail in word and
                        meaning, just as they heard and understood them, and they teach them to others. When those ordinary,
                        immature beings who have not gone through arduous training hear such profound sūtras, they become
                        extremely frightened and terrified. Because they are terrified, they turn back from attaining
                        unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment and aspire to the vehicle of the śrāvakas. This is the
                        first root transgression for a beginner bodhisattva.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-81"/>
                    <p tid="99">“Son of noble family, due to this root transgression, they will forfeit the entirety of their
                        previously generated roots of virtue. They will be in a state of transgression and be deprived of the
                        happiness of the higher realms and of liberation. <ref cRef="F.275.a"/> They will betray their bodhicitta,
                        the <term>mind of enlightenment</term>, and go to the lower realms. </p>
                    <p tid="100">“It is like this. Just as, for instance, one travels the great ocean in stages, similarly
                        bodhisattvas must initially know other sentient beings, their inclinations and latent tendencies. In
                        accordance with the other beginner bodhisattvas’ predispositions, they must teach the Dharma step by step. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-82"/>
                    <p tid="101">“The bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha manifests his birth and appears in different places for their
                        benefit. Therefore, if beginner bodhisattvas who have incurred such a root transgression and are terrified
                        by the lower realms hear the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha and wish to see him in order to disclose
                        those transgressions, they should burn aloe wood and Chinese or other incense, join their palms, and utter
                        the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha at the break of dawn. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-83"/>
                    <p tid="102">“Having seen such sentient beings, this son of noble family will manifest in a form corresponding
                        to their respective fortunes. Thus, in the presence of some, he will manifest in an ordinary form and
                        teach the Dharma. In the presence of others, he will teach in the form of a brahmin, and in the presence
                        of yet others he may manifest in any other form, including the form of a girl, and cause the beginner
                        bodhisattvas to disclose their root transgressions just as they occurred. He also teaches them expertise
                        in skillful means, the profound conduct of the unsurpassable Mahāyāna. He establishes them in meditative
                        concentration, tolerance, the dhāraṇīs, and the grounds. As a result, they will be completely liberated
                        from the lower realms and will not turn back from attaining perfectly complete enlightenment. In
                        vajra-like manner, they will rely upon the six perfections with great strength and determination, and will
                        soon manifestly and completely awaken to unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-84"/>
                    <p tid="103">“If <ref cRef="F.275.b"/> he does not directly appear in front of them, the beginner bodhisattvas
                        should rise before dawn and pray to Aruṇa, uttering these words: ‘Aruṇa, Aruṇa, endowed with great
                        compassion! Aruṇa, as soon as you have risen in this world, enfold me in your compassion. Convey these
                        words of mine to Ākāśagarbha, the one of great compassion: Please show yourself in my dreams so that I may
                        disclose my root transgressions. Lead me to obtain the great eyes of wisdom endowed with the skillful
                        means of the noble Mahāyāna.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-85"/>
                    <p tid="104">“Then they should go back to bed to sleep. Here too, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will appear at
                        the break of dawn in the dreams of those beginner bodhisattvas who have committed a transgression, and
                        with great skillful means of primordial wisdom he will lead them to disclose their root transgressions. He
                        also teaches primordial wisdom endowed with skillful means. This enables the beginner bodhisattvas to
                        obtain the meditative concentration called <distinct>not forgetting the mind of enlightenment</distinct>
                        at that very moment. They will firmly abide by the Mahāyāna and swiftly come to complete the six
                        perfections.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-86"/>
                    <p tid="105">“Furthermore, beginner bodhisattvas may say to some people: ‘You are not able to engage in the
                        practice of the six perfections. You are not able to manifestly and completely awaken to unsurpassable,
                        perfectly complete enlightenment. Therefore, quickly turn your minds to either the śrāvaka vehicle or the
                        pratyekabuddha vehicle and you will swiftly be definitively released from saṃsāra.’ Speaking such words is
                        the second root transgression for a beginner bodhisattva. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-87"/>
                    <p tid="106">“Furthermore, beginner bodhisattvas may say to some, ‘Oh! What is the use of practicing the
                        vinaya of individual liberation, <ref cRef="F.276.a"/> ethical discipline, and good conduct? You should
                        swiftly bring forth the mind that strives for unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment and study
                        the Mahāyāna. Then even the tiniest unwholesome deeds you have committed with your body, speech, and mind
                        due to the afflictions will be purified, and they will not come to maturation.’ Saying these words is the
                        third root transgression for beginner bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-88"/>
                    <p tid="107">“Furthermore, son of noble family, beginner bodhisattvas may say to some, ‘Son of noble family,
                        eschew the discourses of the śrāvaka vehicle! Do not listen to them, do not read them, and do not teach
                        them to others. Son of noble family, eschew the discourses of the śrāvaka vehicle! They are the reason why
                        you cannot obtain the great result, why you are not able to eradicate the afflictions. Therefore, have
                        faith in the discourses of the Mahāyāna. Listen to the Mahāyāna, study the Mahāyāna, and teach it to
                        others. Thus you will not go to the lower realms, you will not enter any path leading to the lower realms,
                        and swiftly you will manifestly and completely awaken to unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment.’
                        If these words are spoken and the listener acts accordingly and adopts a similar view, then both actions
                        incur a root transgression. This is the fourth root transgression of beginner bodhisattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-89"/>
                    <p tid="108">“Furthermore, beginner bodhisattvas may be two-faced, thinking one thing but professing another.
                        They may also propagate and versify the Mahāyāna teachings, and for the purpose of gain and honor they may
                        chant those verses, recite, memorize, read, and explain them, and even teach others things that they have
                        merely heard, saying, ‘I am a follower of the Mahāyāna; <ref cRef="F.276.b"/> others, however, are not.’
                        Because they seek gain and honor, they act jealously and become upset when others are appreciated and
                        respected. Uttering their names, they disparage, abuse, and speak badly of them, praising themselves
                        instead. Out of jealousy, they say, ‘I possess supreme qualities.’ This action constitutes a transgression
                        and deprives them of the happiness of the Mahāyāna. It is therefore considered a very serious
                        transgression that leads to rebirth in the lower realms. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-90"/>
                    <p tid="109">“The analogy here is of a group of people who wish to go to a jewel island and set out to cross
                        the great ocean by boat, but the boat breaks apart in the great ocean. In the same way, even though these
                        beginner bodhisattvas wish to cross the great ocean of the Mahāyāna, they destroy their boat of faith and
                        part from the vital force of wisdom when they lie out of jealousy. Therefore, beginner bodhisattvas incur
                        a very weighty transgression when they lie out of jealousy. This is the fifth root transgression for
                        beginner bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-91"/>
                    <p tid="110">“Furthermore, son of noble family, in the future there will be beginner bodhisattvas,
                        householders or ordained, who will read, recite, and chant sūtras that contain profound emptiness. These
                        Mahāyāna sūtras are the object of understanding of bodhisattvas who need only little effort, and who are
                        greatly intelligent beings, adorned with dhāraṇīs, tolerance, meditative concentration, and the
                        grounds.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-92"/>
                    <p tid="111">“Having recited them, they extensively teach these sūtras to others. They say, ‘I have understood
                        these teachings with my own intelligence; I teach them to you in this way because I am compassionate.
                        Therefore, you must meditate on this profound Dharma in order to directly perceive it <ref cRef="F.277.a"/> and you too will come to behold primordial wisdom, just as I do now.’ Instead of stating, ‘I have not
                        actualized this most profound Dharma, but teach it by merely reading it out,’ they promote themselves for
                        the purpose of gain and honor. Therefore, in the eyes of the tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete buddhas
                        of the three times, bodhisattva mahāsattvas, and noble beings, they have become stained by faults. A heavy
                        transgression has occurred. Having deceived gods and humans using the Mahāyāna, there will be no śrāvaka
                        vehicle of the buddha for those bodhisattvas, much less the Mahāyāna, or the particular realizations which
                        are the entry into the Mahāyāna, or unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-93"/>
                    <p tid="112">“The analogy here is that of someone who travels out into the great secluded wilderness, where he
                        suffers hunger, thirst, and exhaustion. He then approaches a tree, intending to eat of the great fruit it
                        bears. However, ignoring the tree with its fine aroma and delicious fruit, he climbs instead a poisonous
                        tree bearing fruit devoid of taste, and eats its poisonous fruit. In doing so, he causes his own death.
                        Such a beginner bodhisattva committing the sixth transgression is said to be like the person in this
                        analogy.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-94"/>
                    <p tid="113">“Therefore, if beginner bodhisattvas who have gained this hard-to-achieve human birth live with a
                        spiritual friend and wish to enter the Mahāyāna, yet praise themselves and disparage others for the
                        purpose of gain, honor, and fame, they incur a serious transgression. Because of this root transgression,
                        all the wise ones will strongly criticize them and they will go to the lower realms. No kṣatriya, brahmin,
                        vaiśya, or śūdra will rely upon such a person. Anyone who does rely upon such a person is definitely
                        unwise. This, again, is the sixth root transgression for beginner bodhisattvas. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-95"/>
                    <p tid="114">“Furthermore, son of noble family, in the future kṣatriyas will have dishonorable<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-307" index="34">Tib. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag
                                dar ba</foreign>. Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣā­samuccaya</title> quotes this passage
                            from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśa­garbha­sūtra</title>. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag dar ba</foreign> renders the Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caṇḍāla</foreign>,
                            meaning in general “outcast, person of lowest value,” etc. According to Monier-Williams it can also
                            mean “a very low representative of ” (see MW 383/3).</note> advisors<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-308" index="35">Tib. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdun na ’don</foreign> (Skt.
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">purohita</foreign>). This could also be a house priest.
                        </note> and ministers, dishonorable soldiers <ref cRef="F.277.b"/> and physicians—rich and powerful fools
                        who are proud of their expertise. Seeming to engage in many meritorious deeds of giving, they will become
                        proud and haughty due to their giving. Out of arrogance and pride, they will cause division within the
                        kṣatriyas, as well as separation between the monastics and the kṣatriyas. Backed by the kṣatriyas, they
                        may even punish the monastics, robbing them by imposing fines. Thus, being wronged, those monastics will
                        steal from whichever individual, local saṅgha, saṅgha of the four directions, and whichever place of
                        worship they can, and give what they have robbed to pay their fine. And those dishonorable people in turn
                        will offer this to the kṣatriyas. Both of these actions become root transgressions. This is the seventh
                        root transgression.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-96"/>
                    <p tid="115">“Furthermore, those dishonorable kṣatriyas together with the monastics commit the following
                        fault. They declare pure Dharma to be non-Dharma, and refer to that which is non-Dharma as Dharma, thus
                        abandoning the true Dharma. They do not observe the precepts of the sūtras and the vinaya, nor do they
                        observe the black teachings,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-309" index="36">The black teachings
                            are the systems of philosophical views and religious practices which cause one to roam continuously in
                            saṃsāra, in contrast to the great teachings, referring to the Buddhadharma, which liberates from it.
                        </note> nor the great teachings. Having abandoned their training in loving kindness, great compassion, and
                        the perfection of wisdom, as well as their training in skillful means and the trainings taught in other
                        sūtras, they organize duties for the monastic community that are dissociated from such meritorious
                        activities in order to harm the bhikṣus. Because such duties have been organized, the bhikṣus are harmed.
                        They abandon the practices of calm abiding and special insight. Harmful intentions multiply in those
                        meditators, as a result of which they cannot pacify their unpacified emotions. As these do not subside,
                        these bhikṣus then degenerate in terms of intention, ethical discipline, conduct, and view. Therefore,
                        they become negligent, and ever more negligent, and their ethical discipline degenerates. Even though they
                        are not monastics, they pretend to be, and even though they do not lead a chaste life they pretend to.
                            <ref cRef="F.278.a"/> They resemble donkeys, and they explain the Dharma most clearly. Once they have
                        been greatly honored and venerated by the kṣatriyas and their retinues and have received their offerings,
                        they criticize, in front of the householders, the other bhikṣus who diligently practice relinquishment.
                        And the kṣatriyas together with their retinues become angry at the bhikṣus who diligently practice
                        relinquishment, and disparage them. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-97"/>
                    <p tid="116">“If the support and material riches that were destined for the bhikṣus who diligently practice
                        relinquishment are offered to the bhikṣus exerting themselves in recitation, at this point, then both
                            actions<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-310" index="37"> “Both actions” refers to the actions
                            of the monastics as well as those of the donors.</note> become root transgressions. Why? Because the
                        bhikṣu meditators are holy, while those who only recite and advise others are not. The bhikṣu meditators
                        have become vessels for meditative concentration, dhāraṇīs, tolerance, and the grounds. They have become
                        holy beings worthy of receiving offerings; they have become sacred vessels. They illuminate the world and
                        show the way, liberating beings from the realm of karma and afflictions and placing them on the path
                        leading beyond sorrow. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-98"/>
                    <p tid="117">“Son of noble family, since they have no misgivings concerning such actions and fear no
                        consequences, this is the eighth root transgression for beginner bodhisattvas. When beginner bodhisattvas
                        commit these root transgressions, they forfeit all previously generated roots of virtue. They have
                        incurred a transgression, will be deprived of the happiness of the higher realms and of liberation, and
                        have deceived themselves.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-99"/>
                    <p tid="118">“Son of noble family, for the benefit of beginner bodhisattvas, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha is
                        born and appears in the places where such bodhisattvas dwell. To some he teaches in the form of a monastic
                        with the appropriate attire and conduct, displaying to others a variety of forms, from that of a brahmin
                        with the proper attire and conduct to the semblance and conduct of an animal. For an extensive explanation
                        of this, one should read the <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra on the Meditative ‌Concentration of Brave
                            Progression</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śūraṃgama­samādhi­sūtra</title>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-311" index="38">See <ptr target="#bibliography">bibliography</ptr>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-100"/>
                    <p tid="119">“Ākāśagarbha teaches the Dharma in various places according to the specificities of various
                        beings. <ref cRef="F.278.b"/> He conveys the sūtras, meditative concentration, tolerance, and bodhisattva
                        grounds taught by the omniscient one in a way that was previously unheard of and unprecedented.
                        Consequently, beginner bodhisattvas ignorant of skillful means who have incurred transgressions are
                        ashamed. Because of those transgressions, they are very frightened and terrified. They disclose the
                        transgressions, give them up, and reject them. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-101"/>
                    <p tid="120">“If, upon hearing the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, those beings wish to see him, and if,
                        fearful of falling to the lower realms, they wish to disclose their root transgressions, pay homage to the
                        bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, and call out his name, then, son of noble family, in accordance with their merit,
                        he will stand before those sentient beings as an ordinary person, or in front of those beginner
                        bodhisattvas in various forms, from that of a brahmin to that of a girl, and make them disclose those
                        transgressions just as they have occurred. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-102"/>
                    <p tid="121">“He displays his profound skill in means and shows them how to engage in the unsurpassable
                        Mahāyāna. On the various bodhisattva grounds, he establishes them in meditative concentration, dhāraṇīs,
                        and tolerance by having them gradually practice the entire eightfold path. He frees them completely from
                        their immense fear of the lower realms and establishes them on the stage of not turning away from
                        unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment. As quick as a flash of lightning, they thereby become
                        very strong and determined in the practice of the six perfections. In this way they swiftly come to
                        manifestly and completely awaken to unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-103"/>
                    <p tid="122">“If he does not show himself to them directly, the beginner bodhisattvas who pray to him and who
                        have erred in their ways should rise during the watch of dawn, stand facing the eastern direction, and
                        pray to the god Aruṇa, uttering these words: ‘Aruṇa, Aruṇa, endowed with great compassion! Great fortunate
                        one! <ref cRef="F.279.a"/> As soon as you have risen in this world, enfold me in your compassion. Summon
                        the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, who is endowed with great compassion, with these my words: Show yourself in
                        my dreams that I may disclose my transgressions. Lead me to obtain the skillful means and wisdom of the
                        noble Mahāyāna.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-104"/>
                    <p tid="123">“Having spoken these words, they should go back to bed to sleep. Then, at the first light of dawn
                        in this world, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will come and appear in the dreams of those beginner
                        bodhisattvas, in the guise of an ordinary person, and will make them disclose their root transgressions.
                        With great primordial wisdom and skillful means, that expert in skillful means and primordial wisdom will
                        bring these beginner bodhisattvas to attain the meditative concentration called <distinct>not forgetting
                            bodhicitta, the mind of enlightenment</distinct> at that very moment. They will come to firmly abide
                        by the Mahāyāna, to swiftly complete the six perfections, and, before long, to manifestly and completely
                        awaken to unsurpassable, perfectly complete enlightenment. Such skillful means and wisdom will he also
                        teach them. Son of noble family, this is why the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha bears the precious
                        wish-fulfilling jewel, which arises from great bravery, on his head, the holiest part of the body. The
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha is endowed with inconceivable excellent qualities.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-105"/>
                    <p tid="124">“Furthermore, son of noble family, if beings who have heard the name of the bodhisattva
                        Ākāśagarbha, who draw his form or have made offerings to him, venerate him, revere him deeply, and worship
                        and honor him in numerous ways with flowers, incense, garlands, ointments, parasols, banners of victory,
                        and flags—if they pay homage to him and even offer their lives to him, then those beings <ref cRef="F.279.b"/> will not die in fire or in water, nor will they be killed with weapons or poison.
                        Except when their lives are naturally exhausted, no one—neither humans nor non-humans—will be able to rob
                        them of their life force. They will not die an untimely death, become sick, or die of hunger or thirst,
                        nor will they be killed by order of a ruler, and for the rest of their lives they will not incur a single
                        transgression. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-106"/>
                    <p tid="125">“At the time of death they will not see forms with their eyes, hear sounds with their ears, smell
                        odors with their noses, experience tastes with their tongues, or experience tactile objects with their
                        bodies. They will, however, continue to breathe out and breathe in with a subtle breath, and their life
                        force, warmth, and consciousness will still remain in their bodies. At that time, the bodhisattva
                        Ākāśagarbha will show himself to them as an ordinary person. To those beings who in the past revered the
                        brahmins, this son of noble family will show himself in the form of a brahmin. To those who revere
                        Kāmeśvara, he will display the form of Kāmeśvara. To those who have taken refuge in and revere Nārāyaṇa,
                        Śakra, a cakravartin, the sun, the moon, Dhṛtarāṣṭra, Virūḍhaka, Virupākṣa, or Vaiśravaṇa, or who have
                        taken refuge in various objects such as devas, mountains, trees, fountains, ponds, and pools, he will show
                        himself accordingly. And in the form that corresponds to their disposition he will speak the following
                        words:</p>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>“ ‘Whoever has insight into the four truths of the noble ones</l>
                        <l>Is liberated from existence in saṃsāra.</l>
                        <l>Therefore, those dwelling in saṃsāra should know all four. </l>
                        <l>Having understood these Dharmas, these beings will reach the higher realms.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-107"/>
                    <p tid="127">“Appearing before beings who have strong faith in the Buddha, <ref cRef="F.280.a"/> he will
                        display the form of the Buddha and utter these words:</p>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“ ‘The truth of the Buddha’s primordial wisdom</l>
                        <l>Frees those dwelling in the ocean of existence. </l>
                        <l>Swiftly attain that primordial wisdom, </l>
                        <l>And you will be liberated from all suffering.’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-108"/>
                    <p tid="129">“At this time, these beings will be joyful and delighted by the sound (of those words) that bring
                        the Buddha to mind. Then they will die and be reborn in a buddhafield, unsullied and pure, in which a
                        buddha bhagavān dwells, lives, and resides, and where he teaches the Dharma. The same can be said with
                        respect to the Dharma and the Saṅgha. This shows that the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha is endowed with
                        inconceivable excellent qualities.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-109"/>
                    <p tid="130">“Those who wish to perfectly master different kinds of meditative concentration should pay homage
                        to the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha during the watch of dawn and make as many offerings as possible.
                        Establishing the mind in loving kindness for all sentient beings, they should then utter these words:
                        ‘Give heed, give heed to me. Ākāśagarbha, you have achieved great compassion. I pray, please bestow upon
                        me mindfulness and the yoga of meditative concentration. Thus it is: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-110"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="174">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">umuraṇakhe | bakṣamanile | samudra | avadarena | nayanaya |
                            mahā­kāruṇikā | anupama­jambha­smṛti | akra­jambha­smṛti | vajra­jambha­smṛti| koṣa­smṛti |
                            anupama­smṛti | bhūtakoṭi­smṛti svāhā |</foreign>’</ab>
                    <p tid="132">“To those who recite in this way, Ākāśagarbha grants mindfulness and entrance into meditative
                        concentration.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-111"/>
                    <p tid="133">“Those who desire to study treatises, whether the words of the Buddha or expositions by the
                        śrāvakas, should first bathe and then pay homage to the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha at the break of dawn, make
                        as many offerings as possible, generate loving kindness for all sentient beings, and speak these words:
                        ‘Give heed, give heed to me! Greatly learned one, among all beings, Ākāśagarbha, son of noble family
                        beyond imagination, you are supreme. Pray bestow upon me the yoga of mindfulness and meditative
                        concentration. Thus <ref cRef="F.280.b"/> it is: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-112"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="175">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">inīlaja | viṣanaduṣaja | viyavanaja | vibakṣisame | pāśalajasi |
                            sthānaśarave | śastrakarṇṇe | humahuma | mahā­kāruṇika svāhā |</foreign>’</ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-113"/>
                    <p tid="135">“Those who wish to enter the great ocean or caves, or to make use of the sacred essence,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-312" index="39">This probably refers to the old Indian practice of
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rasāyana</foreign>, an alchemical process for attaining
                            health and power, immortality and liberation. See also Sachau (1888: 188).</note> who have been
                        imprisoned, are separated from friends, or face hostile people: such beings may call out the name of the
                        bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, make as many offerings as possible, settle the mind in loving kindness for all
                        sentient beings, and utter these words: ‘Give heed, give heed to me, Ākāśagarbha of great renown, endowed
                        with great compassion and intent on the welfare of beings! You, who are endowed with great compassion,
                        look upon me; liberate me from these circumstances and bestow good fortune upon me. Supremely powerful
                        one, I am worn out by suffering. I am destitute. Relying upon you, I will attain peace and happiness in
                        this and future lives.’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-114"/>
                    <p tid="136">“Then the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will appear in front of them, in various forms including that
                        of a common person and that of a girl, and he will bring them relief and free them from whatever fears
                        they may have. </p>
                    <p tid="137">“This also applies to those who are afraid of fire, water, weapons, toxins, curses, tigers,
                        lions, strong poisons, thieves, and rogues,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-313" index="40">Tib.
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yon can</foreign>. Alternative translation:
                            demons.</note> are shackled, or punished, or are about to be killed; those who are struck by a disease
                        or who are afraid of diseases; and those who are bereft of monastic robes, alms, bedding, a seat, medicine
                        to cure disease, or of basic necessities.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-115"/>
                    <p tid="138">“Some princes <ref cRef="F.281.a"/> may wish to be promoted to a higher rank. They might utter
                        the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha and pay homage to him, worship and venerate him, and so forth.
                        Having heard the name of the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha, those who wish to be promoted to a high rank among
                        the brahmins, householders, craftsmen, those engaged in studies, or meditators, up to whatever high rank
                        they aspire to, should pay homage to him. Once they have bathed and put on clean clothes, they should take
                        refuge in the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha during the watch of dawn and pray to him, uttering these words: ‘O
                        Ākāśagarbha, your compassion is great indeed! I pray, please bestow good fortune upon me. Fulfill my
                        aspirations and intentions, each one of them, according to my wishes. You, who are endowed with great
                        compassion, grant me whatever I wish, and kindly do whatever I request.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-116"/>
                    <p tid="139">“If they do all this and utter these words, the bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha will hear this with the
                        purified faculty of divine hearing which is beyond human capacity and show himself to those beings in
                        whatever form is appropriate. He will also teach them such skillful means.</p>
                    <p tid="140">“The bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha is endowed with the excellent quality of such skillful
                        means. He is endowed with a great ocean-like mind. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-117"/>
                    <p tid="141">“Son of noble family, some may be able to estimate how many drops of water are contained in the
                        great ocean, but no one can fathom the extent to which the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha is gifted in
                        skillful means and wisdom, or the extent of his activities that ripen sentient beings through skillful
                        means. Son of noble family, some may be able to apprehend the expanse of the whole of the infinite,
                        limitless space in the ten directions, but it is impossible to fathom the multitude of forms the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha takes in order to bring sentient beings to spiritual maturity.
                        Sometimes he manifests in the form of a buddha in order to ripen sentient beings, <ref cRef="F.281.b"/>
                        sometimes in the form of a brahmin. He manifests in whatever form is required to tame beings. Among those
                        born in the animal realm he manifests in the form of an animal; among hell beings, in the form of a hell
                        being; and for those of the Yama world, as a being of the Yama world, and so forth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-118"/>
                    <p tid="142">“For some he emanates as a directly perceptible manifestation, for others he manifests in dreams.
                        For some he manifests in various forms at the time of death and transference, at the last movement of
                        consciousness, in order to eliminate the karma of their negative deeds, to liberate them from the lower
                        realms, to place them in the higher realms, and to bring about the wellbeing of sentient beings. Having
                        taken refuge in and seen these manifestations, these beings will obtain all forms of happiness, up to the
                        happiness of abiding in the worlds of the higher realms. It is for this reason that no one can fathom the
                        magnitude of all of the manifestations of Ākāśagarbha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-119"/>
                    <p tid="143">“Indeed, the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha is endowed with the inconceivably excellent
                        qualities of skillful means and wisdom. He is endowed with the excellent qualities of a buddha. That is
                        why a precious wish-fulfilling jewel appears on the head, the supreme part of the body of this son of
                        noble family.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-120"/>
                    <p tid="144">The entire assembly was amazed and marveled at the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha. Having
                        paid homage to their teacher and honored him, they all joined their palms and made offerings to the
                        bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha, and honored him in various ways. They made offerings of flowers,
                        incense, garlands, ointments, lamps, parasols, victory banners, flags, monastic robes, ornaments,
                        garments, praises, songs, and cymbal music. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-121"/>
                    <p tid="145">The bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha in turn <ref cRef="F.282.a"/> presented the Bhagavān with all of
                        these offerings, then prostrated at the feet of the Bhagavān and supplicated him with these words:</p>
                    <p tid="146">“Venerable Bhagavān, in this afflicted buddhafield stained by the five impurities, beings are
                        deluded due to the great darkness of ignorance. How can those beings be benefited, so as to bring about
                        their enlightenment?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-122"/>
                    <p tid="147">The Bhagavān replied:</p>
                    <p tid="148">“It is thus, son of noble family. The sky is neither bound nor liberated. It is not afflicted,
                        nor deluded, and is naturally pristine. The wind scatters particles of dust in the sky, and tosses them
                        around. Thus, the sky appears impure, as dark as night. Then water makes the particles fall and renders
                        the sky stainless and completely pristine. In this case, if the stars, the planets, the sun, and the moon
                        are not visible, then the seconds, minutes, hours,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-314" index="41">The terms in the text are <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skad
                                cig</foreign> (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣaṇa</foreign>), the shortest units of
                            time, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thang cig</foreign> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">lava</foreign>), one-thirtieth of a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">muhūrta</foreign>, and <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yud tsam</foreign> (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">muhūrta</foreign>), one-thirtieth of a day.</note> days, nights,
                        seasons, and years will be imperceptible as well. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-123"/>
                    <p tid="149">“Son of noble family, in the same way, mind—which is pervaded by emptiness, the ultimate reality
                        of the tathāgata—is by nature utterly pristine and pure. However, the minds of sentient beings have been
                        defiled by adventitiously arisen afflictions. For their benefit, the Dharma is taught out of the
                        tathāgata’s great compassion, which is likened to water. Sentient beings’ afflicted minds are completely
                        purified, rendering them pristine and stainless. Because of this, when the sun of the tathāgata has risen,
                        these beings will be filled with the light rays of primordial wisdom and will actualize the inconceivably
                        excellent qualities of a buddha.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-124"/>
                    <p tid="150">“Thus they will be established in the four close applications of mindfulness and so on, up to the
                        eighth branch of the eightfold noble path.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-315" index="42">That
                            is to say, in the thirty-seven factors conducive to enlightenment (see glossary).</note> They will achieve all possible qualities, up to the
                        eighteen unique qualities of a buddha. All of these beings will be firmly rooted in compassion. From among
                        them, arhats will appear in the world. <ref cRef="F.282.b"/> Pratyekabuddhas and bodhisattva mahāsattvas
                        will appear in the world. Tathāgata, arhat, perfectly complete buddhas will appear in the world. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-125"/>
                    <p tid="151">“Son of noble family, what do you think: does space abide in the eye?”</p>
                    <p tid="152">“Bhagavān, it does not,” Ākāśagarbha replied.</p>
                    <p tid="153">“Does it abide in the eye consciousness?” </p>
                    <p tid="154">“Bhagavān, it does not.” </p>
                    <p tid="155">“Does it abide in that which is apprehended by the eye?” </p>
                    <p tid="156">“Bhagavān, it does not.” </p>
                    <p tid="157">“Does space abide anywhere inside, in the arising of the three feelings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-316" index="43">Pleasant, unpleasant, and neutral feelings. </note> caused by
                        the eye apprehending an object?” </p>
                    <p tid="158">“Bhagavān, it does not.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-126"/>
                    <p tid="159">“The same is to be said about the ears, the nose, the tongue, and the body as well. Son of noble
                        family, what do you think: does space abide in the mind, or anywhere else up to the arising of the three
                        feelings caused by the mind apprehending an object?” </p>
                    <p tid="160">“Bhagavān, it does not.” </p>
                    <p tid="161">“Son of noble family, what do you think: do sentient beings abide in space?” </p>
                    <p tid="162">“Bhagavān, they do not.” </p>
                    <p tid="163">“What do you think, son of noble family: does space abide in sentient beings?” </p>
                    <p tid="164">“Bhagavān, it does not.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-127"/>
                    <p tid="165">Thus did the bodhisattva mahāsattva Ākāśagarbha reply to the Bhagavan’s questions. He continued,
                        “Bhagavān, they do not depend on each other. One is not the other’s object. Bhagavān, all phenomena are to
                        be understood in this particular way: they are devoid of concepts, they are empty, devoid of
                        superimposition; they are the final reality and suchness. Bhagavān, with regard to the essence of space,
                        it is thus. Its particular characteristic is that it is not differentiated; it is non-conceptual,
                        completely non-conceptual, unmoving, and lacking in substance. It is devoid of sprout, seed, fruit, and
                        ripening, devoid of words, and of mental fixation. Bhagavān, <ref cRef="F.283.a"/> a bodhisattva
                        mahāsattva who understands all phenomena in this way attains acceptance that all phenomena are
                        non-arising. Bhagavān, it is thus: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-128"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="176">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vyava­rāja | mantakṣāya | jinajaya | jananimamunihara |
                            anayaphala | guṇa­garbha | niyamasurināya | bupaśa | śataśapa | śamaśana | tathakama | śamaṅgu |
                            mātuśiṣa | śama­cetanāya | kleṣāntasaṃśoṣaṇe svāhā |</foreign>”</ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-129"/>
                    <p tid="167">The Bhagavān replied, “Well said, well said. Son of noble family, when you use this dhāraṇī of
                            <distinct>the majestic lion turning backwards, which overwhelms everyone who sees him</distinct>,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-317" index="44">No other reference to this dhāraṇī could be
                            located. </note> at the time of death, at the last moment of beings’ consciousness, you will have the
                        capacity to eliminate their obscuration of afflictions, their obscuration of karma, and their obscuration
                        with regard to phenomena, and send them to the completely pure buddhafields. You will go to limitless,
                        uncountable world systems, and by the power of compassion for sentient beings you will expound various
                        classes of Mahāyāna sūtras in the villages, towns, market places, provinces, countries, and kings’
                        palaces, manifesting in various forms with appropriate attire and conduct. You will bring sentient beings
                        to maturity in such a way that all of them, from the lowliest among the kṣatriyas up to the lowliest among
                        the monastics, will be able to abandon the negative dharmas and will abide by the wholesome dharmas.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-130"/>
                    <p tid="168">As the Bhagavān was teaching, limitless, countless beings of nine types of birth among gods and
                        men attained various states of meditative concentration, dhāraṇīs and tolerance, whereas for others the
                        wisdom of the ten grounds arose. Tens of thousands of beings attained acceptance that all phenomena are
                        non-arising. </p>
                    <lg tid="169">
                        <l>“When beings give up the very basis </l>
                        <l>Of their conflicts, whatever they may be,</l>
                        <l>The very basis of all their views</l>
                        <l>Will quickly change.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-318" index="45">This version of the
                                stanza differs from the several significant variants found in other editions of the Kangyur, both
                                of the Tshalpa and Thempangma traditions. Some versions of this passage, such as those in N and P,
                                are difficult to make sense of; here we followed D, whose editors appear to have revised this
                                stanza carefully.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-131"/>
                    <p tid="170">When the Bhagavān had spoken these words, the monks, the entire retinue, and the whole world,
                        including gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas, <ref cRef="F.283.b"/> rejoiced and praised the Bhagavān’s
                        teachings.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="215">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-132"/>
                    <p tid="171">This completes the Noble Mahāyāna <title xml:lang="en">Ākāśagarbha Sūtra.</title>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="172">Edited, translated, and established by the Indian abbot Śākyaprabha and the monk
                        Ratnarakṣita.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="216">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="217">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-133">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-134">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-135">
                        <abbr>P</abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-136">
                        <abbr>Y</abbr>
                        <expan>Yunglo Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-137">
                        <abbr>BCA</abbr>
                        <expan>Bodhicaryāvatāra</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-066-018-138">
                        <abbr>LVP</abbr>
                        <expan>La Vallée Poussin</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="218">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="219">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-139">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa nam mkha’i snying po zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. Toh.
                        260. Degé Kangyur, vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios 264a–283b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-140">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa nam mkha’i snying po zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’
                        ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi
                        bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research
                        Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006-2009, vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), pp 731-777. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-141">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa kun las btus pa</title>: Toh 3940, Degé Tengyur vol. 103 (dbu ma, khi),
                        folios 3a-194b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-142">Sakya Paṇḍita.<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> thub pa’i dgongs pa rab tu gsal
                            ba.</title> dpal ldan sa skya pa’i bka’ ’bum, vol. 10 (tha), folios 1a-99a. Reprinted in Dehradun
                        U.P.: Sakya Center (1993). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-143">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dpa’ bar ’gro ba’i ting nge ’dzin ces bya ba theg pa chen po’i
                            mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­śūraṅgama­samādhi­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 132.
                        Degé Kangyur, vol. 55 (mdo sde, da) F.253.b - F.316.b. For a translation of this sūtra see Lamotte
                        (1998).</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="220">Secondary Literature</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-144">Bendall, Cecil and W.H.D Rouse. <title xml:lang="en">Śikṣāsamuccaya. A
                            Compendium of Buddhist Doctrine.</title> London: John Murray, 1922. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-145">Davidson, Ronald. “Studies in<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                            Dhāraṇī </foreign>Literature I: Revisiting the Meaning of the Term<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Dhāraṇī</foreign>.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of Indian Philosophy</title> vol.
                        37:2 (April 2009): 97-147. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-146">de Visser, M. W. <title xml:lang="en">The Bodhisattva Ākāśagarbha (Kokūzō)
                            in China and Japan</title>. Amsterdam: Uitgave van de Koninklijke Akademie van Wetenschappen te
                        Amsterdam, 1931. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-147">Harrison, Paul. “Mediums and Messages: Reflections on the Production of
                        Mahāyāna Sūtras.” <title xml:lang="en">Eastern Buddhist</title> 35, nos. 1-2, (2003): 115-151. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-148">Kongtrul Lodrö Tayé, Jamgön. <title xml:lang="en">The Treasury of
                            Knowledge. Book Five: Buddhist Ethics</title>. Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications, 2003. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-149">Lamotte, Étienne. <title xml:lang="en">Śūraṃgamasamādhisūtra: The
                            Concentration of Heroic Progress, An Early Mahāyāna Buddhist Scripture</title>. Translated by Sara
                        Boin-Webb. London: Curzon Press, 1998. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-150">La Vallée Poussin (LVP), Louis de. <title xml:lang="fr">L’Abhidharmakośa de
                            Vasubandhu, traduit et annoté par Louis de la Vallée Poussin: Premier et Deuxième Chapitres.</title>
                        Vol. 1, Paris: P. Geuthner, 1923. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-151">Ngari Panchen, Pema Wangyi Gyalpo and Dudjom Rinpoche. <title xml:lang="en">Perfect Conduct: Ascertaining the Three Vows</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 1996. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-152">Sachau, Edward C., trans. <title xml:lang="en">Alberuni’s India</title>.
                        vol. 1. London: Trübner &amp; Co., Ludgate Hill, 1888. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-153">Shantideva. <title xml:lang="en">The Way of the Bodhisattva</title>.
                        Translated by Padmakara Translation Group. Revised Edition. Boston &amp; London: Shambhala Publications,
                        2006. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-154">Tharchin, Tenzin and Elisabeth Lindmayer. <title xml:lang="de">Das
                            Akashagarbha-Sutra. Allumfassende Liebe und Weisheit: Heilend und wunscherfüllend</title>, München:
                        Diamant Verlag, 2010. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-155">Wangchuk, Dorji. <title xml:lang="en">The Resolve to Become a Buddha. A
                            Study of the </title>Bodhicitta<title xml:lang="en"> Concept in Indo-Tibetan Buddhism</title>. Tokyo:
                        The International Institute for Advanced Buddhist Studies, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-018-156">Zimmermann, Michael. <title xml:lang="en">The Tathāgatagarbhasūtra. The
                            Earliest Exposition of the Buddha-Nature Teaching in India. </title>Tokyo: The International Institute
                        for Advanced Buddhist Studies, 2002. </bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-157">
                            <term>five impurities</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snyigs ma lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྙིགས་མ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">5 kaṣāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Five particular aspects of life which indicate the degenerate nature of a
                                given age. They are the impurities of views, of afflictions, of sentient beings, of life, and of
                                time.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-158">
                            <term>all-basis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་གཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, the foundation of all things of saṃsāra and nirvāṇa. Sometimes
                                synonym for dharmakāya or emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-159">
                            <term>arhat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dgra bcom pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགྲ་བཅོམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arhat</term>
                            <term type="definition">One who has achieved the fourth and final level of attainment on the śrāvaka
                                path, and who has attained liberation with the cessation of all mental afflictions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-160">
                            <term>bases of perception</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye mched </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེ་མཆེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āyatana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The twelve <term type="ignore">bases of perception</term> are divided into two groups, consisting of six
                                inner and six outer bases. These are six sense faculties and six outer corresponding objects.
                                Together they are the causes for the production of the six sense consciousnesses.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-161">
                            <term>beings of the boundless infinity of space</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas pa’i nam mkha’ mtha' yas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་ཡས་པའི་ནམ་མཁའ་མཐའ་ཡས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first of the four classes of gods of the formless realm. The activity
                                field called “infinite as the sky,” or “boundless space” is one of the 28 classes of gods in the
                                formless realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-162">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk of the Buddhist Sangha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-163">
                            <term>bodhisattva mahāsattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ sems dpa’ chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ་སེམས་དཔའ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhi­sattva­mahā­sattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva is a great being (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsattva</foreign>) who has the intention to achieve complete enlightenment for the benefit
                                of all sentient beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-164">
                            <term>brahmin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bram ze </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲམ་ཟེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brāhmaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A person belonging to the highly respected priestly caste of classical Indian
                                society.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-165">
                            <term>cakravartin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor los sgyur ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་ལོས་སྒྱུར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravartin</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “wheel-wielder,” denotes a powerful being who has control over vast
                                regions of the universe.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-166">
                            <term>calm abiding</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śamatha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first of the two main branches of Buddhist meditation, aiming at rendering
                                the mind stable, subtle, and pliable.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-167">
                            <term>chaste life</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs par spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmacarya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The <term type="ignore">chaste life</term> of the monastics.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-168">
                            <term>collection of sūtras</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མདོ་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūtrapiṭaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The collection of discourses of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-169">
                            <term>complete mental construction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu rtog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་རྟོག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parikalpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A complete projection of the mind which has no valid basis in reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-170">
                            <term>definite deliverance</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nges ’byung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངེས་འབྱུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">niḥsaraṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term is also translated as ‘renunciation’ and denotes the practitioner’s
                                mind turning away from the bonds of saṃsāra and towards liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-171">
                            <term>deva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">deva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Gods; a class of beings in the higher planes of existence in the desire realm,
                                as well as in the form and formless realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-172">
                            <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term is used in various ways. For instance, it refers to the mental
                                capacity of not forgetting, enabling one in particular to cultivate positive forces and to ward
                                off negativity. It is also very commonly used as a term for mystical verses similar to mantras,
                                the usage of which will grant a particular power.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-173">
                            <term>discriminating awareness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so so rig pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོ་རིག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prativedana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-174">
                            <term>discursive thought</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtog pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟོག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalpanā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ordinary activity of the mental consciousness, also translated as
                                conceptual thought.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-175">
                            <term>eighteen unique qualities of a buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi chos ma ’dres pa bco brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་མ་འདྲེས་པ་བཅོ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">18 āveṇika­buddha­dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eighteen qualities that are exclusively possessed by a buddha. These are
                                listed in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharma­saṃgraha</title> as follows: The tathāgata does not
                                possess: (1) confusion; (2) noisiness; (3) forgetfulness; (4) loss of meditative equipoise; (5)
                                cognition of distinctness; or (6) nonanalytical equanimity. A buddha totally lacks: (7)
                                degeneration of motivatedness; (8) degeneration of perseverance; (9) degeneration of mindfulness;
                                (10) degeneration of samādhi; (11) degeneration of prajñā; (12) degeneration of complete
                                liberation; and (13) degeneration of seeing the wisdom of complete liberation. (14) A tathāgata’s
                                every action of body is preceded by wisdom and followed through with wisdom; (15) every action of
                                speech is preceded by wisdom and followed through with wisdom; (16) a buddha’s every action of
                                mind is preceded by wisdom and followed through with wisdom. (17) A tathāgata engages in seeing
                                the past through wisdom that is unattached and unobstructed and (18) engages in seeing the present
                                through wisdom that is unattached and unobstructed.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-176">
                            <term>eightfold path</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags lam yang lag brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་ལམ་ཡང་ལག་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryāṣṭāṅga­mārga</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddhist path as presented in the śrāvaka vehicle: right view, right
                                intention, right speech, right action, right livelihood, right effort, right mindfulness, right
                                samādhi.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-177">
                            <term>eternalism</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtag pa’i lta ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟག་པའི་ལྟ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāśvatadṛṣṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first of two extreme views which keep one deluded with regard to reality.
                                <term type="ignore">Eternalism</term> is the view that clings to some eternal, truly existent essence called ‘self,’ based on
                                the experience of a collection of, in fact, transitory phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-178">
                            <term>final reality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag pa’i mtha’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག་པའི་མཐའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtakoṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A synonym for ultimate reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-179">
                            <term>five heinous deeds</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcānantaryāṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Five actions that bring immediate and severe consequences at death. The person
                                will experience a rebirth in the lower realms directly after death. The five are: (1) killing
                                one’s father, (2) killing one’s mother, (3) killing an arhat, (4) causing schism in the saṅgha,
                                and (4) with evil intention making a buddha bleed.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-180">
                            <term>four close applications of mindfulness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa nye bar gzhag pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་ཉེ་བར་གཞག་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">4 smṛtyupasthāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fundamental practice of Buddhist meditation: close application of
                                mindfulness to the body, close application of mindfulness to feelings, close application of
                                mindfulness to mind, and close application of mindfulness to phenomena.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-181">
                            <term>four truths of the noble ones</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa’i bden pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པའི་བདེན་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">4 āryasatya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four truths the Buddha realized at his enlightenment: the truth of
                                suffering, the truth of the origin, the truth of cessation, the truth of the path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-182">
                            <term>four sublime abodes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i gnas bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་གནས་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">4 brahmavihāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The practices and resulting states of boundless loving kindness, compassion,
                                sympathetic joy, and equanimity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-183" mode="marked">
                            <term>fundamental transgression</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phas pham pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕས་ཕམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pārājika</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four downfalls for monastics resulting in the forfeit of the monastic
                                vows: sexual intercourse, theft, murder, and claiming greater realization than one has.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-184">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of sentient being who lives on scents; literally “smell eater.” Also a
                                type of celestial musician living on the rim of Mt. Sumeru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-185">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical bird.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-186">
                            <term>great compassion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snying rje chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྙིང་རྗེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahākaruṇā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A specific state of mind resulting from the four abodes of Brahma and defined
                                as the wish to liberate all beings from suffering.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-187">
                            <term>great element</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung ba chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་བ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahābhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The four elements composing the physical world: earth water, fire, and
                                air.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-188">
                            <term>ground</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The path of a bodhisattva is divided into ten stages of spiritual attainment
                                called <term type="ignore">grounds</term>. The eleventh <term type="ignore">ground</term> corresponds to complete enlightenment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-189" mode="marked">
                            <term>hermit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">drang srong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲང་སྲོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛṣi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A seer or hermit who has attained certain spiritual powers.</term>
<term type="alternative">hermits</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-190">
                            <term>impure conduct</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi tshangs par spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abrahmacarya</term>
                            <term type="definition">This term is the opposite of brahmacarya, ‘pure conduct’ or ‘holy life,’ which
                                denotes the chaste life of those who have renounced the world. The term abrahmacarya therefore
                                refers to sexual conduct, which is regarded as a root downfall for monastics on the śrāvaka
                                path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-191">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Mythical being with a horse’s head and a human body (or vice versa); literally
                                “man or what?” Along with the gandharvas, <term type="ignore">kiṃnaras</term> are celebrated as celestial musicians.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-192">
                            <term>krośa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyang grags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱང་གྲགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krośa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A measure of distance corresponding to one calling-distance. Four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">
                                    <term type="ignore">krośa</term>
                                </foreign> equal one yojana.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-193">
                            <term>kṣatriya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal rigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་རིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣatriya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A member of the ruling caste of classical Indian society.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-194">
                            <term>kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grul bum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲུལ་བུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Vampire demon; a type of yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-195">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Large-bellied demon; literally “large stomach.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!-- <item>
                        <gloss type="term" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-196">
                            <term>maṇḍala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkyil ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཀྱིལ་འཁོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maṇḍala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Circle or orb.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-197">
                            <term>meditative concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A general term for the practice of meditative absorption aimed at developing
                                profound states of concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-198">
                            <term>meditation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsam gtan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསམ་གཏན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhyāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “stability of mind,” denotes specific levels of concentration
                                attained by the sustained practice of calm abiding (śamatha).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-199">
                            <term>meditative concentration of brave progression</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bar ’gro ba’i ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བར་འགྲོ་བའི་ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śuraṅgama­samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A special type of samādhi (meditative absorption).</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">brave equipoise</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-200">
                            <term>mental affliction</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mental states which cause unrest in the mind, distorting the view of
                                reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-201" mode="marked">
                            <term>mind of enlightenment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The determination to attain unsupassable, truly complete enlightenment for the
                                sake of all sentient beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-202">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of beings believed to have a snake body. There are both powerful and
                                powerless types of <term type="ignore">nāgas</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-203">
                            <term>nihilism</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chad pa’i lta ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆད་པའི་ལྟ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ucchedadṛṣṭi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second of two extreme views that keep one deluded with regard to reality.
                                <term type="ignore">Nihilism</term> is a view equally based on clinging to a truly existent self. It is the belief that once
                                this self ends with death, everything associated with it ends. It therefore rejects rebirth and
                                the law of karma, or cause and effect.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-204">
                            <term>non-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyir mi ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱིར་མི་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">One who has achieved the third of the four levels of attainment on the śrāvaka
                                path, and who will not be reborn in saṃsāra any longer.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-205">
                            <term>once-returner</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lan cig phyir ’ong ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལན་ཅིག་ཕྱིར་འོང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sakṛdāgāmin</term>
                            <term type="definition">One who has achieved the second of the four levels of attainment on the
                                śrāvaka path, and who will have only one more rebirth before attaining liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-206">
                            <term>piśāca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piśāca</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of demons; literally “flesh eater.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-207">
                            <term>pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rang sangs rgyas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རང་སངས་རྒྱས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyekabuddha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “buddha for himself,” or “solitary realiser.” Those who attain
                                buddhahood in a time when the Buddha’s doctrine is no longer available in the world, and who
                                remain either in solitude or amongst peers, without teaching the path to liberation to others.
                                They are sometimes called “rhinoceros-like” for their preference to stay in solitude.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">pratyeka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-208">
                            <term>preta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of beings; literally “hungry spirit;” one of the six realms of
                                existence.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-209">
                            <term>primordial wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Specifically refers to an awakened being’s wisdom. Also translated as
                                “transcendental wisdom,” “original wakefulness,” and so forth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-210">
                            <term>pūtana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srul po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲུལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūtana</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of pretas that cause rotting or that have rotting corpses; literally
                                “the rotting one.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-211">
                            <term>saṃsāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khor ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁོར་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃsāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The conditioned realm of cyclic existence in which beings are confined to
                                perpetual suffering and unsatisfactoriness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-212">
                            <term>seven precious materials</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen sna bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་སྣ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin po che sna bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་པོ་ཆེ་སྣ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saptaratna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The list of <term type="ignore">seven precious materials</term> vary. Either they are: gold, silver,
                                turquoise, coral, pearl, emerald, and sapphire; or else they are: ruby, sapphire, beryl, emerald,
                                diamond, pearls, and coral.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-213">
                            <term>six perfections</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rol tu phyin pa drug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ་དྲུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">6 pāramitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva’s practices of giving, ethical discipline, forbearance,
                                perseverence, meditative concentration, and wisdom. To qualify as perfections, those practices
                                must be motivated by bodhicitta−the mind of enlightenment—and embraced with an understanding of
                                emptiness.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-214">
                            <term>special insight</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lhag mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷག་མཐོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vipaśyanā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second of the two main branches of Buddhist meditation, aiming at
                                developing insight into the nature of reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-215">
                            <term>stream-enterer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyun du zhugs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུན་དུ་ཞུགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">srotāpanna</term>
                            <term type="definition">One who has achieved the first of the four levels of attainment on the śrāvaka
                                path, and who is from then onwards continuously approaching liberation.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-216" mode="marked">
                            <term>stūpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchod rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོད་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">stūpa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A Buddhist monument and reliquary representing the enlightened mind of a
                                buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-217">
                            <term>suchness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de kho na nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་ཁོ་ན་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathatā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tattvatā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The ultimate nature of things, or the way things are in reality, as opposed to
                                the way they appear to non-enlightened beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-218">
                            <term>śūdra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dmangs rigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམངས་རིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūdra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The caste of the laborers and servants of classical Indian society.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-219">
                            <term>supernatural knowledge</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mngon par shes pa lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མངོན་པར་ཤེས་པ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhijñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">There are five supernatural faculties resulting from meditative concentration:
                                divine sight, divine hearing, knowing others’ minds, recollecting past lives, and the ability to
                                perform miracles.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-220">
                            <term>tamāla tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing ta ma la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ཏ་མ་ལ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A specific kind of mangosteen.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-221">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “One Gone Thus;” epithet of the Buddha and general term for
                                buddhas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-222">
                            <term>ten unwholesome actions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi dge ba’i las kyi lam bcu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་དགེ་བའི་ལས་ཀྱི་ལམ་བཅུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akuśalakarma</term>
                            <term type="definition">The three unwholesome actions of the body (killing, stealing, and sexual
                                misconduct); the four of speech (lying, divisive speech, harsh speech, and senseless speech); and
                                the three of the mind (covetousness, ill-will, and wrong views).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-223">
                            <term>thirty-seven factors conducive to enlightenment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub phyogs kyi chos sum bcu rtsa bdun </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཕྱོགས་ཀྱི་ཆོས་སུམ་བཅུ་རྩ་བདུན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">37 bodhi­pakṣya­dharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddhist path as presented in the bodhisattva vehicle: the four close
                                applications of mindfulness, the four perfect abandonments, the four bases of miraculous power,
                                the five faculties, the five powers, the seven limbs of enlightenment, and the eightfold noble
                                path.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-224">
                            <term>proclaim the non-existence of causality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyu med par smra ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱུ་མེད་པར་སྨྲ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ahetuvāda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The proponents of a theory of causelessness basically rejecting the law of
                                karma, such as the Ājīvika or the Cārvāka.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-225">
                            <term>tolerance</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཟོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capacity to accept or tolerate experiences which ordinary beings cannot
                                tolerate. It is the preparatory step to profound insight into reality. It also refers to the third
                                stage of the path of joining (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyor lam</foreign>; <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prayogamārga</foreign>).</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">acceptance</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-226">
                            <term>transformative power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byin gyis brlabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱིན་གྱིས་བརླབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adhiṣṭhāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term is also translated as ‘blessing.’ It literally denotes the
                                circumstance of something being affected (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brlabs</foreign>) by a force
                                which has the capacity to change the way of thinking or the appearance of others (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"/>byin).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-227">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The world system of a thousand million (10 to the power of 3) worlds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-228">
                            <term>uragasala tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">u ra ga sa la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨུ་ར་ག་ས་ལ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-229">
                            <term>utpala flower</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ud pa la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨུད་པ་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">utpala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Blue lotus, waterlily.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-230">
                            <term>vaiśya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rje’u rigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྗེའུ་རིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vaiśya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The caste of merchants and farmers of classical Indian society.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-231">
                            <term>vajra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vajra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The term stands for indestructibility and perfect stability. According to
                                Indian mythology, the <term type="ignore">vajra</term> is the all-powerful god Indra’s weapon, likened to a thunderbolt,
                                which made him invincible. It also relates to the diamond which is the hardest physical
                                material.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-232">
                            <term>Vinaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདུལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vinaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The collection of monastic rules and regulations.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-233">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A harmful spirit; literally “harm-bringer.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-234">
                            <term>yojana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpag tshad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔག་ཚད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</term>
                            <term type="definition">A measure of distance corresponding to the distance traversed on horse without
                                unyoking. It is sometimes estimated equal to about 4 or 5 miles, sometimes 9 miles.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">yojanas</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-235">
                            <term>transgression</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ltung ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟུང་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āpatti</term>
                            <term type="definition">Actions of body, speech, and mind that cause one to ‘fall from’ the path to
                                awakening, and in the worst cases fall to the lower realms of existence.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">downfall</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-236">
                            <term>seven-limbed practice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yan lag bdun pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡན་ལག་བདུན་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A set of practices found in many textual forms for recitation, often daily.
                                The seven limbs are paying homage to the buddhas, presenting them with offerings, disclosing one’s
                                negative deeds, rejoicing in the positive deeds of all beings, requesting the Dharma, supplicating
                                the enlightened ones to remain with us, and dedicating all virtues to the benefit of sentient
                                beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-237" mode="marked">
                            <term>bodhicitta of aspiration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smon pa’i byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨོན་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhi­praṇidhi­citta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-238" mode="marked">
                            <term>applied bodhicitta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jug pa’i byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇུག་པའི་བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhi­prasthāna­citta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-239">
                            <term>Ākāśagarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ākāśagarbha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-240">
                            <term>Aruṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skya rengs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱ་རེངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aruṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Aruṇa</term> is the deity of the dawn in Indian mythology, personified as the sun’s
                                charioteer, and the name refers to the morning star Venus, according to de Visser (1931), p 24, n
                                1. In this context, <term type="ignore">Aruṇa</term> functions as a messenger for Ākāśagarbha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-241">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-242">
                            <term>Bhaiṣajyarāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi rgyal po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨན་གྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyarāja</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “King of Medicine.” Name of a bodhisattva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-243">
                            <term>Buddhayaśas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Buddhayaśas</term>
                            <term type="definition">Prolific translator of Vinaya texts into Chinese during the 5th
                                century.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-244">
                            <term>Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yul ’khor srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡུལ་འཁོར་སྲུང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhṛtarāṣṭra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Guardian of the Region.” Name of one of the four great kings who
                                rule over the four directions in the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-245">
                            <term>Eight Close Sons of the Buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye ba’i sras chen brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བའི་སྲས་ཆེན་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">The eight bodhisattvas Mañjuśrī, Avalokiteśvara, Vajrapāṇi, Kṣitigarbha,
                                Ākāśagarbha, Sarva­nivaraṇa­viṣkambhin, Maitreya, and Samantabhadra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-246">
                            <term>Great Nail of Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa’i gzer bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པའི་གཟེར་བུ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­brahmā­śaṅku</term>
                            <term type="definition">Or “Great Spike of Purity,” the name of a bodhisattva. Possibly śaṅku is a
                                misreading or misspelling of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sanatku</foreign> which would be “the
                                bodhisattva Sanatkumāra” (Pali. <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Sanaṅkumāra</foreign>) who was a being of
                                the class of Mahābrahmās−in Vedic legend, one of the four or seven “mind-born” sons of Brahmā−and
                                who appears in various suttas in the Pali canon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-247">
                            <term>Kāmeśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod pa’i dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་པའི་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāmeśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Lord of Desire.” Name of Kubera/Vaiśravaṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-248">
                            <term>Kṣitigarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣitigarbha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="person" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-249">
                            <term>Maheśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maheśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Great Lord.” Name of Śiva.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-250">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The Loving One.” Name of the bodhisattva who will be the next
                                buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-251">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal dbyangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་དབྱངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-252">
                            <term>Māra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Māra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Death” or “Demon.” The personification of everything that
                                functions as a hindrance to awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-253">
                            <term>Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sred med kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲེད་མེད་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nārāyaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Child of No Craving.” Name of Viṣṇu.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-254">
                            <term>Ratnarakṣita</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnarakṣita</term>
                            <term type="definition"> 8th - 9th century Tibetan monk, preceptor, and translator (not to be confused
                                with the 13th century mahāpaṇḍita of the same name). See also <ptr target="#UT22084-066-018-280"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-255">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The one who performed a hundred offerings.” Name of Indra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-256">
                            <term>Sakya Paṇḍita</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa skya paN Di ta </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་སྐྱ་པཎ་ཌི་ཏ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-257">
                            <term>Śākyaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyaprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indian paṇḍita. 9th century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>. See also <ptr target="#UT22084-066-018-280"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-258">
                            <term>Samantabhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samantabhadra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-259">
                            <term>Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbyangs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབྱངས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The Melodious One.” The goddess of eloquence and learning.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-260">
                            <term>Sarva­nivaraṇa­viṣkambhin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrib pa rnam sel </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲིབ་པ་རྣམ་སེལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­nivaraṇa­viṣkambhin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-261">
                            <term>Śrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “The Glorious One.” Name of Lakṣmī, the goddess of fortune and
                                beauty.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-262">
                            <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag na rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajrapāṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-263">
                            <term>Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags skyes po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་སྐྱེས་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Noble Birth.” Name of one of the four great kings who rule over
                                the four directions in the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-264">
                            <term>Virupākṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig mi bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་མི་བཟང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Virupākṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Bad Eye.” Name of one of the four great kings, who rule over the
                                four directions in the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-265">
                            <term>Yama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Lord of the Dead; name of the ruler over the netherworld.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-266">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">The monk <term type="ignore">Yeshé Dé</term>, a prolific translator of sūtras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-267">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam thos kyi bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཐོས་ཀྱི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, “Child of He who has Heard a Lot.” Name of one of the four great
                                kings who rule over the four directions in the desire realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-268">
                            <term>Khalatika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kha la ti ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁ་ལ་ཏི་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khalatika</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a mountain in present day Bihar, possibly at Barabar. The mention of
                                it in this sūtra, as its setting, is the only mention at all in the Kangyur.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-269">
                            <term>River Ganges</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang ga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་ག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṅgā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The sacred river of North India.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-270">
                            <term>Mount Meru</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">meru</term>
                            <term type="definition">A gigantic mountain which forms the center of the universe in classical Indian
                                cosmology.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-271">
                            <term>Sahā world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed kyi 'jig rten </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད་ཀྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahāloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">This present world-system or trichiliocosm. The term is variously interpreted
                                as meaning the world of suffering, of endurance, of fearlessness (because the beings who inhabit
                                it do not fear the three poisons), or of concomitance (of karmic cause and effect).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-018-272" mode="marked">
                            <term>abode of the Sage’s hermits</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub pa’i drang srong rnams kyi gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐུབ་པའི་དྲང་སྲོང་རྣམས་ཀྱི་གནས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A place, described in the opening lines of this sūtra as being on Khalatika
                                mountain, but not mentioned elsewhere in the Kangyur except (as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub
                                    pa’i drang srong chen po’i gnas</foreign>) in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimala­prabha­paripṛcchā</title> (Toh 168) in connection with the Gomasalagandha stūpa in
                                Khotan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>