<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
 <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bzhi bstan pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་བཞི་བསྟན་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra Teaching the Four Factors</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos bzhi bstan pa zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­catur­dharma­nirdeśa­nāma­mahāyāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཆོས་བཞི་བསྟན་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra “Teaching the Four Factors”</title>
                <author ref="contributors.xml#team-47" role="translatorMain">Translated by Adam Pearcey
                    <lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
            <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-258">Adam Pearcey</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-259">Alak Zenkar Rinpoche</consultant>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay, Dr.</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-255">Chandika Maharjan</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">James Gentry</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">John Canti</editor>
                <editor role="associateEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-250">Rory Lindsay</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.5.2 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
           <publicationStmt status="1">
               <publisher>
                   <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                       non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words
                       into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
               <availability>
                   <licence>
                       <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                       <p tid="0">This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons
                           CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0
                           copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                           with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or
                           personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative
                           Commons license.</p>
                   </licence>
               </availability>
               <idno xml:id="UT22084-066-007"/>
               <date>2019-02-18</date>
             </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh249" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 249</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol.66 (mdo sde, za), folios 59.a–59.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="2">
                        <volume number="66" start-page="117" end-page="118"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11901" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-10-27T20:53:14.32Z" user="admin">27/10/2019 20:53:14</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.04" date-time="2019-04-29T12:23:27.57Z" user="mike">v 1.04 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.05" date-time="2019-06-21T14:40:01.226Z" user="celso">v 1.05 2019</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.5.1" date-time="2019-10-07T10:27:24.685Z" user="admin">Publication statement updated</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.5.2" date-time="2019-10-27T20:53:11.596Z" user="celso">Removed slash from wylie title</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
  <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="21">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-1"/>
                <p tid="1">While Buddha Śākyamuni is residing in the Sudharmā assembly hall in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, he explains to the great bodhisattva Maitreya four factors that make it possible to overcome the effects of any negative deeds one has committed. These four are: the action of repentance, which involves feeling remorse; antidotal action, which is to practice virtue as a remedy to non-virtue; the power of restraint, which involves vowing not to repeat a negative act; and the power of support, which means taking refuge in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, and never forsaking the mind of awakening. The Buddha concludes by recommending that bodhisattvas regularly recite this sūtra and reflect on its meaning as an antidote to any further wrongdoing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="22">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by Adam Pearcey, with the assistance of Alak Zenkar Rinpoche. An earlier draft of this translation was published on <ref target="https://www.lotsawahouse.org/">Lotsawa House</ref> in 2013. The present updated version was then completed in 2017 under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="23">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">As its name suggests, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> (<title xml:lang="en">Sūtra Teaching the Four Factors</title>) is an explanation of four <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dharmas</foreign>, here meaning factors or qualities.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-4" index="1"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> is placed in the Degé and other Kangyurs of predominantly Tshalpa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshal pa</foreign>) origin as the second of a group of five short sūtras (Toh 248–52) all with titles and themes involving four topics. It is followed by two very similarly titled sūtras: the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharmaka</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bzhi pa’i mdo</title>, Toh 250), which lists four concerns (for sexual partners, the royal court, attractiveness, and wealth) to be avoided at all costs; and another with the same short-form title, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caturdharmaka</title> (Toh 251) but also, as a Mahāyāna sūtra, the more elaborate long-form title that Toh 250 lacks, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­catur­dharmaka­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>, which describes four dharmas (the mind of awakening, spiritual guides, patience, and living in solitude) that bodhisattvas must never relinquish throughout their lives.</note> These factors relate to the practice of confession (even though no equivalent of that word occurs in the sūtra itself) and the purification of misdeeds or negative, harmful actions (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāpa</foreign>). The four are: (1) the action (or correct approach) of repentance or self-reproach (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vidūṣaṇā­samudācāra</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnam par sun ’byin pa kun tu spyod pa</foreign>), which involves feeling remorse for past negative actions; (2) antidotal or remedial action (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratipa­ṣasamudācāra</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gnyen po kun tu spyod pa</foreign>), which means cultivating virtuous actions as an antidote to misdeeds; (3) the power of restraint (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pratyāpattibala</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sor chud par byed pa’i stobs</foreign>), which means vowing not to repeat a negative action; and (4) the power of support (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āśrayabala</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rten gyi stobs</foreign>), which means taking refuge in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, and never forsaking the mind of awakening. Through employing these four factors, the sūtra says, any negative act, no matter how grave, can be “overcome” in the sense that its karmic consequences can be transformed. This became a crucial idea for Mahāyāna ethics, both in theory and in practice.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-5"/>
                    <p tid="4">The importance of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> is evident from the numerous references to it that appear in Indian Mahāyāna literature. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyā­patti­deśanā­vṛtti</title>
                        (<title xml:lang="en">Commentary on the Confession of Bodhisattva Downfalls</title>), for example, which is attributed to Nāgārjuna, cites the sūtra and elaborates on the four powers (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs bzhi</foreign>), as the four factors came to be known, despite the fact that only the final two are labeled “power” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">stobs</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bala</foreign>) in the sūtra itself. Bhāviveka’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tarkajvālā</title>, too, refers to the sūtra in support of the view that even the very gravest of negative actions can be purified. And chapter eight of Śāntideva’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> (<title xml:lang="en">Compendium of Training</title>), on the purification of misdeeds (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pāpaśodhana</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sdig pa sbyong ba</foreign>), not only quotes from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title>, but even takes the four factors as its central theme.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-6"/>
                    <p tid="5">Tibetan authors, too, make it clear that the four powers are the key elements of confessional practice (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bshags pa</foreign>). In his famous <title xml:lang="en">Ornament of Precious Liberation</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dwags po thar rgyan</title>), Gampopa Sönam Rinchen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgam po pa bsod nams rin chen</foreign>, 1079–1153) relates the powers to episodes in the lives of the Buddha’s contemporaries Nanda, Aṅgulimāla, Ajātaśatru, and Udayana, in order to demonstrate the necessity of each factor. Tsongkhapa Losang Drakpa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsong kha pa blo bzang grags pa</foreign>, 1357–1419) draws on both the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> itself and Śāntideva’s discussion in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title> to explain the powers in some detail in his magnum opus, the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Lamrim Chenmo</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-7" index="2"> See Tsong-kha-pa 2000 vol. 1, 251–4. Dza Patrul Rinpoche’s (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdza dpal sprul</foreign>, 1808–87) famous nineteenth century work <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun bzang bla ma’i zhal lung</title> and its commentary by Khenpo Ngawang Pelzang (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngag dbang dpal bzang</foreign>, 1879–1941) discuss the four powers in relation to meditation on the deity Vajrasattva. See Patrul Rinpoche 1998, 265–7 and Ngawang Pelzang 2004, 226–7.</note> It is also common to find reference to the four powers in Tibetan purificatory rites and commentaries on them.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-8" index="3"> One such text, entitled <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bzhi’i bshags bsdoms bya tshul</title>, was composed by the First (or Fourth according to some methods of counting) Paṇchen Lama, Losang Chökyi Gyaltsen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo bzang chos kyi rgyal mtshan</foreign>, 1570–1662). The same author also wrote another rite incorporating the four powers that focuses on the thirty-five buddhas of confession. See <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bzhi tshang ba sangs rgyas so lnga’i bya tshul</title>.</note> There are slight variations in the spelling of the names and the sequence of these powers, and not all Tibetan works cite the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> as their source, but the derivation is clear enough.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-9" index="4"> Patrul Rinpoche’s <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun bzang bla ma’i zhal lung</title>, for example, makes no reference to the sūtra and discusses the four powers in a different sequence, beginning with the power of support. See Patrul Rinpoche 1998, 265–7.</note>
                        </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-10"/>
                    <p tid="6">At least two Sanskrit editions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> exist today.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-11" index="5"> Besides the Potala manuscript, there is also a Sanskrit edition included in Samten and Pandey 2003, 45–52.</note> One is a manuscript from a collection held in the Potala library in Lhasa, which recently became available in a critical edition.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-12" index="6"> See Tseng 2010.</note> It exhibits several variations from the versions in the Tibetan canon, most notably in its inclusion, near the end, of a four-line verse that it attributes to the Buddha himself: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-13"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="7">
                        <l>“Even minor transgressions prove the downfall of the foolish,</l>
                        <l>Whereas even serious transgressions do not affect the wise.</l>
                        <l>A lump of iron, though small, sinks in water;</l>
                        <l>But even a great mass of iron, when made into a vessel, floats.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-14" index="7"> The Potala Sanskrit edition (Tseng 2010, vol. 1, 404) is as follows: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">kṛtvābudho ’lpam api pāpam adhaḥ prayāti kṛtvā budho mahad api prajahāty anarthān | majjaty ayo ’lpam api vāriṇi saṃhataṃ hi pātrīkṛtaṃ mahad api plavate tad eva ||.</foreign> The verse also appears, without mention of its source, in Vasubandhu’s auto-commentary to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhidharmakośa</title>. For alternative English translations see Tseng 2010, vol. 1, 405, and Pruden 1988, 962.</note> 
                     </l>
                    </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-15"/>
                    <p tid="8">Some other minor differences are also noted below. The following translation was made primarily on the basis of the Degé block print and the Comparative Edition (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>), although it follows the Peking Yongle and Kangxi recensions on one significant point, for reasons that are explained in a note. Otherwise, since the various Tibetan canonical versions vary among themselves only slightly in matters of orthography, such instances have not been specified here. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="24"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="25">The Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra Entitled</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="26">Teaching the Four Factors</head>
                <div type="section">
                   <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-16"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <ref cRef="F.59.a" type="folio"/> Homage to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas!</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-55"/>
                    <p tid="10">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in the Sudharmā assembly hall in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, together with a great gathering of five hundred monks,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-17" index="8"> The Potala Sanskrit edition (Tseng 2010, vol. 1, 397) reads “one thousand two hundred and fifty monks” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ardha­trayoda­śabhir bhikṣuśatair</foreign>).</note> and very many bodhisattva mahāsattvas, including Maitreya and Mañjuśrī. 
                 </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-18"/>
                    <p tid="11">At that time the Blessed One said to the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, <ref cRef="F.59.b" type="folio"/> “O Maitreya, bodhisattva mahāsattva, if you possess four factors, the misdeeds you have committed and accumulated will be overcome. 
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-19"/>
                    <p tid="12">“What are these four? The action of repentance, antidotal action, the power of restraint, and the power of support.
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-56"/>
                    <p tid="13">“The action of repentance is to feel intense remorse for any non-virtuous action you have committed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-57"/>
                    <p tid="14">“Antidotal action is to put great effort into virtuous actions once you have committed a non-virtuous action.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-58"/>
                    <p tid="15">“The power of restraint is to make a pledge and thereby refrain from any similar action.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-20" index="9"> Here the translation follows the Peking Kangxi and Yongle Kangyurs, as well as the Potala Sanskrit manuscript and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>, in reading <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi phyed pa’i sdom pa</foreign> as <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi byed pa’i sdom pa</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">akaraṇasaṃvara</foreign>). This reading not only accords with the available Sanskrit, it also follows the definitions of the other powers in providing an instruction rather than a mere description. Moreover, the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi byed pa’i sdom pa</foreign> is also retained in the citations of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title> that appear in several treatises in the Tengyur, including Bhāviveka’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tarkajvālā</title>, Prajñākaramati’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhi­caryā­vatāra­pañjikā</title>, and Abhayākaragupta’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Munimatālaṃkāra</title>. The alternative reading, which is to be found in the other Kangyurs, could be translated as: “The power of restraint is to make a pledge and thereby gain an inviolable vow.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-59"/>
                    <p tid="16">“The power of support is to take refuge in the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha, and not to forsake the mind of awakening. By relying on such powerful forces, you will be immune to misdeeds.
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-21"/>
                    <p tid="17">“O Maitreya, bodhisattva mahāsattva, if you possess these four factors, you will overcome any misdeeds that you have committed and accumulated. The bodhisattva mahāsattva should continually read this sūtra, recite it aloud, and reflect and meditate on it, doing so many times. Through this, the effects of negative conduct will not come about.”
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-22"/>
                    <p tid="18">Once the Blessed One had said this, the whole assembly, including the bodhisattva mahāsattva Maitreya, the monks, the bodhisattvas, and the ranks of the gods, such as Śakra, were overjoyed and full of praise for what the Blessed One had taught.
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-23"/>
                    <trailer tid="19">This concludes the noble Mahāyāna sūtra entitled “<title xml:lang="en">Teaching the Four Factors</title>.” 
                    </trailer>
                </div>
               <div type="colophon">
                <head type="colophon" tid="27">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-24"/>
                    <p tid="20">Translated, edited, and corrected by the Indian preceptor Surendrabodhi and the principal editor and translator venerable Yeshé Dé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="28">Notes</head>
            </div>
          <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="29">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="30">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-30">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos bzhi bstan pa zhes bya theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtra</title>). Toh 249, Degé Kangyur vol. 66 (mdo sde, za), folios 59a–59b. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-31">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa chos bzhi bstan pa zhes bya theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripiṭaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 66, pp. 163–5.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-25">Bhāviveka. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbu ma’i snying po’i ’grel pa rtog ge ’bar ba </title>(<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyamaka­hṛdaya­tarka­jvālā</title>). Toh 3856. Degé Tengyur vol. 98 (dbu ma, dza), folios 40b–329b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-26">Gampopa Sönam Rinchen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgam po pa bsod nams rin chen</foreign>). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam chos yid bzhin gyi nor bu thar pa rin po che’i rgyan</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstan rim gces btus</title> (Institute of Tibetan Classics vol. 10). Delhi: bod kyi gtsug lag zhib ’jug khang, 2009, pp. 45–243.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-27">Losang Chökyi Gyaltsen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo bzang chos kyi rgyal mtshan</foreign>). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bzhi’i bshags bsdoms bya tshul</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo bzang chos kyi rgyi mtshan dpal bzang po’i gsung ’bum</title>, 5 volumes, bkra shis lhun po’i par khang. 199? vol. 4, pp. 527–32. (Cf. vol. 5, pp. 293–6).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-28">———. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs bzhi tshang ba sangs rgyas so lnga’i bya tshul.</title> In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo bzang chos kyi rgyal mtshan dpal bzang po’i gsung ’bum</title>, 5 volumes, bkra shis lhun po’i par khang. 199? vol. 5, 286–9.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-29">Nāgārjuna. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi ltung ba bshags pa’i ’grel pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bodhyāpatti­deśanā­vṛtti</title>). Toh 4005. Degé Tengyur vol. 116 (mdo ’grel, ji), folios 178a–187b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-32">Śāntideva. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa kun las btus pa</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣāsamuccaya</title>). Toh 3940. Degé Tengyur vol. 111 (dbu ma, khi), folios 3a–194b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-33">Tsongkhapa Losang Drakpa (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsong kha pa blo bzang grags pa</foreign>). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyes bu gsum gyi nyams su blang ba’i rim pa thams cad tshang bar ston pa’i byang chub lam gyi rim pa</title> in <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rje tsong kha pa’i gsung ’bum</title>. 18 volumes. Dharamsala: Sherig Parkhang, 1997, vol. 13, folios 1–521.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="31">Western Language Sources and Translations</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-34">Bendall, Cecil and W.H.D. Rouse. <title xml:lang="en">Śikshā­Samuccaya: A Compendium of Buddhist Doctrine Compiled by Śāntideva</title>. London: John Murray, 1922.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-35">Feer, Henri Léon. “Le Sūtra des Quatre Préceptes.” <title xml:lang="fr">Journal Asiatique</title>, sér. 6, tome 8 (1866): 269–357.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-36">Gampopa. <title xml:lang="en">The Jewel Ornament of Liberation: The Wish-fulfilling Gem of the Noble Teachings</title>. Translated by Khenpo Konchog Gyaltsen Rinpoche. Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-37">Goodman, Charles. <title xml:lang="en">The Training Anthology of Śāntideva: A Translation of the Śikṣā-samuccaya</title>. New York: Oxford University Press, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-38">Ngawang Pelzang. <title xml:lang="en">A Guide to The Words of My Perfect Teacher</title>. Translated by Padmakara Translation Group. Boston: Shambhala Publications, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-39">Patrul Rinpoche. <title xml:lang="en">The Words of My Perfect Teacher</title>. Translated by Padmakara Translation Group. Boston: Shambhala Publications, 1998.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-40">Pruden, Leo M. <title xml:lang="en">Abhi­dharma­kośa­bhāṣyam by Louis de la Vallée Poussin.English Translation</title>. 4 vols. Berkeley, California: Asian Humanities Press, 1988. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-41">Samten, Ngawang and Janarden Pandey (ed.). “Ārya­Catur­dharma­nirdeśa­sūtram.” <title xml:lang="en">Dhīḥ: Journal of Rare Buddhist Texts Research Unit</title>, 35 (2003): 45–52.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-42">Tseng, Vinita. <title xml:lang="en">A unique collection of twenty Sūtras in a Sanskrit manuscript from the Potala</title>. Volume I.1. Austrian Academy of Sciences Press, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-43">Tsong-kha-pa. <title xml:lang="en">The Great Treatise on the Stages of the Path to Enlightenment</title>. vol. 1. Translated by the Lamrim Chenmo Translation Committee. Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications, 2000.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-066-007-44">Wangchuk, Dorji. <title xml:lang="en">The Resolve to Become a Buddha: A Study of the Bodhicitta Concept in Indo-Tibetan Buddhism</title>. Tokyo: The International Institute for Buddhist Studies, 2007.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-45">
                            <term>action of repentance </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam par sun ’byin pa kun tu spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་པར་སུན་འབྱིན་པ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidūṣaṇā­samudācāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Feeling remorse for past negative actions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-46">
                            <term>power of support </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rten gyi stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟེན་གྱི་སྟོབས།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āśrayabala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Calling upon the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha and vowing not to
                                forsake the mind of awakening as a support in avoiding negative actions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-47">
                            <term>power of restraint </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sor chud par byed pa’i stobs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོར་ཆུད་པར་བྱེད་པའི་སྟོབས།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyāpattibala</term>
                            <term type="definition">Pledging not to repeat past negative actions.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-48">
                            <term>antidotal action </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnyen po kun tu spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཉེན་པོ་ཀུན་ཏུ་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prati­pakṣa­samudācāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Carrying out virtuous actions as an antidote to past negative
                                deeds.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-49">
                            <term>Maitreya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་པ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maitreya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of loving kindness; the next buddha to follow
                                Śakyāmuni.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-50">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Bodhisattva of wisdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-51">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                            <term type="definition">An alternative name for Indra, lord of the gods, who, according to
                                Buddhist cosmology, resides in the Heaven of the Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-52">
                            <term>Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">su ren dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུ་རེན་དྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Surendrabodhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An Indian paṇḍiṭa resident in Tibet during the late eighth and early
                                ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-53">
                            <term>Yeshé Dé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་སྡེ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">A prolific Tibetan translator active during the late eighth and
                                early ninth centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-54">
                            <term>Sudharmā </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་བཟང་།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sudharmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">An assembly hall located in the southwest of the Heaven of the
                                Thirty-Three.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-066-007-60">
                            <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second heaven of the desire realm located above Mount
                                Meru.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
 </TEI>