<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa gsum gyi mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བསླབ་པ་གསུམ་གྱི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śikṣātrayasūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa gsum gyi mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-10">Translated by the Dharmasāgara Translation Group<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-79">Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-80">Rebecca Hufen</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-82">Shanshan Jia</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-81">Jason Sanche</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-83">Arne Schelling</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-95">Celso Wilkinson</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.12 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-068-016"/>
                <date>2018-01-21</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh282" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 282</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 68 (mdo sde, ya), folios 55.b–56.a</biblScope>
                    <location count-pages="2">
                        <start volume="68" page="112"/>
                        <end volume="68" page="113"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11943" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-06-18T16:36:06.701Z" user="admin">18/06/2019 16:36:06</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.12" date-time="2019-06-18T16:36:03.968Z" user="celso">v 1.12 2019</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--
                    <p>Contents</p>
            <p>Summary</p>
            <p>Acknowledgments</p>
            <p>Introduction</p>
            <p>The Translation</p>
            <p rend="italic">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</p>
            <p>Notes</p>
            <p>Bibliography</p>< -->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="12">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</title>, Buddha Śākyamuni briefly
                    introduces the three elements or stages of the path, widely known as “the three trainings,” one by one in a
                    specific order: discipline, meditative concentration, and wisdom. He teaches that training progressively in
                    them constitutes the gradual path to awakening.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="13">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This text was translated from the Tibetan, with comparison to Sanskrit, Chinese, and Pali editions,
                    introduced and edited by the Dharmasāgara Translation Group: Raktrul Ngawang Kunga Rinpoche, Rebecca Hufen,
                    Shanshan Jia, Jason Sanche, and Arne Schelling.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="14">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</title> is, in essence, a brief outline of the
                        core teachings of Buddha Śākyamuni, which he gave while travelling toward Kuśinagara in the last year
                        before his parinirvāṇa. It was given to a large audience of fully ordained monks in a grove to the north
                        of Kuṭigrāmaka, a village in the ancient Indian country of Vṛji, which extended from the north bank of the
                        Ganges opposite Pāṭaliputra up to the Madhesh regions of what is currently southern Nepal. The sūtra’s
                        condensed teaching represents the three stages of the gradual Buddhist path to enlightenment and
                        emphasizes how the trainings are undertaken in progression. The first training, discipline, is taught as
                        the basis for the second training, meditative concentration, which in turn is a prerequisite to wisdom,
                        the third training.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-4"/>
                    <p tid="4"> There appear to be several parallels or versions of this text. In its Tibetan translation it is
                        preserved not only as an independent sūtra, but also in the form of short passages in two long vinaya
                        texts, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title> (sixth chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>)<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-5">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>, Degé Kangyur vol. 2, F.36b–37a. See also Yao
                            (forthcoming).</note> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title>.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-6">
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title>, Degé Kangyur vol. 11, F.239a–239b. See also
                            Jamspal et al. (forthcoming).</note> It is also found as a passage in the non-Mahāyāna <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra</title>, of which so far only incomplete Sanskrit manuscripts
                        are extant, although a Sanskrit version has been reconstructed by Ernst Waldschmidt (1951). With some
                        variant readings, the same passage appears, too, in the still extant Pali <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Mahāparinibbāna Sutta</title>. Translations of it in Chinese can be found as part of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra</title> and passages in some vinaya texts.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-7"> 1. Taishō No. 1 <title xml:lang="zh">長阿含經</title>; 2. Taishō No.
                            5 <title xml:lang="zh">佛般泥洹經</title>; 3. Taishō No. 6 <title xml:lang="zh">般泥洹經</title>; 4. Taishō
                            1451 <title xml:lang="zh">根本說一切有部毘奈耶雜事</title>; 5. Taishō No. 1448 <title xml:lang="zh">根本說一切有部毘奈耶藥事</title>; 6. Taishō No. 1421 <title xml:lang="zh">彌沙塞部和醯五分律</title>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-8"/>
                    <p tid="5">A number of studies and translations of the aforementioned texts in Western languages have been
                        carried out, for example those by Waldschmidt (1951) and Rhys Davids (1951). However, there have hitherto
                        been no translations, as far as we know, of the independent sūtra.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-9"/>
                    <p tid="6">In this translation of the sūtra from the Tibetan Kangyur, the text is introduced with the title in
                        Sanskrit and Tibetan, proceeding with the homage and then the general opening formula of “Thus have I
                        heard at one time.” Naturally, in the other versions in which this text is embedded as part of a larger
                        work, these introductory statements and the concluding sentence are not included. Besides this, there are
                        a few variant readings in the Tibetan, Sanskrit, Pali, and especially in the Chinese. Since most of them
                        do not alter the meaning significantly, we have chosen to note only the most important variants.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="15">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="16">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-10"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <ref cRef="F.55.b"/> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-32"/>
                    <p tid="8">Thus have I heard at one time. As the Bhagavān was wandering in the land of Vṛji, he arrived at the
                        village of Kuṭigrāmaka and settled to the north of that village in a grove of sāl trees,<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-11"> The Tibetan versions in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title>, as well as the
                            Sanskrit and Chinese versions in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇa Sūtra</title>, here
                            instead have <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śiṃśapā</foreign> (Tib. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing sha pa</foreign>), which refers to the Indian rosewood tree (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">Dalbergia sissoo</foreign>).</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.56.a"/> with a great saṅgha of bhikṣus. Thereupon the Bhagavān taught the following to the
                        bhikṣus:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-12"/>
                    <p tid="9">“This, bhikṣus, is discipline.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-13"> All versions
                            except that in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title> have a plural here, thus
                            referring to a set of ethical-moral rules. With “discipline” being a well established translation for
                            the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla</foreign> and the Tibetan <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims</foreign>, and the plural “disciplines” being rather
                            misleading in English, we have kept the singular form, though in the sense of a mass noun. </note>
                        This is meditative concentration. This is wisdom. Bhikṣus, training in discipline will lead one to abide
                        for a long time in meditative concentration. Training in meditative concentration will lead one to gain
                        wisdom. By training in wisdom, one’s mind will be completely liberated from desire, anger, and ignorance.
                        In this way, having a completely liberated mind, a noble śrāvaka will perfectly know: ‘My defilements<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-14"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāparinirvāṇasūtra</title> instead
                            read “My births (Skt. <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jāti</foreign>; Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skye ba</foreign>) have ceased,” which is another commonly found statement made
                            by an arhat, as taught in other discourses.</note> have ceased. I have lived the sublime life. What
                        was to be done has been done. From here onward, I will not know any further existence.’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-15"/>
                    <p tid="10">After the Bhagavān had thus spoken, the bhikṣus rejoiced and praised the Bhagavān’s words.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-33"/>
                    <p tid="11">This completes <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Threefold Training</title>.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="17">Bibliography</head>
                                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="18">Tibetan texts</head>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-16">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa gsum gyi mdo.</title> Toh 282, Degé Kangyur, vol. 68 (mdo sde, ya),
                            folios 55b–56a. </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-17">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bslab pa gsum gyi mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition
                            of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                            Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i
                            bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 68, pp. 165–166. </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-18">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sman gyi gzhi</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>),
                            chapter 6 of <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba gzhi</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>), Toh 1. Degé Kangyur, vol. 1 (’dul ba, ka), folio 277b– vol.3 (’dul ba, ga),
                            folio 50a. Translated in Yao (forthcoming).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-19">
                            <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba phran tshegs kyi gzhi</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣudrakavastu</title>), Toh 6. Degé Kangyur, vol. 10 (’dul ba, tha), folio 1a– vol. 11
                            (’dul ba, da), folio 333a. Translated in Jamspal et al. (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="19">Other works</head>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-20">Jamspal, L., and Fischer, K. <title xml:lang="en">The Finer Points of
                                Discipline‌</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayakṣurakavastu</title>, Toh 6). 84000:
                            Translating the Words of the Buddha (forthcoming).</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-21">Rhys Davids, Caroline A. F. and Thomas W. <title xml:lang="en">Dialogues
                                of the Buddha: Translated from the Pali of the Dîgha Nikâya</title>. Third Edition. Published for
                            the Pali Text Society. London: Luzac, 1951.</bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-22">Waldschmidt, Ernst. “Das Mahāparinirvāṇasūtra: Text in Sanskrit und
                            Tibetisch, verglichen mit dem Pali nebst einer Übersetzung der chinesischen Entsprechung im Vinaya der
                            Mūlasarvāstivādins auf Grund von Turfan-Handschriften,” in <title xml:lang="de">Abhandlungen der Deutschen Akademie
                                der Wissenschaften zu Berlin, Klasse für Sprachen, Literatur und Kunst.</title> Berlin:
                            Akademie-Verlag, 1951, vol. 2, pp. 101–303. </bibl>
                        <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-016-23">Yao, Fumi. <title xml:lang="en">The Chapter on Medicinal
                                Materials</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>, chapter 6 of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha
                            (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-24">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-25">
                            <term>sāl tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shing sa la </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤིང་ས་ལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">Usually identified as <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">Shorea
                                    robusta</foreign>, known as the kind of tree under which the Buddha was born and passed
                                away.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-26">
                            <term>discipline</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śīla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A mind set on abandoning the undisciplined conduct of body, speech, and
                                mind.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-27">
                            <term>meditative concentration</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A mind focused one-pointedly on an object of concentration.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-28">
                            <term>wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A mind that sees the ultimate truth directly.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-29">
                            <term>śrāvaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyan thos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉན་ཐོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Primarily referring to those disciples of the Buddha who aspire to attain the
                                state of an arhat by seeking self liberation. It is usually defined as “those who hear the
                                teaching from the Buddha and make it heard to others.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-30">
                            <term>Vṛji</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spong byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤོང་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vṛji</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the sixteen principal <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahājanapadas</foreign> (great
                                countries) of ancient India, and a confederacy of eight or nine clans. It extended from the north
                                bank of the Ganges opposite Pāṭaliputra up to the Madhesh regions of present southern
                                Nepal.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-068-016-31">
                            <term>Kuṭigrāmaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyil bu can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱིལ་བུ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kuṭigrāmaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A settlement / village in the country of Vṛji. According to a commentary on
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvaṃsa</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaṃsatthappakāsinī</title>, it is one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">gāvuta</foreign>
                                (about two miles) away from the river Ganges.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>