<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sku gsum pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྐུ་གསུམ་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Three Bodies</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trikāya­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་སྐུ་གསུམ་ཞེས་བྱ་བ་ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sku gsum zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble ‌Mahāyāna Sūtra “The Three Bodies”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­trikāya­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-7">
                    Translated by the Buddhavacana Translation Group
                    <lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-30"/>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-31"/>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-28"/>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.1 <date>2013 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-068-017"/>
                <date>2013-10-26</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh283" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 283</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 68 (mdo sde, ya), folios 56.a–57.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Unknown</author>
                    <location count-pages="3">
                        <start volume="68" page="113"/>
                        <end volume="68" page="115"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11945" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:26:36 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- Contents
                Summary
                Acknowledgments
                Introduction
                The Translation
                The Sūtra of the Three Bodies
                Notes
                Bibliography-->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="22">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-1"/>
                <p tid="1">As the title suggests, this sūtra describes the three bodies of the Buddha. While the Buddha is
                    dwelling on Vulture Peak in Rājgṛha, the Bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha asks whether the Tathāgata has a body, to
                    which the Buddha replies that the Tathāgata has three bodies: a dharmakāya, a saṃbhogakāya, and a nirmāṇakāya.
                    The Buddha goes on to describe what constitutes these three bodies and their associated meaning. The Buddha
                    explains that the dharmakāya is like space, the saṃbhogakāya is like clouds, and the nirmāṇakāya is like rain.
                    At the end of the Buddha’s elucidation, Kṣitigarbha expresses jubilation, and the Buddha declares that whoever
                    upholds this Dharma teaching will obtain immeasurable merit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="23">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translation by the Buddhavacana Translation Group, Vienna, under the supervision of Khenpo Konchok
                    Tamphel. Translated into English by Rolf Scheuermann and Casey Kemp.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="24">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The setting of this sūtra is Vulture Peak in Rajgir (Rājgṛha), said to be the location where the
                        Buddha, explaining the doctrine of emptiness in the second turning of the wheel of Dharma, taught the
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā­pāramitā</foreign> and other topics associated with Mahāyāna
                        Buddhism. It is here that the bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha asks the Buddha a series of questions regarding the
                        body of the Buddha, which the Buddha answers by expounding the teaching on the three bodies.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The doctrine of the Buddha’s three bodies (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trikāya</foreign>) has tended to be associated with the Yogācāra school of Buddhist thought, although the
                        terms dharmakāya and rūpakāya (form body) are certainly to be found in sūtras such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṣṭa­sāhasrikā­prajñā­pāramitā­sūtra</title>.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-53">For more on the philosophical considerations of the three bodies, see
                            Harrison (1992) pp 44-94.</note> It has been suggested that sūtras such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trikāyasūtra</title> may have evolved after such Yogācāra treatises as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­yāna­sūtrālaṃkāra</title>.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-54">See Makransky (1997) pp.274.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">This tri-fold scheme can also be interpreted as describing different aspects of enlightenment or
                        buddhahood itself. The dharmakāya, sometimes translated as the “truth body” or “reality body,” generally
                        refers to the essential nature of the Buddha, as is stated in this sūtra. The saṃbhogakāya and the
                        nirmāṇakāya, known collectively as the form bodies, are understood as emanations of the dharmakāya, or
                        essential nature, of the Buddha. In other words, they are the manifestations of the enlightened activity
                        of the Buddha. The saṃbhogakāya, sometimes translated as “enjoyment body,” is the apparitional form the
                        Buddha takes for bodhisattvas and practitioners in meditative states or in dreams. The nirmāṇakāya,
                        sometimes translated as “manifestation body,” is the physical form of the Buddha that can be seen by any
                        sentient being. The Buddha, who is able to emanate in countless forms, does so in order to liberate beings
                        through the illumination and demonstration of the Dharma. All three bodies<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-55">Some Mahā­yāna works such as the Abhi­samayālaṃkāra of Maitreya also
                            mention a fourth body, a svā­bhāvika­kāya, or “innate body.” There are conflicting interpretations by
                            Indian and Tibetan commentators as to the relationship between the svā­bhāvika­kāya and the
                            dharma­kāya. For more on the four bodies, see Makransky (1997).</note> are ultimately considered
                        inseparable. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">This is the only known sūtra in the Tibetan Kangyur solely dedicated to teaching the doctrine of
                        the three bodies. The Buddha explains here how one should view the bodies of the Buddha using analogies,
                        and relates the three bodies to other relevant Buddhist doctrines such as the four wisdoms.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-56">For information on the relationship between the
                            three bodies and four wisdoms in Buddhist literature, see Brunnhölzl (2009) pp.71-76.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">This sūtra was first translated by W. Woodville Rockhill in his 1884 publication of <title xml:lang="en">The Life of the Buddha and the Early History of His Order</title>. There is currently no
                        known extant version in Sanskrit, and among the different published Tibetan versions of the source text,
                        there do not seem to be any significant variants.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="25">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="26">The Noble ‌Mahāyāna Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="27">The Three Bodies</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">
                        <ref cRef="F.56.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling on Vulture Peak Mountain in Rājgṛha. He
                        was accompanied by his entire retinue, by immeasurable, countless bodhisattvas, and by gods and nāgas.
                        They paid respect to the Blessed One and made offerings to him.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">At that time, the bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha, who was sitting among the retinue, rose from his seat
                        and asked, “Has the Blessed One a body?”</p>
                    <p tid="12">The Blessed One replied, “Kṣitigarbha, the Blessed One, the Tathāgata, <ref cRef="F.56.b"/> has
                        three bodies: a dharmakāya, a saṃbhogakāya and a nirmāṇakāya. Son of a noble family, the three bodies of
                        the Tathāgata are these: the pure nature is the dharmakāya, pure meditative absorption is the
                        saṃbhogakāya, and pure conduct is the nirmāṇakāya of all buddhas.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">“Son of a noble family, the dharmakāya of the Tathāgata consists in the fact that he has no
                        nature, just like the sky. His saṃbhogakāya consists in the fact that he comes forth, just like a cloud.
                        His nirmāṇakāya consists in the activity of all the buddhas, the fact that it soaks everything, just like
                        rain.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">The bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha then asked the Blessed One, “How should one view this explanation on
                        the three bodies of the Blessed One?” </p>
                    <p tid="15">The Blessed One answered the bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha, “Son of a noble family, you should view the
                        three bodies of the Tathāgata in the following way. The dharmakāya should be viewed as that which is the
                        essence of the Tathāgata. The saṃbhogakāya should be viewed as that which is the essence of the
                        bodhisattvas. The nirmāṇakāya should be viewed as that which is the essence of ordinary beings who conduct
                        themselves devotedly. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-13"/>
                    <p tid="16">“Son of a noble family, the dharmakāya remains the same nature for all the buddhas. The
                        saṃbhogakāya remains the same meditative absorption for all the buddhas. The nirmāṇakāya remains the same
                        awakened activity for all the buddhas. </p>
                    <p tid="17">“Son of a noble family, the basis-of-all in its pure state is mirror-like wisdom, the dharmakāya.
                        The afflicted mind in its pure state is the wisdom of equality. Mental cognition in its pure state is
                        discriminating wisdom, the saṃbhogakāya. The five sense cognitions in their pure state are
                        all-accomplishing wisdom, the nirmāṇakāya.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-14"/>
                    <p tid="18">The bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha then exclaimed to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, the noble Dharma that
                        I have heard from the Blessed One <ref cRef="F.57.a"/> is excellent, Sugata, really excellent!”</p>
                    <p tid="19">The Blessed One then declared, “Son of a noble family, whoever fully upholds this Dharma discourse
                        of the Blessed One will obtain merit that is immeasurable, inexpressible, incalculable and unfathomable.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-15"/>
                    <p tid="20">When the Blessed One had spoken, the world, including the bodhisattva Kṣitigarbha, the gods,
                        nāgas, yakṣas, and gandharvas rejoiced and praised the teachings of the Blessed One. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="28">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-16"/>
                    <p tid="21">This concludes the Noble Mahāyāna Sūtra, <title xml:lang="en">The Three Bodies</title>.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-57">The colophon makes no mention of who the Tibetan
                            translators were, and the Degé catalogue (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag</title>, vol. 103,
                            lak+Sh+mI, F.133.a.3) states that this is not known.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="29">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="30">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-18">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sku gsum zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­trikāya­nāma­mahā­yāna­sūtra</title>). Toh 283. Degé Kangyur, vol. 68 (mdo sde,
                        ya), folios 56a–57a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-19">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa sku gsum zhes bya ba theg pa chen po’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe
                        bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan
                        dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripiṭaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009,
                        vol. 68 (mdo sde, ya), pp 168-170.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-20">Brunnhölzl, Karl (2009). <title xml:lang="en">Luminous Heart: The Third
                            Karmapa on Consciousness, Wisdom, and Buddha Nature</title>. Ithaca: Snow Lion Publications,
                        2009.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-21">Harrison, Paul (1992). “Is the Dharma-kāya the Real ‘Phantom Body’ of the
                        Buddha?” In <title xml:lang="en">The Journal of the International Association for Buddhist Studies</title>
                        Vol. 15 No 1, 1992. pp 44-94.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-22">Makransky, John J. (1997). <title xml:lang="en">Buddhahood Embodied: Sources
                            of Controversy in India and Tibet. </title>SUNY Series in Buddhist Studies. Albany: State University
                        of New York Press, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-23">Nagao, Gadjin M. <title xml:lang="en">Mādhyamika and Yogācāra: A Study of
                            ‌Mahāyāna Philosophies</title>. Leslie S. Kawamura (Trans.) Albany: State University of New York,
                        1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-068-017-24">Rockhill, W. Woodville (Trans.) <title xml:lang="en">The Life of the Buddha
                            and The Early History of His Order Derived from Tibetan Works in the Bkah-hgyur and
                            Bstan-hgyur</title>. London: Trübner &amp; Co., Ludgate Hill, 1884.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-25">
                            <term>bodhisattva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub sems dpa’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་སེམས་དཔའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhisattva</term>
                            <term type="definition">According to the Mahāyāna, an individual with the intent to achieve awakening
                                for the sake of all beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-26">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Snake-like mystical creature with supernatural powers belonging to the animal
                                realm.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-27">
                            <term>dharmakāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Dharmakāya</term> or body of dharma refers to the Buddha’s realization of reality.
                                Sometimes translated “truth body” or “reality body.” In other contexts, particularly in early
                                texts, the term may also refer to the Buddha’s qualities as a collective whole, or to his
                                teachings as embodying him.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-28">
                            <term>saṃbhogakāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">longs spyod rdzogs pa’i sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལོངས་སྤྱོད་རྫོགས་པའི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃbhogakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Saṃbhogakāya</term> or body of enjoyment. Aspect of buddhahood perceptible to
                                bodhisattvas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-29">
                            <term>nirmāṇakāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sprul pa’i sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྲུལ་པའི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nirmāṇakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Nirmāṇakāya</term> or body of manifestation. Aspect of buddhahood perceptible to
                                ordinary individuals with good karma.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-30">
                            <term>three bodies</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sku gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐུ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trikāya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-31">
                            <term>basis-of-all</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun gzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་གཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Here, probably the short form for <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ālayavijñāna</foreign>. </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-32">
                            <term>mirror-like wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me long lta bu’i ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ལོང་ལྟ་བུའི་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ādarśajñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-33">
                            <term>afflicted mind</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs pa’i yid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས་པའི་ཡིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kliṣṭamana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-34">
                            <term>wisdom of equality</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyam pa nyid kyi ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉམ་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samatājñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-35">
                            <term>mental cognition</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid kyi rnam par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་ཀྱི་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">manovijñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">Just as the five sense cognitions occur on the basis of the five sense
                                faculties, <term type="ignore">mental cognition</term> is the cognition that occurs on the basis of the mind faculty.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-36">
                            <term>discriminating wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">so sor kun du rtog pa’i ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སོ་སོར་ཀུན་དུ་རྟོག་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratyavekṣaṇā­jñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-37">
                            <term>five sense cognitions</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgo lnga’i rnam par shes pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒོ་ལྔའི་རྣམ་པར་ཤེས་པ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-38">
                            <term>all-accomplishing wisdom</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya ba grub pa’i ye shes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་བ་གྲུབ་པའི་ཡེ་ཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṛtyānuśṭhāna­jñāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-39">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Yakṣas</term> or harm givers. A class of mostly malevolent spirits.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-40">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Gandharvas</term>, literally “smell-eaters,” are a class of spirits, sometimes
                                described as celestial musicians. In other contexts the term can also refer to beings in the
                                bardo-state.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-41" mode="marked">
                            <term>prajñā­pāramitā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab kyi pha rol tu phyin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ་ཀྱི་ཕ་རོལ་ཏུ་ཕྱིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā­pāramitā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-42">
                            <term>Mahāyāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">theg pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐེག་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāyāna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-43">
                            <term>emptiness</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śūnyatā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-44">
                            <term>Yogācāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣལ་འབྱོར་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogācāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Influential philosophical school belonging to Mahāyāna Buddhism.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <!--<item>
                        <gloss type="term" priority="0" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-45">
                            <term>teachings of the Buddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>-->
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-46">
                            <term>rūpakāya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs kyi sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཀྱི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Used to refer to the two form bodies of the Buddha, i.e. the nirmāṇakāya and
                                the saṃbhogakāya.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-47">
                            <term>form bodies</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs kyi sku </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས་ཀྱི་སྐུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rūpakāya</term>
                            <term type="definition">See “rūpakāya.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-48">
                            <term>Blessed One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavat</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-49">
                            <term>Kṣitigarbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa’i snying po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སའི་སྙིང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṣitigarbha</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important bodhisattva disciple of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-50">
                            <term>tathāgata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དེ་བཞིན་གཤེགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tathāgata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of the Buddha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-51">
                            <term>Rājgṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal po’i khab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་པོའི་ཁབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rājgṛha</term>
                            <term type="definition">Town close to Nālānda in the modern state of Bihar.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-068-017-52">
                            <term>Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bya rgod phung po’i ri </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱ་རྒོད་ཕུང་པོའི་རི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gṛ̥dhra­kūṭa-parvata</term>
                            <term type="definition">Name of a mountain close to Rājgṛha. It is famous as the place where the Buddha
                                is said to have taught the Prajñāpāramitā and other teachings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>