<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i bshes gnyen bsten pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན་བསྟེན་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on Reliance upon a Virtuous Spiritual Friend</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalyāṇa­mitra­sevana­sūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན་བསྟེན་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dge ba’i bshes gnyen bsten pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Noble Sūtra on Reliance upon a Virtuous Spiritual Friend</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­kalyāṇa­mitra­sevana­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-27">Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy
                    Division)<lb/> under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-182">Christian Bernert</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-174">Khenpo Ngawang Jorden</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.15.3 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-071-014"/>
                <date>2011-09-23</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh300" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 300</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol 71 (mdo sde, sha), folios 304.b–305.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Paṇḍita Dharmākara</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Lotsāwa Zangkyong (bzang skyong)</author>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="2">
                        <volume number="71" start-page="608" end-page="609"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11967" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-02-21T20:12:16.731Z" user="admin">21/02/2020 20:12:16</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 2.15" date-time="2019-06-18T02:59:11.828Z" user="celso">v 2.15 2019</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 2.15.1" date-time="2019-10-07T10:27:24.685Z" user="admin">Publication statement updated</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 2.15.2" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version increment</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 2.15.3" date-time="2020-02-21T20:12:14.041Z" user="celso">corrected dash in &lt;biblscope&gt;</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- Contents
                Summary
                Acknowledgments
                Introduction
                Notes on the Introduction
                The Translation
                The Sūtra on Reliance upon a Virtuous Spiritual Friend
                Bibliography
                Notes -->
            <!--            COULD NOT FIND NOTE 3
            <note place="end">DN: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn>Āryakalyāṇamitrasevanisūtra;</title> Q:
                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryakalyanemitrasevanaṃsūtra.</title>
            </note>-->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="23">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-1"/>
                <p tid="1">Just prior to his passing away, Buddha Śākyamuni reminds his disciples of the importance of living with
                    a qualified spiritual teacher. Ānanda, the Blessed One’s attendant, attempts to confirm his teacher’s
                    statement, saying that a virtuous spiritual friend is indeed half of one’s spiritual life. Correcting his
                    disciple’s understanding, the Buddha explains that a qualified guide is the whole of, rather than half of, the
                    holy life, and that by relying upon a spiritual friend beings will be released from birth and attain
                    liberation from all types of suffering.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="24">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This sūtra was translated from Tibetan into English by Khenpo Ngawang Jorden and Christian Bernert,
                    members of the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division), Kathmandu.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="25">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The setting for this sūtra is a grove near Kuśinagara, the capital of the Malla kingdom, where
                        Buddha Śākyamuni spent his last hours before passing into parinirvāṇa, the final state of release from the
                        suffering of worldly existence. Kuśinagara, situated in what is now the north-Indian state of Uttar
                        Pradesh, is venerated by Buddhists as one of the four holiest shrines. The other three are Lumbini, his
                        birthplace in what is now southern Nepal; Bodhgaya in modern Bihar, where he attained enlightenment; and
                        Sarnath, near modern Varanasi, where he delivered his first sermon.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">In this sūtra, the Buddha discusses the importance of following a qualified spiritual teacher as a
                        support for one’s spiritual development. As it was delivered just prior to his passing away, we can see
                        how highly the Buddha esteemed the role of a teacher on the path. Correcting his disciple Ānanda’s
                        understanding, the Buddha explains that one’s spiritual development depends entirely on reliance upon a
                        qualified guide or virtuous spiritual friend.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">Indeed, teachers play an eminent role in all Buddhist traditions, and are respected and venerated
                        accordingly in traditional Buddhist cultures. In different sūtras, the Buddha taught the four
                            reliances,<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-34">The teaching on the four reliances
                            reads as follows: “Rely on the teaching, rather than on the person. Rely on the meaning, rather than
                            on the syllables. Rely on the definitive meaning, rather than on the provisional meaning. Rely on
                            wisdom, rather than on consciousness.” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos la rton pa bya yi / gang zag
                                la rton pa mi bya bo// don la rton pa bya yi / tshig ’bru la rton pa mi bya bo // nges don la rton
                                pa bya yi / drang don la rton pa mi bya bo // ye shes la rton pa bya yi / rnam shes la rton pa mi
                                bya bo //</foreign>).</note> as one of which he advised his followers to rely on the teaching,
                        rather than on the person. In Buddhism, no person—no teacher, that is—functions as an ultimate refuge.
                        Even the Buddha’s physical form was subject to decay and thus not an ultimate object of refuge.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">However, as the Buddha explains in this sūtra, without the help of a spiritual friend, progress on
                        the path is very difficult, if not impossible. The teacher functions as a qualified and experienced guide,
                        capable of guiding others along the arduous path to liberation. A teacher inspires students by embodying
                        the results of the practice, guides them by pointing out the right direction, and supports their
                        development by removing doubts and confusions. While genuine progress is impossible without a teacher,
                        misguided advice could, even if well intended, be detrimental to one’s whole path. Consequently, the
                        Buddha stresses the importance of a qualified spiritual friend, but counsels caution in choosing the
                        teacher.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">This sūtra is quoted at the end of two <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avadāna</foreign>
                        stories, which like the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jātakas</foreign>, are accounts of the
                        great deeds of the Buddha and bodhisattvas in previous lives.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-35">For an analysis of those <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">avadānas</foreign> and an edition of the Sanskrit text of this sūtra see Alsdorf (1961).</note>
                        The translators of the Tibetan version are not recorded in the Tibetan colophon, but the Degé Kangyur
                        catalogue states that the text was translated by the (Indian) paṇḍita Dharmākara and the (Tibetan)
                        translator Zangkyong (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lo tsA ba bzang skyong</foreign>). Dharmākara contributed
                        to several Vinaya translations and, as a team, this pair was responsible for several other translations in
                        this part of the Kangyur as well as two commentaries in the Tengyur (Toh 4015 and 4038). There is evidence
                        that both were contemporaries of Kawa Paltsek (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ska ba dpal brtsegs</foreign>),
                        a major translator of the early period and active in at least part of the 8th century. However, unlike two
                        other works by the same translators (Toh 285 and 295), the translation of this text is not listed in the
                        early 9th century Denkarma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar ma</title>) or Pangthangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang thang ma</title>) inventories, which means either that it was completed only
                        later in the 9th century, or that it existed already but was listed as a canonical text only in later
                        compilations. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">In the Pāli canon, we find a corresponding sutta in the Mahā-vagga section of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">the Saṃyutta Nikāya,</title> namely the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upaḍḍha
                            Sutta</title> (SN 45.2), where the Buddha further mentions the eightfold path of the Noble Ones, which
                        those who are supported by a spiritual friend should follow.</p>
                    <p tid="10">There are corresponding sūtras extant in the Chinese (T 2.99) and the Korean (K 650) canons. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-9"/>
                    <p tid="11">The version of this sūtra in the Degé Kangyur was compared to those in the Narthang, Peking and
                        Lhasa Kangyurs. However there were no differences that required changing a word in the English
                        translation.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">A French translation of this sūtra from Tibetan by Léon Feer was published in the <title xml:lang="fr">Journal Asiatique</title> in 1866.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="26">Notes on the Translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">The terms <emph>virtuous spiritual friend</emph> and <emph>non-virtuous spiritual friend</emph>
                        are used in the translation to render the Tibetan terms <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i bshes
                            gnyen</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdig pa’i bshes gnyen.</foreign> While the terms
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdig pa</foreign> are not
                        literal opposites (as opposed to <emph>virtuous</emph> and <emph>non-virtuous</emph>), we chose this
                        rendering because in this sūtra, the Buddha makes the broad distinction between two types of teachers:
                        those worthy of being relied upon, and those who are not. To express this opposition clearly, we therefore
                        opted to translate <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sdig pa</foreign> as <emph>non-virtuous</emph>. Strictly
                        speaking, too, the word “spiritual” is an addition to the basic meaning of both the Tibetan and Sanskrit
                        terms. It seems, however, justified by the connotations in this context—good and bad teachers or spiritual
                        guides are implied, not simply ordinary friends and companions. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="27">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="28">The Noble Sūtra on</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="29">Reliance upon a Virtuous Spiritual Friend</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">
                        <ref cRef="F.304.b" type="folio"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">--> Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling in the Grove of Twin Sāl-Trees in the
                            vicinity<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-36">DK<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyen ’khor;</foreign> N: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye
                                ’khor</foreign>. </note> of the Malla town of Kuśinagara,<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-37">DN: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku sha na gyad;</foreign> K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>:
                                <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku shi na gyad</foreign>. </note> together with a retinue
                        of śrāvakas. Then, when the Bhagavān was about to pass into parinirvāṇa, he addressed the bhikṣus,
                        “Bhikṣus, you should train in this way. Bhikṣus, you should train thinking, ‘One should live with a
                        virtuous spiritual friend, a virtuous companion, a virtuous support. One should not, however, live with a
                        non-virtuous spiritual friend, a non-virtuous companion, a non-virtuous support.’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">Then, the venerable Ānanda spoke to the Bhagavān, “Honorable One, having come here alone to a
                        secluded place, I had gone into meditative retreat<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-38">
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nang du yang dag ’jog</foreign>; <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prati­saṃlayana</foreign>. </note> when the following thought arose in my mind:
                        ‘A virtuous spiritual friend, a virtuous companion, a virtuous support is half the holy life. A
                        non-virtuous spiritual friend, a non-virtuous companion, a non-virtuous support, however, is not.’ ”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">The Bhagavān replied, “Ānanda, <ref cRef="F.305.a" type="folio"/> do not say that a virtuous spiritual friend,
                        a virtuous companion, a virtuous support is half the holy life, but that a non-virtuous spiritual friend,
                        a non-virtuous companion, a non-virtuous support is not.</p>
                    <p tid="18">“Why? Ānanda, the point is that a virtuous spiritual friend, a virtuous companion, a virtuous
                        support is the whole, the unadulterated, the complete, the pure, the totally purified holy life, but a
                        non-virtuous spiritual friend, a non-virtuous companion, a non-virtuous support is not.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-16"/>
                    <p tid="19">“Why is that? Ānanda, it is because, by relying on me as their spiritual friend,<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-39">This translation is based on the Sanskrit, rather than the
                            Tibetan version of the text which would have to be rendered: “... relying on a spiritual friend and on
                            me ... .” Alsdorf (1961, p 12) remarks that the Tibetan version is faulty at this point.</note>
                        sentient beings subject to birth will be completely released from being subject to birth, and sentient
                        beings subject to aging, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering, distress, and agitation will be
                        completely released from being subject to aging, sickness, death, sorrow, lamentation, suffering,
                        distress, and agitation.</p>
                    <p tid="20">“Therefore, Ānanda, you should understand this in the following way alone. A virtuous spiritual
                        friend, a virtuous companion, a virtuous support is the whole, the unadulterated, the complete, the pure,
                        the totally purified holy life, but a non-virtuous spiritual friend, a non-virtuous companion, a
                        non-virtuous support is not. Ānanda, you should train thinking in this way.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-17"/>
                    <p tid="21">When the Bhagavān had spoken these words, the bhikṣus rejoiced and highly praised what the Blessed
                        One had taught. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-18"/>
                    <trailer tid="22">This completes “<title xml:lang="en">The Noble Sūtra on Reliance upon a Virtuous Spiritual
                        Friend</title>.”<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-40">The colophon makes no mention
                            of who the Tibetan translators were, but the Degé catalogue (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar
                                chag</title>, vol. 103, lak+Sh+mI, F.134.a.7) states that the text was translated by the Paṇḍita
                            Dharmākara and the Lotsāwa Zangkyong (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bzang skyong</foreign>). See
                            Introduction, <ptr target="#UT22084-071-014-7"/>.</note>
                    </trailer>
                </div>
                <!--<div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="30">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-18"/>
                   
                </div>-->
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="31">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="32">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-071-014-19">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-071-014-20">
                        <abbr>N</abbr>
                        <expan>Narthang Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-071-014-21">
                        <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>Peking (Qianlong) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="33">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-071-014-22">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dge ba’i bshes gnyen bsten pa’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­kalyāṇa­mitra­sevana­sūtra</title>). Toh 300, Degé Kangyur, vol 71 (mdo sde, sha), folios
                        304.b-305.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-071-014-23">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dge ba’i bshes gnyen bsten pa’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
                        [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur
                        khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009, vol 71, pp
                        829-831.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-071-014-41">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa dge ba’i bshes gnyen bsten pa’i mdo</title>. rKTs-K300, Q 966, Peking Qianlong (K<hi rend="subscript">Q</hi>), vol. 38 (mdo sna tshogs, lu),
                        folios 334a-335a.
                    </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-071-014-24">Alsdorf, Ludwig. <title xml:lang="de">Śaśa-Jātaka und Śaśa-Avadāna</title>.
                        In: Wiener Zeitschrift für die Kunde Süd-und Ostasiens, 5, 1-17, 1961. Reprinted in: Wezler, Albrecht
                        (ed.). Ludwig Alsdorf, Kleine Schriften. Wiesbaden: F. Steiner, 1974. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-071-014-25">Bhikkhu Bodhi. <title xml:lang="en">The Connected Discourses of the Buddha:
                            A New Translation of the Samyutta Nikāya</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2000.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-26">
                            <term>bhikṣu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge slong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སློང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhikṣu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A fully ordained monk of the Buddhist saṅgha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-27">
                            <term>virtuous spiritual friend</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i bshes gnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་བཤེས་གཉེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kalyāṇamitra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A general term to denote a qualified spiritual teacher.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-28">
                            <term>holy life</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs par spyod pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པར་སྤྱོད་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmacarya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Lit. “brahma conduct,” this denotes the conduct of those who have renounced
                                worldly life and entered the ordained Buddhist Sangha to devote themselves to spiritual study and
                                practice.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-29">
                            <term>parinirvāṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yongs su mya ngan las ’das pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡོངས་སུ་མྱ་ངན་ལས་འདས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parinirvāṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">The name given to the display of the Buddha’s passing away in
                                Kuśinagara.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-30">
                            <term>four reliances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rton pa bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟོན་པ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratisaraṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">See <ptr target="#UT22084-071-014-34"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-31">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s cousin and attendant.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-32">
                            <term>Kuśinagara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku shi na </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུ་ཤི་ན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kuśinagara</term>
                            <term type="definition">The capital of the Malla kingdom, and the town, in the vicinity of which the
                                Buddha passed into parinirvāṇa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-071-014-33">
                            <term>Malla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Malla</term>
                            <term type="definition">A kingdom of ancient India situated to the North of Magadha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>