<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’khor lo’i mdo</title>
            <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་འཁོར་ལོའི་མདོ།</title>
            <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title>
            <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharmacakrasūtra</title>
            <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
            <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’khor lo’i mdo</title>
            <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en"/>
            <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
            <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
            <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee <lb/>under the patronage and
               supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha </author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40"/>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92"/>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>v 1.21, <date>2018</date>
                </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt status="1">
            <publisher>
               <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to translate
               all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence>
                  <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                  <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial -
                     No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full attribution, and
                     not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details, see the Creative Commons
                     license.</p>
               </licence>
            </availability>
            <idno xml:id="UT22084-072-037"/>
            <date>2018-01-01</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl key="toh337" type="text">
               <ref>Toh 337</ref>
               <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 72, folios 275.a-277.a</biblScope>
               <location count-pages="5">
                        <start volume="72" page="551"/>
                        <end volume="72" page="555"/>
                    </location>
            <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12017" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
         
            </sourceDesc>
         <notesStmt>
            <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:26:43 by admin</note>
         </notesStmt>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div type="summary">
            <head type="summary" tid="42">Summary</head>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-1"/>
            <p tid="1">
               <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title> contains the Buddha’s teaching to his five former
               spiritual companions on the four truths that he had discovered as part of his awakening: (1) suffering, (2) the
               origin of suffering, (3) the cessation of suffering, and (4) the path leading to the cessation of suffering.
               According to all the Buddhist traditions, this is the first teaching the Buddha gave to explain his awakened
               insight to others.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="acknowledgment">
            <head type="acknowledgment" tid="43">Acknowledgements</head>
            <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-2"/>
            <p tid="2">This sūtra was translated and introduced by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of
               Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche.</p>
            <p tid="3">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the
               Buddha.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <head type="introduction" tid="44">Introduction</head>
            <div type="section">
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-3"/>
               <p tid="3">
                  <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title> contains one of the most well-known teachings of
                  Buddhism: the four truths of the noble ones. These four truths are: (1) the truth of suffering, (2) the truth of
                  the origin of suffering, (3) the truth of the cessation of suffering, and (4) the truth of the path leading to
                  the cessation of suffering. According to traditional accounts, this is the first teaching taught by the Buddha
                  following his attainment of awakening. The Buddha is said to have journeyed from the seat of awakening in
                  Bodhgaya to the Deer Park outside Varanasi, where he delivered this teaching to his five former spiritual
                  companions. Since this was the first time the Buddha turned the wheel of Dharma, this discourse also became
                  known as <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title>, or, more commonly, <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Turning of the Wheel of Dharma</title>. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-4"/>
               <p tid="4">Although very brief, this classical presentation of the four truths has remained central to the Buddhist
                  tradition since its very early days. As such, this teaching is included in all the major canons of Buddhism, so
                  that versions in Pali, Sanskrit, Chinese and Tibetan are found.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-84"> For a summary of the Pali, Sanskrit, and Chinese sources of this teaching, see
                     Anderson 1999, p. 15-16. See also Bronkhorst 1993, p. 80, n. 200.</note> As far as translations into Tibetan
                  are concerned, we find the classical presentation of the four truths embedded in no fewer than five individual
                  works in the Kangyur. Of these, the following three contain accounts of this first teaching in passages that are
                  clearly closely related, being almost verbatim identical:<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-85">Although the precise historical relationship between these three texts has not been fully confirmed, it is
                     highly likely that Toh 1 is the source, from which Toh 301 is an extract relating the Buddha’s life as a
                     whole (naturally including this episode), while Toh 337 is a very short extract of this episode alone.
                  </note>
               </p>
               <list type="bullet">
                  <item>
                     <p tid="39"> • <title xml:lang="en">The Chapter on Schism in the Sangha</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title>). This very long text forms the 17th chapter of the
                        Mūlasarvāstivādin vinaya scripture <title xml:lang="en">Chapters on Monastic Discipline</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vinayavastu</title>, Toh 1), and includes, interspersed with all sorts of other material,
                        passages recounting the life and deeds of the Buddha.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-86">The section corresponding to the present sūtra is found in <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dul ba</title>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nga</foreign>, folios
                           42b.3-44a.5</note>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p tid="40"> • <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on Going Forth</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­niṣkramaṇa­sūtra</title>, Toh 301). In this text all the passages in <title xml:lang="en">The Chapter on Schism in the Sangha</title> recounting the
                        Buddha’s life have been extracted verbatim to form a continuous narrative, including the passage on this
                           teaching.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-87">The corresponding section is found in
                              <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdo sde</title>, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa</foreign>,
                           60a.1-61b.3</note>
                     </p>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <p tid="41"> • <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharma­cakra­sūtra</title>, Toh 337). This text is also a verbatim extract from the account of the
                        teaching as found in Toh 1, but this time only of this particular episode. However, it does add a brief
                        introduction and conclusion to give to the account the form of an independent sūtra.</p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-5"/>
               <p tid="8">In addition, the Kangyur also contains a translation of the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dhamma­chakkappavattana­sutta</title> from the Pali canon:</p>
               <list type="bullet">
                  <item>
                     <p tid="9"> • <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Turning of the Wheel of Dharma</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dharma­cakra­pravartana­sūtra</title>, Toh 31). This is one of only fourteen texts in
                        the Kangyur that were translated into Tibetan from the Pali. As such it mirrors closely the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhamma­chakkappavattana­sutta</title> of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṃyuttanikāya</title>, although some differences exist.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-88">This text is found in the Degé Kangyur, vol. 34 (shes phyin, ka), folios
                           180b.1-183a.6, in the section of “Thirteen Late Translated Texts.” This group of works is traditionally
                           placed in the Perfection of Wisdom section but is not, in fact, related to that genre. The texts were
                           translated from Pali in the fourteenth century at the monastery of Tharpa Ling by a Sri Lankan monk,
                           Ānandaśrī, and the Tibetan translator Nyima Gyaltsen Pel Zangpo. According to Skilling (1993, p. 97),
                           this was during the first decade of the fourteenth century; Skilling has compared this particular text
                           against the extant Pali <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dhamma­chakkappavattana­sutta</title> (1993, pp. 103-106),
                           and concludes that the Tibetan follows the Pali version but contains some significant omissions that he
                           attributes to an erroneous manuscript or translation errors.</note>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-6"/>
               <p tid="10">Lastly, the teaching is also found as part of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalita­vistara­sūtra</title>:</p>
               <list type="bullet">
                  <item>
                     <p tid="11"> • <title xml:lang="en">The Play in Full</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalitavistara</title>,
                        Toh 95). In this lengthy account of the Buddha’s deeds the teaching on the four truths has many
                        similarities with the other texts, yet clearly belongs to another manuscript tradition as there are a
                        number of significant differences as well. Here the teaching is found in the penultimate chapter (ch. 26),
                        entitled “Turning the Wheel of Dharma.”<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-89">The
                           relevant section is found in Degé Kangyur, vol. 46 (mdo sde, kha), folios 200b.1-201a.4. For the
                           translation, see Dharmachakra Translation Committee (2013), <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-046-001.html#UT22084-046-001-2121">26.60 -
                              26.78</ref>.</note>
                     </p>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-7"/>
               <p tid="12">In general, the plethora of versions that exist of this teaching in Pali, Sanskrit, Chinese, and
                  Tibetan are very similar, yet all of them contain a number of idiosyncrasies—some minor, others
                  significant—that set them apart from the rest. These differences have been studied in great detail over the last
                  two centuries and a rich body of scholarship on the philological and theoretical aspects of this teaching has
                     emerged.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-90"> For a summary of modern scholarship on the
                     four truths, see Anderson 1999, pp. 168-211.</note> As a result, we now know that the teaching on the four
                  truths as we today find it included in the various canons is the product of several editorial revisions over the
                  centuries. As such, the “original” version of this teaching remains elusive, as does the role played by this
                  teaching in the earliest days of the Buddhist tradition.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-91">
                     See Bronkhorst 1993, pp. 71-85. See also Anderson 1999, pp. 15-23.</note>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-8"/>
               <p tid="13">As these scriptures became the focus of scholarly attention, a number of translations both from the
                     Pali<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-92"> E.g. Anderson 1999, pp. 64-67, and Bodhi
                     2000.</note> and Sanskrit<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-93"> E.g. Sastri 1938, pp.
                     479-480, and Kloppenborg 1973, pp. 24-27.</note> have been produced. The translation presented here has been
                  made on the basis of the Tibetan translation of <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title>
                  (Toh 337). As mentioned above, this text is with minor exceptions identical to the corresponding sections in Toh
                  1 and Toh 331. Toh 337 contains no mention of the translators, but the translator of Toh 1 is listed as the
                  Tibetan Kawa Paltseg (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ka ba dpal brtsegs</foreign>), who was a prolific translator
                  during the early period of Tibetan translations, which took place at the beginning of the ninth century.
                  Unfortunately, the Sanskrit version that formed the basis for Kawa Paltseg’s translation of Toh 1 is no longer
                  extant. The Sanskrit manuscript of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title> that is available to us today (Gnoli 1977) has enough differences
                  from the Tibetan translation for us to conclude that it was not the text that was used to produce the Tibetan
                  translation. Nevertheless, it does represent an important witness of the Sanskrit, and our translation
                  benefitted greatly from comparing it with the Tibetan. Our main sources were the Degé prints of Toh
                  1, Toh 301, and Toh 337, taking into account the variants noted in the Pedurma comparative edition of each.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="translation">
            <head type="translation" tid="45">The Translation</head>
            <head type="titleHon" tid="46"/>
            <head type="titleMain" tid="47">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</head>
            <div type="section">
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-9"/>
               <p tid="14">
                  <ref cRef="F.275.a"/> Homage to the Omniscient One!</p>
               <lb/>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-78"/>
               <p tid="16">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One, the Buddha, was residing in the Deer Park at Ṛṣivadana by
                  Vārāṇasī. At<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-94"> The equivalent section in Toh 1 begins at
                     this point (p. 42b.3) and in Toh 301 (p. 60a.1).</note> that time the Blessed One spoke to the group of five
                     monks:<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-95"> At this point, the corresponding passage in
                     the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalita­vistara­sūtra</title> begins (Lefmann, p. 417; Dharmachakra Translation
                     Group, 26.65).</note>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-10"/>
               <p tid="17">“Monks, as I<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-96">The Sanskrit of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title> does not include the first person personal pronoun in this
                     first paragraph, although it does in the subsequent paragraphs (Gnoli 1977, p. 135). However, the Tibetan
                     does include the first person personal pronoun throughout, including in this first paragraph. This is also
                     the case with the Sanskrit of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalita­vistara­sūtra</title> (Lefmann, p. 417) and
                     the Pali <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Dhamma­cakkappavattana­sutta</title> (Saṃyutta Nikāya, 56.11; see also Anderson
                     1999, p. 18). </note> focused my mind correctly on the things<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-97">Here “things” translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dharma</foreign> (Pali: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">dhamma</foreign>, Tibetan: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos</foreign>). The commentaries suggest that <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharma</foreign> is used here in the sense of “truth.” For example, the <title xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">Puggala­paññattipa­karaṇa-mūlaṭīkā</title> says: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">ananussutesu dhammesūti ca ananussutesu saccesūti attho</foreign>.
                     http://www.tipitaka.org/romn/cscd/abh03t.tik1.xml).</note> that I had not hitherto heard, <ref cRef="F.275.b"/> thinking, ‘This is suffering, a truth of noble beings,’ vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding,
                  and realization<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-98">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title> does not include “realization” (Tibetan: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtogs pa</foreign>) in this or the following several repetitions of this phrase. Instead
                     the list only includes “knowledge (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jñāna</foreign>), apprehension
                        (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</foreign>), and understanding (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhi</foreign>)” (Gnoli 1977, p. 135). </note> arose.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-79"/>
               <p tid="18">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘This is
                  the origin of suffering,<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-99">Before the phrase “This is the
                     origin of suffering,” Toh 337 in the Degé Kangyur includes the phrase “This is suffering.” However, here we
                     have omitted it, as it is absent in all other versions of this passage, including the recensions of this
                     sūtra in the Yonglé, Lithang, Coné, Narthang, and Peking Kangyurs; the Sanskrit of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title>; and the Tibetan of both Toh 1 and Toh 301 in D and other
                     Kangyurs.</note> this is the cessation of suffering, and this is the path leading to the cessation of
                  suffering,’ vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization arose.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-11"/>
               <p tid="19">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I should comprehend suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ vision arose; knowledge,
                  apprehension, understanding, and realization arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-80"/>
               <p tid="20">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I should relinquish the origin of suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ vision arose;
                  knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-12"/>
               <p tid="21">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I should actualize<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-100"> At this point Toh
                     337 includes the words “the knowledge of…” However, we have omitted this, since the phrase is absent in Toh 1
                     and Toh 301, as well as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title>.</note> the cessation of
                  suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization
                  arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-81"/>
               <p tid="22">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I should cultivate the path leading to the cessation of suffering, that truth of noble beings,’
                  vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-13"/>
               <p tid="23">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I have comprehended suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ vision arose; knowledge,
                  apprehension, understanding, and realization arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-82"/>
               <p tid="24">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I have relinquished the origin of suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ <ref cRef="F.276.a"/>
                  vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-14"/>
               <p tid="25">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I have actualized<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-101"> At this point Toh
                     337 includes the words “the knowledge of…” However, we have omitted this, since the phrase is absent in Toh 1
                     and Toh 301, as well as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Saṅgha­bheda­vastu</title>.</note> the cessation of
                  suffering, that truth of noble beings,’ vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization
                  arose. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-83"/>
               <p tid="26">“Monks, as I focused my mind correctly on the things that I had not hitherto heard, thinking, ‘With
                  higher knowledge I have cultivated the path leading to the cessation of suffering, that truth of noble beings,’
                  vision arose; knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization arose.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-15"/>
               <p tid="27">“Monks, until I had achieved the vision, knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization of
                  these four truths of noble beings that are turned in three phases and comprise twelve aspects,<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-102"> The three phases refer to the three stages of (1) identifying the
                     four truths, (2) understanding how to relate to each of the four truths, and (3) knowing that the respective
                     goals of the four truths have been accomplished. When these three stages are applied to each of the four
                     truths, there are twelve aspects in all. For a classical explanation of this enumeration by Haribhadra
                     (eighth cent.), see Sparham 2008, p. 264. See also Anderson 1999, p. 70. Note that these twelve aspects are
                     unrelated to the alternative enumeration of sixteen aspects associated with the four truths (four for each
                     truth). The sixteen aspects counteract sixteen incorrect views associated with the four truths. On the
                     sixteen aspects, see Buswell 2013, p. 304-305. For a classical account by Candrakīrti (c. 570-650 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>), see
                     May 1959, p. 212-216. </note> I had not been freed from the world replete with gods, māras, Brahmā,
                  mendicants, brahmins, humans, and gods. I had not escaped from it, severed ties with it, or been delivered from
                  it. Nor did I dwell extensively with a mind free from error. Monks, I did not have the knowledge that I had
                  fully awakened to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-16"/>
               <p tid="28">“Monks, once I had achieved the vision, knowledge, apprehension, understanding, and realization of
                  turning these four truths of noble beings in three phases with twelve aspects, I was freed from the world
                  replete with gods, māras, Brahmā, mendicants, brahmins, humans, and gods. I had escaped from it, severed ties
                  with it, and been delivered from it. I dwelled extensively with a mind free from error. <ref cRef="F.276.b"/>
                  Monks, I then had the knowledge that I had fully awakened to unsurpassed and perfect buddhahood.”<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-103"> At this point, the corresponding passage in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalita­vistara­sūtra</title> ends (Lefmann, p. 418).</note>
               </p>
               <lb/>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-17"/>
               <p tid="29">When the Blessed One had given this Dharma discourse, venerable Kauṇḍinya, along with eighty thousand
                  gods, achieved the Dharma vision that is free from dust and stainless with regard to phenomena. </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-18"/>
               <p tid="30">The Blessed One now asked venerable Kauṇḍinya, “Kauṇḍinya, did you understand the Dharma?”</p>
               <p tid="31">“Blessed One,” he replied, “I understood.” </p>
               <p tid="32">“Kauṇḍinya, did you understand? Did you understand?”</p>
               <p tid="33">“Blissful One,” he replied, “I understood. I understood.”</p>
               <p tid="34">“Because venerable Kauṇḍinya has understood the Dharma, venerable Kauṇḍinya shall now be known as
                     Ājñātakauṇḍinya.”<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-104"> This name means “Kauṇḍinya who
                     has understood.”</note>
               </p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-19"/>
               <p tid="35">At that point the terrestrial yakṣas called out, “Venerable Kauṇḍinya has understood the Dharma!” And
                  they continued, “Friends, in the Deer Park at Ṛṣivadana by Vārāṇasī, the Blessed One has turned the wheel of
                  Dharma in three phases with twelve aspects. He has turned the wheel of Dharma in a way that no mendicant or
                  brahmin, and no god, māra, or Brahmā in the world could ever do in accord with the Dharma. He has done so for
                  the benefit of many beings, for the happiness of many beings, out of love for the world, and for the welfare,
                  benefit, and happiness of gods and humans. Hence, the gods will flourish and the demigods will be on the
                  wane.”</p>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-20"/>
               <p tid="36">As the voices of the terrestrial yakṣas rang out—at that very moment, in that very instant, and at that
                  very time—the news passed to the celestial yakṣas, as well as to the gods in the Heaven of the Four Great Kings,
                  the Heaven of the Thirty-Three, the Heaven Free from Strife, the Heaven of Joy, the Heaven of Delighting in
                  Emanations, the Heaven of Making Use of Others’ Emanations, and all the way to the Brahmā realm. Thus, also the
                  gods in the Brahmā realm announced, “Friends, in the Deer Park at Ṛṣivadana by Vārāṇasī, <ref cRef="F.277.a"/>
                  the Blessed One has turned the wheel of Dharma in three phases with twelve aspects. He has turned the wheel of
                  Dharma in a way that no mendicant or brahmin, and no god, māra, or Brahmā in the world could ever do in accord
                  with the Dharma. He has done so for the benefit of many beings, for the happiness of many beings, out of love
                  for the world, and for the welfare, benefit, and happiness of gods and humans. Hence, the gods will flourish and
                  the demigods will be on the wane.”</p>
               <lb/>
               <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-21"/>
               <p tid="37">In the Deer Park at Ṛṣivadana by Vārāṇasī, the Blessed One turned the wheel of Dharma in three phases
                  with twelve aspects. Therefore, this Dharma teaching was named <title xml:lang="en">Turning the Wheel of
                     Dharma</title>.<note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-105"> Toh 1 (p. 44a.5) and Toh 301 (p.
                     61b.3) end at this point.</note>
               </p>
               <lb/>
               <p tid="38">This completes <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Wheel of Dharma</title>.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="listBibl">
            <head type="listBibl" tid="48">Bibliography</head>
            <div type="section">
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-49">
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’khor lo’i mdo</title>. Toh 337, Degé Kangyur, vol. 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios
                  275a-277a.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-50">
                  <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’khor lo’i mdo</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the
                  Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka
                  Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                  khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 72, p. 794–799.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-51">Anderson, Carol S. <title xml:lang="en">Pain and its Ending: The Four Noble
                     Truths in the Theravāda Buddhist Canon</title>. Richmond, Surrey: Curzon, 1999.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-52">Bodhi, Bhikkhu. <title xml:lang="en">The Connected Discourses of the
                     Buddha</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2000.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-53">Bronkhorst, Johannes. <title xml:lang="en">The Two Traditions of Meditation in
                     Ancient India</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1993.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-54">Buswell, Robert E. and Donald S. Lopez Jr. <title xml:lang="en">The Princeton
                     Dictionary of Buddhism</title>. Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2013.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-107">Dharmachakra Translation Committee. <title xml:lang="en">The Play in
                     Full</title>. (<title xml:lang="en">Lalitavistara</title>). 84000:Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2013.
                  See <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-046-001.html">The Play in Full</ref>.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-57">Gnoli, Raniero. <title xml:lang="en">The Gilgit manuscript of the
                     Saṅghabhedavastu: Being the 17th and last section of the Vinaya of the Mūlasarvāstivādin</title>, Part I.
                  Roma: Istituto Italiano per il Medio ed Estremo Oriente, 1977.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-55">Kloppenborg, Ria. <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on the Foundation of the
                     Buddhist Order (Catuṣpariṣatsūtra): Relating the Events from the Bodhisattva's Enlightenment up to the
                     Conversion of Upatiṣya (Śāriputra) and Kolita (Maudgalyāyana)</title>. Leiden: Brill, 1973.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-58">Lefmann, Salomon. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lalita Vistara</title>. Halle: Verlag
                  der Buchhandlung des Waisenhauses, 1883.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-56">May, Jacques. <title xml:lang="fr">Prasannapadā madhyamakavṛtti: douze
                     chapitres traduits du sanscrit et du tibétain</title>. Paris: Adrien-Maisonneuve, 1959.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-59">Sastri, N. Aiyaswami. “The First Sermon of the Buddha” in <title xml:lang="en">New Indian Antiquary</title>, vol. 1. Bombay: Karnatak Publishing House, 1938.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-60">Skilling, Peter. “Theravadin Literature in Tibetan Translation” in <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the Pali Text Society</title>, 1993, vol. 19: 69-201.</bibl>
               <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-037-61">Sparham, Gareth. <title xml:lang="en">Abhisamayālaṃkāra with Vṛtti and
                     Ālokā</title>, vol. 2. Fremont: Jain Publishing Company, 2008.</bibl>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="glossary">
            <list type="glossary">
               <item>
                  <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-62">
                     <term>yakṣa</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                     <term type="definition">A class of semidivine beings said to dwell in the north, under the jurisdiction of
                        the Great King Vaiśravaṇa, otherwise known as Kubera.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-63">
                     <term>demigod</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                     <term type="definition">The traditional adversaries of the devas (gods) who are frequently portrayed in
                        Brahmanical mythology as having a disruptive effect on cosmological and social harmony.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-64">
                     <term>truth of noble beings</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa’i bden pa </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པའི་བདེན་པ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āryasatya</term>
                     <term type="definition">The four truths that the Buddha realized: suffering, origin, cessation, and path.
                        They are named “truths of noble beings” since only “noble beings” with knowledge of reality can understand
                        them.</term>
                     <term type="alternative">truths of the noble ones</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-65">
                     <term>Brahmā</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsangs pa </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">ཙངས་པ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                     <term type="definition">A high ranking deity, presiding over a divine world where other beings consider him
                        the creator; he is also considered to be the “Lord of the Sahā-world (our universe).”</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-66">
                     <term>Kauṇḍinya</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kauN Di nya </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">ཀཽཎ་ཌི་ཉ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kauṇḍinya</term>
                     <term type="definition">One of the five former spiritual friends with whom Gautama had practiced meditation
                        before his awakening.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-67">
                     <term>Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun shes kauN Di nya </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎ་ཌི་ཉ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term>
                     <term type="definition">Another name for Kauṇḍinya. As he was the first to understand the Buddha's teaching
                        on the four truths, he received the name <term type="ignore">Ājñātakauṇḍinya</term> (“Kauṇḍinya who understood”).</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-68">
                     <term>Deer Park </term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri dags kyi nags </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">རི་དགས་ཀྱི་ནགས།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mṛgadāva</term>
                     <term type="definition">The forest, located outside of Varanasi, where the Buddha first taught the
                        Dharma.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-69">
                     <term>Ṛṣivadana</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">drang srong smra ba </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">དྲང་སྲོང་སྨྲ་བ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṛṣivadana</term>
                     <term type="definition">A sacred area located outside of Vārāṇasī where many sages are said to have practiced
                        in the past.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-70">
                     <term>Vārāṇasī</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bA rA Na sI </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">བཱ་རཱ་ཎ་སཱི།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vārāṇasī</term>
                     <term type="definition">City in North India where the Buddha first taught the Dharma</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-71">
                     <term>Heaven Free from Strife</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’thab bral </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">འཐབ་བྲལ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yāma</term>
                     <term type="definition">The third lowest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-72">
                     <term>Heaven of Delighting in Emanations</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phrul dga’ </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">འཕྲུལ་དགའ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nirmāṇarati </term>
                     <term type="definition">The second highest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-73">
                     <term>Heaven of Joy</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ldan </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་ལྡན།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tuṣita</term>
                     <term type="definition">The third highest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-74">
                     <term>Heaven of Making Use of Others’ Emanations</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzhan ’phrul dbang byed pa </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">གཞན་འཕྲུལ་དབང་བྱེད་པ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paranirmitavaśavartin </term>
                     <term type="definition">The highest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-75">
                     <term>Heaven of the Four Great Kings</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal chen bzhi’i ris </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་ཆེན་བཞིའི་རིས།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caturmahārājika</term>
                     <term type="definition">The lowest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-76">
                     <term>Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sum cu rtsa gsum </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">སུམ་ཅུ་རྩ་གསུམ།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Trāyastriṃśa </term>
                     <term type="definition">The second lowest of the six heavens of the desire realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-037-77">
                     <term>Brahmā realm</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs ris </term>
                     <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་རིས།</term>
                     <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmakāyika</term>
                     <term type="definition">The lowest heaven of the form realm.</term>
                  </gloss>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>