<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཚེ་འཕོ་བ་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར་བ་ཞུས་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuṣpatti­yathākāra­paripṛcchā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཚེ་འཕོ་བ་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར་བ་ཞུས་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuṣpatti­yathākāra­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཆི་འཕོ་བ་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར་བ་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཆི་འཕོ་བ་ཇི་ལྟར་འགྱུར་བ་ལུང་བསྟན་པ།</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba’i bstan pa</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba’i lung bstan pa</title>
                <author ref="contributors.xml#team-13" role="translatorMain">Translated by Tom Tillemans<lb/> under the patronage
                    and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
            <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-84">David Rawson</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-260">Seth Davis</consultant>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-87">Russell Shipman</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-230">Tom Tillemans</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">James Gentry</consultant>
                <editor role="externalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-51">James Gentry</editor>
                <editor role="copyEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-257">Raynald Prévèreau</editor>
                <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-92">Laura Goetz</editor>
                <editor role="finalReviewer" ref="contributors.xml#person-139">John Canti</editor>
                <editor role="proofreader" ref="contributors.xml#person-249">Konchog Norbu</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.22.3 <date>2020</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit
                    initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern
                    languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-072-008"/>
                <date>2019-03-15</date>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh308" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 308</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur vol. 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios
                        145.b–155.a</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="20">
                        <volume number="72" start-page="290" end-page="309"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11978" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-02-26T21:36:31.849Z" user="admin">26/02/2020 21:36:31</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.9" date-time="2019-03-02T20:14:42.638Z" user="john">v 0.9 2019</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.91" date-time="2019-03-12T17:57:44.717Z" user="john">v 0.91 2019</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.0" date-time="2019-03-17T12:28:45.008Z" user="john">v 1.0 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="1" date-time="2019-03-17T12:28:45.008Z" user="john">1</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.1" date-time="2019-03-18T22:04:31.631Z" user="john">v 1.1 2019</note>
            <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.2" date-time="2019-03-28T20:10:21.193Z" user="john">v 1.2 2019</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.22" date-time="2019-06-21T14:42:50.635Z" user="celso">v 1.22 2019</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.22.1" date-time="2019-10-07T10:27:24.685Z" user="admin">Publication statement updated</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.22.2" date-time="2019-12-02T00:17:15.8Z" user="konchog">Added "the" to first sentence of translation; changed "non-virtue" to "nonvirtue".</note>
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 1.22.3" date-time="2020-02-26T21:36:29.131Z" user="celso">fixed non-breaking spaces in ellipsis</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="94">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-1"/>
                <p tid="1">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</title>
                    contains explanations of Buddhist views on the nature of life and death, and a
                    number of philosophical arguments against non-Buddhist conceptions, notably some
                    based broadly on the Vedas. The sūtra is set in the town of Kapilavastu at the
                    time of the funeral of a young man of the Śākya clan. King Śuddhodana wonders
                    about the validity of the ritual offerings being made for the deceased by the
                    family and asks the Buddha seven questions about current beliefs on death and
                    the afterlife. The Buddha answers each of the questions in turn. After two
                    interlocutors interrupt to test the Buddha’s omniscience, the discourse
                    continues to present the Buddhist account of death and rebirth using a
                    set of eight analogies, each of which complements the others in a detailed explanation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="95">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-2"/>
                <p tid="2">An initial draft translation of this sūtra was done by Four Reliances
                    Translations (David Rawson, Seth Davis, and Russell Shipman) of Sera Monastery
                    in South India. An unpublished paraphrase prepared by Geshé Damdul Namgyal was 
                    a helpful resource. Tom Tillemans thoroughly retranslated the
                    sūtra in a seminar at the University of Vienna in 2014. He also wrote the
                    introduction, notes, and final version of the glossaries. James Gentry provided
                    valuable feedback.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="96">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-3"/>
                    <p tid="3">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</title> is
                        a short sūtra set in Kapilavastu that explains Buddhist views on death via a
                        dialogue between the Buddha and his father, King Śuddhodana. King Śuddhodana
                        observes the brahmanical funeral rites for a fellow member of the Śākya clan
                        called Nandaja.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-4" index="1">A
                            natural reconstruction from the Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dga’ skyes</foreign>. However, there seems to be no
                            information on this individual. There is, for example, nothing relevant
                            in G.P. Malalasekera’s <title xml:lang="en">Dictionary of Pali Proper
                                Names</title> or in Negi.</note> Wondering what benefit will be
                        derived from the various rituals and offerings that are being performed for
                        the deceased by the family, King Śuddhodana asks the Buddha a number of
                        pertinent questions: (1) Are beings consistently reborn as their own kind,
                        with humans being reborn as humans, and so on? (2) Do beings become utterly
                        nonexistent after death? (3) Do beings, after their death, accompany their
                        dead ancestors and relatives in a “world of Death”? (4)
                        Is wealth and poverty consistent from life to life, with the wealthy continuing
                        to be wealthy and the poor to be poor? (5) Is enjoyment of clothes, mounts,
                        and so on consistent from life to life, with people continuing to have the same
                        clothes, horses, and so forth? (6) Can one dedicate food and other offerings
                        to the deceased and thus assure their perpetual welfare and nourishment? (7)
                        Do the dead show themselves to their relatives just as they were when
                        alive?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-5"/>
                    <p tid="4">To each of these seven questions, the Buddha’s answer is always “no.” Several
                        beliefs that must have been current in India at the time are thus taken up
                        and criticized, beginning with simple skepticism that anything can survive
                        after death at all. The main position being examined, however, seems to be
                        that the deceased survive in an afterlife which is essentially a
                        continuation of the present one, in the company of the same friends,
                        relatives, ancestors, and possessions. The deceased are sustained by the
                        offerings dedicated to them by their living relatives; they remain forever
                        in the “world of Death,” not taking rebirth in future
                            incarnations.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-6" index="2">The
                            sūtra regularly uses the term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gshin gyi ’jig rten</foreign>, which is not a usual term, but is
                            probably the same as the more usual <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gshin rje’i ’jig rten</foreign>, i.e., the Sanskrit
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yamaloka</foreign>, the world
                            of Yama, Death, or the lord of death and ruler over the various departed
                            ancestors (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign>). Cf.
                            Negi s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gshin rje’i ’jig
                                rten</foreign> (= <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yamaloka</foreign>). </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-7"/>
                    <p tid="5">This is a broadly Vedic eschatology, a conception of death and the
                        afterlife that goes well back to the first millennium <hi rend="small-caps">bce</hi>, in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ṛgveda</title>, especially in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atharvaveda</title>, as well as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brāhmaṇas</title>. When the sūtra says that the
                        deceased are “befriended by their ancestors” after death, this is no doubt a
                        reference to the Vedic idea that the dead transition to the realm of
                        their ancestors, or their “fathers” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign>). The dead person
                        also comes to be in the presence of a lineage of ancestors all the way back to an
                            “original ancestor” (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mes po dang po</foreign>), 
                        which seems to be an allusion to the
                        idea of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign> as including first ancestors, the founders of the human
                            race.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-8" index="3">Note that
                            the Tibetan term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mes po</foreign>
                            is often used in the sūtra to simply mean “grandfather,” but in other
                            places the sūtra clearly uses it to mean “ancestor.” It is attested in
                            the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> 3880 and in other
                            glossaries as the equivalent of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitāmaha</foreign> (paternal grandfathers), which can also mean
                            simply the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign> or
                            “ancestors.” See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-136">Monier-Williams</ptr>, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitāmaha</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-9"/>
                    <p tid="6">The brahmanical conception is that the family should present <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">piṇḍa</foreign>—balls of cooked rice
                        typically mixed with sesame <term type="ignore">seed</term>s, milk, butter,
                        and honey—and other offerings to assure the transition of the newly dead
                        spirit (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">preta</foreign>) from a type
                        of limbo to the more secure status of an ancestor in heaven, i.e., in
                        Yamaloka, the world presided over by Death, the <term type="ignore">god</term> Yama. The brahmanical rites for Nandaja, the deceased person
                        mentioned at the start of the sūtra, seem to be <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">śrāddha</foreign>-rites, the ancestral offering rituals
                        incumbent upon householders. One of those śrāddha-rites, 
                        the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sapiṇḍīkaraṇa</foreign>, is performed by
                        the deceased’s son and is the postcremation offering of piṇḍa to complete
                        his transition to the afterworld.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-10" index="4">On the four śrāddha-rites, see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-140">Sayers (2013)</ptr>, chapter 4.
                            Brahmanical texts, like the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āpastamba
                                Dharma­sūtra</title>, advocate other offerings too, such as beans,
                            barley, water, roots, fruits, cattle, buffalo, fish, and even rhinoceros.
                            See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-140">Sayers (2013)</ptr>, pp. 107–8.
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āpastamba</title>’s list does not, however,
                            seem to match the offerings of the family of Nandaja, viz., “horses,
                            elephants, clothes, and a variety of ornaments, gold and silver, pearls,
                            crystals, and other jewels, and a variety of delicious and sweet food
                            and drink.”</note> More generally, in the Vedic conceptions of death and
                        the afterlife, rebirth as well as the closely related theories of karma and
                        liberation (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mokṣa</foreign>)
                        generally play no (or at most obscure) roles; significantly, the sūtra
                        states that rebirth does not figure at all in the afterlife as it is
                        imagined by the mourners of Nandaja.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-11" index="5">Cf. <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-139">Renou
                                and Filliozat (1985)</ptr> vol. 1, §670: “All the images of future
                            lives are physical; it is said in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atharvaveda</title> that cremation produces a new body that is
                                <distinct>revitalized</distinct>, free from imperfections.” Cf. also
                            ibid. §674: “The term <distinct>fathers</distinct> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign>) designates, in the
                                <title xml:lang="en">Vedas</title>, the first ancestors, the
                            founders of the human race, those who gave their names to the
                            brahmanical families. But more generally it designates the dead as a
                            whole, providing that they have been cremated or buried according to the
                            rituals.” (Our translation from the original French of Louis Renou).
                                <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-140">Sayers (2013)</ptr> provides a recent
                            and thorough treatment of brahmanical ancestor worship; see also <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-129">Hopkins (1992)</ptr> as well as <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-130">Jamison and Witzel (1992/2003)</ptr>
                            on the role of Vedic ritual and the offerings of food (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">piṇḍa</foreign>) in death and the
                            afterlife. See also <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-131">Knipe
                                (1977)</ptr> on <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sapiṇḍīkaraṇa</foreign> and <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-125">Bodewitz (1999)</ptr> on the Vedic afterlife and the role of the
                                <term type="ignore">god</term> of Death (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yama</foreign>) in particular. <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-142">Shushan (2011)</ptr> gives an overview
                            of the basic Vedic eschatology. <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-127">Doniger O’Flaherty (1983)</ptr> looks at the early Vedic and
                            Purānic antecedents of theories of karma and reincarnation, notably the
                            idea of <distinct>redeath</distinct> (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">punarmṛtyu</foreign>), a type of dissolution of the
                            afterlife that is to be <emph>prevented</emph> by ritual.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-12"/>
                    <p tid="7">The sūtra’s stance on the rites is complex, however, as offerings to
                        the dead are not just dismissed categorically as pointless. We find, for
                        example, the following passage allowing a nuanced acceptance:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="8">The Great King then asked, “Blessed One, if that is the case,
                            then is it useless to offer deceased individuals the food, drink,
                            mounts, clothes, and ornaments that were beneficial to them in the
                            present world?”</p>
                        <p tid="9">The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, take the case where a
                            deceased person is being reborn in one of various different states of
                            being because actions he had done are ripening. And suppose people help
                            that person by dedicating to him all sorts of virtuous actions that will
                            constitute a collection of merit without any nonvirtue. In that case,
                            the person will be reborn in higher states, or attain liberation. On
                            the other hand, when someone has already taken rebirth, then if one aids
                            him through the dedication of a virtuous action that constitutes merit,
                            that will aid the already reborn person to gain wealth, have good crops,
                            more and more of the pleasures he wishes, as well as honor and respect
                            from all his other fellow beings. However, it is not so that the
                            deceased individual stays on in the ‘world of Death,’
                            without rebirth, and taking on food and drink,
                            mounts, clothing, and ornaments.” (<ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-70"/>) </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-13"/>
                    <p tid="10">This seems to be a recognizable Buddhist position, one also found in
                        some Pāli texts. Indeed, as Sayers 
                        shows,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-186" index="6">
                            <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-140">Sayers</ptr> 
                            (2013), pp. 86–99.</note> there are passages in texts like the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aṅguttara­nikāya</title> that do acknowledge
                        brahmanical śrāddha-rites as having some efficacy. The approach of texts in the Pāli Canon is
                        typically to rationalize offerings and ancestor worship as a form of
                            <distinct>gifting</distinct>. The present sūtra also seems to follow
                        this broad approach in many respects: gifting leads to merit, which can
                        then be dedicated to the deceased and, in the capacity of dedicated 
                        karmic merit, serve to benefit them. What is
                        being targeted, then, does not seem to be the efficacy of householders’
                        rites to benefit the dead <emph>in any way</emph>, but rather the efficacy
                        of the offerings to nourish the dead eternally in an everlasting realm of
                        ancestors. It is especially <emph>that</emph> conception of the afterlife
                        that is being rejected.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-14"/>
                    <p tid="11">The argumentation against such a Vedic eschatology follows several
                        strategies. Sometimes it invokes the fully developed theory of karma
                        governing reincarnation, the worldview of moral causality and retribution
                        accepted in most post-Vedic Indian thought. For example, wealth, poverty,
                        and the like do not remain constant throughout one’s subsequent lives, as
                        they are karmic results that vary because of the ethical nature of actions
                        in those lives. At other times simple human common sense and observation is
                        invoked: for example, if beings, after their death, supposedly continued on
                        with their relatives and ancestors in a “world of Death,”
                        they would be unable to recognize one another, for their usual physical form
                        is obviously destroyed in cremation or in the grave. At still other times
                        the argument depends upon the supernatural. For example, dreams and
                        apparitions of the deceased turn out to be due to a very special type of
                        spirit that mimics the appearance of the deceased in order to trick the living
                        into making offerings that the spirits can then appropriate.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-15"/>
                    <p tid="12">The sūtra itself hardly attempts to provide a positive proof for
                        rebirth. It is almost exclusively devoted to refuting what Buddhists
                        take to be wrong conceptions of death and the afterlife. After the Buddha’s
                        extensive refutation of the Vedic views, the renegade Devadatta challenges
                        the Buddha to prove the reliability and superiority of his own
                        understanding—he is asked to identify the different sorts of wood from which
                        various ashes come. The Buddha’s success in this and another test leads his
                        interlocutors to conclude that he has suprasensible knowledge enabling him
                        to directly understand all things, including the process of death and
                        rebirth in all its details. The closest thing to a positive argument for a
                        Buddhist eschatology is thus that its truth is assured by the Buddha’s
                        omniscience. <foreign xml:lang="la" type="term">A fortiori</foreign>, one
                        finds no trace of the main Buddhist metaphysical argument for reincarnation,
                        the so-called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">para­loka­sādhana</foreign>, or “proof of other lives,” that turns on
                        the nature of mind and was so important in the second chapter of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pramāṇa­vārttika</title> of Dharmakīrti (sixth–seventh
                        century) and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jātakamālā</title> of Āryaśūra
                        (fourth century).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-16" index="7">See
                                <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-137">Namai (1991)</ptr>. The argument
                            of Āryaśūra and Dharmakīrti alike is that consciousness can only exist
                            when preceded by a previous consciousness; thus the initial
                            consciousness of a baby must have an anterior consciousness in a
                            previous life.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-17"/>
                    <p tid="13">The last part of the sūtra takes up the non-Buddhist idea that a
                        permanent entity survives and transmigrates. A series of eight analogies are
                        then presented in detail to show, among other things, that 
                        reincarnation needs no such permanent entity. As
                        pointed out in <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-143">Skilling (1997)</ptr>,
                        these eight analogies also figure in verse 5 of the <title xml:lang="en">Verses on the Essence of Dependent Origination</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya­kārikā</title>), a text
                        credibly attributed to Nāgārjuna.</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="14">It is by means of [the analogies of] a recitation, a lamp, a
                            stamp, a mirror, [echoing] sound, a magnifying glass, a seed, and a sour
                            taste that the wise should understand that aggregates take rebirth but
                            without transmigration (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">asaṃkrama</foreign>) [of anything].<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-18" index="8">The Sanskrit of verse five of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya­kārikā</title>, as
                                cited in Candrakīrti’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title>
                                428.11–12 and 551.14 (ed. La Vallée Poussin), reads: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">svādhyāya­dīpa­mudrā­darpaṇa­ghoṣārkakānta­bījāmlaiḥ /
                                    skandha­pratisaṃdhir asaṃkramaś ca vivadvadbhir
                                    avadhāryau</foreign>* // *<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prasannapadā</title> 428: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">upadhāryau</foreign>. The translation is our own,
                                informed by the sūtra’s own explanation of the eight. Cf. the
                                translations of this verse in <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-135">May
                                    (1959)</ptr>, p. 259, and <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-143">Skilling (1997)</ptr>, p. 253. For further canonical sources for
                                each of the eight examples, see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-135">May (1959)</ptr>, n. 908 and n. 933. On the “sunstone” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">arkakānta</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sūryakānta</foreign>), which is
                                contrasted with the “moonstone” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">candrakānta</foreign>), see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-133">Lamotte (1949)</ptr>, p. 446, n. 1.
                                Cf. Kālidāsa’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Abhi­jñāna­śākuntala</title>
                                II, 7: “Indeed, burning fiery energy lies hidden in ascetics
                                focussed on calm, just as sūryakāntas which are cool enough to be
                                touched spit out their [fiery energy] when another such energy
                                prevails.” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">śama­pradhāneṣu
                                    tapodhaneṣu gūḍaṃ hi dāhātmakam asti tejaḥ / sparśānukūlā iva
                                    sūrya­kāntās tad anya­tejo’bhibhavād vamanti</foreign>). Less
                                poetically put, a sunstone functions as a magnifying glass: it emits
                                heat when aligned with the blazing sun.</note>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-19"/>
                    <p tid="15">Indeed, it may well be, as Skilling opines, that Nāgārjuna’s own
                        verse was based on this sūtra: the eight analogies in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya­kārikā</title> are the same (and practically
                        in the same order) as those in the sūtra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-20" index="9">
                            <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-143">Skilling (1997)</ptr>, p. 255: “The
                            eight similes are not only identical to those of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya-kārikā</title>, but also
                            occur in a very similar order: this is sufficient to establish a
                            relationship between the two texts. We may therefore conclude that one
                            of the texts is referring to the other. Since the similes are not only
                            listed in the sūtra, but also described at length, and since the similes
                            are only a part of the long sūtra, of which they form a natural
                            component, I suggest that it is Nāgārjuna who has based his verse on the
                            sūtra, and not the composer or editor of the sūtra who has adapted
                            Nāgārjuna’s verse into his text. It is indeed characteristic of
                            Nāgārjuna’s style to give brief paraphrases of canonical passages in his
                            important works, such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Madhyamaka-kārikās</title>, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnāvalī</title>, and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suhṛllekha</title>.” Skilling points out that Sanskrit and Tibetan
                            texts of Nāgārjuna’s verse 5 have the eight analogies in slightly
                            different orders, but that the order in the sūtra is
                                <emph>exactly</emph> the same as that in the Tibetan of verse
                            5.</note> Skilling’s historical point would be important, because it
                        would tell against interpreting Nāgārjuna’s own term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">asaṃkrama</foreign> as somehow indicating
                        an unqualified rejection of transmigration. The sūtra, in its extensive
                        explanations of the eight analogies (<ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-98"/>–<ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-115"/>), makes it clear that “no transmigration” does
                        not mean that there is <emph>no</emph> transmigration or rebirth, but rather
                        that nothing actually transmigrates; there is no transmigration from one
                        life to another of any entity whatsoever, be it permanent or extinguished. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-21"/>
                    <p tid="16">A brief word on the title. The key Tibetan term that figures in the
                        title, and repeatedly in the body of the text, is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshe ’pho ba</foreign>, which literally means “shifting
                        lives.” Much like the English euphemism “passing on,”
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshe ’pho ba</foreign> too can
                        have both the sense of “death” as well as “moving to another life” or
                        “transmigration.” In the sūtra most occurrences of the term can be
                        translated by “death” and “dying.” And elsewhere in Buddhist literature too
                        the term is generally used to mean simply “to die,” as we see in <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> 230 where the Sanskrit for
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshe ’phos nas</foreign> is given
                        as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cyuta</foreign>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-22" index="10">The other entry for <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshe ’phos pa</foreign> in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>, i.e., 2980, gives the
                            Sanskrit as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">jāti­vyativṛttaḥ</foreign>, “one who has left birth”; the Tibetan
                            given here is <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ’phos pa’am
                                tshe rjes pa</foreign>, “leaving life or changing lives.”</note>
                        Nonetheless, in the final sections of the sūtra there are passages where the
                        term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’pho ba</foreign> must be
                        understood as referring to transmigration to the next life or to the
                            afterlife.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-23" index="11">See
                                <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-77"/><!--n. 38-->.</note> Taking this
                        dual usage into account we have hence translated the title as “Questions
                        Regarding Death and Transmigration.” At the end of the text in all Kangyurs 
                        the title is given as <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba bstan pa’i
                            mdo</title>, with <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’chi ’pho
                            ba</foreign> (“death and transmigration”) replacing the 
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tshe ’pho ba</foreign> in the title 
                        given at the beginning of the text.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-24" index="12">Note too that in this version of the title found at the end of the 
                            text, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstan pa’i mdo</foreign> (“The Sūtra Teaching . . .”) 
                            replaces <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">zhus pa’i mdo</foreign> (The Sūtra of Questions 
                            Regarding . . .”). This title given at the end of the text is the one that 
                            figures in Butön’s list of canonical translations (F.144.b), Situ Paṇchen’s catalogue 
                            (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">dkar chag</foreign>) of the Degé Kangyur (F.134.b), and 
                            quite frequently (or as the variant <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur 
                                ba lung bstan pa’i mdo</title>) in later commentarial literature 
                            citing the sūtra.</note> Finally, it should be noted that the
                        Sanskrit in the title, i.e., <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āyuṣpatti</foreign> (or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">āyuḥpatti</foreign>), is not well attested. Indeed the usual complete
                        title <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuṣpatti­yathākāra­paripṛcchā</title> is
                        dubious and probably a back translation from the Tibetan.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-25" index="13">The <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">them spangs ma</foreign> recension Kangyurs have <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥyathabhutāgraha­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>
                            (S, L: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥ­yatha­bhutāgraha­sūtra</title>), which also remains dubious
                            even when corrected to <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥ­yathābhūta­graha­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title> (S: <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥ­yathābhūta­graha­sūtra</title>). Cf. <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-143">Skilling (1997)</ptr>, p. 257: “Both
                            titles seem awkward and unlikely, and may be later concoctions.” </note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-26"/>
                    <p tid="17">The sūtra is not extant in Sanskrit, nor was it translated into
                        Chinese, and nor is there a Pāli counterpart. According to the colophon it
                        was translated into Tibetan during the earlier dissemination of the 
                        teachings. Unusually, the colophon also states that the translation was <emph>not</emph> 
                        modified with the “revised terminology” that we find in translations from the opening
                        decades of the ninth century on; nevertheless, the language does not seem to be
                        heavily reliant on so-called “ancient linguistic usage” either. No
                        translator is mentioned. This translation was clearly done outside the ninth century institutional
                            mainstream.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-27" index="14">The sūtra is absent from both
                                early ninth century inventories, the Denkarma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ldan dkar 
                                    ma</foreign>) and Phangthangma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phang thang ma</foreign>), but 
                                is mentioned in Butön’s fourteenth century list of canonical texts. On
                            Tibetan institutions of translation and their procedures, before and
                            during the ninth century, see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-141">Scherrer-Schaub (2002)</ptr>, which also provides, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="la">inter alia</foreign>, a bibliography of
                            the main research on these subjects.</note> </p>
                      <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-188"/>
                      <p tid="17">Although the important theme
                        of reincarnation is treated here with a sophisticated argumentation much
                        more typical of the Tengyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstan
                            ’gyur</foreign>) than the Kangyur (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bka’ ’gyur</foreign>) literature, the sūtra does not seem to have
                        attracted notable attention in India, apart from possibly figuring as
                        Nāgārjuna’s source for the eight analogies, and not much in Tibet, either. A global
                        search of the Tibetan text input on the site of the Buddhist Digital
                        Resource Center (<ref target="http://www.tbrc.org">www.tbrc.org</ref>) shows
                        only relatively few references to this text in indigenous Tibetan
                        scholarship. The Geluk scholastic writer Choné Drakpa Shedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne grags pa shes sgrub</foreign>, 1675–1748) quotes
                        a large section of this sūtra in his <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lho sgo’i cho
                            ga’i rgyas ’grel gzhan phan nyi ’od</title>, pp. 225–27 and pp. 243–44.
                        We have on occasion cited variants found in his text. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-28"/>
                    <p tid="18">This sūtra is significant both philosophically as well as
                        historically, being a reliable witness to relatively early Indian
                        non-Buddhist views concerning death and the Buddhist polemics against them.
                        However, with its often long, convoluted sentences and involved
                        argumentation, the text was manifestly not an easy one for scribes, nor
                        probably for its anonymous Tibetan translators. We have not attempted a
                        critical edition, but have given the most significant variants that underlie
                        our understanding of the text. The Tibetan of the Degé Kangyur was our base text, 
                        and its folio numbers appear in the translation. The versions in the Peking Kangxi,
                        Peking Yongle, Lithang, Narthang, Choné, Urga, and Lhasa Zhol Kangyurs were also consulted via the
                            Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) of the Kangyur. 
                        The Stok Palace and Shelkar (“London”) manuscript Kangyurs, as
                        representatives of the Thempangma (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">them spangs ma</title>) line of 
                        Kangyur transmission, provide invaluable alternative
                        readings, especially on the not infrequent occasions where the Comparative Edition has only implausible
                        variants.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-189" index="15">See 
                            <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-121">Bibliography</ptr> 
                            and <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-117">Abbreviations</ptr> for details.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="97">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="98">The Sūtra</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="99">Questions Regarding Death and Transmigration</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-29"/>
                    <p tid="19">
                        <ref cRef="F.145.b" type="folio"/>  Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-191"/>
                    <p tid="20">Thus did I hear at one time. The Blessed One, seeing that the time had
                        come to train all the various householders of the great city of Kapilavastu,
                        went there with a retinue of five hundred to cause them to generate
                        faith.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-30"/>
                    <p tid="21">At that time, a man in the prime of his life called Śākya Nandaja,
                        who was cherished by all his relatives and praised by all, had died. In
                        front of his body his children, wife, relatives, and dependents had gathered
                        together his horses, elephants, clothes, and a variety of ornaments, gold
                        and silver, pearls, crystals, and other jewels, as well as a variety of
                        delicious and sweet food and drink. They offered them, wailing, “We give
                        these to Nandaja!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-193"/>
                    <p tid="22">This made King Śuddhodana wish <ref cRef="F.146.a" type="folio"/> to
                        ask the Blessed One what benefit<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-31" index="16">We 
                            find <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sman pa</foreign> in all editions. It clearly needs to
                            be read in its attested sense of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">phan pa</foreign> 
                            (“benefit”) and not in the sense of “a doctor.” See
                                <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-144">Zhang Yisun et al. (1985)</ptr>,
                            s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sman pa</foreign>.</note>
                        and good would ensue if, in such a fashion, offerings, food,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-32" index="17">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gsol ba</foreign> = honorific for
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">lto chas</foreign>.</note>
                        and honors to the deceased were presented according to the brahmins’
                        formulae. He approached the Blessed One, prostrated, and asked, “Blessed
                        One, would you allow me to ask some questions about what it is like for
                        sentient beings to die?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-192"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, ask
                        whatever you wish. It will be explained to the Great King’s
                        satisfaction.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-33"/>
                    <p tid="22">The Great King Śuddhodana then asked the Blessed One, “Blessed One,
                        regarding the rebirths of beings who pass from this world to the next, are
                            <term type="ignore">god</term>s reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s? Likewise, are humans, animals, hungry ghosts, and hell-beings
                        also reborn consistently as their own kind, respectively, as humans,
                        animals, hungry ghosts, and hell-beings? Or is it the case, Blessed One,
                        that when <term type="ignore">god</term>s pass from this life, they are
                        reborn as humans and other kinds of beings? Likewise, are humans, animals,
                        hungry ghosts, and hell-beings reborn as other kinds of beings, such as
                            <term type="ignore">god</term>s and so forth, as well?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-34"/>
                    <p tid="23">“Or, Blessed One, when they pass from this life do sentient beings
                        become utterly nonexistent, becoming like the ashes of a fire that has died
                        out, and not taking any rebirth at all?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-195"/>
                    <p tid="24">“Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? Do all 
                        sentient beings live on after their deaths, befriending their kin<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-35" index="18">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">ris ’thun pa</foreign>. The term
                            is later replaced by <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mes
                                po</foreign>, “ancestors.”</note> in a beginningless lineage
                        including fathers, grand­fathers, great-grandfathers, and more, not taking
                        rebirth in a future life but living just as they do in this life? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-36"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Blessed One, do those who are wealthy and proud in this life go on
                        to be wealthy and proud in the hereafter too, <ref cRef="F.146.b" type="folio"/> and do
                        those who are poor and humble in this life go on to be poor and humble in
                        the next? Or do people simply switch back and forth between the two?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-37" index="19">It is clear in the
                            reply later that the type of “switching” being
                            discussed is one that would occur arbitrarily, without karmic or other
                            causes. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-196"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? Those who, in
                        this life, ride horses and elephants, wear fine clothes and ornaments, eat
                        food and drink, do they continue in their future lives to ride, dress, and eat in the
                        same way? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-38"/>
                    <p tid="27">“Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? When their
                        parents, siblings and cousins, children, and so forth give or dedicate small
                        portions of food or drink to someone who has passed from this world, is the
                        deceased then able to eat and drink inexhaustibly for many eons? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-197"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Blessed One, is it really as the worldly say it is? When sentient
                        beings pass on from this world, do they later, after death, tell their
                        parents, siblings, children, and so forth the same things, such as stories and so
                        forth, that they had told them earlier before they died? And do they later
                        exhibit the same physical features to them as they had earlier before death?
                        Are they seen and heard to do this?”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-39"/>
                    <p tid="29">After these queries, the Blessed One replied to the king Śuddhodana,
                        “O Great King, with regard to your question as to whether <term type="ignore">god</term>s are reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s
                        and so forth, the answer is ‘no.’ Suppose that when <term type="ignore">god</term>s died they were reborn only as <term type="ignore">god</term>s and not reborn as other types of beings, and the same for
                        humans and so forth. O Great King, initially humans come from <term type="ignore">god</term>s, and the three lower realms come from humans’
                        engagement in nonvirtue. Therefore, those <term type="ignore">god</term>s
                        and so forth who die <ref cRef="F.147.a" type="folio"/> are reborn in various other types
                        of migrations.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-40"/>
                    <p tid="30">“O Great King, suppose, moreover, that the answer to this question
                        of yours were to be ‘yes.’ Then it would be logical that the quantities of
                        the six types of beings would always be the same as they are now. But
                        notice how the three lower realms are more numerously repopulated<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-41" index="20">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">phyir zhing mang ba</foreign>,
                            literally, “once again many/more.”</note> due to the preponderance<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-42" index="21">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mang ba</foreign>, “more.”</note>
                        of humans’ engagement in nonvirtue! Moreover, O Great King, if the arhats
                        of today come from the ranks of humans, then it cannot be right that beings
                        are consistently reborn in their own types. What is more, it would be
                        impossible for anyone to obtain the fruit of being an arhat. Therefore, O
                        Great King, through virtuous and nonvirtuous actions beings are reborn as
                        different types, such as those in the heavens and those in the lower
                        realms.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-43"/>
                    <p tid="31">“O Great King, regarding your question as to 
                        whether <term type="ignore">god</term>s that die are reborn as other types of beings,
                        such as humans and the like, the answer is ‘yes.’</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-194"/>
                    <p tid="32"> “O Great King, regarding your question as to whether sentient
                        beings die and become utterly nonexistent, like the ashes of a fire that has
                        died out, and as to whether rebirth is utterly nonexistent, the answer is
                        ‘no.’ O Great King, just as when you have a seed, a fruit will come forth,
                        so from the seed of this life the fruit of the next life comes about. O
                        Great King, just as the sun rises, slowly sets, becomes obscured, and then
                        rises again the following morning, so too one passes from this life and
                        takes rebirth. O Great King, sentient beings would become extinct species if
                        they died without any subsequent rebirth. O Great King, if we take the grass
                        and trees outside too, those that have withered will grow again through the
                        changing of the seasons. Likewise, sentient beings will be reborn and die
                        through actions and afflicted emotions, which are like the changing of the
                        seasons. So, O Great King, know that there are future lives.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-44"/>
                    <p tid="33">“O Great King, you asked whether <ref cRef="F.147.b" type="folio"/> it is as the worldly say it is. You
                        asked whether all sentient beings after their deaths live on, befriending
                        their kin in a beginningless lineage, including parents, grandparents,
                        great-grandparents, and so forth, and not taking rebirth in a future life
                        but living just as they did in this life. O Great King, in this life, when a
                        parent or a child and the like see each other, it is one embodied being
                        seeing another, not one mind seeing another. If, in this life, the body
                        perishes and is gone, then in the hereafter how would one mind see another
                        and befriend it? Children, nephews, and nieces who are alive and have
                        physical forms cannot even see their deceased parents, grandparents, and
                        great-grandparents. Then how would disembodied deceased people see and
                        befriend their formless parents, grandparents, and great-grandparents? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-45"/>
                    <p tid="34">“What is more, O Great King, in this life, when the many parents,
                        children, and other relatives get together, even then, it is only their
                        respective physical forms that appear. Unable to see even their own
                            minds,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-46" index="22">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rang gi sems kyang rang gis mi
                                mthong na</foreign>. Here the point seems to be that they do not
                            literally see their minds. Seeing is reserved for physical
                            objects.</note> how could children and other relatives ever see each
                        other’s minds? How would they see them after death? How would they, in an
                        afterlife, first see the children, relatives, grandparents, and
                        great-grandparents and then befriend them?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-47"/>
                    <p tid="35">“O Great King, let us suppose that an ancestor, one who had no one
                        before him at any point in beginningless time, and his presently existing
                        descendants were to befriend each other in a future life. Now, there are at
                        present many different clans, castes, factions, and parties, some of which
                        have become enemies of each other and whose places of residence, associates
                        of clan and caste, language, and style of dress are neither heard of nor
                        seen. Suppose that they too issued from the same original ancestor.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-48" index="23">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">thog ma mes po gcig las gyes pa
                                yin na</foreign>.</note> How would you delineate which children and
                        relatives do or do not befriend present children, relatives, grandfathers,
                        and so forth? The offspring from this first ancestor, up to and including
                        the presently existing relatives and children, <ref cRef="F.148.a" type="folio"/> would
                        be alike in their respective affections [and antagonisms] for one another,
                        just like the presently existing children and relatives. If this is so, who
                        befriends whom and who fails to befriend whom?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-49" index="24">The argument seems to be as follows. Among
                            our presently existing kin some are enemies (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dgra</foreign>), unfriendly to each other, while some
                            are not. If we take the collection of kinfolk from the first ancestor
                            on, the same would hold. We thus could not determine that our kinfolk
                            are precisely the ones associated as friends (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">grogs</foreign>), and other people’s kin are the ones
                            that are not.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-50"/>
                    <p tid="36">“People who are now living each apprehend their own factions and parties,
                        saying, ‘So-and-so is our ancestor.’ And they determine the factions and
                        parties, saying, ‘We are children of the same father as so-and-so.’
                        Suppose, too, that they now each grasped as ‘our ancestors’
                        the lineage of all the fathers, grandfathers, great-grandfathers, and
                        great-great-grandfathers all the way down to the first ancestor—that is, the
                        lineage of all those who respectively apprehend each other as
                            ‘ancestors.’ And suppose, following what the worldly
                        say, these ancestors did not take rebirth after passing from this world, but
                        instead befriended children and relatives in an afterlife. Then they would
                        have to befriend as one unified faction<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-51" index="25">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">phyogs gcig nas</foreign>. The
                            textual passage is long and difficult, and the translation is therefore
                            unsure. It appears that the argument is essentially an elaboration on
                            the argument of the previous paragraph. A collection of ancestors, some
                            of whom are very different from and even antagonistic to the others,
                            would have to be somehow apprehended and befriended as a unified
                            harmonious party.</note> the presently different clans, castes, and
                        factions, as well as all those people that have become enemies, too.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-52"/>
                    <p tid="37">“O Great King, in this life, although people appear as embodied
                        entities, nonetheless when they are in the dark or hidden they do not see
                        one another. Then, given that deceased beings do not have any bodies, how
                        could they see and thus befriend one another? O Great King, if embodied
                        sentient beings who are alive now cannot even make their bodies visible to
                        people in some other country or in the different places that they do not see,
                        then how could they ever make their bodies visible after death? O Great
                        King, you should not listen to worldly individuals who seek fame and
                            gain<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-53" index="26">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rnyed pa</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">lābha</foreign>.</note> and thus
                        deceive others with the tales they tell.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-54"/>
                    <p tid="38">“O Great King, you asked whether those who are wealthy and proud in
                        this life are also wealthy and proud in the hereafter, whether the poor and
                        humble in this life go on to be poor and humble in the next, or whether
                        people switch between the two. O Great King, just take sentient beings in
                        this life who have not yet died: some are wealthy and proud from the moment
                        of birth, but are then poor and humble from the age of fifty or sixty onward
                        into their old age; <ref cRef="F.148.b" type="folio"/> others are poor and humble from birth
                        and throughout their youth, but then, from the age of fifty or
                        sixty up until their old age, they are wealthy and proud. If that is 
                        so, then it is all the more obvious that
                        people’s riches and poverty are impermanent when they are dead! O Great
                        King, to use an analogy, in this world when conditions like warmth and
                        moisture are present, grass, trees, and other plants grow leaves, but when
                        it is cold and dry they wither. Similarly, one becomes wealthy and proud
                        due to conditions such as generosity, but poor and humble from theft and
                        miserliness. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-55"/>
                    <p tid="39">“O Great King, some people are wealthy and proud from life to life
                        because they have always been generous. Others are poor and humble in some
                        lives, or at the beginning or end of certain lives, because they were partial
                        or had regrets about giving. Some are poor and humble life after life
                        because they always stole or were miserly. Yet others are wealthy and proud
                        in some lives, or at the beginning or end of certain lives, because they
                        regretted their theft and miserliness. O Great King, being poor and humble
                        does not come about through generosity. Being wealthy and proud does not
                        come about through miserliness. One does not simply [arbitrarily] switch
                        between riches and poverty from one life to the next. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-56"/>
                    <p tid="40">“O Great King, you asked whether what the worldly say is really
                        true. You asked whether those who, in this life, ride horses and
                        elephants and so forth, wear fine clothes and ornaments, and eat food and
                        drink, continue in future lives after their deaths to ride, dress, 
                        eat, and drink in the same ways. O Great King, when humans die, they take
                        rebirth in the heavens or in the lower realms in line with how they had
                        practiced virtuous or nonvirtuous actions. O Great King, it is not as the
                        worldly say it is.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-57"/>
                    <p tid="41">“What about an apparition of a deceased individual’s style of dress?
                        In the heavenly realm there exists an unfathomable, unimaginable, limitless
                            <ref cRef="F.149.a" type="folio"/> world of gandharvas. One type there is called
                            <distinct>the gandharva who preys upon the minds of those on the verge
                            of death</distinct>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-58" index="27">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">dri za ’chi ka ma’i sems la nye
                                bar ’jug pa zhes bya ba’i rigs</foreign>. We unfortunately have no
                            information on this type of gandharva.</note> In search of the food that
                        gandharvas eat, they create an illusion of the body, clothes, ornaments, and
                        style of dress of someone who lived previously. They thus create and display
                        illusions of the style of dress and the speech of a deceased person. But
                        there is more here, O Great King. Not only gandharvas, but other spirits,
                        such as yakṣas, piśācas, and bhūtas, also seek to trick the deceased
                        person’s father, sons, relatives, and so forth. Thus these demons use their
                        worldly magical powers to know the distinctive signs, final resting place,
                        and the history of the deceased individual, and then they use their demonic
                        influence so that parents and others see and dream of that individual. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-59"/>
                    <p tid="42">“Furthermore, O Great King, consider the following. It is due also
                        to the maturation of habitual tendencies stemming from longstanding
                        association that one sees children and relatives and that they appear in
                        dreams. Suppose, for example, that a person dreamed of their own presently
                            undeceased<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-60" index="28">Read
                            with D, A, S, L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">da ltar
                                tshe ma ’phos pa’i rang gi pha ma</foreign>. C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">da ltar tshe ’phos pa’i rang gi pha
                                ma</foreign>. </note> parents, relatives, servants, or any others
                        who might befriend them, and as well dreamed of their pleasures coming from
                        various enjoyments, or their pleasures and pains from grappling with enemies
                        or thieves. If the parents, relatives, and servants they dreamed of, or any
                        others appearing in their dream, actually were to have the feelings in
                        question, just as that person dreamed they did, then that of which they
                        dreamed would have been real. But how could the parents, relatives, and
                        servants they dreamed of, or any others appearing in their dream, ever be
                        thought to be real?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-61" index="29">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mi des rmis pa bzhin du gang
                                rmis pa’i pha ma’am / spun zla’am / bran khol lam gzhan su yang rung
                                ba rmi lam na snang ba der* tshor ba yod na ni rmis pa de bden pa
                                yin na / des rmis pa’i pha ma’am / spun zla’am / bran khol lam /
                                gzhan su yang rung rmi lam na snang ba de bden par ji ltar bzung
                                /</foreign>. *S, L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">der</foreign>; D, A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">des</foreign>. C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi> appears to be truncated: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">mi des rmis pa bzhin du gang rmis
                                pa’i pha ma’am / spun zla’am / bral [<foreign xml:lang="la">sic</foreign>] khol lam / su yang rung ba rmi lam na snang ba
                                des tshor ba yod na ni rmis pa de bden pa yin na / des rmis pa ltar
                                med pas bden par ji ltar bzung</foreign>. “If the parents,
                            relatives, and servants they dreamed of, or any others appearing in
                            their dream, actually were to have the feelings in question, just as that
                            person dreamed they did, then that which they dreamed would have been
                            real. They do not exist as they dreamed them, so how could they be
                            thought to be real?”</note> O Great King, even among living people, that
                        which one person dreams is never felt by another. Then how could what is
                        dreamed concerning a deceased person ever be that deceased person?<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-62" index="30">D, A, S, L:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ’phos pa’i rmis pa tshe
                                ’phos pa de yin par ga la ’gyur</foreign>; C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ma ’phos pas rmis pa de tshe
                                ’phos pa de yin pa ga la ’gyur</foreign>. “How could what is dreamed
                            by a non-deceased person ever be that deceased person?”</note> What is
                        involved is the maturation of habitual tendencies.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-63"/>
                    <p tid="43">“O Great King, there is yet another analogy for this being a matter of habitual
                        tendencies. Suppose that a person left whatever castles, houses, and cities
                        they had been in during an earlier part of their life, and that in the later
                        part of their life, <ref cRef="F.149.b" type="folio"/> when they lived elsewhere, the
                        city they knew previously was destroyed. This person dreams of the
                        shape and size of their house as they were when it was neither destroyed nor
                        scattered about,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-64" index="31"> We
                            read with S and L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’grams</foreign>. This is a variant of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gram</foreign>, the intransitive verb meaning “to be
                            spread, dispersed, scattered.” See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-128">Golstein (2004)</ptr>, s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’grams</foreign>. The numerous implausible variants in editions (D,
                            A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’drams</foreign>; K,
                            K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’drangs</foreign>; C:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’drems</foreign>; S, L:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’grams</foreign>; C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>:
                            missing) suggest that the word in question was not understood by
                            scribes. A search of the BDRC site shows that <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’drams</foreign> (homophonous with <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’grams</foreign>) is not attested
                            elsewhere.</note> no different from before. If the city and the house
                        were to have mental natures,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-65" index="32">We follow D and A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">grong dang khang pa de la sems yod na
                                ni khang pa de’i sems snang du rung na</foreign>. More literally,
                            “If the city and house had a mind” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">sems yod 
                                na ni</foreign>). All witnesses in A, as well as S and L, 
                            have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems</foreign> (“mind”), except for C as recorded in A, which
                            has <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems can</foreign> (“being”).
                            However, C does not have <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">sems can</foreign> in any of the subsequent text of this
                            argument.</note> then the mental nature of that house might have
                        actually appeared to them. But since their house and city are earth and
                            stone,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-66" index="33">A reads
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">des rdo</foreign>, but one
                            should no doubt read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de sa
                                rdo</foreign>. The intersyllabic dot (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">tsheg</foreign>) appears 
                                quite clearly in S and L.</note> then why would what that person dreamed not be a
                        maturation of their habitual tendencies? Likewise, that which has the
                        distinctive signs of a now deceased person is comparable to the
                        undestroyed house of one’s dreams. And if the deceased individual’s mind too
                        had already taken rebirth in accordance with their previous actions, then
                        could they actually appear<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-67" index="34">Read <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snang</foreign> with D; A has mistakenly recorded <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">snad</foreign>. </note> to anyone? We
                        conclude, O Great King, that it is through the maturation of habitual
                        tendencies that people see and dream of distinctive signs and styles of
                        dress of now deceased individuals. Likewise, the appearances and
                        occurrences in dreams of the deceased holding swords and other weapons,
                        wearing clothes and other ornaments, and riding their horses and elephants,
                        and so forth are also just appearances due to habitual tendencies. You
                        should understand them along the lines of the analogy of the house.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-68"/>
                    <p tid="44">“O Great King, you asked whether it is as the worldly say it
                        is. You asked whether those who have passed on from this world can eat and
                        drink inexhaustibly for many eons the small portions of food and drink given
                        and dedicated to them by their parents, siblings and cousins, children, and
                        other relatives. O Great King, anywhere, be it on the four continents, in
                        the chiliocosms, the dichiliocosms, the trichiliocosms, or in the limitless,
                        unfathomable, unimaginable world systems, have you ever seen a sentient
                        being who consumes one small portion of food and drink all the time and over
                        many eons? Have you ever heard of such a sentient being? O Great King,
                        though the Cakravartin king has a wish-fulfilling gem that gives whatever he
                        might wish, it came to exist because of immeasurable <ref cRef="F.150.a" type="folio"/>
                        collections of merit collected earlier over numerous eons—it did not fall
                        from the sky or emerge accidentally. Is it then reasonable that this small
                        portion of food and drink would remain unexpended until the end of the
                        eon?</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-69"/>
                    <p tid="45">“O Great King, suppose that some living parents, children, siblings,
                        and cousins, who have a mutual relationship and wish to be of benefit to
                        one another, have not yet died and are still physically embodied. And suppose
                        one of them went off to another country. Although any of the parents, children,
                        siblings, or cousins might resolve to give and offer a lot of food and drink
                        to that person, none of that would appear to the person who had gone off
                        to the other country, even in their dreams—let alone food and drink
                        in reality. So why even mention food and drink dedicated to people who
                        have died and have no body? O Great King, how would those people, whose minds
                        have separated from their bodies after death, use their immaterial and formless
                        minds to take possession of the real items of food and drink provided to them
                        by their children, siblings, and the like? Why would this be a problem? The
                        answer is that eating and chewing depend on the workings of body parts. In that
                        case, are the workings of the parts of the body to be found present in the
                        mind?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-70"/>
                    <p tid="46">The Great King then asked, “Blessed One, if that is the case, then
                        is it useless to offer deceased individuals the food, drink, mounts,
                        clothes, and ornaments that were beneficial to them in the present
                        world?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-200"/>
                    <p tid="47">The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, take the case where a
                        deceased person is being reborn in one of various different states of being
                        because actions he had done are ripening. And suppose people help<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-71" index="35">We follow D, A:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstangs</foreign>; S:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btang</foreign>; L:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gtang</foreign>.
                        </note> that person by [dedicating to him] all sorts of virtuous actions that will
                        constitute a collection of merit without any nonvirtue. In that case, the
                        person will be reborn in higher states, or attain liberation. On the
                        other hand, when someone has already taken rebirth, then if one aids<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-72" index="36">D, A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bstangs</foreign>; S, L:
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">btang</foreign>.
                        </note> him through [the dedication of] a virtuous action that constitutes
                        merit, that will aid the already reborn person to gain wealth, have good
                        crops, more and more of the pleasures he wishes, as well as honor and
                        respect from all his other fellow beings. However, it is not so that the
                        deceased individual stays on in the ‘world of
                            Death,’<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-73" index="37">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">gshin gyi ’jig rten</foreign> is
                            not a usual term, but is probably the same as the more usual <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje’i ’jig rten</foreign>, i.e., the
                            Sanskrit <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yamaloka</foreign>, the
                            world of Yama, the lord of Death and ruler over the various departed
                            ancestors (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pitṛ</foreign>). Cf.
                            Negi s.v. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">gshin rje’i ’jig
                                rten</foreign> (= <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yamaloka</foreign>). On the Vedic afterlife, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">yamaloka</foreign>, see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-125">Bodewitz (1999)</ptr>, <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-142">Shushan (2011)</ptr>.</note> without
                        rebirth, <ref cRef="F.150.b" type="folio"/> and taking on food and drink, mounts,
                        clothing, and ornaments. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-74"/>
                    <p tid="48">“O Great King, suppose people say that things seen by the worldly
                        and dreamed of by parents and others are dedicated to the deceased,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-75" index="38">Read with S,
                            L, C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ’phos pa
                                la</foreign>; D, A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe
                                ’phos pa las</foreign>.</note> and that consequently the dead
                        person is satisfied with the food and drink, rides the mounts, and wears the clothes
                        and ornaments. While this might appear to be so,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-76" index="39">Read 
                            with S, L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">… rgyan thogs so zhes smra na / de
                                ltar snang ba de yang…</foreign>; D, A, C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">… rgyan thogs so // zhes smra zhing
                                de ltar snang ba de yang…</foreign>.</note> there are demons and
                        gandharvas who prey upon the minds of those on the verge of death, and who make
                        such apparitions manifest in that way and [make them seem to be] saying they
                        are unsatisfied with the food and drink, do not have the mounts, and do not wear
                        the clothes and ornaments.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-77" index="40">We have translated on the basis of S and
                            L. Here is the whole passage in those editions: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">kye rgyal po chen po ’jig rten pa dag
                                gang gis mthong ba dang / pha ma la sogs pas rmi lam du rmis te /
                                tshe ’phos pa la bsngos pas gshin de bza’ btung gis mgu’o // bzhon
                                pa zhon no // *gos gon no* // rgyan thogs so zhes smra na / de ltar
                                snang ba de yang bza’ btung gis mi mgu’o // zhon pa med do // **gos
                                mi gon no** // rgyan mi thogs so zhes smra zhing de ltar snang ba
                                dag dri za ’chi ka’i sems la nye bar ’jug pa dang / mi ma yin pa dag
                                gis de ltar snang bar byed pa yod do //</foreign>. *…* omitted in
                            L. **…** omitted in L. The Tibetan text may be corrupt in all
                            editions; it has a seeming over-use of the phrase <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">de ltar snang ba</foreign> several
                            times in the same sentence. We have tried to take them into account as
                            best as possible, but the translation remains tentative. The basic
                            point, however, seems to be as earlier (see <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-57"/>), viz., people think that
                            offerings will enable the dead to eat, ride, be clothed, etc., but what
                            actually happens is that certain sorts of gandharvas create an
                            apparition of a dissatisfied deceased person so that they themselves can
                            profit from the clothes, food, etc., offered by relatives to the
                            deceased.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-78"/>
                    <p tid="49">“O Great King, the worldly say the following: whatever words
                        sentient beings say and stories they tell, and whatever physical
                        features they exhibit to their parents, siblings, and so forth when on the
                        verge of death, later, after death, they will tell the same stories and so
                        forth to their parents, siblings, and children that they had told earlier before
                        they died, and they will exhibit the same physical features to them later as
                        they had earlier before their death—such visions and exhibitions supposedly
                        exist. The Great King has asked whether what the worldly say is true or not. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-79"/>
                    <p tid="50">“O Great King, take the case of speech. Speech depends upon the
                        vocal tract of an embodied person. So then, if the body of the dead person
                        is left behind in this world, how could their incorporeal mind ever speak?
                        Now, when we say that a dead person has a body, we mean that they have taken
                        rebirth, for which parents were required. So there is no ‘world of
                            Death’ either.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-80"/>
                    <p tid="51">“O Great King, what the worldly call characteristics and distinctive
                        signs of the living<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-81" index="41">There are quite divergent readings of more or less equal plausibility.
                            We read with D and A: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ma
                                ’phos pa’i mtshan ma dang dan rtags ’jig rten pa gang dag smra ba
                                ni</foreign>. C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe
                                ’phos pa’i mtshan ma dang dan rtags ’jig rten pa gang dag smra ba
                                ni</foreign>; S, L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">tshe ma ’phos pa’i mtshan ma dang dan rtags dang bcas pa’i ’jig
                                rten pa gang dag smra ba ni</foreign>. “What one calls worldlings
                            who have characteristics and distinctive signs of the living . . . .”</note>
                        are things fabricated by a type of gandharva called <distinct>the
                            pervader</distinct>. The so-called <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vicana</foreign> sorts of gandharvas, the talkative sorts of
                        yakṣas, and the inquisitive <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bar hi ni
                            ta</foreign> sorts of bhūtas pervade the minds of all the dying, just
                        like a strong wind that instantly blows over the wide plains and
                            waters.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-82" index="42">The
                            Sanskrit names for the sorts of gandharva and bhūta spirits are given
                            with variants in the canonical editions as well as in C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>. We have
                            followed D and A here, but are unable to ascertain the correct
                            Sanskrit names for these spirits and have simply given the Tibetan
                            transcription as is. Cf. S, L: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ba tsi na</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">ba ra hin ti</foreign>. </note> They conjure up<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-83" index="43">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bsgrub</foreign>.</note> such
                        things. And then, <ref cRef="F.151.a" type="folio"/> in order to trick the worldly, these
                        demons tell stories in the same way the deceased people used to do earlier, and
                        exhibit their characteristic styles of dress.”</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-84"/>
                    <p tid="52">At that time Devadatta was present and, not believing what the Blessed One had said, he questioned him:
                        “Gautama, you have explained whatever distinctive signs there are, or are not,
                        in the afterlife that follows death. From whom did you first hear about them, Gautama?
                        When did you come to know about them? Who heard and knew about them along
                        with you?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-85"/>
                    <p tid="53">The Blessed One replied, “Devadatta, for countless eons I practiced
                        numerous sorts of austerities, such as sacrificing my body; I purified all
                        obstructions, perfectly accumulated a great collection of merit, and thus
                        attained omniscient wisdom. There is nothing I do not know concerning any
                        knowable matter before me in the past or in the limitless ten directions in
                        the present, or concerning all knowable matters that will occur in the
                        future.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-201"/>
                    <p tid="54">“Just as when the sun shines here in Jambudvīpa, it does not shine
                        over things gradually or in stages, but shines clearly all at once, so too I
                        know, in one instant, everything that can be known. And thus it is said that
                        I possess the exalted wisdom that knows all aspects.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-86"/>
                    <p tid="55">Devadatta did not believe in these sorts of statements either. In
                        order to test whether the Blessed One actually did possess omniscience, he
                        cut samples of a vast number<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-87" index="44">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">shing tha dad pa brgya stong bye
                                ba dag</foreign>; literally, “the one hundred thousand times ten
                            billion different sorts of wood.”</note> of different sorts of wood,
                        that is, of all the types of trees here on Jambudvīpa, including sandalwood,
                        waved-leaf fig trees, catechu, and so forth. He burnt them and made small
                        bags for the ashes of each one. So as not to be mistaken about which type of
                        wood each bag of ash came from, he labelled each bag of ash with the
                        appropriate name. He then went to the Blessed One and asked, “Blessed One
                            <ref cRef="F.151.b" type="folio"/>, if you possess omniscient wisdom, then which bag
                        of ash belongs to which tree?” And he showed him the small bags of ashes one
                        by one. For each small bag, the Blessed One explained unmistakenly which
                        tree the ash had come from, saying, “This one is sandalwood ash. This one is
                        waved-leaf fig tree ash. This one is catechu ash,” and so forth. Devadatta
                        thus came to believe that the Blessed One really did have omniscient wisdom.
                        Thinking that the Blessed One’s pronouncements on death were all true, he
                        praised him in the following terms:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-88"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“The Blessed One is omniscient;</l>
                        <l>What he has said about death must be true.</l>
                        <l>Without previously seeing them or hearing of them,</l>
                        <l>He recognizes these different varieties of ashes of wood.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="57">He thus praised him and was left at a loss for words.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-89"/>
                    <p tid="58">At that time the Śākya Mahānāman was present, too. Not believing what the
                        Blessed One had said about death, he asked, “Blessed One, did you directly
                        perceive what you have explained about the death of beings, or did you hear
                        it from someone else?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-202"/>
                    <p tid="59">The Blessed One replied, “Mahānāman, there is nothing in the world
                        that my buddha-eye does not see. When a fresh gooseberry is placed in the
                        palm of the hand, all the features of the hand are conspicuous in it.
                        Likewise, there is no knowable thing whatsoever in the three times that I do
                        not see. I do not base myself on hearsay.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-90"/>
                    <p tid="60">In order to test whether the Buddha was truly omniscient or not,
                        Śākya Mahānāman then went to the great city of Kapilavastu. From each
                        household, he took a small bag of rice, and so that he would not mistake
                        whose rice was whose, he wrote down the name of every Śākya he took them
                        from and put these names inside the small bags. When the rice bags came to
                        be a full load for an elephant, <ref cRef="F.152.a" type="folio"/> he went to the Blessed
                        One and requested of him, “Blessed One, if your buddha-eye sees all, then please
                        recognize, without opening them, which Śākyas’ small bags of rice are
                        which.” And he put down the elephant’s load of small bags in front of the
                        Buddha. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-91"/>
                    <p tid="61">The Blessed One held up each small bag in turn and said, “This one
                        belongs to Śākya Nandaka, this one belongs to Śākya Kaya, this one belongs
                        to Śākya Desire,”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-92" index="45">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’dod sred</foreign>. This term has
                            Sanskrit equivalents, but it is not sufficiently clear what the
                            equivalent would be if it is being used as a proper name.</note> and so
                        forth, assigning the appropriate Śākya to each bag of rice and thus
                        unmistakenly, step by step, stating the names till they were finished. With
                        this, Śākya Mahānāman and the others were all convinced that the Blessed
                        One’s buddha-eye saw all things. They thought that the Blessed One’s
                        explanation about death was surely right and commended him as follows:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-93"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“With his buddha-eye, he sees all.</l>
                        <l>Unlike the worldly, he does not lie.</l>
                        <l>He unmistakenly knows the small bags of rice</l>
                        <l>Of everyone in Kapilavastu.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-94"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>“The world lies about beings’ deaths</l>
                        <l>And how they appear in the beyond.</l>
                        <l>The Blessed One has spoken truly.</l>
                        <l>Praise and homage to you who sees all.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="64">They were at a loss for words after offering such praises, and thus
                        remained silent.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-95"/>
                    <p tid="65">The father, the Great King, then spoke. “Blessed One, there are
                        sentient beings who have committed nonvirtues, such as the actions that bring
                        immediate retribution, on account of which they come to experience
                        the unbearable ripening of such actions. Please explain what sorts of things
                        they should do to attain happiness.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-96"/>
                    <p tid="66">The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, those sentient beings who
                        have committed nonvirtuous actions, like those actions that bring immediate
                        retribution, will become pure if they sincerely believe in 
                        the <ref cRef="F.152.b" type="folio"/> ripening of the actions and confess them deeply. If, at
                        death, they regret the negative actions they committed earlier, pay homage,
                        and go for refuge to all the buddhas and bodhisattvas, their negativities
                        will become pure; such beings will also be reborn in high states. Do not
                        think that there are no future lives. Nor should you think that rebirth is
                        caused by God, arbitrarily, or through mere caprice and the like. Have no
                        attachment to any worldly happiness or cyclic existence. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-203"/>
                    <p tid="67">“O Great King, when you pass from this world to the next and take
                        rebirth, it is not something permanent that transmigrates in this way,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-97" index="46"> Here the term
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">’pho ba</foreign> clearly has
                            the sense of “transmigrate,” “pass from one life to the next.” When the
                            Tibetan reads <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="quote">rtag pa mi
                                ’pho</foreign> here, i.e., “it is not something permanent that
                            transmigrates/passes,” the Tibetan <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ’pho</foreign> is to be understood like the Sanskrit term
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">asaṃkrama</foreign> (= Tib.
                                <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mi ’pho ba</foreign>) in
                            verse 5 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya­kārikā</title>. 
                            See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-19"/> in our introduction.</note> nor something
                        that is extinguished, halted, and hence nonexistent. It is neither uncaused,
                        nor arisen from something without a cause, nor made by an external agent. Understand
                        it to be produced by an aggregate of causes and conditions, that is, actions
                        and afflictive emotions.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-98"/>
                    <p tid="68">The Great King then asked, “Blessed One, if the transmigration and
                        rebirth of sentient beings is not the transmigration of something permanent,
                        nor of something extinguished, nor without a cause, nor made by an external agent,
                        and if, moreover, the established fact of rebirth in the world beyond is
                        difficult to understand, are there any analogies for it?”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-99"/>
                    <p tid="69">The Blessed One replied, “O Great King, there are eight analogies
                        for rebirth: (1) the analogy of students learning that which is recited by
                        the teacher, (2) a lamp being lit from another lamp, (3) a reflection
                        occurring because of a mirror, (4) an impression and image coming from a
                        stamp, (5) fire coming from a magnifying glass, (6) a sprout arising from a
                        seed, (7) the production of saliva when someone says the word
                            ‘sour,’ and (8) the sound of an echo. O Great King,
                        in these eight analogies, the fact that earlier things give rise to the
                        later ones illustrates how nothing permanent transmigrates. The fact that
                        later things arise from <ref cRef="F.153.a" type="folio"/> earlier ones illustrates how
                        transmigration and rebirth do not occur without a cause and that they are
                        not of something extinguished and halted.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-100"/>
                    <p tid="70">“Furthermore, O Great King, all of these analogies are things that
                        come about when three conditions are gathered together. When there are
                        teachers, students, and sense faculties, we have recitation and language
                        learning. When there exist butter, wicks, and vessels, we have lamps. When
                        there are bright skies, faces, and mirrors, we have reflections. When there
                        are signets, lumps of clay, and human manual effort, we have impressions and
                        images from stamps. When there are crystals, sunlight, grass, and wood, we
                        get fire. When there are seeds, earth, and moisture, we get sprouts. When
                        there is salt, a previous experience of drinking salty water, and when the
                        word ‘sour’ is pronounced, people then begin to salivate.
                        When someone speaks, when there is no other loud sound, and when there is a
                        nearby mountain, then an echo will occur. These are all analogies showing
                        how sentient beings’ rebirths are not made by external agents, but are produced
                        through the causal conditions of actions and afflictive emotions.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-101"/>
                    <p tid="71">“Furthermore, O Great King, the teacher illustrates this life; the
                        student illustrates future lives; recitation illustrates how consciousness
                        bridges the gap between lives. The earlier lamp illustrates this present
                        life; the later lamp illustrates future lives; though the later lamp arose
                        from the earlier lamp, the fact that the one existed before the other
                        illustrates how nothing permanent transmigrates. That the later one arose
                        from the earlier one illustrates how things do not occur without causes. The
                        mirror illustrates how future lives exist because present lives exist, how
                        nothing real transmigrates, and how future lives definitely do exist. The
                        stamp illustrates how one takes rebirth in a future life in accordance with
                        actions one has done in this life. The magnifying glass illustrates how one
                        exists as one type of being and is then reborn as another. The seed
                        illustrates how one does not cease and become nonexistent. The sour taste
                        illustrates how one takes rebirth due to actions one has experienced. The
                        echoing sound illustrates how one takes a rebirth 
                        when causes and conditions are present without other annulling conditions;
                        <ref cRef="F.153.b" type="folio"/> it illustrates how a [reborn individual] is not the same as or different
                        [from that of the earlier life].</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-102"/>
                    <p tid="72">“O Great King, if I had not explained all eight analogies but had
                        taught only some of them, then those who maintain that rebirth is due to God,
                        arbitrary, due to mere caprice, or without any causes would use the Śramaṇa
                        Gautama’s analogy of recitation to say that consciousness will transmigrate
                        to the next life without losing the aggregates and consciousness of this
                        life. To refute those who might say this, I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-103"/>
                    <p tid="73">“Some might use the analogy of the lamp to say that the aggregates
                        in both this life and the next exist at one and the same time. To refute
                        them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-204"/>
                    <p tid="74">“Some others might use the mirror analogy to say that the lame are
                        reborn lame and the fair are reborn fair because the mirror illustrates
                        similarity. To refute them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-104"/>
                    <p tid="75">“Others might use the analogy of the stamp to say that <term type="ignore">god</term>s who have died are reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s and that humans who have died are reborn as
                        humans. To refute them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-205"/>
                    <p tid="76">“Yet others might use the analogy of the magnifying glass to say
                        that from virtue come the lower realms and from nonvirtue comes high status
                        because a magnifying glass illustrates dissimilarity.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-105" index="47">The point seems to be that the
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūryakānta</foreign> itself is cool to the touch and yet it emits heat. See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-18"/><!--n. 7--> for a verse from Kālidāsa
                            to this effect.</note> To refute them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-106"/>
                    <p tid="77">“Some might use the analogy of the seed to say that one consciousness
                        grows to be many. To refute them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-206"/>
                    <p tid="78">“Some too might use the analogy of a sour taste, because it
                        illustrates experience, to say that those who have a history of rebirth as
                            <term type="ignore">god</term>s will be reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s even though they have not done virtuous deeds, and that
                        those who have a history of rebirth in the lower realms will be reborn in
                        the lower realms even though they have done no nonvirtuous deeds. To refute
                        them I taught the remaining analogies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-107"/>
                    <p tid="79">“Yet some others might use the analogy of the echoing sound to say
                        that rebirth does not come from causes and conditions, as they would
                        maintain that such an analogy illustrates agency. To refute them I taught
                        the remaining analogies. It is for these reasons that I taught all eight
                        analogies.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-108"/>
                    <p tid="80">“O Great King, it is not the case that life ceases, with no rebirth
                        in the hereafter, and that it is extinguished and halted. Neither is this
                        life a permanent entity that transmigrates to the hereafter intact. People
                        cannot take rebirth in the hereafter without any dependence upon this life.
                        Nor do they have a rebirth by simply thinking that they <ref cRef="F.154.a" type="folio"/> will take such and such a rebirth. Rebirth does not occur because people
                        think that they rely on God and the like, and that they will thus be reborn
                        in the heavens. Nor do people take rebirth thinking that they will be reborn
                        wherever they wish, whether in the heavens or in the lower realms. And
                        rebirth does not occur because people think that they will in any case be
                        reborn, even without doing anything and irrespective of causes and
                        conditions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-109"/>
                    <p tid="81">“Nor can one say that one’s aggregates perish, one dies, and that
                        afterward there is nothing at all. One cannot say either that after death
                        in this world, people in the afterlife abide continuously<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-110" index="48">The term <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mu chags su</foreign> is obscure. We
                            have taken it as having a sense like that of <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">mu mthud kyis</foreign>, “continually.”</note> in the
                            ‘world of Death,’ and thus do whatever they did in
                        this life without taking rebirth. Nor can one say that consciousness takes
                        rebirth without any halt to the consciousness one has in the present life.
                        One cannot say that the aggregates of this life and the next exist at the
                        same time. Nor can one say that the lame are reborn lame, the fair are
                        reborn fair, and so forth. One cannot say that <term type="ignore">god</term>s who have died are reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s
                        and that humans who have died are reborn as humans. Nor can one say that
                        virtue leads to the lower realms and that nonvirtue leads to higher status.
                        Many consciousnesses do not develop from one. Beings are not reborn as <term type="ignore">god</term>s without having practiced virtue, nor are they
                        reborn in the lower realms without having committed some nonvirtuous deeds.
                        Rebirth is not brought about through the actions of an external agent. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-111"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Let us suppose someone asks why these things are not the case. Here
                        is what we would reply. Someone might say about the analogy of a recitation
                        that it shows that one takes rebirth in the next life without the
                        consciousness of this life perishing. To eliminate this misinterpretation we
                        put forth the analogy of the seed. Indeed, if a sprout were to be produced
                        without the seed being destroyed, then the positions of those who accept
                        real selves would be right. However, the sprout is produced upon the
                        destruction of the seed—that is, from something that has changed from what it
                        was earlier on.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-112"/>
                    <p tid="83">“Someone might say about the analogy of the lamp that it shows that
                        the aggregates of this life and the next exist at one and the same time,
                        because when one lamp is lit from another they both exist at the same time. It
                        is in order to rule out this misinterpretation that we put forth the analogy
                        of echoing sound. An echo does not resound without a person having first
                        spoken and does not occur at the same time as that speech. So the aggregates
                        do not exist at the same time. <ref cRef="F.154.b" type="folio"/>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-207"/>
                    <p tid="84">“About the illustration of the mirror, it might be said that lame
                        people are born from lame people because of the similarity the mirror
                        illustrates. To refute such ideas we put forth the analogy of the magnifying
                        glass, for a magnifying glass gives rise to a fire from which it is
                        dissimilar.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-113"/>
                    <p tid="85">“Someone might say that the analogy of the stamp shows that dead
                            <term type="ignore">god</term>s are born as <term type="ignore">god</term>s and dead people as people. To rule this out we put forth
                        the analogy of a recitation: what illustrates the present life is the
                        teacher and what illustrates the next life is the student; as they are
                        different, the teacher is not the student, nor the student the teacher. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-208"/>
                    <p tid="86">“About the analogy of the magnifying glass, someone might say that
                        it is an illustration of dissimilarity and thus shows that virtue leads to
                        lower states and nonvirtue to higher states. To rule this out we put forth
                        the analogy of a lamp. A lamp does not give rise to something dissimilar to
                        a lamp, but rather to a lamp. Similarly, it is logical that virtue gives
                        rise to high status and nonvirtue to lower states. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-114"/>
                    <p tid="87">“As for the analogy of the seed, someone might say that it shows
                        that [many different] consciousnesses develop. To rule this out we put forth
                        the analogy of the stamp, for the image produced in the lump of clay is not
                        other than that of the stamp.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-209"/>
                    <p tid="88">“Because of the analogy of the sour taste, someone might say that
                        those who experience a history of birth as <term type="ignore">god</term>s
                        will always be born as <term type="ignore">god</term>s, in spite of doing no
                        virtue, and that those who experience a history of birth in the lower realms
                        will always be born in lower realms, though they have done no nonvirtue. To
                        refute this we put forth the illustration of the mirror, for just as a face
                        appears in a mirror as it is, so too the similar results of virtue and
                        nonvirtue would match [their respective causes] and it would thus be
                        contradictory to make them dissimilar. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-115"/>
                    <p tid="89">“Some might say, with regard to the analogy of echoing sound, that
                        echoes do not come about unless they are made by an external agent—that is,
                        unless someone shouts. And analogously, so it might be said, beings are not
                        born unless made by an external agent. To rule out that misinterpretation
                        we put forth the illustration of the sour taste. The point is that it is
                        those who have previously had the experience of eating or drinking something
                        who will later salivate when it is described, and likewise, it is because of
                        previously engaging in actions and afflictions that one will later take
                        rebirth.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-210"/>
                    <p tid="90">“O Great King, let it be known that such are the ways sentient
                        beings take birth, perish, and transmigrate from this life to the next.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-116"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="91">All the retinue <ref cRef="F.155.a" type="folio"/> then rejoiced and praised what
                        the Blessed One had said. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-211"/>
                    <trailer tid="92">Thus ends “<title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of the Teaching Regarding
                        Death and Transmigration</title>.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-212" index="49">The title given here at the end of the sūtra, in all Kangyurs, is <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’chi ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba bstan pa’i mdo</title>, and differs from the main title at the beginning. See <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-21"/> and <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-24"/>.</note>
                    </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="100">Colophon</head>
                    <p tid="93">The translation done at the time of the earlier dissemination of the
                        teaching has not been modified at all with revised terminology.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="101">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="102">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-118">
                        <abbr>A</abbr>
                        <expan>Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) of the Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-185">
                        <abbr>BDRC</abbr>
                        <expan>Buddhist Digital Resource Center (www.tbrc.org)</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-199">
                        <abbr>C</abbr>
                        <expan>Choné (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne</title>) Kangyur
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-182">
                        <abbr>C<hi rend="small-caps">ds</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>Choné Drakpa Shedrup, <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lho sgo’i cho ga’i
                                rgyas ’grel</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-117">
                        <abbr>D</abbr>
                        <expan>Degé (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</title>) Kangyur </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-190">
                        <abbr>K<hi rend="subscript">Y</hi>
                        </abbr>
                        <expan>Peking Yongle (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yung lo</title>) Kangyur
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-181">
                        <abbr>L</abbr>
                        <expan>Shelkar (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shel mkhar</title>) or “London” manuscript Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-183">
                        <abbr>MW</abbr>
                        <expan>M. Monier-Williams, <title xml:lang="en">Sanskrit-English
                                Dictionary</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-184">
                        <abbr>Negi</abbr>
                        <expan>J.S. Negi, <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit Dictionary</title>
                        </expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-072-008-180">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Stok Palace manuscript (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang bris ma</title>) Kangyur</expan>
                    </item>
                    </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="103">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="104">Source Texts in Tibetan</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-121">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥpatti­yathākāra­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>).
                        Toh 308, Degé Kangyur vol. 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios 145.b–155.a. Also
                        available online at <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W22084">BDRC</ref>, vol. W22084.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-124">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuṣpatti­yathākāra­paripṛcchā­sūtra</title>).
                        bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i
                        bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripiṭaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: Krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 72, pp. 408–29.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-122">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥyathābhūta­graha­sūtra</title>). Shel 294,
                        Shel Palace Kangyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shel mkhar bka’ ’gyur</title>, 
                        also known as the London manuscript Kangyur)
                        vol. 82 (mdo sde, ci), folios 247.b–262.b. Scanned from a rare
                        eighteenth century handwritten set of the Kangyur of Shel made available by
                        the Cultural History of the Western Himalaya Project (University of Vienna).
                        Also available online at <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W1PD127393">BDRC</ref>, vol. W1PD127393.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-123">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshe ’pho ba ji ltar ’gyur ba zhus pa’i mdo</title>
                            (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āyuḥyathābhūta­graha­sūtra</title>). Stok 284,
                        Stok Palace Kangyur (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ ’gyur stog pho brang bris
                            ma</title>). Leh: Smanrtsis shesrig dpemzod, 1980, vol. 86, pp. 511–37.
                        Also available online at <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W22083">BDRC</ref>, vol. W22083.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-119">Choné Drakpa Shedrup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">co ne grags pa bshad sgrub</foreign>). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lho sgo’i cho ga’i rgyas ’grel gzhan phan nyi
                            ’od</title>. In <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rje btsun grags pa bshad sgrub
                            kyi gsung ’bum (glog klad par ma)</title>, <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Collected Works by Geluk Master Chone Drakpa Shedrup
                        (1675-1748)</title>, vol. 13, 216–49. Taipei: The Corporate Body of the
                        Buddha Educational Foundation, 2010. Also available online 
                        at <ref target="https://www.tbrc.org/#!rid=W1KG13759">BDRC</ref>, vol.
                        W1KG13759.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-120">
                        <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title>. Edited by Ryōzaburō Sakaki.
                        2 volumes. Kyoto, 1916–1925. Reprint, Tokyo: Suzuki Research Foundation,
                        1962. Also available online at: <ref target="https://www2.hf.uio.no/polyglotta/index.php?page=volume&amp;vid=263">Thesaurus Literaturae Buddhicae</ref>. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-187">Butön Rinchen Drup (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bu ston rin 
                        chen grub</foreign>). <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi ’byung gnas gsung  rab rin po 
                            che’i gter mdzod</title>. In: gsung ’bum (zhol par ma/ ldi lir bskyar par brgyab pa), 
                        vol. 24 (ya), pp. 633–1055. New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1965–1971.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="105">Other Works</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-125">Bodewitz, H.W. “Yonder World in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Atharvaveda</title>.” <title xml:lang="en">Indo-Iranian
                            Journal</title> 42 (1999): 107–20.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-126">Damdul Namgyal, Geshé. <ref target="https://www.scribd.com/document/54737607/S%C5%AATRA-IN-RESPONSE-TO-A-QUERY-OVER-WHAT-HAPPENS-AFTER-DEATH-A-REVIEW">“Sūtra in Response to
                        a Query over What Happens After Death: A Review. Buddha’s response to a
                        number of questions over the issue of rebirth.”</ref> Unpublished draft on Scribd 
                        (accessed November 11, 2016).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-127">Doniger O’Flaherty, Wendy. “Karma and Rebirth
                        in the Vedas and Purāṇas.” In <title xml:lang="en">Karma and Rebirth in
                            Classical Indian Traditions</title>, edited by Wendy Doniger O’Flaherty,
                        3–37. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-128">Goldstein, Melvyn C. <title xml:lang="en">The
                            New Tibetan-English Dictionary of Modern Tibetan</title>. New Delhi:
                        Munshiram Manoharlal Publishers, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-129">Hopkins, Thomas J. “Hindu Views of Death and
                        Afterlife.” In <title xml:lang="en">Death and Afterlife: Perspectives of the
                            World Religions</title>, edited by H. Obayashi, 143–55. New York:
                        Greenwood Press, 1992.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-130">Jamison, Stephanie W., and Michael Witzel.
                        <title xml:lang="en">
                            <ref target="http://www.people.fas.harvard.edu/~witzel/vedica.pdf">Vedic 
                                Hinduism</ref>
                        </title>. 1992/2003 (accessed
                        September 5, 2016). A shortened version appeared in <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Study of Hinduism</title>, edited by A. Sharma, 65–113. Columbia, S.C.:
                        University of South Carolina Press, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-131">Knipe, David M. “Sapiṇḍīkaraṇa: The Hindu
                        Rite of Entry into Heaven.” In <title xml:lang="en">Religious Encounters
                            with Death. Insights from the History and Anthropology of
                            Religions</title>, edited by Frank Reynolds and Earle H. Waugh, 111–24.
                        Philadelphia: Pennsylvania State University Press, 1977. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-132">La Vallée Poussin, Louis de. <title xml:lang="fr">Mūlamadhyamakakārikās (Mādhyamikasūtras) de Nāgārjuna avec
                            la Prasannapadā Commentaire de Candrakīrti</title>. Originally published
                        in Saint Petersburg: Bibliotheca Buddhica IV, 1903–1913. Reprint, Osnabrück:
                        Biblio Verlag, 1970.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-133">Lamotte, Étienne. <title xml:lang="fr">Le
                            Traité de la grande vertu de sagesse de Nāgārjuna</title>. Tome I.
                        Louvain: Institut Orientaliste, 1949. Reprinted 1966.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-134">Malalasekera, G. P. <title xml:lang="en">Dictionary of Pāli Proper Names</title>. New Delhi: Munshiram
                        Manoharlal, 1983.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-135">May, Jacques. <title xml:lang="fr">Candrakīrti Prasannapadā Madhyamakavṛtti. Douze chapitres traduits du
                            sanscrit et du tibétain, accompagnés d’une introduction, de notes et
                            d’une édition critique de la version tibétaine</title>. Collection Jean
                        Przyluski, tome II. Paris: Adrien-Maisonneuve, 1959.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-136">Monier-Williams, M. <title xml:lang="en">A
                            Sanskrit-English Dictionary</title>. Reprint of 1899 edition. Oxford:
                        Oxford University Press, 1976.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-137">Namai, Chishō Mamoru. “Two aspects of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">para­loka­sādhana</title> in the Dharmakīrtian
                        Tradition.” In <title xml:lang="en">Studies in the Buddhist Epistemological
                            Tradition (Proceedings of the Second International Dharmakīrti
                            Conference, Vienna, June 11–16, 1989)</title>, edited by Ernst
                        Steinkellner, 227–41. Vienna: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der
                        Wissenschaften, 1991.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-138">Negi, J.S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit Dictionary</title>. 16 volumes. Sarnath, Varanasi:
                        Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies, 1993–2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-139">Renou, Louis, and Jean Filliozat. <title xml:lang="fr">L’Inde classique. Manuel des études indiennes</title>. 2
                        volumes. Paris: Librairie d’Amérique et d’Orient, Jean Maisonneuve,
                        1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-140">Sayers, Matthew R. <title xml:lang="en">Feeding the Dead: Ancestor Worship in Ancient India</title>. Oxford/New
                        York: Oxford University Press, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-141">Scherrer-Schaub, Cristina. “Enacting Words. A
                        Diplomatic Analysis of the Imperial Decrees (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">bkas bcad</foreign>) and their Application in the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">Sgra sbyor bam po gñis pa</foreign>
                        Tradition.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of
                            Buddhist Studies</title> 25, no. 1–2 (2002): 263–340.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-142">Shushan, Gregory. “Afterlife Conceptions in
                        the Vedas.” <title xml:lang="en">Religion Compass</title> 5/6 (2011):
                        202–13.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-143">Skilling, Peter. “ ‘Eight Appropriate Similes’
                            (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’Thun pa’i dpe brgyad</title>): Verse 5 of
                        Nāgārjuna’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pratītya­samutpāda­hṛdaya-kārikā</title> and the <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra on the Questions on how Transmigration Occurs</title>.” In <title xml:lang="fr">Mélanges offerts au Vénérable Thích Huyên-Vi à l’occasion
                            de son soixante-dixième anniversaire dirigés par Bhikkhu Tampalawela
                            Dhammaratana [et] Bhikkhu Pāsādika</title>, 251–60. Paris: Éditions
                        You-feng, Libraire Éditeur, 1997.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-008-144">Zhang Yisun et al. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Bod rgya tshig mdzod chen mo, Zang han da ci dian</title>. 3 volumes.
                        Beijing: Mi rigs dpe skrun khang, 1985.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-145">
                            <term>Blessed One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhagavat</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-146">
                            <term>heavens</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtho ris</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐོ་རིས།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svarga</term>
                            <term type="definition">The realms of <term type="ignore">god</term>s
                                according to Buddhism; in Vedism the blissful afterlife presided
                                over by Yama.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-147">
                            <term>actions that bring immediate retribution</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtshams med kyi las</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཚམས་མེད་ཀྱི་ལས།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ānantaryakarman</term>
                            <term type="definition">Matricide, parricide, killing an arhat, causing
                                a schism in the monastic order, and drawing a buddha’s blood with
                                malicious intention. These actions are said to result in immediate
                                birth in the hells.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-148">
                            <term>afflictive emotion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nyon mongs</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉོན་མོངས།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kleśa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-149">
                            <term>buddha-eye</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kyi spyan</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་ཀྱི་སྤྱན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhacakṣus</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the five “eyes,” or qualities of vision,
                                possessed by a buddha, viz., the eye made of flesh (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">māṃsacakṣus</foreign>), the divine
                                eye (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">divyacakṣus</foreign>),
                                the eye of insight (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñācakṣus</foreign>), the eye of Dharma (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dharmacakṣus</foreign>), and the
                                    <term type="ignore">buddha-eye</term>. The <term type="ignore">buddha-eye</term> is the omniscience seeing both how things are
                                ultimately and how they manifest in their variety.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-150">
                            <term>omniscient</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thams cad mkhyen pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐམས་ཅད་མཁྱེན་པ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun mkhyen</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་མཁྱེན།</term>
                            <!---->
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarvajña</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-151">
                            <term>demons</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ma yin pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མ་ཡིན་པ།</term>
                            <!---->
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amānuṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amanuṣya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally “the non-humans,” i.e., demonic
                                spirits.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-152">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                            <term type="definition">Here and very frequently in the canonical 
                                texts, a type of non-human, semi-divine celestial 
                                being or spirit. In a very few texts (but not this one), 
                                e.g. <title xml:lang="en">
                                    <ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/toh83.html">The 
                                    Questions of Bhadrapāla the Merchant</ref>
                                </title>, the term is also used to refer to the 
                                consciousness of a being between death and the next rebirth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-153">
                            <term>waved-leaf fig tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blag sha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བླག་ཤ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">plakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Monier-Williams s.v. plakṣa: “Ficus Infectoria
                                (a large and beautiful tree with small white fruit).”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-154">
                            <term>catechu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">seng ldeng</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེང་ལྡེང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khadira</term>
                            <term type="definition">Monier-Williams s.v. khadira: “Acacia <term type="ignore">Catechu</term> (having very hard wood, the resin
                                of which is used in medicine, called ‘<term type="ignore">Catechu</term>,’ ‘Khayar,’ ‘Terra japonica’).”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-155">
                            <term>gooseberry</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyu ru ra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱུ་རུ་ར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmalaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āmalakī</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Indian <term type="ignore">gooseberry</term>, or emblic myrobalan. The simile of an āmalakī in the
                                palm of one’s hand is used to illustrate yogic perception (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogipratyakṣa</foreign>) where the
                                clarity aspect (compared to a crystal) is emphasized. See, e.g.,
                                Dharmottara’s <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nyāyabindhuṭīkā</title> 1.11.
                                It is also used to illustrate omniscience, or seeing all aspects of
                                things, probably on the analogy of being able to see through the
                                semi-transparent skin of the berry into its interior
                                structure.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-156">
                            <term>caprice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gyi na</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྱི་ན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svecchā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-157">
                            <term>lamp</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar me</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མར་མེ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dīpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-158">
                            <term>revised terminology</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skad gsar chad</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐད་གསར་ཆད།</term>

                            <term type="definition">The ninth century revision and codification of
                                translational equivalents and procedure in Tibet. It was undertaken during
                                the reigns of Senalek (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sad na legs</foreign>, d. 815 <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>) and Ralpachen (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ral pa can</foreign>, r. 815–838) and resulted
                                in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvyutpatti</title> and <title xml:lang="en">Drajor Bampo Nyipa</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title>), the very
                                influential manuals of translation from Sanskrit to Tibetan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-160">
                            <term>ancient linguistic usage</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brda rnying</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྡ་རྙིང་།</term>

                            <term type="definition">Translational terminology used before the
                                revisions and codification of the ninth century.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-161">
                            <term>recitation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kha ton</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁ་ཏོན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svādhyāya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-162">
                            <term>stamp</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mudrā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A <term type="ignore">stamp</term>, signet, or
                                seal.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-163">
                            <term>mirror</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me long</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ལོང་།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">darpaṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-164">
                            <term>echoing sound</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ghoṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-165">
                            <term>magnifying glass</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">me shel</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མེ་ཤེལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">arkakānta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sūryakānta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Literally, a “sunstone” or “sun-crystal.”</term>
                            <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-18"/>.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">sūryakānta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-166">
                            <term>seed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa bon</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་བོན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bīja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-167">
                            <term>sour taste</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyur ba</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱུར་བ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">amla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-168">
                            <term>echo</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brag ca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲག་ཅ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pratiśrutkā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-213">
                            <term>external agent</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byed pa po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱེད་པ་པོ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kartṛ</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-214">
                            <term>Śramaṇa Gautama</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge sbyong gau ta ma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་སྦྱོང་གཽ་ཏ་མ།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śramaṇa Gautama</term>
                            <term type="definition">“The renunciant Gautama,” the name by 
                                which the Buddha might have been referred to prior to his 
                                enlightenment or by those who were not his followers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-169">
                            <term>Śākya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The clan from which the Buddha was
                                descended.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Śākyan</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-170">
                            <term>God</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang phyug</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཕྱུག</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">īśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">The lord of the world; the permanent, single
                                agent who created the universe; <term type="ignore">God</term> as
                                accepted by theistic brahmanical schools.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-171">
                            <term>Nandaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ byed</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བྱེད།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nandaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A member of the Śākya clan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-172">
                            <term>Desire</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dod sred</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འདོད་སྲེད།</term>

                            <term type="definition">A member of the Śākya clan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-173">
                            <term>Kaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ka ya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀ་ཡ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A member of the Śākya clan.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-174">
                            <term>Mahānāman</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ming chen</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིང་ཆེན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahānāman</term>
                            <term type="definition">A Śākyan cousin of the Buddha. See Malalasekera
                                s.v. Mahānāma, son of Amitodana.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-175">
                            <term>Śuddhodana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zas gtsang ma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟས་གཙང་མ།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śuddhodana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Buddha’s father, a Śākyan king.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-176">
                            <term>Nandaja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ skyes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་སྐྱེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nandaja</term>
                            <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-4"/>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-177">
                            <term>Devadatta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha sbyin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་སྦྱིན།</term>

                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Devadatta</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Śākyan cousin of the Buddha traditionally
                                depicted as eager for gain and jealous of the Buddha’s fame.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-178">
                            <term>Kapilavastu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ser skya’i grong khyer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སེར་སྐྱའི་གྲོང་ཁྱེར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kapilavastu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The city in the Śākyan kingdom where Gautama
                                Buddha grew up. It is located on the northern side of the Gangetic
                                plain near Lumbini.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-179">
                            <term>world of Death</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin gyi ’jig rten</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་གྱི་འཇིག་རྟེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yamaloka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Vedic afterlife presided over by the lord of
                                death, Yama, and inhabited by the ancestors (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pitṛ</foreign>).</term>
                            <term type="definition">See also <ptr target="#UT22084-072-008-6"/>.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">Yamaloka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-215">
                            <term>chiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāhasralokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A “thousandfold universe,” also called a “small chiliocosm” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāhasra­cūḍiko loka­dhātu</foreign>), consisting of a thousand worlds each made up of their own Mount Meru, four continents, sun, moon, and <term type="ignore">god</term> realms.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-216">
                            <term>dichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gnyis pa ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གཉིས་པ་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvisāhasra­lokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A “twice thousandfold universe,” i.e. a 
                                millionfold universe, sometimes called a “second-order midsized-chiliocosm” 
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dvitīya­madhyama­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</foreign>), 
                                consisting of a thousand chiliocosms (q.v.).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-008-217">
                            <term>trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po’i ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོའི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tri­sāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­lokadhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A “thrice thousandfold universe,” i.e. a 
                                billionfold universe, sometimes called a “third-order great chiliocosm” 
                                (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tṛtīya­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</foreign>), 
                                consisting of a billion worlds, i.e. a million chiliocosms (q.v.), or a thousand dichiliocosms (q.v.).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>