<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད་ཀྱི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on Impermanence</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en"/>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-27" role="translatorMain">
                    Translated by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division) 
                    <lb/>under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-182">Christian Bernert</author>
                <editor role="reviser" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-246">Vivian Paganuzzi</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.1 <date>2015</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-072-009"/>
                <date>2013-10-20</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh309" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 309</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios 155.a-155.b</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Surendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Zhang Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="2">
                        <start volume="72" page="311"/>
                        <end volume="72" page="312"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC14668"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC11980" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 05/02/2019 at 16:43:10 by laura</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- Contents
            Summary
            Acknowledgments
            Introduction
            The Translation
            The Sūtra on Impermanence
            Notes
            Bibliography-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="19">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-1"/>
                <p tid="1">In this brief sūtra, the Buddha reminds his followers of one of the principal characteristics of
                    saṃsāric existence: the reality of impermanence. The four things cherished most in this world, the Buddha
                    says—namely good health, youth, prosperity, and life—are all impermanent. He closes his teaching with a verse,
                    asking how beings, afflicted as they are by impermanence, can take delight in anything desirable, and
                    indirectly urging his disciples to practice the path of liberation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="20">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translation by the Sakya Pandita Translation Group (International Buddhist Academy Division,
                    Kathmandu). This sūtra was translated from the Tibetan into English by Christian Bernert and edited by Vivian
                    Paganuzzi.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="21">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-3"/>
                    <p tid="4"> This sūtra highlights one of the most fundamental teachings of the Buddha—recognizing the
                        impermanence (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anityatā</foreign>) of conditioned phenomena. The
                        fact that such phenomena are impermanent (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</foreign>) is
                        listed as the first of the three principal characteristics of existence, the other two being the
                        suffering, or unsatisfactoriness, of phenomena (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</foreign>),
                        and their no-self, or lack of an inherent substance (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</foreign>). It is the clear understanding of the reality of these facts of life that can
                        bring about a profound and essential change in a person’s worldview, marking the point of entry to the
                        path to liberation.<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-28">See <title xml:lang="en">The
                                Three Basic Facts of Existence</title> (The Wheel, Publication no. 186, 187) (details in
                            bibliography).</note> Impermanence is also one of the four seals of the Buddha’s teaching (comprising
                        these three characteristics of existence and a fourth principle, that nirvāṇa is peace), often described
                        as summarizing or epitomizing the Buddhadharma, and more particularly as the criteria that together enable
                        the variety of Buddhist philosophical views to be distinguished from non-Buddhist ones.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-29">See, for example, <title xml:lang="en">The Questions of the Nāga
                                King Sāgara</title> (Toh <ref target="UT22084-058-002.html">155</ref>). </note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="22">Sūtras on impermanence</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">The Tibetan canon contains two sūtras with the title <title xml:lang="en">Sūtra on Impermanence
                            </title>(<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title>), both found in the same section of
                        the Kangyur (mdo sde, Toh. 309 and 310). The sūtra translated here is the first, the shorter of the two.
                        Sūtras with equivalent titles are also found in other Buddhist canons, but their contents differ
                        substantially from the one translated here. The Chinese Tripiṭaka, for instance, contains two sūtras so
                        entitled (Taishō Nos. 801 and 759), and in the Samyutta Nikāya of the Pāli canon, the collection of
                        discourses grouped by themes, there are a number of different texts with the title <title xml:lang="en">Sutta on Impermanence</title> (P. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aniccasutta</title>).<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-30">For instance Samyutta Nikaya 22.45 and 46, and Samyutta Nikaya
                            36.9.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="23">Note on the translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">The content of this sūtra is rather straightforward and its interpretation does not pose any major
                        difficulties. One particular term, however, did present a problem of translation: the Tibetan <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa</foreign>, which commonly translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka / vivikta </foreign>and is usually related to concepts of
                        isolation and seclusion. Here it seems to refer more specifically to the act of picking something out,
                        separating it from other things and thus singling it out from them as special.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="24">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="25">The Sūtra on Impermanence</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <ref cRef="F.155.a"/>
                        <!--<modularPassage type="homage">-->Homage to all buddhas and bodhisattvas!<!--</modularPassage>-->
                    </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">Thus did I hear at one time. The Bhagavān was dwelling in Anāthapiṇḍada’s park, in the Jeta Grove
                        in Śrāvastī, along with a large monastic assembly. The Bhagavān addressed the monks as follows:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">“Monks, four things are appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, and highly
                        appreciated by everyone. What are those four? </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">“Monks, good health is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, and highly
                        appreciated by everyone. Good health, however, ends with sickness. Monks, sickness is neither appealing,
                        nor is it singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by anyone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">“Monks, youth is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, and highly appreciated by
                        everyone. Youth, however, ends with the aging of the body. Monks, the aging of the body is neither
                        appealing, nor is it singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by anyone.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">“Monks, prosperity is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, and highly
                        appreciated by everyone. Prosperity, however, ends with its decline. Monks, the decline of prosperity is
                        neither appealing, nor is it singled out, nor considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by
                        anyone. <ref cRef="F.155.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">“Monks, life is appealing, singled out, considered valuable, pleasant, and highly appreciated by
                        everyone. Life, however, ends in death. Monks, death is neither appealing, nor is it singled out,
                        considered valuable, pleasant, or highly appreciated by anyone.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-13"/>
                    <lb/>
                    <p tid="14">Thus spoke the Bhagavān, the Sugata, and having spoken the Teacher added these words:</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-14"/>
                    <lg tid="15">
                        <l>“Good health is impermanent, </l>
                        <l>Youth does not last. </l>
                        <l>Prosperity is impermanent, </l>
                        <l>And life, too, does not last. </l>
                        <l>How can beings, afflicted as they are by impermanence,</l>
                        <l>Take delight in desirable things like these?”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-15"/>
                    <p tid="16">When the Bhagavān had thus spoken, the monks rejoiced and praised his words. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="26">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-16"/>
                    <p tid="17"> This completes <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra on Impermanence</title>. </p>
                    <p tid="18">Translated and edited by the Indian scholar Surendrabodhi and the principal editor-translator, the
                        monk Zhang Yeshé Dé. It was then also reviewed and finalized in accordance with current language
                        reforms.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="27">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="28">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-009-17">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>).
                        Toh 309, Degé Kangyur vol. 72 (mdo sde, sa), folios 155a.2–155b.4. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-009-18">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid kyi mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anityatāsūtra</title>).
                        bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas
                        kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research
                        Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House),
                        2006–9, vol. 72, 434-436.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-009-19">Nyanaponika Thera (transl.).<title xml:lang="en"> Anicca Sutta:
                            Impermanent</title> (SN 36.9), translated from the Pali. <title xml:lang="en">Access to
                            Insight</title>, 30 June 2010, <ref target="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sn/sn36/sn36.009.nypo.html">www.accesstoinsight.org</ref> . Retrieved on 10 May 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-072-009-20">“The Three Basic Facts of Existence: I. Impermanence (Anicca), with a
                        preface by Nyanaponika Thera,” <title xml:lang="en">Access to Insight</title>, 2 December 2011, <ref target="http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/various/wheel186.html">www.accesstoinsight.org</ref> . Retrieved on 10 May 2013.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-21">
                            <term>three principal characteristics of existence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkar btags gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཀར་བཏགས་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">Impermanence, suffering, and no-self. They are called in Pāli <foreign xml:lang="Pi-Ltn">tilakkhaṇa</foreign>, the “three
                                characteristics,” a term that has no direct equivalent in the Sanskrit or Tibetan
                                literature; in Tibetan, these three factors are usually called the “three seals of the Buddha's
                                teaching” in parallel to the “four seals of the Buddha’s teaching,” q.v.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-22">
                            <term>impermanent</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་རྟག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anitya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-23">
                            <term>impermanence</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi rtag pa nyid </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་རྟག་པ་ཉིད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anityatā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-24">
                            <term>suffering</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdug bsngal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདུག་བསྔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">duḥkha</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">unsatisfactoriness</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-25">
                            <term>no-self</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bdag med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བདག་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">anātman</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">lack of an inherent substance</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-26">
                            <term>four seals of the Buddha’s teaching</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bka’ rtags kyi phyag rgya bzhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཀའ་རྟགས་ཀྱི་ཕྱག་རྒྱ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkar btags bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཀར་བཏགས་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">chos kyi sdom bzhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཆོས་ཀྱི་སྡོམ་བཞི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caturdharmoddāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">All conditioned phenomena are impermanent; all defilements are suffering; all
                                phenomena are without self; nirvāṇa is peace.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-072-009-27">
                            <term>singled out</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dben pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viveka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vivikta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>