<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">སྒྱུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་མོའི་རྒྱུད།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The ​Mahā­māyā Tantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་སྒྱུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་མོའི་རྒྱུད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud kyi rgyal po</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The King of Tantras, the Glorious ‌Mahāmāyā</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrī­mahā­māyā­tantra­rāja­nāma</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-61">Catherine Dalton</consultant>
                <editor role="reviser" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 2.1 <date>2013 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p type="tantricRestriction">
                        <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
                        restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                        translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                        or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-080-009"/>
                <date>2013-01-26</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh425" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 425</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 80 (rgyud ’bum, nga), folios 167.a–171.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jinavara</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Gö Lhetsé</author>
                    <location count-pages="9">
                        <start volume="80" page="335"/>
                        <end volume="80" page="343"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21412"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12129" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
                <!-- <section rid="O4JW3334JW814">rgyud 'bum/</section>
                    <provenance>Buddhist Literary Heritage Project</provenance>-->
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 13/02/2019 at 08:32:06 by admin</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--    		
           Contents
           Summary
           Acknowledgements
           Introduction
           The Translation
           The ‌Mahāmāyā Tantra
           The First Instruction
           The Second Instruction
           The Third Instruction
            
           Notes
           Bibliography
-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="121">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-1"/>
                <p tid="1">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>, named after its principal deity Mahāmāyā, is a
                    tantra of the Yoginītantra class in which Mahāmāyā presides over a maṇḍala populated primarily by yoginīs and
                    ḍākinīs. The practitioner engages the antinomian power of these beings through a threefold system of yoga
                    involving the visualization of the maṇḍala deities, the recitation of their mantras, and the direct experience
                    of absolute reality. As well as practices involving the manipulation of the body’s subtle energies, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> incorporates the transgressive practices that are the hallmark of
                    the earlier tantric systems such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>, specifically the
                    ingestion of sexual fluids and other polluting substances. The tantra promises the grace of Mahāmāyā in the
                    form of mundane and transcendent spiritual attainments to those who approach it with diligence and
                    devotion.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="122">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This text was translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee. The translation was prepared by
                    Ryan Damron with the assistance of Catherine Dalton, and was edited by Andreas Doctor.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="123">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>, named after its principal deity Mahāmāyā,
                        belongs to the class of Yoginītantras. According to the post-tenth-century classification scheme of the
                        Tibetan New Schools (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gsar ma</foreign>), the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> is categorized as a Mother tantra (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma rgyud</foreign>) among <term>Unexcelled Yoga tantra</term>s (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla na med pa’i rnal ’byor gyi rgyud</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> yoga­niruttara­tantra </foreign>). It earns this classification due both to the
                        importance placed on female divinities in the tantra’s maṇḍala and to its inclusion of practices focused
                        on the manipulation of the body’s subtle energies. In this tantra, Mahāmāyā presides over a maṇḍala
                        populated primarily by yoginīs and ḍākinīs, those semi-divine female figures known throughout South Asian
                        tantric traditions for the power they derive from being propitiated with blood, flesh, and sex. The
                        practitioner engages the antinomian power of these beings through a threefold system of yoga involving the
                        visualization of the maṇḍala deities, the recitation of their mantras, and the direct experience of
                        absolute reality. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> also incorporates the transgressive
                        practices that are the hallmark of earlier tantric systems such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>,<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-161">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> clearly postdates the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title> because of the instances of intertextuality indicated below in notes
                            3 and 51–55. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>, and similar works like the
                                <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­garbha­tantra</title> demonstrate significant iconographic and
                            ritual innovations over those works typically identified as Yoga‌ tantras, such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarva­tathāgata­tattva­saṃgraha</title>. Beginning in approximately the eighth
                            century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi>, the pacific and regal Vairocana was replaced at the center of tantric maṇḍalas by deities
                            associated with the vajra family, frequently in the wrathful form of Akṣobhya known as Heruka. This
                            shift is related to the introduction of transgressive practices and a wrathful, mortuary aesthetic
                            into the established structure of the Yoga‌ tantras, leading some Indian Buddhist commentators to
                            begin to refer to Mahāyoga, or “Great yoga,” tantras. In the later Tibetan doxographical schemes of
                            the New Schools these tantras would be identified as Father tantras (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">pha rgyud</foreign>), joining the yoginītantras in the class of Unexcelled Yoga
                            tantra (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoga­niruttara­tantra</foreign>). The yoginītantras
                            would build upon the framework of these tantras as they introduced their own unique iconographies and
                            practices.</note> specifically the ingestion of sexual fluids and other polluting substances. The
                        tantra promises the grace of Mahāmāyā in the form of mundane and transcendent spiritual attainments
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhi</foreign>) to those who approach it with diligence,
                        courage, and devotion.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Though it is difficult to pinpoint precisely when the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> first began to circulate within Buddhist tantric communities, the work rose to
                        prominence toward the end of the first millennium <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> as part of an efflorescence of new tantric material
                        associated with yoginīs, ḍākinīs, and other female divinities. The designation “yoginītantra” was
                        conferred on these texts precisely because of their incorporation of a more feminized vision of divinity
                        and power. Yoginītantras vary in style and content, ranging from somewhat disordered and obscure works
                        like the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakra­saṃvara­tantra</title> to refined and doctrinally coherent texts
                        such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāla­cakra­tantra</title>. With its distinct narrative style, focus
                        on the mundane spiritual attainments, and near total absence of clearly articulated Buddhist doctrine, the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> demonstrates a thematic and rhetorical similarity to
                        the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakra­saṃvara­tantra</title>, one of the earliest yoginītantras.<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-162">On the dating of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakra­saṃvara­tantra</title>, see Gray (2007) pp 11–14, and Sanderson (2009) pp 158–69.</note>
                        Additionally, considering instances of intertextuality with the earlier <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>,<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-163">Verses 3.12–14
                            of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> contain a number of close correspondences
                            with verses 12.52, 53, and 55 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>.</note> and
                        a seeming lack of awareness of more doctrinally and structurally developed yoginītantras such as the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hevajra­tantra</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kāla­cakra­tantra</title>, it is reasonable to assume that the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> was among the earlier of the yoginītantras, appearing in Buddhist tantric
                        circles in the late ninth or early tenth centuries. It had certainly gained enough popularity by the
                        eleventh century to draw the attention of the prominent monastic scholars of the period.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-5"/>
                    <p tid="6"> In India the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> probably circulated within both the
                        major monastic institutions and the communities surrounding charismatic tantric masters. Foremost among
                        the monastic scholars who commented on the text was Ratnākaraśānti,<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-164">Regarding Ratnākaraśānti’s dating, see Isaacson (2001) p 458, n 4.</note>
                        whose <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇavatīṭīkā</title> (<title xml:lang="en">A Commentary Endowed with
                            Qualities</title>) grounds the often enigmatic verses of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> in mainstream Buddhist philosophy, especially that of Yogācāra. Kṛṣṇavajra’s
                            commentary,<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-165">For the dating of Kṛṣṇavajra, see
                            Isaacson (2001) p 457, n 2.</note> the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantrasya vṛtti
                            smṛti</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Recollection: A Commentary on the Mahāmāyā Tantra</title>),
                        frequently cites the oral tradition, pointing to the body of unwritten instructions that present the
                        practical techniques almost completely absent in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>
                        itself. Contributions to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> corpus came from outside the
                        walls of the monastery as well. Kukkuripa and Kṛṣṇācārya, both of whom would eventually be counted among
                        the eighty-four <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāsiddhas</foreign>, composed practice liturgies
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhana</foreign>) for the tantra, while the siddhas Nāropa
                        and Kaṇha are said to have taught the tantra to Marpa, thus facilitating its transmission to Tibet.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-166">Tāranātha, F.3a.7–3b.6. Although there is no
                            definitive evidence, some assert that Kaṇha and Kṛṣnācārya are identical.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-6"/>
                    <p tid="7"> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> arrived in Tibet in the early eleventh century
                        as part of the second wave of Buddhist teachings to reach the Land of Snows. It appears to have entered
                        Tibet via two distinct lines of transmission, through Marpa Chökyi Lodrö and Gö Lhetsé. The lineage of Gö
                        Lhetsé, a prolific translator and important teacher of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>,<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-167">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">’gos lo tsa wa</foreign> (1988) pp 208–9.</note> appears to have died out,
                        though the translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> and the majority of its
                        associated texts preserved in the Kangyur and Tengyur are his. The converse is true of Marpa; if he ever
                        produced a translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>, it has been lost, and yet
                        it is his lineage, as passed through his disciple Ngoktön Chöku Dorjé (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rngog
                            ston chos sku rdo rje</foreign>, 1036–1102), that continues to be transmitted to this day. The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> also received a great deal of attention from the Tibetan
                        polymath Tāranātha (1575–1634), who composed two commentaries and a practice manual for it.<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-168">See <ptr target="#bibliography">bibliography</ptr>.</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="124">The Text</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> describes, in verses both terse and enigmatic,
                        the practices and attainments associated with the deity Mahāmāyā and her retinue of yoginīs. Yoginīs, and
                        their close counterparts the ḍākinīs, are renowned for their ability to grant mastery of temporal and
                        transcendent spiritual attainments to devoted and courageous practitioners who are willing to brave an
                        encounter with these often ferocious beings. In this tantra Mahāmāyā is invoked as the queen of ḍākinīs,
                        the queen of the yoginīs, and the supreme secret of these secret goddesses, making her the paramount
                        source of spiritual attainment. The tantra promises the accomplishment of such powers through the
                        visualization of its deities and their maṇḍalas, the manipulation of the body’s subtle energies and the
                        cultivation of the power of transgression through the ingestion of impure substances. And yet these
                        practices are only hinted at within the tantra itself; the specifics are reserved for initiates and are to
                        be spoken only by a lineage holder. Thus, as is the case with most tantras, this text is meant to be
                        practiced only after receiving initiation and instruction from a qualified master.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>’s three chapters and eighty-one verses depart
                        from the traditional narrative structure of Buddhist scripture. Buddhist tantras typically follow the
                        sūtra tradition by beginning with a formulaic introduction meant to establish the time, place, audience,
                        and above all the authority of a given scripture. This formula, which begins “Thus I have heard...”
                            (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">evaṃ mayā śrutaṃ</foreign>), is absent in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>, which begins instead with a perfunctory “Now...” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ataḥ</foreign>).<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-169">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakra­saṃvara­tantra</title> shares this abrupt beginning. For an
                            in-depth discussion of the implications of this style of introduction, see Gray (2007) pp
                            28–35.</note> This deviation is in part explained by the fact that this is not a discourse of the
                        Buddha, but rather a dialogue between two deities associated with the tantra. However, the lack of a
                        formal introduction leaves it unclear precisely who these deities are. The interlocutor appears to be none
                        other than Mahāmāyā herself; verse 1.25 invokes her by name as the recipient of the tantra’s instruction.
                        The speaker, however, is never explicitly identified within the text. Kṛṣṇavajra ventures a guess,
                        suggesting Vajraḍākinī as the source of the teaching.<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-170">S, F.108b, lines 6–7. His attribution is somewhat problematic as he
                            contradicts the tantra by stating that the recipient of the discourse is Buddhaḍākinī, not
                            Mahāmāyā.</note> Ratnākaraśānti takes a different approach and, instead of concerning himself with
                        identifying figures not explicitly named in the text, considers the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> to be derived from a much larger mythical compendium of tantras (which he
                        refrains from identifying).<note place="end" index="11" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-171">G, pp 2–4. </note> It
                        is in that collection, he declares, that one may find the traditional introduction that establishes the
                        important details of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>’s setting.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">From this abrupt beginning, the first chapter continues with several verses invoking Mahāmāyā’s
                        qualities and describing the powers acquired through her successful propitiation. Tantras centered upon
                        yoginīs and ḍākinīs, whether Buddhist or non-Buddhist, typically emphasize the attainment of mundane
                        powers over the transcendent; in this the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> is no different.
                        The yogī who masters the practices of Mahāmāyā will, the text promises, be able to magically influence and
                        attack others, acquire whatever he desires, fly through the sky, travel through other realms, become
                        invisible, possess the bodies of others, and become immortal. Compared to this comprehensive and
                        repetitive list of mundane attainments, the tantra makes only passing reference to the more altruistic and
                        transcendent attainments. Only once does the text mention that its attainments can be used to benefit
                        others (1.28), and only once does it explicitly announce that its practice can result in buddhahood
                        (3.25).</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-10"/>
                    <p tid="11">Following this exhaustive account of the attainments, the first chapter closes with a description
                        of a short sequence of visualization. The reader may be puzzled at this point to find that Mahāmāyā, who
                        had, up to this point, been invoked using explicitly feminine epithets, is suddenly referred to using
                        undeniably masculine terms. Though some suggest this is the tantra of a male deity with a feminine
                            name,<note place="end" index="12" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-172">English (2002) p 47.</note> Mahāmāyā
                            <emph>is</emph> a female deity, as the verses of invocation make clear—she is the great Queen
                        Mahāmāyā, the mother of the guhyakas, and the queen of yoginīs. She is consistently addressed using a
                        specifically feminine epithet, vidyā, that simultaneously invokes her status as the embodiment of
                        knowledge and as the female deity presiding over a maṇḍala. And yet here, and in the third chapter where
                        her iconography is fully described, she becomes the male Heruka, the Virile One (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīra</foreign>) embracing the consort Buddhaḍākinī. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">This gender ambiguity is clarified when we consider that the tantra describes Mahāmāyā as a
                        feminized form of absolute reality. She is said to pervade everything in the three worlds, to be the
                        source of all the gods, and to create, sustain, and destroy the universe. Most importantly, she is exactly
                        what her name suggests, the “great illusion” that constitutes apparent reality. When she takes embodiment,
                        she can do so in any form necessary, which in the context of this tantra is Heruka, the male deity most
                        frequently found at the center of tantric maṇḍalas. Ratnākaraśānti makes explicit the ontological primacy
                        of the feminine Mahāmāyā; in his commentary he equates her with Vajradhara, the embodiment of absolute
                        reality, who is typically male, and identifies her as “she who has the form of Heruka.”<note place="end" index="13" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-173">G, p 6: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saiṣeti
                                heruka­rupā Mahā­māyā</foreign>. Elsewhere [G, p 20] Ratnākaraśānti identifies Mahāmāyā as the
                            fundamental identity of both the male Heruka and his consort, Buddhaḍākinī. He writes, “The lord of
                            the maṇḍala is the glorious Heruka, who is Mahāmāyā; the vidyā Buddhaḍākinī is also Mahāmāyā because
                            they both possess a singular intrinsic nature” (<foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">maṇḍalādhipatiḥ śrī­heruko mahā­māyā, tadvidyā api buddha­ḍākinī mahā­māyā tayoḥ
                                eka­svabhāvatvāt</foreign>).</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-12"/>
                    <p tid="13">The second chapter is the tantra’s shortest and most challenging. Its verses only hint at the
                        techniques and visualizations to which they refer. The communities in which the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title> circulated would have guarded their teachings and techniques closely, making
                        complete explanations accessible only to an intimate circle of initiates. The tantra’s verses—especially
                        those that appear to refer to specific techniques—are not meant to be edifying, only allusive. It is the
                        role of the tantric master to unpack each verse and convey its practical content to those prepared to
                        receive it. Thus in this chapter we are offered only the barest of introductions to what was likely a
                        complex sequence of techniques.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-13"/>
                    <p tid="14">The fifth verse of the second chapter introduces the primary structure of the tantra’s practices,
                        one the later Tibetan commentators would identify as a framework for the development stage and completion
                        stage practices unique to the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>.<note place="end" index="14" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-174">See particularly Jamgön Kongtrul (2008) pp 69–70 and 183–86.
                            He writes: “The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā</title> and other tantras set forth the threefold
                            [formulation consisting of] appearance, mantra and reality [yogas]. These three apply to both path and
                            result; and within the path itself, to both the creation phase and completion phase.” (We have emended
                            “shape” to “appearance” to conform with the terminology used in this translation.) Though the concepts
                            of the development and completion stages were present in the Indian Buddhist tantric tradition, they
                            never reached the degree of uniformity there that they did in the Tibetan tradition. The terms appear
                            nowhere in the commentarial literature of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                            Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>.</note> Verse 2.5 states:</p>
                    <!-- <p style="quote"> -->
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="15">
                            <l>The threefold practice is said to be essentially mantra, appearance, and reality.</l>
                            <l>Through three aspects of wisdom he will not be stained by the faults of existence.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <!-- </p> -->
                    <p tid="16"> Kṛṣṇavajra provides the necessary elaboration:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="17">
                            <emph>Mantra</emph> refers to those mantras such as <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign> and so forth that are fixed in the six places, the eyes and the rest.
                                <emph>Appearance</emph> refers to the [deity’s] manner of appearance as explained below—his color,
                            form, posture and faces. <emph>Reality</emph> refers to the fundamental nature which is completely
                            free from all conceptual fabrication.<note place="end" index="15" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-175">S,
                                F.109b.3–4: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngags zhes bya ba ni mig la sogs pa’i gnas drug tu bkod
                                    pa’i oṁ la sogs pa’i sngags so / dbyibs zhes bya ba ni og gnas ’byung ba’i tshul dang / mdog
                                    dang dbyibs dang phyag dang zhal gyi bdag nyid can no / chos zhes bya ba ni kun brtags pa
                                    thams cad las rnam par grol ba’i rang bzhin nyid do.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="18">The visualizations, recitations, and sequences of practice that follow in the text are to be
                        understood and employed in terms of this threefold structure.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-14"/>
                    <p tid="19">The remainder of the chapter presents a series of practical techniques for attaining mastery over
                        the phenomenal world and generating bodily energies and fluids for use in ritual practice. Each verse from
                        2.7 to 2.14 alludes to a specific visualization centered on a single mantric syllable and its associated
                        deity, the practice of which leads to the stated outcome. Yet it is impossible to determine, based on the
                        verses alone, what practices are being described. It is left to the commentators and the oral tradition to
                        fill in the detail. Consider verse 2.7:</p>
                    <!-- <p style="quote"> -->
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="20">
                            <l>Meditate upon the first syllable which is the color of Indra.</l>
                            <l>Merged fully with one’s own awareness it is summoned in an instant.</l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <!-- </p> -->
                    <p tid="21"> Ratnākaraśānti comments:</p>
                    <q>
                        <p tid="22">This is explained as follows: once the vulva of Buddhaḍākinī and so forth is rendered red like
                            saffron, imagine the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign> red like saffron
                            in the vessel of the Virile One and fix the Virile One in the subtle sphere. Once the Virile One has
                            been made red by the light of the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign>, two
                            rays of red light emerge from the Virile One. Imagine a noose on the tip of the first and a hook on
                            the second. Binding the neck of the object to be accomplished with the noose and piercing its heart
                            with the hook, imagine that it is quickly summoned.<note place="end" index="16" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-176">G, p 28: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">etaduktaṃ bhavati
                                    buddha­ḍākinyādi­yogaṃ kuṅkumāruṇaṃ kṛtvā vīrabhājane kuṅkumāruṇaṃ praṇavaṃ vicintya tadbindau
                                    vīraṃ vinasya praṇa­varaśmi­bhirvīra­maruṇī­kṛtya vīrā­daruṇaraśmi­rekhādvayaṃ niḥsārya ekasyā
                                    agre pāśaṃ dvitīyasyā aṅkuśaṃ vicintayet / sādhyaṃ pāśena kaṇḍe baddhvā aṅkuśena hṛdi viddhvā
                                    kṣipramākṛṣymāṇaṃ vicintayet.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </p>
                    </q>
                    <p tid="23">It thus becomes apparent that the words of the tantra itself provide merely an outline, a
                        shorthand version for tantric practitioners already well versed in its practices. Likewise, each of the
                        subsequent verses of this chapter points to complex meditation techniques, a type of knowledge that is, as
                        verse 2.17 indicates, “secret, obscure, and unwritten.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-15"/>
                    <p tid="24">The third and final chapter brings the tantra to a close with a description of the rites for
                        preparing and consuming impure substances, followed by a complete presentation of the iconography of
                        Mahāmāyā and her retinue. The cultivation of the power of transgression through deliberate consumption of
                        impure, polluting substances is an important aspect of Buddhist tantra. Notions of purity and pollution
                        have been formative elements of South Asian identity since Vedic times. Such an identity is destabilized
                        through contact with and ingestion of impure substances and bodily fluids. Indian Buddhist tantras,
                        especially those of the later <term type="ignore">Yoga</term> tantra class such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>,<note place="end" index="17" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-177">On the ingestion of sexual fluids in these tantras, see Dalton (2004) pp
                            14–17.</note> positioned the consumption of sexual fluids at the climax of the ritual process so as to
                        harness the force of the transgressive act into a powerful soteriological moment. The same holds true for
                        the ingestion of illicit meats: their ritual consumption negated a social identity formed through the
                        observation of dietary and behavioral proscriptions. Through the eating of taboo substances,
                        practitioners’ bonds with mundane society are fully severed and their acceptance into the community of
                        spiritual adepts is confirmed.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-16"/>
                    <p tid="25">Yoginītantras, including the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>, carried on the
                        transgressive practices that developed in tantras such as the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­garbha­tantra</title>. In the
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</foreign>, the consumption of sexual fluids is presented
                        at the end of the second chapter and the ingestion of illicit meats in the early verses of the third. The
                        final two verses of the second chapter describe, in a typically occluded fashion, the ingestion of sexual
                        fluids that marks the culmination of the meditation sequence. The verses instruct the yogī to keep his
                        mind free of concepts and take the “wish-granting jewel” between his thumb and ring finger and place it in
                        his mouth. Kṛṣṇavajra explains that this refers to the ingestion of “relative <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</foreign>” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun rdzob kyi byang
                            chub sems</foreign>, i.e. semen) after its prolonged retention in the tip of the penis.<note place="end" index="18" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-178">S, F.213a.</note> In the parlance of the later
                        tradition, this marks the completion stage section of the practice. In the words of the tantra itself, the
                        ingestion of sexual fluids triggers “everlasting spiritual attainment.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-17"/>
                    <p tid="26">Moving into the third chapter, the tantra introduces a sequence of verses outlining the rites
                        associated with the ingestion of sacramental substances. The yogī is instructed to gather the five illicit
                        meats (elephant, horse, cow, dog, and human), roll them individually into pellets, and store them for
                        seven days. Next they are mixed together and stored in the cavity of a rotting jackal for an additional
                        seven days. Finally they are taken out and consumed, resulting in an experience of “the great fruitions”
                            (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāphalāni</foreign>, 3.6), which Ratnākaraśānti identifies
                        as “the state of wisdom.”<note place="end" index="19" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-179">G, p 37: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahāphalāni tāni jñātvetyarthaḥ</foreign>.</note> Though the five illicit meats
                        are common enough in tantric literature, the especially polluting addition of a jackal corpse appears to
                        be a unique contribution of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>. We can understand this
                        distinctly unpalatable process as intended to collapse the binaries of pure and impure, precipitating a
                        more complete rejection of dualistic concepts and, as verse 3.1 states, leading to “omniscience.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-18"/>
                    <p tid="27">The final section of the tantra concerns the method of practice, the sādhana, for the deity,
                        including the details of the visualization of Mahāmāyā and her maṇḍala. The stages by which a tantra is to
                        be practiced are frequently concealed within the text—the order will be scrambled and the details
                            elided.<note place="end" index="20" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-180">We thank Jacob Dalton for bringing
                            this technique of concealment to our attention.</note> The act of organizing these elements is left to
                        tantric teachers and lineage masters, who composed independent ancillary texts to codify the proper
                        sequence of practice. These texts incorporated practices drawn from the oral tradition and embedded the
                        basic outline provided by the tantra within an established sādhana framework that normally included common
                        Buddhist elements such as refuge in the Three Jewels, the generation of the aspiration for awakening, the
                        offering of confession, and so forth. Thus while the core material for a sādhana is found within the
                        tantra itself, each sādhana is unique, reflecting styles and interpretations that are as diverse as their
                        authors. Sādhanas composed on the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</foreign> by the Indian
                        authors Ratnākaraśānti, Kukkuripa, Ratnavajra, and Kumé Dorjé (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sku
                            med rdo rje</foreign>), as well as a number composed by Tibetan authors, have been preserved in
                        Sanskrit and Tibetan.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-19"/>
                    <p tid="28">Within the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>, although verse 3.7 announces the
                        commencement of the sādhana, the majority of practices have already been introduced in the preceding two
                        chapters. But it is only here, at the end of the tantra, that we are finally given the complete
                        iconographic description required for the self-visualization of the deity that precedes all other
                            practices.<note place="end" index="21" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-181">The description that follows
                            organizes the sequence of visualization following the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhana</foreign> composed by Ratnākaraśānti as preserved in the SM.</note> The visualization
                        begins by imagining a red lotus flower with four petals, in the middle of which sits a single subtle
                        sphere. From this sphere, four additional subtle spheres emerge and come to rest on each of the four
                        petals. These four spheres then transform into four yoginīs, each distinct in color and wielding the
                        specific implements described in the tantra. They sing a song of invocation in the language of the yoginīs
                            <note place="end" index="22" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-182">The fact that the language of the yoginīs’
                            song (3.21) is different from that of the root verses is entirely lost in the Tibetan translation.
                            Ratnākaraśānti's <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhana</foreign> preserves the original,
                            which is composed in a form of Prākrit distinct from the rest of the Sanskrit verses.</note> to the
                        central subtle sphere, summoning Mahāmāyā and consort from their essential state, first in the form of
                        mantra syllables, then in full iconographic detail. Mahāmāyā takes the dark blue form of Heruka embracing
                        the red Buddhaḍākinī. (S)he has four faces—blue in the east, yellow in the south, red in the west, and
                        blue-green in the north. (S)he has four hands, each holding a different implement: a skull cup, a
                        khaṭvāṅga, a bow, and an arrow.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-20"/>
                    <p tid="29">Once this five-deity maṇḍala has been fully imagined, the practitioner is prepared to apply any of
                        the diverse practices that have been described throughout the work: the visualization of mantra syllables
                        and additional maṇḍala deities, the manipulation of subtle energies, or the consumption of sexual fluids
                        and illicit meats. Through identification with Mahāmāyā and engagement in these potent practices, the
                        diligent practitioner will be rewarded with mundane powers, reach “highest attainment of suchness” (3.25),
                        and, as we are told in the tantra’s final verse, be forever protected by Mahāmāyā, “the queen of the
                        yoginīs.”</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="125">About the Translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-21"/>
                    <p tid="30">This translation is based upon a comparative edition, made by the translators, of the Tibetan
                        recensions of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> drawn from the Degé (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sde dge</title>), Lhasa, Narthang (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snar thang</title>),
                        Peking, and Stok Palace (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stog pho brang</title>) editions of the Tibetan Kangyur.
                        Though the tantra itself no longer exists in Sanskrit, Ratnākaraśānti’s important commentary, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇavatīṭīkā</title>, is preserved in two Sanskrit manuscripts held in Nepal’s Royal
                        Archive, which have been edited by the Central Institute of Higher Tibetan Studies. Because the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇavatīṭīkā</title> attests to the majority of the Sanskrit terms, it allows access
                        to much of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> in its original language. We have
                        therefore given careful consideration to both the Sanskrit edition of this commentary and the manuscripts
                        upon which it is based. Where the Sanskrit term is available, we have privileged the semantic range of the
                        Sanskrit over that of the Tibetan, allowing us to recapture something of the flavor of the original
                        Sanskrit. The commentaries of Ratnākaraśānti and Kṛṣṇavajra were consulted throughout the translation
                        process and greatly influenced our reading of the root text.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-22"/>
                    <p tid="31">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> is a challenging text. It is thematically
                        inconsistent and disjunctive in places, and at times the referent of a given verse is unclear. Though this
                        is certainly due in part to attempts by its authors to conceal the meaning or proper sequence of the
                        tantra, it is clear that a grammatically flawed work is hiding behind the Tibetan translation. This is
                        common among Buddhist tantras, as their authors did not always possess a solid command of the Sanskrit
                        language. Where possible we have clarified the text to make it more readable, but there remain passages
                        that are enigmatic and difficult to follow.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="126">Note</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-23"/>
                    <p tid="32">In the translation, the numbers within square brackets preceded by F. indicate the folio numbers
                        of the Degé edition of the Tibetan; the numbers without letters indicate the page numbers of the <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title> (comparative) edition of the Tibetan (see bibliography). </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="127"> The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="128">The King of Tantras, the Glorious Mahāmāyā </head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="129">Chapter 1</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="130">The First Instruction</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-24"/>
                    <p tid="33">
                        <ref cRef="F.167.a"/> Homage to the Glorious Vajraḍākinī!</p>
                    <lg tid="34">
                        <l>I pay homage to the protector of beings, Glorious Vajraḍākinī,</l>
                        <l>Universal sovereign of the ḍākinīs, the very essence of the five wisdoms and three bodies.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-25"/>
                    <lg tid="35">
                        <l>I pay homage to all the vajraḍākinīs</l>
                        <l>Who cut the bonds of conceptual thought and descend to act in the world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-26"/>
                    <lg tid="36">
                        <l>Now, following that, I will explain the tantra called <title xml:lang="en">The Supreme Secret of the
                                Secret Goddesses, the Vajraḍākinīs</title>. <ref cRef="F.167.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-27"/>
                    <lg tid="37">
                        <l>She pervades the entire Egg of Brahmā, the animate and inanimate.</l>
                        <l>She is the source of all goddesses and rules over Brahmā and the rest.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-28"/>
                    <lg tid="38">
                        <l>She is their great secret, the great Queen Mahāmāyā.</l>
                        <l>She is the great illusion, intensely fierce, who destroys all that exists.<note place="end" index="23" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-183">“Who destroys all that exists:” this translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta­saṃhāra­kāriṇī</foreign> (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung ba yang dag sdud mdzad ma</foreign>). We have pushed the translation
                                toward the more extreme end of the term’s semantic range in a nod to Ratnākaraśānti, who glosses
                                the term with (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pralayakartī</foreign>), “she who causes
                                annihilation.” [G, p 5] This refers to the dissolution of the universe that comes at the end of
                                the cosmogonic stages of emanation, absorption and dissolution of the universe that are standard
                                in Brahmanical cosmology.</note> [507]</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-29"/>
                    <lg tid="39">
                        <l>She pervades all of this: the animate and inanimate, the three worlds.</l>
                        <l>Time after time she gathers in and again emanates the triple world.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-30"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>This mother of the guhyakas is celebrated as the essence of illusion.</l>
                        <l>She is the knowledge that perfects the three worlds and fulfills all desires.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-31"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>Through the mere thought of the queen of the accomplished, knowledge itself,</l>
                        <l>The devas, dānavas, gandharvas, yakṣas, āsuras, and humans,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-32"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>The vidyādharas, the kinnaras, and mahodaras,</l>
                        <l>The rākṣasas and piśācas—all are mastered for practitioners.</l>
                        <l>All creatures are subdued: those born in the water and on land.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-33"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>Phenomena are naturally luminous; they are primordially pure and without stain.</l>
                        <l>The methods of those possessing the self-arisen five wisdoms are to be praised;<note place="end" index="24" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-184">“Are to be praised:” here we have followed the Sanskrit
                                attested by Ratnākaraśānti which is quite different from the Tibetan translation: the methods
                                (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">upāyāḥ</foreign>) of those who are endowed with the
                                five wisdoms (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañca­jñānināṃ</foreign>) are to be
                                praised (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pragīyante</foreign>) [G, pp 9-10]. This is
                                an interesting verse as it seems thematically disjuntive with the preceding and subsequent lines
                                and may have been inserted here by a later redactor. Krṣṇavajra, who is otherwise attentive to
                                every verse, does not acknowledge it at all. Ratnākaraśānti, on the other hand, uses this verse as
                                the basis for an extensive discourse linking into Yogācāra philsophy.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-34"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>These are the yoginīs, the mother of yoga, and the entirety of the three worlds.<note place="end" index="25" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-185"> Ratnākaraśānti identifies the yoginī, mother of yoga
                                (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogamātā</foreign>), and the entirety of the three
                                worlds (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">traidhātukaṃ aśeṣataḥ</foreign>) as the
                                praiseworthy methods of the previous verse [G, p 10].</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>The entire play of illusion is accomplished without exclusion or remainder.<note place="end" index="26" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-186">The second line of this verse begins a new sequence of verses that
                                indentify the accomplishments that will come to the yogī who successfully accomplishes the
                                practices of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Mahā­māyā Tantra</title>. It concludes in verse
                                1.15.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-35"/>
                    <lg tid="45">
                        <l>Abducted from the buddhas, the maidens of the highest gods are enjoyed.</l>
                        <l>The yogī has knowledge, masters yoga and weaves Indra’s Web.<note place="end" index="27" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-187">“Weaves Indra’s Web:” this translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indrav­jālaṃ karoti</foreign>, which is rendered as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig ’phrul byed</foreign> in the Tibetan.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-36"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>He beguiles and paralyzes, slays, dissuades, and more.</l>
                        <l>He tames, magnetizes, and so forth; he flies through the sky.</l>
                        <l>He enters the citadel of another, is invisible, and so on.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-37"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>He causes hostility, renders mute and moves under the earth;</l>
                        <l>Becomes the universal sovereign of vidyādharas, does not age, and is deathless.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-38"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>One with <term type="ignore">knowledge</term> of yogic illusion is likewise free from disease—</l>
                        <l>Yogīs revel in the form of the mantra’s syllables. <ref cRef="F.168.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-39"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>Through recitation and contemplation, meditation and absorption, [508]</l>
                        <l>The vidyā created through recitation brings about the accomplishment of knowledge.<note place="end" index="28" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-188">The Sanskrit term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">
                                    vidyā </foreign> (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa</foreign>) appears twice
                                in this verse with different connotations. According to Ratnākaraśānti, the first instance is as
                                the techinical term for the central female deity of the maṇḍala, Mahāmāyā, and has therefore been
                                left untranslated. The second instance is in specific reference to the <term type="ignore">knowledge</term> (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prajñā</foreign>) that arises from meditation and has here been
                                translated as <term type="ignore">knowledge</term> [G, p 13].</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-40"/>
                    <lg tid="50">
                        <l>Without discipline or austerities, without hardship, fasting, or vows,</l>
                        <l>Bliss and Joy bring accomplishment through constancy in knowledge and method.<note place="end" index="29" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-189">The Tibetan translation adds an additional <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtag tu</foreign>, meaning “constant,” which is not attested in
                                any of the commentaries. Because it appears to be largely redundant, it has been omitted
                                here.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-41"/>
                    <lg tid="51">
                        <l>The Virile One stands in the center of the navel, in the hidden space of the blossom;</l>
                        <l>He is mind, the absence of mind, and mental form—the nature of knowledge and what can be known.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-42"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>I will now describe him—this is the profound instruction of the Buddha:</l>
                        <l>A chain equal to that of the āli kāli is coiled there.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-43"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>The upper chain ignites and is made to flow downward,</l>
                        <l>A drop of nectar flowing in the form of semen.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-44"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>Whatever comes on the path of the senses is naturally just that.</l>
                        <l>Through the practice of supreme benefit all becomes the nature of the Buddha.<note place="end" index="30" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-190">This verse is complicated by two substantial variants.
                                Where the Tibetan translation reads “practice of supreme benefit” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog tu phan pa</foreign>), Ratnākaraśānti reads “practice of supreme
                                settling” (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">paramāhita</foreign> / Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog tu bzhag pa</foreign>) [G, p 19]. The similarity of the
                                Sanskrit terms for supreme benefit (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parama hita</foreign>)
                                and for supreme settling (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">parama āhita</foreign>)
                                probably led to a scribal error resulting in different versions of the verse. Because the version
                                found in the Tibetan translation is attested in Kṛṣṇavajra’s commentary, it was followed here,
                                though Ratnākaraśānti’s reading seems clearer. Where the Tibetan translation reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas kun gyi rang bzhin ’bab</foreign> (“become the
                                nature of all Buddhas”), Kṛṣṇavajra reads <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas rang
                                    bzhin thams cad ’gyur</foreign> (“everything becomes the nature of the Buddha”) [S, F.206b]
                                which is in agreement with the Sanskrit attested by Ratnākaraśānti and which is followed
                                here.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-45"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>The spiritual attainment of the great commitment is the perfection of the great pill.<note place="end" index="31" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-191"> Ratnākaraśānti and Kṛṣṇavajra are unanimous in
                                identifying the spiritual attainment of the great commitment with the perfection of the great
                                pill. This relationship is not clear in the Tibetan translation. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>In the embrace of Mahāmāyā you should practice yogic union.<note place="end" index="32" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-192">“Mahāmāyā:” though the Tibetan verse reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyu ’phrul chen po</foreign> here, Ratnākaraśānti attests to <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā</title> [G, p 20].</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-46"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>Endowed with the five offerings together with the five objects of desire,</l>
                        <l>The power of accomplishment will be known and spiritual attainment made permanent.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-47"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>I will explain this spiritual attainment of wisdom,</l>
                        <l>By which the state of a god is swiftly attained—Goddess, I speak truthfully!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-48"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>To you, Mahāmāyā, I will explain the accomplishment of the three worlds,</l>
                        <l>The garland of syllables of the most excellent among the great yoginīs.<note place="end" index="33" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-193">This verse appears to be slightly different in the recension of the
                                tantra used by Ratnākaraśānti. A tentative prose reconstruction would read: “To you (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tvām</foreign>), the vidyā Mahāmāyā who is the means for
                                accomplishing the three worlds (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā­māyāṃ vidyāṃ
                                    trailokya­sādhanīṃ</foreign>) I will explain (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tad ahaṃ
                                    vakṣyāmi</foreign>) the Vīra, the most excellent among the great yogīs (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā­yoginām divyam</foreign>) along with the garland of
                                syllables (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">akṣarapaṅktibhiḥ</foreign>).” [G, p 21].
                            </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-49"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>The great yogī who masters the animate and inanimate with thought alone</l>
                        <l>Is constantly offered desirable things and served according to his pleasure.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-50"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>He is always at play and accomplishes the vajra yoginīs. [509]</l>
                        <l>In a variety of forms the essential practice is revealed. <ref cRef="F.168.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-51"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>The great attainment, the splendor of the tathāgatas, is granted;<note place="end" index="34" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-194">Tathāgatas, or “thus-gone ones” here: where the Tibetan translation
                                reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">de bzhin gshegs pa kun</foreign>, Ratnākaraśānti
                                attests to the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tāthāgātī</foreign>, a feminine
                                derivative adjective formed from <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tathāgata</foreign> [G, p
                                22]. In his reading the term is in the singular. Thus in at least one recension of the text the
                                line would read “the splendor of the thus-gone lady.”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Through extracting various essences the yogī constantly benefits beings.<note place="end" index="35" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-195"> Kṛṣṇavajra reads a different line here. In the recension of the root
                                text available to him, the final line of the text as translated in Tibetan is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gar ni thugs rjes bsams bzhin mdzad</foreign> (“He dances with compassion
                                according to his whim”) [S, F.208a].</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-52"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>With the collected semen, liquor, and extracted large pill,</l>
                        <l>He mixes in the great flesh and unites with the yoginī.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-53"/>
                    <lg tid="63">
                        <l>He gains long life, great virility,<note place="end" index="36" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-196">“Virility:” translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīrya</foreign> and
                                the Tibetan <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brtson ’grus</foreign>.</note> great splendor,
                            and becomes exceedingly powerful; </l>
                        <l>He possesses divine sight, magical ability, and drinks the moon day after day;</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-54"/>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l>He becomes long-lived so that he lives for a great age;</l>
                        <l>He manifests an alluring form and conjures miracles;</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-55"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>With merely a thought his appearance is transformed— </l>
                        <l>The queen of vidyās, the great enchantress, is unfailingly accomplished through recitation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-56"/>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l> Vidyā! In the three worlds there is nothing equal to my knowledge.<note place="end" index="37" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-197">There are a couple of noteworthy variants of this verse found in
                                commentarial works. The version from the Degé edition translated here, which is supported in
                                Kṛṣṇavajra’s commentary, reads: “Vidyā! In the three worlds (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten gsum po na</foreign>) there is nothing equal to my knowledge (Tib:
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nga yi rig dang mnyam pa med</foreign>).” The recension
                                of the tantra used by Ratnākaraśānti appears to have, instead, “there is nothing (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāsti</foreign>) like you (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">te sadṛśī</foreign>) in the triple worlds (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">triṣu lokeṣu</foreign>)” [G, p 21]. Taranātha attests to yet another
                                variation. In his <title xml:lang="en">Lamp of Suchness</title> [F.2b] he cites the same line as
                                “Vidyā! In the three worlds there is nothing like you apart from me” (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa ’jig rten gsum po na / khyod dang mnyams pa nga las
                                med</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>This transmission of all tantras has been explained to you, Magnificent One!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <trailer tid="118">This completes the first instruction on the signs of spiritual attainment of <title xml:lang="en">The Great Vidyā, Queen of the Yoginīs</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="131">Chapter 2</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="132">The Second Instruction</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-57"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>Now, following that, I will explain the sublime secret syllable that bestows the result of the
                            spiritual attainment for the practice of the great queens of yoga.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-58"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>Merely visualizing her, the yoginī grants the best of things.</l>
                        <l>Apply the first syllable and sustain the upward breath.<note place="end" index="38" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-198">“Sustain the upward breath:” this translates the Sanskrit <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ucvāsasam kurute</foreign>, which is rendered in the Tibetan
                                translation as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbug gtang bar bya</foreign>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-59"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>Taking that which comes at the end of the eight together with <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ū</foreign> and the bindu,</l>
                        <l>The yogī moves the downward breath, abandoning the real and unreal. [510]</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-60"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l>The observances are not explained: the activities of the garland mantra,</l>
                        <l>Of retention, and of fire offerings are all omitted.<note place="end" index="39" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-199"> Ratnākara­śānti reads “restriction” (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yantraṇa</foreign>) in place of “garland” (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mālā</foreign>) [G, p 27]. In his commentary he connects both restriction
                                and retention with the movements of the breath (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yantraṇā
                                    dhāraṇā ca prāṇavāyoḥ</foreign>). A variant of the first line of this verse is attested, in
                                Sanskrit, in a sādhana associated with the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title> found
                                in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sādhana­mālā</title> (#221 in SM vol. 2, p 434–36): <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">na japaṃ na vrataṃ tasya nopavāso vidhīyate</foreign>.
                                Kṛṣṇavajra confirms this variant in his commentary.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-61"/>
                    <lg tid="71">
                        <l>The threefold practice is said to be essentially mantra, appearance, and reality.</l>
                        <l>Through three aspects of wisdom he will not be stained by the faults of existence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-62"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>The yogī who constantly meditates on this without interruption</l>
                        <l>Is equal to Vajrasattva and gains accomplishment in a single month. <ref cRef="F.169.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-63"/>
                    <lg tid="73">
                        <l>Meditate upon the first syllable which is the color of Indra.</l>
                        <l>Merged fully with one’s own awareness it is summoned in an instant.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-64"/>
                    <lg tid="74">
                        <l>The one possessing the second syllable is imagined and cultivated.</l>
                        <l>One gains power over everything within the whole of the three worlds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-65"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>Brahmā, and lord Viṣṇu, so too Indra and the Lord of Desire;</l>
                        <l>Invoked with the wisdom syllable, they are summoned along with their wives.<note place="end" index="40" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-200">“Wisdom syllable:” according to Ratnākaraśānti, this term only
                                appears in some recensions of the text [G, p 27]. As he does not gloss it in his commentary it
                                seems it did not appear in his recension of choice.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-66"/>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>Endowed with the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ā</foreign>, settled in awakened
                            body, speech, and mind,<note place="end" index="41" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-201"> Ratnākaraśānti
                                attests to the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ā</foreign> [G, p 27], which has
                                been used here instead of the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">a</foreign> as
                                given in the Tibetan translation.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Perform the threefold union—this is the supreme extraction of the pill.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-67"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>Possessing the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khe</foreign> is the four-faced one
                            with a red body.<note place="end" index="42" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-202">Kṛṣṇavajra reads <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṣa</foreign> in place of <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khe</foreign> [S, F.211a]; Ratnākaraśānti reads white in place of red [G, p
                                30].</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Skull cup in hand he is passion itself—this is the supreme extraction of semen.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-68"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>Possessing the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ci</foreign> is one yellow in color
                            who shines brightly,</l>
                        <l>With the form of a horse’s face—engaging him is the supreme extraction of the liquor.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-69"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>The one possessing the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ra</foreign> is red in color
                            and exceedingly bright,</l>
                        <l>Has four arms and four faces, and appears in the form of a jackal.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-70"/>
                    <lg tid="80">
                        <l>Cultivating this wrathful mind is the supreme extraction of blood.</l>
                        <l>Endowed with the six syllables, they are fixed in the six places.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-71"/>
                    <lg tid="81">
                        <l>The practice, the host of ḍākinīs, and the vajra yoginīs are accomplished, [511]</l>
                        <l>The two eyes, the ears, and so too the nose and the mind.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-72"/>
                    <lg tid="82">
                        <l>Yogīs take the posture of a sporting lion;<note place="end" index="43" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-203">The
                                Tibetan syntax differs significantly from the Sanskrit, which has been translated here. In the
                                Sanskrit the subject, the yogīs, is in the plural, not the instrumental as in the Tibetan. The
                                object, the posture (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mudrā</foreign>), is in the accusative
                                singular, not the genitive as in the Tibetan, which construes with the term “sporting lion”
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siṃha­vikrīḍitā</foreign>). The Sanskrit attested by
                                Ratnākaraśānti could read as follows: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siṃha­vikrīḍitāṃ
                                    mudrāṃ bandha­yanti yoginaḥ</foreign> [G, p 32].</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>While meditating with the movement of breath controlled, it blazes in an instant</l>
                        <l>Throughout Akaniṣṭha, the summit of existence, and in the seven worlds of the animate and
                            inanimate.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-73"/>
                    <lg tid="83">
                        <l>All meditate upon it, but they don’t realize it.</l>
                        <l>If everyone realized it, the manifestations of beings would utterly collapse.</l>
                        <l>Therefore this wisdom is secret, obscure, and unwritten.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-74"/>
                    <lg tid="84">
                        <l>Because the awakened ones know, they who are immersed in yogic sleep,<note place="end" index="44" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-204">“Awakened ones:” the Sanskrit word here is <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃbuddhāḥ</foreign>, which conveys a slightly different sense than the
                                Tibetan term used, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas rnams</foreign>. Whereas the
                                latter could easily be translated as “buddhas,” the former is best rendered as “awakened
                                ones.”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>They concentrate upon the pill and meditate on the singular nature of forms. <ref cRef="F.169.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-75"/>
                    <lg tid="85">
                        <l>They meditate on the essence of the substances arisen from the nine doors,<note place="end" index="45" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-205">Essence of the substances: Ratnākaraśānti reads “the essence of
                                buddhahood” (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">buddhātman</foreign>) in place of “the
                                essence of the substances” (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzas kyi bdag
                                    nyid</foreign>). [G, p 34].</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>And consume them with a mind free of concepts and devoid of intrinsic nature.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-76"/>
                    <lg tid="86">
                        <l>With the thumb and ring finger, place the wish-granting jewel in the mouth,</l>
                        <l>And attain the everlasting spiritual attainment arisen from the nature of the nectar.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <trailer tid="119">This completes the second instruction on the practice of <title xml:lang="en">The Great
                            Vidyā, Queen of the Yoginīs</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="133">Chapter 3</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="134">The Third Instruction</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-77"/>
                    <lg tid="87">
                        <l>Now comes a thorough explanation of the supreme accomplishment of the samaya: </l>
                        <l>The ingestion of the other gathered substances that bestow the result of omniscience.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-78"/>
                    <lg tid="88">
                        <l>By their mere consumption the mothers of the spirits are accomplished:<note place="end" index="46" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-206">“Mothers of the spirits:” we have here followed Ratnākaraśānti in
                                reading the Sanskrit term <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gūḍhamātaraḥ</foreign> [G, p 36],
                                which appears as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po mi rnams</foreign> in Tibetan
                                translation. In South Asian mythology, the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gūḍhas</foreign>
                                are a class of beings that attend upon Kubera, the lord of wealth.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Elephant and horse, and so too cow and dog.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-79"/>
                    <lg tid="89">
                        <l>Mixed with the great one and also the five wisdom nectars, </l>
                        <l>From the fourteenth to the eighth they are combined and mingled together.<note place="end" index="47" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-207">Kṛṣṇavajra identifies this line as corrupt [S, F.213b]. He notes that
                                it should read “from the eighth until the fourteenth,” which is the span of seven days mentioned
                                in the next verse.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-80"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>Left inside a jackal for seven days, remove them. [512]</l>
                        <l>Roll the five into pellets the size of mustard seeds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-81"/>
                    <lg tid="91">
                        <l>Indeed this tantra teaches that from the eighth to the fourteenth</l>
                        <l>Cultivate them individually for seven days, mix them, and place them in a jackal.<note place="end" index="48" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-208"> Ratnākaraśānti cites a different line of verse here,
                                which collapses this line and the first line of the next verse: “On the night of the spirits (Skt:
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūtarau</foreign>) these fruits of accomplishment
                                (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhārtha­phalāni</foreign>) are to be placed inside
                                a jackal (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śivāṅgamadhye sthāpyānti</foreign>).” [G, p
                                37]. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-82"/>
                    <lg tid="92">
                        <l>Take them out—from the five make pellets the size of the fruit of spiritual attainment.</l>
                        <l>Because the great fruition is perfectly realized, it is taught in this tantra but fully concealed</l>
                        <l>The buddhas have concealed the great fruition in every instance.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-83"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>Next follows the method of practice: visualize a mind lotus</l>
                        <l>Glowing red in color and endowed with the four goddesses.</l>
                        <l>It is adorned with the figure of the Buddha.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-84"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>In the east he shines like a blue lotus, to the south he is yellow,</l>
                        <l>To the west whitish red, and in the north he glows emerald.<note place="end" index="49" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-209">According to Ratnākaraśānti’s commentary, the deity has a purely
                                white face in the west [G, p 39].</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Shrouded in a garland of flames, he is beautiful with three eyes, four faces, and four arms.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-85"/>
                    <p tid="95">Imagine that the goddess in the east has three eyes and holds a khaṭvāṅga and bell in her left
                        hands and a vajra and skull cup in her right hands. The goddess in the south wields a trident, a jewel, a
                        banner, and a jackal. The goddess in the west holds a bow, an arrow, a multi-colored lotus, and a skull
                        cup. <ref cRef="F.170.a"/> The goddess in the north wields a sword, a noose, a hand drum, and a skull
                        cup.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-86"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>In its center visualize the vajra body, speech, and mind</l>
                        <l>Bearing a skull cup and khaṭvāṅga, and so too a bow and arrow.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-87"/>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>Meditating on that which possesses the first mantra, it blazes for an instant.</l>
                        <l>Practicing like this, the yogī is granted the spiritual attainment of the substance. [513]</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-88"/>
                    <lg tid="98">
                        <l>Through the accomplishment of the yoginī, confidence swiftly develops.<note place="end" index="50" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-210">“Yoginī:” Ratnākaraśānti reads “yogas” (Skt: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yogāḥ</foreign>) [G, p 41] where the Tibetan has “yoginī” (Tib: <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor ma</foreign>).</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>One can become entirely invisible and manifest a thousandfold at once.<note place="end" index="51" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-211">This line corresponds closely with verse 12.52, line 2 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-89"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>Plunder from the buddhas and enjoy sublime celestial girls.<note place="end" index="52" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-212"> Ratnākaraśānti reads <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhānāṃ kanyām</foreign>, “the maidens of the siddhas” [G, p 41]. This line corresponds
                                closely with verse 12.52, line 3 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>.</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>With vajra eyes one will see, like an āmalaka fruit in the palm of one’s hand.</l>
                        <l>Buddhas equal to grains of sand in the Ganga residing in their vajra realms,<note place="end" index="53" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-213">This line corresponds closely with verse 12.53, line 2 of
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-90"/>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>Pure realms numerous as sand in the Ganga, the features of awakened body, speech, and mind,<note place="end" index="54" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-214">This line corresponds closely with verse
                                12.55, line 1 of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>. </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>The intrinsic condition of all objects—know them to arise from the mind’s dance.<note place="end" index="55" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-215">This line corresponds closely with verse 12.55, line 2 of
                                the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-91"/>
                    <lg tid="101">
                        <l>Apply the syllables in reverse and meditate on the mantra.</l>
                        <l>Ingest each one of the pills infused with the vajra drink.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-92"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>Take the last of the eight syllables together with the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">ū</foreign> and
                            bindu;</l>
                        <l>Fix it firmly at the end and clearly pronounce the mantra: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">guhya bhakṣa abhakṣe
                                hūṁ.</foreign>
                            <note place="end" index="56" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-216">In his commentary on verse 3.18 Kṛṣṇavajra
                                gives the mantra as <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ a guhya aguhya bhakṣa abhakṣe hūṁ</foreign> [S,
                                F.216a].</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-93"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>In perfect union with the yoginī take possession of the first syllable.</l>
                        <l>If desiring accomplishment through the vajra holder, a yogī consumes the manifest mantra seven
                            times.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-94"/>
                    <lg tid="104">
                        <l>The last of the three syllables sits clearly at the end of the eight.</l>
                        <l>Endowed with the <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ū</foreign> and bindu it remains as the
                            supreme syllable.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-95"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>The one linked to the first syllable is united with <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hrīḥ</foreign>. <ref cRef="F.170.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Apply the last of the syllables and fix in place the five seeds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-96"/>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>Meditate upon the syllable and cause the lotus to fully bloom.</l>
                        <l>For those who seek the accomplishment of a vajra holder, this union should be fully known.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-97"/>
                    <p tid="107">Then, the sublime vajra song which is the realization of the vajra yoginīs welcomes the one who
                        thoroughly accomplishes existence:<note place="end" index="57" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-217">Both
                            Ratnākaraśānti [G, p 160] confirms a genitive relationship between the terms “vajra yoginīs” and
                            “realization,” which has been followed here. The Tibetan editions all contain the agentive <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kyis</foreign>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="117">
                        <l>“Hey, friend! The vajra makes the lotus swell and bloom.</l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">A la la la la ho!</foreign> You have been aroused by the dance
                            of great bliss.</l>
                        <l>The rays of the sun fully open the face of the lotus. [514]</l>
                        <l>You have become aroused by the dance of great bliss.”<note place="end" index="58" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-218">This song has been translated from the Prākrit as it appears in
                                Ratnākaraśānti’s sādhana [SM #239, p 460]: <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hale sai
                                    viasia kamalu pabohiu vajjeṁ / a la la la la ho mahāsuheṇa ārohiu ṇacceṁ / ravikiraṇeṇa
                                    paphulliu kamalu mahā­suheṇa / a la la la la ho mahā­suheṇa ārohiu ṇacceṁ</foreign>. </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-98"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>Then, simply through this song sung to the great vajra holder</l>
                        <l>The vajraḍākinīs dance and call out to Vajrasattva.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-99"/>
                    <lg tid="109">
                        <l>In this way one with consistent devotion gains the spiritual attainment of union.</l>
                        <l>Through perfect union in the four times, accomplishment is gained—this is the supreme meditation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-100"/>
                    <lg tid="110">
                        <l>Adorned with all perfect ornaments and wreathed with flowers and perfume,</l>
                        <l>So the spiritual attainment that bestows the sublime three bodies is certainly attained,</l>
                        <l>Causing its perfect illumination within a hundred miles.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-101"/>
                    <lg tid="111">
                        <l>From the perfect application of the two powers arise the substances of the nine doors.</l>
                        <l>One will accomplish the unsurpassable essence, the peace of abiding in the awakening of buddhahood.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-102"/>
                    <lg tid="112">
                        <l>Now, in verse form:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="113">
                        <l>The forms, the seals, and the attributes,</l>
                        <l>The substances, absorptions, and meditations—</l>
                        <l>These various ritual methods have been set forth,</l>
                        <l>Taught according to the desires of the goddess’s mind.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-103"/>
                    <p tid="114">Whoever keeps this tantra at home, keeps it with him always, and chants and meditates upon it
                        will no longer experience illness, aging, obstacles, or death. He will be forever protected from obstacles
                        by the queens among yoginīs.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <trailer tid="120">This completes the third instruction on the method of practice and ancillary activities,
                        the supreme secret of secrets, that are the intent of the great vajraḍākinīs. <ref cRef="F.171.a"/>
                    </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="135">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-104"/>
                    <p tid="115">This completes the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyātantra</title>.</p>
                    <p tid="116">It was translated and edited by the Indian paṇḍita Jinavara and the great Tibetan translator Gö
                        [515] Lhetsé.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="136">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head type="abbreviations" tid="137">Abbreviations</head>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-080-009-105">
                        <abbr>G</abbr>
                        <expan>Guṇavatīṭīkā</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-080-009-106">
                        <abbr>SM</abbr>
                        <expan>Mahāmāyāsādhanam (in Sādhanamālā)</expan>
                    </item>
                    <item xml:id="UT22084-080-009-107">
                        <abbr>S</abbr>
                        <expan>Mahāmāyātantrasya vṛtti smṛti</expan>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="138">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="139">Sanskrit and Tibetan Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-109">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sgyu ’phrul chen po’i rgyud kyi rgyal po</title>. Toh. 425. Degé Kangyur,
                        vol. 80 (rgyud ’bum, nga), folios 167a–171a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-110">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud kyi rgyal po</title>. Lhasa Kangyur, vol. 82
                        (rgyud ’bum, nga), folios 43a–49b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-111">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud</title>. Narthang Kangyur, vol. 83 (rgyud ’bum, nga),
                        folios 38a–44b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-112">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sgyu ’phrul chen po’i rgyud</title>. Peking Kangyur, rgyud ’bum, vol. nga,
                        folios 153a–157a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-113">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud</title>. Stok Palace Kangyur, vol. 94 (rgyud ’bum,
                        ga), folios 344b–349b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-114">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal sgyu ’phrul chen po’i rgyud kyi rgyal po</title>. bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma)
                        [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur
                        khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes.
                        Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006-2009, vol. 80
                        (rgyud ’bum, nga), pp 536-547.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-115">Kṛṣṇavajra. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i rgyud kyi ’grel
                            pa dran pa</title> (*<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantrasya vṛtti smṛti</title>) [<title xml:lang="en">Recollection: A Commentary on the Mahāmāyā Tantra</title>]. Toh. 1624, Degé Tengyur vol.
                        25 (rgyud ’grel, ya), ff. 201.a–219.a. (S)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-116">Ratnākaraśānti. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guṇavatīṭīkā</title> [<title xml:lang="en">A Commentary Endowed with Qualities</title>]: (1) dpal sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i ’grel pa
                        yon tan ldan pa. Toh. 1623, Degé Tengyur vol. 25 (rgyud ’grel, ya), folios 180b–201a. (2) <title xml:lang="en">Mahāmāyātantram with Guṇavatī by Ratnākaraśānti</title>. Rare Buddhist Text Series vol.
                        10. Edited by Samdhong Rinpoche and Vrajavallabh Dwivedi. Varanasi: Central Institute of Higher Tibetan
                        Studies, 1992. (G) (3) Kaiser Library, Kathmandu (ms. 226). Palm leaf manuscript in Golmola script. (4)
                        Nepal National Archives, Kathmandu (ms. 2–906). Nepali paper manuscript in Devanāgarī script.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-117">____________. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­sādhanam</title> [<title xml:lang="en">A Sādhana for the Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>]: (1) sgyu ma chen mo’i sgrub thabs
                        (Mahāmāyāsādhanam). Toh. 1643, Degé Tengyur vol. 25 (rgyud ’grel, ya), folios 269b–273b. (2) In <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sādhanamālā</title> vol. 2. Edited by Benoytosh Bhattacarya. Baroda: Oriental
                        Institute, 1968. pp. 458–64. (SM)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-118">Tāranātha. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal rgyud kyi rgyal po sgyu ’phrul
                            chen mo ma ha ma ya’i rgya cher bshad pa de kho na nyid kyi sgron ma</title> [<title xml:lang="en">The
                            Lamp of Suchness: A Detailed Explanation of the Glorious King of Tantras, the Mahāmāyātantra</title>].
                        In gsung ’bum, ’dzam thang par ma ed., vol. 11 (da), pp 465-657. dzam thang dgon: [s.n.], 199-. (TBRC
                        W22276)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-119">____________. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo’i khrid yig
                            rgyal ba’i lam bzang</title> [<title xml:lang="en">The Excellent Path of the Victorious Ones: The
                            Instruction Manual for Mahāmāyā</title>]. Ibid., vol. 11 (da), pp 447 - 464.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-120">____________. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal ma ha ma ya’i dkyil ’khor gyi
                            sgrub thabs rin chen myu gu</title> [<title xml:lang="en">The Jeweled Sprout: A Practice Manual for
                            the Maṇḍala of the Glorious Mahāmāyā</title>]. Ibid., vol. 11 (da), pp 431 - 445.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-121">’gos lo tsa wa gzhon nu dpal. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">deb ther sngon
                            po</title>. New Delhi: International Academy of Indian Culture, 1974. Translated as The Blue Annals,
                        see below.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="140">English Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-122">Dalton, Jacob (2004). “The Development of Perfection: The Interiorization
                        of Buddhist Ritual in the 8th and 9th Centuries.” Journal of Indian Philosophy 23 (2004): 1–30.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-123">___________ (2005). “A Crisis of Doxography: How Tibetans Organized Tantra
                        during the 8th–12th Centuries.” Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies 28:1 (2005):
                        115–181.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-124">English, Elizabeth. <title xml:lang="en">Vajrayoginī: Her Visualizations,
                            Rituals, and Forms</title>. Boston: Wisdom Publications, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-125">’gos lo tsa wa. <title xml:lang="en">The Blue Annals</title>. Translated by
                        George N. Roerich. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 1988.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-126">Gray, David B. <title xml:lang="en">The Cakrasaṃvara Tantra (The Discourse
                            of Śrī Heruka): A Study and Annotated Translation</title>. New York: American Institute of Buddhist
                        Studies, 2007.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-127">Isaacson, Harunaga. “Ratnākaraśānti’s Hevajrasahajasadyoga: Studies in
                        Ratnākaraśānti’s Tantric Works I.” In <title xml:lang="fr">Le Parole e i Marmi: studi in onore di Raniero
                            Gnoli nel suo 70° compleanno</title>. Serie Orientale Roma XCII. vol. 1. Roma: Istituto Italiano per
                        l’Africa e l’Oriente, 2001, pp. 457–487.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-128">Kongtrul, Jamgön. <title xml:lang="en">The Treasury of Knowledge: The
                            Elements of Tantric Practice</title>. Translated by Elio Guarisco and Ingrid McLeod. Ithaca: Snow Lion
                        Publications, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-080-009-129">Sanderson, Alexis. “The Śaiva Age.” In <title xml:lang="en">Genesis and
                            Development of Tantra</title>, edited by Shingo Einoo, pp. 17–349. Tokyo: Institute of Oriental
                        Culture, University of Tokyo, 2009.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-130">
                            <term>āli kāli</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">A li kA li </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཨཱ་ལི་ཀཱ་ལི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āli kāli</term>
                            <term type="definition">The vowels (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āli</foreign>) and
                                consonants (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāli</foreign>) of the Sanskrit
                                alphabet.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-131">
                            <term>semen</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byang chub kyi sems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱང་ཆུབ་ཀྱི་སེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bodhicitta</term>
                            <term type="definition">In normative Mahāyāna doctrine, bodhicitta refers to the awakened mind both in
                                its relative and aboslute aspects. In tantric thought it is frequently used as a code word for
                                <term type="ignore">semen</term> in the context of its generation and manipulation in sexual yogic rites.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-132">
                            <term>movement of breath</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srog dang rtsol ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲོག་དང་རྩོལ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prāṇāyāma</term>
                            <term type="definition">The manipulation of breath by means of yogic exercise. The Tibetan translation
                                of the Sanskrit compound <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prāṇāyāma</foreign> is more
                                usually the compound <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srog rtsol</foreign>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-133">
                            <term>commitment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam tshig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམ་ཚིག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The level of <term type="ignore">commitments</term> specifically associated with tantric practice. Also rendered here as “samaya.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-219">
                            <term>samaya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam tshig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམ་ཚིག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">The level of commitments specifically associated with tantric practice. Also rendered here as “commitment.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-134">
                            <term>sacramental substances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam tshig gyi rdzas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམ་ཚིག་གྱི་རྫས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samayadravya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Sacramental substances ingested as part of tantric ritual; frequently composed
                                of bodily fluids or illicit meats.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-135">
                            <term>completion stage</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdzogs pa’i rim pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྫོགས་པའི་རིམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">niṣpannakrama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The second of the two stages of tantric sādhana practiced. Its practices are
                                specific to individual tantric systems but typically include sexual yogas, the consumption of
                                illicit substances, manipulation of the subtle energetic anatomy or resting in an uncontrived
                                state.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">completion phase</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-136">
                            <term>ḍākinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mkha’ ’gro ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཁའ་འགྲོ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ḍākinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Like yoginīs, these are semi-divine female beings who have long haunted the
                                margins of South Asian culture. They are frequently propitiated in order to acquire mundane and
                                transcendent spiritual accomplishment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-137">
                            <term>development stage</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skyed pa’i rim pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྱེད་པའི་རིམ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">utpattikrama</term>
                            <term type="definition">The first of the two stages of tantric practice focused on the visualized
                                development of the tantric maṇḍala and its deities and the recitation of mantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-138">
                            <term>Egg of Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs sgo nga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་སྒོ་ང།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">brahmāṇḍā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Traditional Brahmanical term for the created universe.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-139">
                            <term>guhyaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang ba pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསང་བ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">guhyaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of semi-divine being frequently found in the entourage of Kubera, the
                                lord of wealth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-140">
                            <term>Indra’s Web</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig ’phrul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་འཕྲུལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">indrajāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">Traditional Brahmanical term for the illusory structure of mundane
                                reality.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-141">
                            <term>khaṭvāṅga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kha TwAM ga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁ་ཊྭཱཾ་ག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khaṭvāṅga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A staff with a single or three pointed tip and a freshly decapitated head, a
                                rotting head and a skull skewered on its shaft.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-142">
                            <term>mahāyoga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor chen po’i rgyud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣལ་འབྱོར་ཆེན་པོའི་རྒྱུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahā­yoga­tantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A term used to describe the later tantras of the Yoga class that incoporated
                                more transgressive pactices and a wrathful aesthetic. Typified by the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title> and Guhya­garbha­tantra.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">Great Yoga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-143">
                            <term>sādhana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrub thabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲུབ་ཐབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhana</term>
                            <term type="definition">The method of practice. Experiential methods for actualizing spiritual
                                attainments and liberation.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">practice method</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-144">
                            <term>spiritual attainment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngos grub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དངོས་གྲུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">The mundane and transcendent abilities that are conferred through the
                                perfection of yogic practices.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-145">
                            <term>vidyā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the female deity of the maṇḍala (most frequently as the consort
                                of the main deity) who represents knowledge; the tantric consort; knowledge; frequently used in
                                the sense of magical incantations and magical power. Also rendered here as “knowledge.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-221">
                            <term>knowledge</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the female deity of the maṇḍala (most frequently as the consort
                                of the main deity) who represents <term type="ignore">knowledge</term>; the tantric consort; <term type="ignore">knowledge</term>; frequently used in
                                the sense of magical incantations and magical power. Also rendered here as “vidyā.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-146">
                            <term>vidyādhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa ’dzin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་པ་འཛིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyādhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of semi-divine being whose identiy has shifted over time and genre. In
                                their most popular form they are spell (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</foreign>)
                                wielding (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhara</foreign>) beings capable of granting
                                magical abilities to those they favor. The Buddhist tradition associated them more closely with
                                soteriological aims, identifying them as realized beings who possess (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhara</foreign>) knowledge or awareness (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</foreign>).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-147">
                            <term>Virile One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vīra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Closely associated with notions of virility, this term can denote the male
                                deity of the maṇḍala (whose consort is the Vidyā) or the yogī who practices this mode of
                                Tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-148">
                            <term>yoga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣལ་འབྱོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoga</term>
                            <term type="definition">A term which is generally used to refer to a wide range of spiritual
                                practices. It literally means to be merged with or “yoked to,” in the sense of being fully
                                immersed in one’s respective discipline.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-149" mode="marked">
                            <term>Unexcelled Yoga tantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla na med pa’i rnal ’byor gyi rgyud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བླ་ན་མེད་པའི་རྣལ་འབྱོར་གྱི་རྒྱུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoga­niruttara­tantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A category of tantra that includes the so-called father tantras like the
                                    <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja Tantra</title> and the “mother,” or Yoginī, tantras into
                                a single genre of tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-150">
                            <term>yoginī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣལ་འབྱོར་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoginī</term>
                            <term type="definition">With a long history in South Asian folklore and religious traditions, yoginīs
                                are liminal, trangressive and often ferocious semi-divine female figures associated with the
                                bestowal of temporal and transcendent spiritual accomplishment. In Buddhist tantra they are
                                identical to ḍākinīs.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-151">
                            <term>Yoginītantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnal ’byor ma’i rgyud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣལ་འབྱོར་མའི་རྒྱུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yoginī­tantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">The last development of Buddhist tantra in India; focused upon the figure of
                                the yoginī and the meditative manipulation of the subtle energetic anatomy of the physical body.
                                Typified by the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">He­vajra­tantra</title>, <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakrasaṃvaratantra</title> and the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā­tantra</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-152">
                            <term>Kṛṣṇavajra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag po rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནག་པོ་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kṛṣṇavajra</term>
                            <term type="definition">An 11th or 12th century Buddhist commentator. Wrote <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Recollection: a commentary on the Mahāmāyā Tantra</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-153">
                            <term>Gö Lhetsé</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’gos lhas btsas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འགོས་ལྷས་བཙས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                            <term type="definition">11th century translator and teacher of <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-154">
                            <term>Mahāmāyā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྱུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The female central deity of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā
                                    Tantra</title> who appears in the form of the male Heruka. She was also a popular form of the
                                Brahmanical great goddess (Mahādevī), to whom the Buddhist figure is intimately related. Also rendered here as “Great Illusion.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-220">
                            <term>Great Illusion</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgyu ’phrul chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྱུ་འཕྲུལ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">The female central deity of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā
                                Tantra</title> who appears in the form of the male Heruka. She was also a popular form of the
                                Brahmanical great goddess (Mahādevī), to whom the Buddhist figure is intimately related. Also rendered here as “Mahāmāyā.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-155">
                            <term>Heruka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">he ru ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཧེ་རུ་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Heruka</term>
                            <term type="definition">The wrathful form of Akṣobhya, buddha of the vajra family, who appears in the
                                center of many tantric maṇḍalas. He is typicaly depicted wearing mortuary implements and wreathed
                                in flame.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-156">
                            <term>Kukkuripa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku ku ri pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུ་ཀུ་རི་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kukkuripa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Counted among the most famous of the Indian Buddhist Mahāsiddhas and renowned
                                for his association with packs of dogs (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kukkura</foreign>),
                                he is a central figure in a number of tantric lineages, specifically of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja Tantra</title> and <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyā
                                    Tantra</title>. He was active sometime between the 8th and 10th centuries.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-157">
                            <term>Marpa Chökyi Lodrö</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mar pa chos kyi blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མར་པ་ཆོས་ཀྱི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <!--<term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">-</term>-->
                            <term type="definition">(1012 - 1097) Tibetan translator and lay practitioner from Lhodrak, traveled
                                several times to Nepal and India to receive tantric Buddhist teachings, notably from Nāropa and
                                Maitripā, and in Tibet established an important set of lineages through his “four pillar”
                                disciples Milarepa, Ngoktön Chöku Dorje, Tshurtön Wangki Dorje, and Metön Tshönpo.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="en">Marpa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-158">
                            <term>Nāropa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">na ro pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ན་རོ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nāropa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Indian scholar and practitioner (956 - 1041), a major figure in the
                                transmission of tantric Buddhism to Tibet; earlier in his life he was an important paṇḍita of
                                Nālandā, but left to become a yogi and siddha, the student of Tilopā, and later the teacher of
                                Kukkuripa, Marpa, and others.</term>
                            <term type="alternative" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nāropadā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-159">
                            <term>Ratnākaraśānti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rin chen ’byung gnas zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིན་ཆེན་འབྱུང་གནས་ཞི་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ratnākaraśānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">An important 11th century Buddhist monastic scholar who wrote prolifically on
                                a number on both Mahāyāna and Mantrayāna works.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-080-009-160">
                            <term>Akaniṣṭha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’og min </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོག་མིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Akaniṣṭha</term>
                            <term type="definition">The highest of the buddhafields. The term can be used to indicate the pure
                                realm of the dharmakāya in general or can refer to the the six realms between the highest heaven
                                of the form realm and the realm of dharmakāya.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>