<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das phyag na rdo rje gos sngon po can gyi rgyud</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་གོས་སྔོན་པོ་ཅན་གྱི་རྒྱུད།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavannīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi­tantra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">བཅོམ་ལྡན་འདས་ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ་གོས་སྔོན་པོ་ཅན་གྱི་རྒྱུད་ཅེས་བྱ་བ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das phyag na rdo rje gos sngon po can gyi rgyud ces bya
                    ba</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Tantra entitled “The Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi”</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhagavannīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi­tantra­nāma</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Group<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" ref="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-61">Catherine Dalton</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-74">Ryan Damron</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-76">Wiesiek Mical</author>
            <editor role="TEImarkupEditor" ref="contributors.xml#person-253">Michael Engle</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 3.22 <date>2013 - 2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p type="tantricRestriction">
                        <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
                        restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                        translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                        or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-087-003"/>
                <date>2013-10-20</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh498" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 498</ref>, <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 87 (rgyud ’bum, da), folios 158.a–167.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Celu</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Phakpa Sherab</author>
                    <location count-pages="19">
                        <start volume="87" page="317"/>
                        <end volume="87" page="335"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21414"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12218" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2019-03-01T17:41:23.641Z" user="admin">01/03/2019 17:41:23</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!-- 
                <title style="contentsPage">Contents</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Summary</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Acknowledgments</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Introduction</title>
            <title style="contentsTranslation">The Translation</title>
            <title style="contentsTextTitle">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 1 ........... Accomplishing Peaceful Activity</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 2 .......................................... The Oblation</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 3 .............................................. Vaiśravaṇa </title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 4 ...................... The Wheel of Suppression</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 5 ...... The Ritual for Drawing the Diagram</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 6 .............. The Stages of the Fire Offering</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 7 ......................... The Wheel of Expulsion</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 8 .................................................... Mantra</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 9 ............................... Certainty and Purity</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 10 .............................................. Protection</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 11 ................ The Arrangement of Mantras</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 12 .. Bestowing Empowerment on Students</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 13 ........................... Establishing the Secret</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Notes</title>
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Bibliography</title> -->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="256">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-1"/>
                <p tid="1"> In the Kangyur and Tengyur collections there are more than forty titles centered on the form of
                    Vajrapāṇi known as the “Blue-Clad One,” a measure of this figure’s great popularity in both India and Tibet.
                    This text, <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title>, is a scripture that
                    belongs to the Conduct tantra (Caryātantra) class, the third of the four categories used by the Tibetans to
                    organize their tantric canon. It introduces the practice of Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi, while also providing the
                    practitioner with a number of rituals directed at suppressing, subduing, or eliminating ritual targets.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="257">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This translation was produced by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of Chökyi
                    Nyima Rinpoche. Catherine Dalton and Andreas Doctor translated the text, with assistance from Ryan Damron and
                    Wiesiek Mical.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="258">Introduction</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-3"/>
                <p tid="4">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title> is a scripture that, in the
                    fourfold classification that the Tibetans employed to organize their tantric canon, belongs to the “Conduct”
                    or Caryātantra class. The small number of tantras in this category were grouped together because of their
                    similarities in philosophical view and ritualistic conduct. The Caryātantra class is the second of the “three
                    outer tantras.” It adopts features from both Kriyātantra and Yogatantra (the first and third, respectively),
                    being characterized by its attention to worldly rituals (as found in Kriyātantra) as well as more
                    soteriological insights (as emphasized in Yogatantra). From an historical perspective, the Caryātantras can
                    also be viewed as exemplifying the transition in Indian tantric practice from a role of predominantly
                    protecting against worldly calamities to one of providing a path toward personal awakening, as the later
                    tantric systems promise. Generally the texts of the Caryātantra class have been tentatively dated to the early
                    seventh century <hi rend="small-caps">ce</hi> (Williams 2000, 207). There is, however, some evidence within this tantra (which will be
                    discussed below) that might point to a slightly later date for this text. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-4"/>
                <p tid="5">More specifically, the tantra presented in this translation concerns a form of Vajrapāṇi known as the
                    Blue-Clad One. In this form Vajrapāṇi is dark blue, with one face, three eyes, and two hands. His clothing is
                    blue and his thick matted hair streams upward. His body is adorned with eight serpents in various places, and
                    in his right hand he brandishes a vajra. For the Tibetans, and no doubt for Indian tantric practitioners, this
                    form of Vajrapāṇi was highly popular—to the extent that the Kangyur contains no less than seven tantras and
                    two dhāraṇī texts centered on this awakened figure. Of the seven tantras, three (Toh 498, 499, 501) belong to
                    the Caryātantra class, while the remaining four (Toh 454, 456, 457, 461) are found in the class called the
                    “Unexcelled tantras” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla na med pa’i rgyud</foreign>) by Tibetan exegetes. Seen
                    from an historical standpoint, it seems likely that the Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi of the Caryātantras may have
                    functioned as the prototype for the later Unexcelled tantras associated with this figure. As such, the tantra
                    translated here is of particular importance for understanding the early developments of this tradition. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-5"/>
                <p tid="6">The popularity of Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi can also be gleaned from the number of texts concerned with this
                    figure in the Tengyur (the Indian commentarial collection in Tibetan translation), where we find no less than
                    thirty-seven works that focus on Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi. They are made up of actual commentaries as well as of
                    several shorter practice manuals and of various rituals. Almost all of these texts, and importantly all of the
                    commentaries, relate to the later tantras found in the Unexcelled tantra section. We can therefore deduce that
                    the tradition of this deity gained its primary popularity in the later days of the tantric movement in India,
                    where it seems that a particularly colorful group of devotees took to wearing blue robes as the hallmark of
                    their community<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-272" index="1">See Davidson (2002) p 204.</note>. In
                    the West, however, Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi has remained surprisingly unexplored, and to date hardly any mention of
                    the deity can be found in modern scholarship. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-6"/>
                <p tid="7">The text begins with the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi requesting the Buddha Akṣobhya to teach a tantra that
                    can tame all evil spirits that live beneath the ground. The notion that an underworld exists in which various
                    forms of evil spirits flourish was well developed in Indian Buddhism since the very early days<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-273" index="2">See Mayer (2007).</note>. Both of the two other
                    Caryātantra tantras on Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi (Toh 499 in seven chapters and Toh 501 in five chapters) share the
                    same theme, unfolding as Vajrapāṇi requests the Buddha to teach the rituals that can tame the nāgas and yakṣas
                    below the ground and, in the process, accomplish the wealth that they guard and repel the disease that they
                    inflict on humans. These two other tantras thus appear to be slightly condensed (or perhaps earlier) versions
                    of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-274" index="3">Despite being the shortest of the three tantras, Toh 501 is somewhat broader
                        in scope as it also includes rituals to tame beings above the ground.</note>
                </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-7"/>
                <p tid="8">The Buddha Akṣobhya agrees to Vajrapāṇi’s request, and then prepares to teach the tantra known as
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Vajra that Subjugates the Evil Forces Below the Vajra Earth</title>, which
                    throughout this text is synonymous with the main title of the tantra. Before he begins, however, he first
                    blesses Vajrapāṇi with the ability to tame the various serpent beings living in the environment below, headed
                    by the nāga king Anantaka (another name for Śesa, the serpent associated with Viṣṇu). Once tamed in this way,
                    the serpent beings join in the request being put to the Buddha that he teach the tantra. With the stage thus
                    set, the Buddha Akṣobhya proceeds to teach.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-8"/>
                <p tid="9">The instructions begin with a short, unnumbered chapter (here included at the end of the Prologue)
                    called “Taming the Nāgas,” which details a very brief ritual practice for taming nāgas, grahas, and other evil
                    forces that live beneath the earth. After this initial instruction, the remainder of the tantra is structured
                    in thirteen chapters, all of which are numbered and given titles in the tantra itself.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-9"/>
                <p tid="10">Chapter 1, entitled “Accomplishing Peaceful Activity” or the “Chapter of the Gods,” presents the
                    “ritual for the action deity,” which amounts to a succinct practice manual for the visualization of Blue-Clad
                    Vajrapāṇi and the recitation of his mantra. The practice manual is well structured and simple, and contains
                    the tantra’s main iconographic description of Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-10"/>
                <p tid="11"> Chapter 2, “The Oblation,” describes the ritual for making an oblation and other offerings to
                    Vajrapāṇi and his retinue. This contains the offering mantra for Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi, as well as mantras for
                    each of the nine yakṣas in his retinue named in this chapter.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-11"/>
                <p tid="12">Chapter 3 is entitled “Vaiśravaṇa,” and focuses on the yakṣa Vaiśravaṇa who, according to the previous
                    chapter, is the first among Vajrapāṇi’s retinue. In this chapter Vaiśravaṇa is encouraged by the Buddha (one
                    assumes this is still Akṣobhya, as in the opening of the tantra, but this is not made explicit) to give
                    instructions on his own practice, in which Vaiśravaṇa himself is the main figure and the other eight yakṣas
                    are members of his retinue. The practices described include making offerings to Vaiśravaṇa and his retinue, as
                    well as a wrathful suppression ritual performed with an effigy.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-12"/>
                <p tid="13">Chapter 4, “The Wheel of Suppression,” describes a short ritual of suppression, connected with the
                    yoga of Vajrapāṇi, which “strikes all wicked ones,” presumably clearing away evil or obstructing forces. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-13"/>
                <p tid="14"> Chapter 5, entitled “The Ritual for Drawing the Diagram,” outlines a wrathful ritual for killing a
                    person or subduing a place, and is taught by the Vajra Holder (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje ’dzin
                        pa</foreign>), an epithet that probably refers to Vajrapāṇi. The appropriate target for such wrathful
                    practices is not mentioned explicitly in this chapter, but chapter 3 describes such a ritual target as “those
                    hostile toward the teachings.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-14"/>
                <p tid="15">In chapter 6, “The Stages of the Fire Offering,” Vajrapāṇi asks the Blessed One (again, probably
                    Akṣobhya) whether or not one is liberated through ritual practices such as the fire offering (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin sreg</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign>). The Blessed One
                    replies that one is indeed liberated through the performance of such ritual practices when they are combined
                    with the maintenance of sacred commitments, and he proceeds to describe the stages of the fire-offering
                    ritual.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-15"/>
                <p tid="16">Chapter 7, “The Wheel of Expulsion,” describes a short ritual in which the practitioner visualizes
                    himself as the activity deity (presumably Vajrapāṇi) and summons the target into an effigy, which is burned
                    and then discarded in water.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-16"/>
                <p tid="17">Chapter 8, entitled “Mantra,” is an extremely concise chapter that mentions Vajrapāṇi’s main mantra
                    together with a claim that it “accomplishes all activity, even without practice.” The rest of the chapter is a
                    list of activities that one might wish to accomplish (being affectionate toward all beings, killing all
                    enemies, protecting against epidemics, accomplishing wealth, and so forth) and a concise statement of the
                    method for accomplishing each of them.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-17"/>
                <p tid="18">Chapter 9, “Certainty and Purity,” initially focuses on the recitation of mantras. Here several
                    mantras are mentioned that are used in the practice of the activity deity (presumably according to the same
                    ritual manual outlined in the first chapter of the tantra), and concise advice is given on the recitation of
                    Vajrapāṇi’s mantra and its attendant visualization. In its later stanzas, however, this chapter stands out
                    from the rest of the text in its use of a much more abstract and almost poetic language to describe the
                    intended results of practice, with a perceptible shift to a more soteriological focus. For example, the
                    “nondual nature” that is the result to be obtained in a single lifetime is described as “inexpressible,
                    nonconceptual, the meaning of thatness.” This contrasts rather sharply with the more ritualistic language of
                    the other chapters, where the emphasis is mostly on suppressing, subduing, or killing ritual targets. Here the
                    use of terms like “natural luminosity” and “supreme awakening” suggests an orientation transcending mere
                    worldly ritual. It is true that throughout the other chapters there are hints to be found of a more
                    soteriological orientation, such as in the introductory section of the tantra when the nāga kings are made to
                    generate the mind of enlightenment; in chapter 1 when the goal of the “supreme attainment” is mentioned; in
                    chapter 6 when Vajrapāṇi asks the Blessed One if it is possible to be liberated through a ritual such as the
                    fire offering; and in the final chapter when Vajrapāṇi asks Vajradhara to explain the secret of enlightened
                    mind. However, it is in this ninth chapter that the whole tenor of the text changes most perceptibly, with the
                    language and content reflecting what is only hinted at in other parts of the text.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-18"/>
                <p tid="19">Chapter 10, “Protection,” describes a number of detailed protection rituals spoken by Vajradhara to
                    Vajrapāṇi. Among the protection rituals described are those that seem intended to counteract possession—for
                    “those beings who are seized by wicked ones”—as well as general negative influences, and to reverse
                    obstacles.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-19"/>
                <p tid="20">Chapter 11, “The Arrangement of Mantras,” describes the ritual arrangement of mantra syllables within
                    a triangular maṇḍala and explains their ritual recitation. The arrangement describes syllables from the
                    “first” through the “seventh,” but then later mentions the “thirteen syllables,” which are presumably the
                    thirteen syllables of Vajrapāṇi’s root mantra, taught earlier in the tantra. The relationship between this
                    thirteen-syllable mantra and the arrangement of the seven syllables described earlier in the chapter, however,
                    remains unclear.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-20"/>
                <p tid="21">Chapter 12, “Bestowing Empowerment on Students,” describes the ritual for performing initiation for
                    the Vajrapāṇi practice. After discussing the preparation of the ground and the maṇḍala, the tantra mentions
                    five initiations that are to be bestowed: the vase, vajra, bell, crown, and name initiations. These five
                    initiations are characteristic of an early stage in the development of Buddhist initiatory rites (Tib.
                        <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">abhiṣeka</foreign>) in which
                    these five initiations as a group constituted the full initiatory procedure, and the later, now well-known set
                    of four consecrations (in which these earlier five were condensed into the first of the four, the vase
                    initiation) had not yet developed (Isaacson 2010, 263–64). If, as it appears, the tantra is following this
                    early system—which had, by this point, developed into the full form of the fivefold consecration—this might
                    suggest a seventh-century or even early-eighth-century date, since the continued development of initiations,
                    starting with the “secret initiation” (Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">guhyābhiṣeka</foreign>), took place
                    with the mid-eighth century <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhya­samāja­tantra</title>.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-21"/>
                <p tid="22">In chapter 13, the final chapter of the tantra, “Establishing the Secret,” Vajrapāṇi asks the Blessed
                    One (again identified as Vajradhara, which we may assume here is a different name for Akṣobhya) to explain the
                    secret of enlightened mind. The reply he receives is the instruction to generate the enlightened attitude and
                    to gather the two accumulations of merit and wisdom, and then to perform a version of Vajrapāṇi’s ritual
                    practice, which is described in brief and presented as a method for taming unruly beings and subduing
                    obstructing forces. Then, after a brief verse lauding the qualities of this particular tantra, Vajrapāṇi and
                    his retinue praise the words of the Blessed One, and the text concludes.</p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-22"/>
                <p tid="23"> If we look at the structure of the tantra as a whole, the various chapters of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title>, with the exception of the ninth chapter, appear to
                    be a collection of related ritual manuals centered on the figure of this particular form of Vajrapāṇi. The
                    first chapter seems to be the foundational ritual manual for the visualization and mantra recitation of
                    Blue-Clad Vajrapāṇi, while the later chapters describe ancillary rituals that, it seems, are to be connected
                    with the framework of the main ritual manual. These ritual texts are all presented within the tantra’s larger
                    narrative framework. While the initial introductory narrative framework (Tib. <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gleng
                        gzhi</foreign>, Skt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nidāna</foreign>) of the tantra is somewhat detailed, its
                    closing framework is very brief—a single sentence. Additionally, each of the chapters, again with the single
                    exception of chapter 9, has its own short introductory narrative framework. These statements, ranging from a
                    single sentence in some chapters to a few paragraphs in others, give the context for the rituals presented
                    therein, stating what the ritual is for and who taught it, thus framing the actual ritual instructions as
                    quotations of the words spoken by the teacher. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-23"/>
                <p tid="24">This presentation of teachings as a discourse by a particular teacher, or a dialogue between teacher
                    and student, is a standard framework for both sūtras and tantras. What is interesting here, however, is that
                    the content presented within this framework is almost entirely ritual instruction. In a recent article, Jacob
                    Dalton has argued convincingly that ritual manuals were often a major source upon which the tantras themselves
                    were based, rather than the other way around as traditional scholarship mostly holds (Dalton forthcoming, 4).
                    Here we see what seems to be a clear example of this inversion, since apart from its narrative framework, the
                    content of the tantra is nearly exclusively ritual instruction. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-24"/>
                <p tid="25"> In this tantra, the ninth chapter is the single exception to both the presence of this narrative
                    framework and the exclusive ritual content (here we include within “ritual content” laudatory words praising
                    the efficacy of the ritual, which are commonly found within ritual works). This chapter names no teacher as
                    the one imparting the instructions; it simply begins, “Then, moreover, the certainty of recitation / will be
                    taught now.” </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-25"/>
                <p tid="26">As discussed above, the initial part of chapter 9 is a description of the visualization for mantra
                    recitation, followed by a short list of the mantras required for the practice. This part of the chapter can be
                    considered as ritual content, though it does not contain a full or self-contained ritual as the other chapters
                    do; instead it appears to be a sort of supplemental instruction to be integrated into the practice described
                    in chapter 1. The text then shifts, however, in both content and tone to an overtly soteriological orientation
                    with the use of abstract language that is not found in other parts of the tantra. The lack of the narrative
                    framework found in the other chapters combined with the overt soteriological orientation and abstract language
                    single out chapter 9 as being, perhaps, a later addition to the tantra. </p>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-26"/>
                <p tid="27"> Although the language of the text is sometimes obscure and difficult, <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra
                        of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</title> represents a fascinating stage in the historical development of
                    Buddhist tantra and offers a beautiful example of early tantric literature. We hope that this English
                    translation will open the doors to further engagement with this and other tantras, by both practitioners and
                    scholars of Buddhist tantra alike. </p>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="259">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="260">The Tantra of the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi</head>
                <div type="prologue">
                    <head type="prologue" tid="261">Prologue</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-27"/>
                    <lg tid="28">
                        <l>
                            <ref cRef="F.158.a"/> I prostrate to the Blue-Clad Blessed Vajrapāṇi!</l>
                        <l>I prostrate to the buddhas and bodhisattvas of the three times!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-28"/>
                    <p tid="29"> Thus have I heard at one time. Blessed Akṣobhya, the buddha of the vajra family, was residing in
                        the palace in Alakāvatī together with a retinue of millions of bodhisattvas, including Vajrapāṇi, <ref cRef="F.158.b"/> Vajra Regiment, Constant Vajra Holder, Vajra Tamer, Terrible Vajra Conqueror, Vajra
                        Tamer of All Evil, Vajra Victor of Basic Space, Vajra Joyfully Abiding Protector, and others. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-29"/>
                    <p tid="30">At that time, the great being, the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi himself, brandished a vajra three times
                        at his heart center. He made three circumambulations of the Blessed One and prostrated himself.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-30"/>
                    <p tid="31">Then, kneeling on his right knee, Vajrapāṇi requested, “Blessed One, Thus-Gone One, Great Vajra
                        Holder, please explain the great tantra called <title xml:lang="en">The All-Subjugating Vajra</title> that
                        subjugates all bhūtas and that tames the evil ones that dwell beneath the earth. Great Vajra Holder, I
                        supplicate you to teach! Great Lord of All, I supplicate you to teach! Great Tamer of All Evil Forces, I
                        supplicate you to teach! Great Dispeller of All Darkness, I supplicate you to teach!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-31"/>
                    <p tid="32">At this request from Vajrapāṇi, the Blessed One declared, “It is excellent that you, Great
                        Vajradhara, Secret One, have, for the benefit of sentient beings, requested from me the tantra called
                            <foreign xml:lang="en">The All-Subjugating Vajra</foreign>. Lord of Secrets, that is excellent! Great
                        Bodhisattva, that is excellent! Thus, you who share Vajrapāṇi’s lineage, listen and remember this! I will
                        reveal and explain the tantra called <title xml:lang="en">The Vajra that Subjugates the Evil Forces Below
                            the Vajra Earth</title>. Receive it!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-32"/>
                    <p tid="33">After pronouncing these words, the Blessed One, by means of the absorption of the all-subjugating
                        vajra, entered equipoise in the absorption called <emph>vanquishing all grahas and bhūtas from below the
                            earth</emph>.</p>
                    <p tid="34">No sooner had the Blessed One entered equipoise than a multitude of wrathful subjugators of evil
                        forces emanated from all the pores of his body and filled the space under the earth, on the earth, and
                        above the earth. The entire land of the underground nāgas was filled with the horrible sound <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>. <ref cRef="F.159.a"/> The eight nāga kings together
                        with their retinues were tamed, and bowed before the Blessed One.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-33"/>
                    <p tid="35">But the nāga king Anantaka then gave rise to an evil thought, intending to release a scalding
                        breath. But the Blessed One knew his intention and blessed the Lord of Secrets, Vajrapāṇi, who spoke this
                        mantra called <title xml:lang="en">the mantra that completely pacifies the anger of all nāgas</title>:
                            “<foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ nīlavajra krodhanāga hūṃ phaṭ</foreign>.”</p>
                    <p tid="36">Now the mind of the nāga Anantaka was completely pacified; he became endowed with the awakened
                        mind, through which the minds of all the nāgas were completely pacified. Then all of the nāga kings like
                        Anantaka, who live below the earth, supplicated the Blessed One, the Great Vajra Holder, with these words: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-34"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Blessed One, we supplicate you to explain a ritual that will, in future times and onward, prevent
                        the grahas that are living below the earth from making obstacles for sentient beings, and that will also
                        pacify the evil of those spirits. We supplicate you to explain why we, the nāga kings and our retinues,
                        are unable to create obstacles for that great being. We supplicate you to explain to us, the nāga kings,
                        our purpose.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-35"/>
                    <p tid="38">The Blessed One, the Great Vajra Holder, glanced at the nāga kings and replied, “Nāga kings, that
                        is excellent! Your request is timely. I will reveal this for the benefit of sentient beings. I will
                        explain; listen!” </p>
                    <p tid="39"> The nāgas and the others replied, “Excellent, Blessed One!”</p>
                    <p tid="40"> They then listened appropriately. At that point, the Blessed One explained the following chapter
                        called “Taming the Nāgas.” </p>
                    <div type="section">
                        <head type="section" tid="262">Taming the Nāgas</head>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-36"/>
                        <lg tid="41">
                            <l>
                                <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hūṃ</foreign>!</l>
                            <l>For the benefit of all sentient beings,</l>
                            <l>The Teacher, the Great Vajra Holder,</l>
                            <l>Carefully observed his own retinue,</l>
                            <l>Projected light into all directions,</l>
                            <l>And then taught the method for destroying all grahas:</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-37"/>
                        <lg tid="42">
                            <l> “On the eighth day of the waxing moon,</l>
                            <l>Or likewise on the fourteenth and fifteenth days,</l>
                            <l>In an extremely isolated place,</l>
                            <l>Contemplate wrathful Vajrapāṇi,</l>
                            <l>Youthful and with majestic poise. <ref cRef="F.159.b"/>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-38"/>
                        <lg tid="43">
                            <l>“Next, purify gold and so forth, the seven precious things,</l>
                            <l>And place these in a jeweled vessel or clay pot.</l>
                            <l>Recite 108 mantras.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-39"/>
                        <lg tid="44">
                            <l>“Resorting to the true utterance of the Three Jewels,</l>
                            <l>Give an oblation to the bhūtas.</l>
                            <l>Bury it in firm ground wherever they abide,</l>
                            <l>And the bhūtas and evil nāgas will be pacified.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-40"/>
                        <lg tid="45">
                            <l>“When these peaceful methods are not sufficient,</l>
                            <l>With terrible weapons</l>
                            <l>Set their homes ablaze.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-41"/>
                        <lg tid="46">
                            <l>“This fierce, unbearable suffering</l>
                            <l>Will remind them of their previous intentions,</l>
                            <l>And they will undoubtedly be pacified.”</l>
                        </lg>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="263">Chapter 1</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="264">Accomplishing Peaceful Activity</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-42"/>
                    <p tid="47">Then the Blessed One explained the ritual for the action deity:</p>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>“Always in possession of the awakened mind,</l>
                        <l>And endowed with all commitments and vows,</l>
                        <l> Engage in all of the acts of bathing.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-43"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>“In a clean and pure place,</l>
                        <l>Beautify the maṇḍala as is fitting.</l>
                        <l>Visualize an iron hook that emerges from the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>,</l>
                        <l>Bringing the buddhas and bodhisattvas instantaneously before you.</l>
                        <l>Make offerings and so forth to them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-44"/>
                    <lg tid="50">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ śūnyatā­jñāna­vajra­svabhāvātmako 'haṃ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Meditate on the absorption of emptiness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-45"/>
                    <lg tid="51">
                        <l>“In the expanse of space, visualize the letter <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āḥ</foreign>,</l>
                        <l>And the first moon, the letter <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Blazing with great light.</l>
                        <l>This purifies the negative emotions of the six classes of beings,</l>
                        <l>Definitively placing them in the state of complete liberation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-46"/>
                    <lg tid="52">
                        <l>“Imagine the light gathered back in the form of <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Marked with a five-pronged vajra.</l>
                        <l>A garland of light shines forth from this,</l>
                        <l>Causing all sentient beings</l>
                        <l>To dissolve into the vajra essence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-47"/>
                    <lg tid="53">
                        <l>“From this the Great Wrathful One</l>
                        <l>Blue in color, blazes forth.</l>
                        <l>Seated with his left leg extended, he is sixteen years of age.</l>
                        <l>He is adorned with eight ornaments, Anantaka, and so forth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-48"/>
                    <lg tid="54">
                        <l>“His form is dark in color,</l>
                        <l>With one face and two hands, holding a vajra.</l>
                        <l>His clothing is blue and luminous,</l>
                        <l>His three eyes are beautifully red and looking upward.</l>
                        <l>His dreadlocks stream upward</l>
                        <l>Bound by a vajra ornament—imagine him like this.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-49"/>
                    <lg tid="55">
                        <l>“Then great wrathful wisdom</l>
                        <l>Is invoked and ushered in with <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ</foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-50"/>
                    <lg tid="56">
                        <l>“Visualize, at his head, throat, and heart center,</l>
                        <l>A wheel, a lotus, and a vajra</l>
                        <l>Marked by the syllables <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṃ āḥ hūṃ</foreign>, <ref cRef="F.160.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Ornamented with the thirteen-syllable mantra.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-51"/>
                    <lg tid="57">
                        <l>“Visualize that Akṣobhya-Vajra confers empowerment,</l>
                        <l>And all is conquered and perfectly purified.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-52"/>
                    <lg tid="58">
                        <l>Then the Blessed One resolutely spoke his root mantra, the statement of all activity:</l>
                        <l>“<foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ</foreign>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-53"/>
                    <lg tid="59">
                        <l>“The garlands of mantra as well</l>
                        <l>Should be white for peaceful, red for magnetizing,</l>
                        <l>Yellow for increasing, and black for wrathful activity.</l>
                        <l>Completely abandon thoughts and recite this.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-54"/>
                    <lg tid="60">
                        <l>“With the distinct techniques of emanating and absorbing,</l>
                        <l> Engage in concentration on whatever you wish for.</l>
                        <l>Give up the practice of what you do not desire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-55"/>
                    <lg tid="61">
                        <l>“The wrathful king Vajrapāṇi</l>
                        <l>Will benefit this mind, the support of all virtues,</l>
                        <l>With whatever is striven for!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-56"/>
                    <lg tid="62">
                        <l>“The stages such as Perfect Joy,</l>
                        <l>And abilities such as invisibility, will be accomplished.</l>
                        <l>The support of everything is virtuous</l>
                        <l>And the supported is devoid of activity.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-282">We are unsure of these two lines: <foreign type="quote" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun rten rab tu spyad dge can / rten can sbyor ba rab tu dben.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>The supreme attainment will be perfectly accomplished!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-57"/>
                    <trailer tid="242">This was the first chapter from <title xml:lang="en">The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in
                            the Underworld</title>, “Accomplishing Peaceful Activity” or the “Chapter of the Gods.” </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="265">Chapter 2</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="266">The Oblation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-58"/>
                    <p tid="63">Then the great bodhisattva, the great being Vajrapāṇi, supplicated the Blessed One with these
                        words:</p>
                    <lg tid="64">
                        <l> “Blessed One, Teacher, Vajra Holder, </l>
                        <l>Please explain the supreme ritual</l>
                        <l>For the oblation that pacifies obstacles.</l>
                        <l>Make this effort for the benefit of beings!”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-59"/>
                    <lg tid="65">
                        <l>Then the Blessed One said:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="66">
                        <l> “Excellent, principal Vajra Holder!</l>
                        <l> I will explain the basis of all oblations:</l>
                        <l>The ritual for pacifying obstacles,</l>
                        <l>And the ritual that is a method for gaining spiritual accomplishment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-60"/>
                    <lg tid="67">
                        <l>“In a beautiful vessel,</l>
                        <l>Place many excellent articles</l>
                        <l>Such as food, drink, and so forth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-61"/>
                    <lg tid="68">
                        <l>“Through entering the absorption of emptiness,</l>
                        <l>From <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bruṃ</foreign> generate a beautiful vessel.</l>
                        <l>With <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kham</foreign> visualize food and drink</l>
                        <l>Filling all of space, and recite this mantra:</l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ āḥkāro mukhaṃ sarva­dharmāṇām ādyanta­panna tathā oṃ āḥ
                                hūṃ phaṭ svāhā</foreign>. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-62"/>
                    <lg tid="69">
                        <l>“Visualizing it as nectar, expand it greatly.</l>
                        <l>Through two expansions, purify it.</l>
                        <l>In space, from the letter <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hrīḥ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Visualize eight lotuses, immeasurably large. <ref cRef="F.160.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-63"/>
                    <lg tid="70">
                        <l> “Then invite the protector Vaiśravaṇa,</l>
                        <l>The central figure surrounded by a retinue of ten million yakṣas,</l>
                        <l>The recipient of the offerings of the eight nāga kings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-64"/>
                    <lg tid="71">
                        <l>“Imagine that the yakṣa kings—</l>
                        <l>Jambhala and Pūrṇabhadra,</l>
                        <l>Maṇibhadra, Kubera,</l>
                        <l>Samprajñāna, Guhyasthāna, Pāñcika,</l>
                        <l>And Bījakuṇḍalī—</l>
                        <l>Gather round the central figure like a retinue</l>
                        <l>In all the main and intermediate directions.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-65"/>
                    <lg tid="72">
                        <l>“The common retinue of ten million</l>
                        <l>Are behind the eight nāgas and yakṣas.</l>
                        <l>Next, for the invitation, use hooks</l>
                        <l>That are conjoined from the central deity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-66"/>
                    <lg tid="73">
                        <l>“Imagine them on mounts of lions and horses,</l>
                        <l>All with one face and two hands,</l>
                        <l>With victory banners, blazing with gems</l>
                        <l>And the vase of precious jewels.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-67"/>
                    <lg tid="74">
                        <l>“They hold swords blazing with gems,</l>
                        <l>Daggers and spears, celestial chariots, swords, and shields,</l>
                        <l>And various weaponry raised on high; visualize them thus.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-68"/>
                    <lg tid="75">
                        <l>“At the time of invitation, offer drum</l>
                        <l>And trumpet music, fruits and incense.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="76">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vaiśravaṇa saparivāra samāja jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Oṃ ve svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ vaiśravaṇa ākarṣaya hūṃ jaḥ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is the mantra for the invitation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-69"/>
                    <lg tid="77">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ amṛta­kuṇḍalī hana hana hūṃ phaṭ</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is the mantra for dispelling obstructors.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-70"/>
                    <lg tid="78">
                        <l>“Then with flowers and so forth,</l>
                        <l>Make pure offerings in the sky,</l>
                        <l>Offering them with joy.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-71"/>
                    <lg tid="79">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi ājñāpayati imaṃ
                                baligṛhnantu</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samayarakṣantu</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mama sarva­siddhiṃ me prayacchantu mama karmāmogha
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ vaiśravaṇāyā svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ jambhalāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ pūrṇavhadrāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ maṇibhadrāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ kuberāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ samprajñānāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ guhyasthānāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ pāñcikāya svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ bījakuṇḍaline svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>These are the mantras for offering the oblation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-72"/>
                    <lg tid="80">
                        <l>“Then make that offering to the guests.</l>
                        <l>Hooks of light rays shine forth,</l>
                        <l>And immediately they arrive.</l>
                        <l> Perform the ritual of equal enjoyment.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-73"/>
                    <trailer tid="243">This was the second chapter of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Vajra in the
                            Underworld</title>, “The Oblation.” </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="267">Chapter 3</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="268">Vaiśravaṇa</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-74"/>
                    <p tid="81">Then, for the benefit of those who wish to attain worldly accomplishment, the Blessed One entered
                        the absorption called <emph>the origination of all worldly wheels</emph>
                        <ref cRef="F.161.a"/> and emanated rays of light from the pores of his body. Vaiśravaṇa and his retinue
                        were thus inspired and gathered around him. He prostrated to the Blessed One, scattered dust made from
                        precious gems, and made this request: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-75"/>
                    <p tid="82">“Blessed One, I am the Dharma-upholding king named Vaiśravaṇa. If I myself were to proclaim a
                        secret in order to protect the Dharma of the pious and ensure that the Dharma abides for a long time,
                        would the Blessed One grant me an opportunity?” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-76"/>
                    <p tid="83">The Blessed One said, “Great King, excellent! Explain your secret well! I rejoice and give my
                        blessings. May all vajra holders also bless you. Speak well!” </p>
                    <p tid="84"> Then Vaiśravaṇa got up from his seat, prostrated to the Blessed One, and spoke his own
                        incantation: “<foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya hūṃ hūṃ paca paca chinda chinda
                            svāhā.</foreign>” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-77"/>
                    <p tid="85"> Once he had spoken these words, he requested the Blessed One, “O Blessed One, the accomplishment
                        of this, my mantra, is excellent. Whoever wants to accomplish my state of being should arrange great
                        offerings in the three times. To make the offering to me and my retinue, the practitioner should remain
                        with one-pointed concentration in an isolated place. A practitioner of the blessed Vajrapāṇi must recite
                        my mantra ten thousand times, and then accomplish the activities. One who thus accomplishes my state of
                        being and my activity should offer an oblation and make vast offerings to me and to my retinue. The mantra
                        to recite for making vast offerings and offering the oblation to me and my retinue is this: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-78"/>
                    <lg tid="86">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ jambhalāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ pūrṇabhadrāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ maṇibhadrāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ kuberāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ samprajñānāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ guhyasthānāya svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ pāñcikāya svāhā </foreign>
                            <ref cRef="F.161.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ bījakuṇḍaline svāhā </foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-79"/>
                    <p tid="87">“Know that these are the mantras both for making offerings and giving an oblation to me and my
                        retinue.</p>
                    <p tid="88">“Then, with respect to accomplishing my activity, I requested the Blessed One to bless me with his
                        explanation. The explanation of the activity is this: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-80"/>
                    <lg tid="89">
                        <l>“Whoever wishes to gain accomplishment</l>
                        <l>Must know the stages</l>
                        <l>Of killing, the burnt offering, and the suppression ritual.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-81"/>
                    <lg tid="90">
                        <l>“Make an effigy out of beeswax</l>
                        <l>Of the target—those hostile toward the teachings.</l>
                        <l>Draw him, make him enter, and then take control.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-82"/>
                    <lg tid="91">
                        <l>“The eighteen-syllable mantra</l>
                        <l>Forcefully strikes down in the three times,</l>
                        <l>And suddenly his spirit is broken.</l>
                        <l>There is no doubt that the target will be slain.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-83"/>
                    <lg tid="92">
                        <l>“If one is practicing the burnt offerings </l>
                        <l>From among peaceful, increasing, magnetizing, and wrathful activities,</l>
                        <l>Here one should perform liberation wrathfully.</l>
                        <l>Thoroughly burn with a blazing fire.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-275" index="5">Translation based on the spelling in the Yongle, Peking, Narthang, and Lhasa Kangyurs: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mer sbar.</foreign> The Degé Kangyur has:<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> ner
                                    sba. </foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-84"/>
                    <lg tid="93">
                        <l>“With respect to the superior, average, and inferior hearth,</l>
                        <l>Construct the superior one in three measures, the average in two,</l>
                        <l>And the inferior in whatever measure is possible.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-85"/>
                    <lg tid="94">
                        <l>“With fuel of thorny wood,</l>
                        <l>Great wrath is accomplished.</l>
                        <l>Burn dough and mustard seeds in the fire;</l>
                        <l>Dissolve the body, speech, and mind of the aggressor</l>
                        <l>Into the substances, and make the burnt offering.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-86"/>
                    <lg tid="95">
                        <l>“Imagine the retinue of yakṣas in the fire</l>
                        <l>And present them with the burnt substances,</l>
                        <l>Or scatter the activity-fire yakṣas with the substances.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-276" index="6">We are unsure about this line: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">las me gnod
                                    sbyin rdzas kyis brab.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>However you do it, it will be accomplished.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-87"/>
                    <lg tid="96">
                        <l>“At that time, also, with these words of praise</l>
                        <l>Focus your mind one-pointedly and offer praise:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="97">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Hūṃ!</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>All-conquering, terrifying yakṣa and the rest,</l>
                        <l>Terrorizing with your noxious brilliant heat,</l>
                        <l>Bellowing loudly with wrathful splendor.</l>
                        <l>Homage and praise to you and your retinue!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-88"/>
                    <lg tid="98">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> puṣpe hūṃ
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> dhupe hūṃ
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> dīpaṃ hūṃ
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> gandhe hūṃ
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> naivedye hūṃ svāhā
                            </foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-89"/>
                    <lg tid="99">
                        <l>“Worship the central deity and also his retinue;</l>
                        <l>Make offerings in sequence.</l>
                        <l>Recite, spreading secret mantras;</l>
                        <l> Perform the projection and reabsorption.</l>
                        <l>This is the ordinary form of propagation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="100">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vaiśravaṇaya chegemo māraya phaṭ svāhā</foreign>
                            <ref cRef="F.162.a "/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-90"/>
                    <lg tid="101">
                        <l>“For the retinue, just as for the main deity,</l>
                        <l>Worship them with their own incantations.</l>
                        <l>Fully supported by incantations,</l>
                        <l>Imagine that they crush them into dust.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-91"/>
                    <lg tid="102">
                        <l>“Enjoin them to perform activity and give an oblation.</l>
                        <l>As for the stages of sprinkling and offering the oblation,</l>
                        <l>Offer them in order.</l>
                        <l>The sequence for the peaceful activity is as follows:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-92"/>
                    <lg tid="103">
                        <l>“On a hearth of sufficient size,</l>
                        <l>Offer the burning substances and so forth.</l>
                        <l>Having conquered the evil deeds of body, speech, and mind,</l>
                        <l>Transform them into the essence of wisdom fire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-93"/>
                    <lg tid="104">
                        <l>“Discard the vessel and the hearth.</l>
                        <l>Completely burn all grahas there,</l>
                        <l>And also make a ransom rite to pacify the great obstructors.</l>
                        <l> In order to increase and magnetize</l>
                        <l>For the activity and specific stages,</l>
                        <l>Know that the details of the shape of the hearth</l>
                        <l>Are in accordance with the previously explained activities.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-94"/>
                    <lg tid="105">
                        <l>“As for the substantial offering,</l>
                        <l>With the stages of red and yellow firewood and so forth:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="106">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vaiśravaṇāya dhanapuṣṭiṃ kuru ye svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term> vaśaṃ kuru
                                svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ vaiśravaṇāye śāntiṃ kuru svāhā</foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-95"/>
                    <lg tid="107">
                        <l>“Just as for the main deity, for the retinue also</l>
                        <l>Make offerings with the incantatory substances.</l>
                        <l>Offer the burned substances of dough,</l>
                        <l>Mustard seeds, sweets, and so forth in sequence.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-96"/>
                    <lg tid="108">
                        <l>“The four activities are perfectly accomplished.</l>
                        <l>With superior diligence, they are fully accomplished.</l>
                        <l>With middling and lesser diligence, know that</l>
                        <l>They are accomplished in a middling and lesser way.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-97"/>
                    <p tid="109">Then Vaiśravaṇa and his retinue declared to the Blessed One, “Blessed One, whoever engages in the
                        practices that we have explained here should continually worship the Blessed Vajrapāṇi and the yakṣas with
                        the three white substances. He must completely avoid alcohol. He must acquire meats that are suitable and
                            auspicious.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-277" index="7">Tibetan: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">drang bar bya.</foreign>
                        </note> If we fail to accomplish, properly and one-pointedly, the activities that are our accomplishments,
                        then we will have insulted the Blessed One and we will have failed to protect the Dharma. This is our
                        oath. <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ <term type="ignore">vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            arthakathama.</foreign>” <ref cRef="F.162.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-98"/>
                    <p tid="110">“Great Vaiśravaṇa, that is excellent. So very excellent!” said the Blessed One. “So very
                        excellent! The secret of which you have spoken will be of great benefit for the people of the future. In
                        order that their benefit will certainly be accomplished, I also will pronounce this mantra. Listen!”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-99"/>
                    <p tid="111">“Excellent!” said Vaiśravaṇa and the others to the Blessed One, and listened accordingly.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-100"/>
                    <p tid="112">The Blessed One then said, “<foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṃ vajrapāṇi nīlāmbara­dhara
                            vajrasphoṭa hūṃ phaṭ svāhā</foreign>. This incantation is a mantra that brings control over
                        activities. Great Vaiśravaṇa brings about possession of the secret just as he promised.”</p>
                    <p tid="113">“That is so,” said the yakṣas, and vanished. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-101"/>
                    <trailer tid="244"> This was the third chapter of <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Vajra in the
                            Underworld</title>, the chapter on Vaiśravaṇa. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="269">Chapter 4</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="270">The Wheel of Suppression</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-102"/>
                    <p tid="114">Then, once again, the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi requested the Blessed One, “Lord, for the sake of
                        sentient beings of the future, please teach a wheel that strikes all wicked ones!”</p>
                    <p tid="115">The Blessed One mentally consented to this request, yet remained completely silent. Instead he
                        projected an all-pervading light from his heart center that embraced all sentient beings with love.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-103"/>
                    <p tid="116">Then he told Vajrapāṇi, “Vajrapāṇi, I shall now teach a wheel that strikes the obstructors within
                        the ground below. So listen one-pointedly, and I will teach.” </p>
                    <p tid="117">Vajrapāṇi listened accordingly, and the Blessed One began to speak: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-104"/>
                    <lg tid="118">
                        <l>“Whoever wishes to construct such a diagram </l>
                        <l>Should go to pleasant and solitary places</l>
                        <l>And perform the practice of Vajrapāṇi.</l>
                        <l>Visualize the world and its contents as Vajracaṇḍa.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-105"/>
                    <lg tid="119">
                        <l>“From the element of wind up until the central mountain,</l>
                        <l>Imagine it to consist of enlightened bodies as numerous as there are particles.</l>
                        <l>Amid this, cultivate the practice of Vajrapāṇi.</l>
                        <l>His feet are placed on the holder of the hare.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-106"/>
                    <lg tid="120">
                        <l>“On this moon, the size of the trichiliocosm,</l>
                        <l>Visualize the great obstructor, utterly shaking.</l>
                        <l>Vajrapāṇi’s body shines with the splendor of a thousand suns.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-107"/>
                    <lg tid="121">
                        <l>“Visualize that this light, which is unbearable to watch,</l>
                        <l>Burns away all obstructors without exception.</l>
                        <l>The mantra chain recited from the tongue <ref cRef="F.163.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Is seen to fill the trichiliocosm.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-108"/>
                    <lg tid="122">
                        <l>“The eight adorning nāgas</l>
                        <l>Release a giant breath of steam</l>
                        <l>That terrifies all gods and nāgas.</l>
                        <l>Wrathful ones are projected from his heart center</l>
                        <l>And, like the winds at the end of an eon, cause them to disperse.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-109"/>
                    <lg tid="123">
                        <l>“With his hand, he strikes with the vajra;</l>
                        <l>Like a bolt shot from a crossbow, it strikes down.</l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hūṃ hūṃ</foreign> resounds like thunder; </l>
                        <l> They are thoroughly suppressed by his voice.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-110"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>“Act like that, and all will be accomplished;</l>
                        <l>Karmic torment will come to an end.</l>
                        <l>If one does not know Vajrapāṇi,</l>
                        <l>Other accomplishments will be inferior.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-111"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>“Whatever is accomplished hereby accomplishes all—</l>
                        <l>In particular, the supreme and the common.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-112"/>
                    <trailer tid="245"> This was the fourth chapter on the wheel of suppression from <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="271">Chapter 5</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="272">The Ritual for Drawing the Diagram</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-113"/>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>Then, at another time, the Vajra Holder</l>
                        <l>Taught the ritual of the diagram:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-114"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>“On a piece of birch bark or rind,</l>
                        <l>Draw a wheel</l>
                        <l>With twenty-one sections.</l>
                        <l>Commence this on the waxing phase of the moon,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-115"/>
                    <lg tid="128">
                        <l>“And write, with a one-pointed mind.</l>
                        <l>In the center, place the wrathful syllable.</l>
                        <l>In the second, the syllable of the wealth holder.</l>
                        <l>In the third, comes the vajra.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-116"/>
                    <lg tid="129">
                        <l> “In the fourth, place the first syllable of water.</l>
                        <l> In the fifth, place the <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṇi</foreign>.</l>
                        <l>At the four borders, write the essence mantra for killing the target.</l>
                        <l>These are the inner sections.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-117"/>
                    <lg tid="130">
                        <l>“On the twelve outer sections</l>
                        <l>Are the twelve syllables, omitting <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṃ</foreign>.</l>
                        <l>On these the secret mantra is as follows:</l>
                    </lg>
                        <p tid="255">
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nīlāmbara­dhara­vajra­pāṇi hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                        </p>

                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-118"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l> “This completed wheel</l>
                        <l>Should be rolled up and fixed to the heart center of the target;</l>
                        <l>It should be rolled up from the front edge.</l>
                        <l>Then the fire-offering ritual should be performed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-119"/>
                    <lg tid="132">
                        <l>“If one wishes to subdue,</l>
                        <l>The diagram should be completed as before.</l>
                        <l>At the end, perform the ritual of subjugation.</l>
                        <l>Place the diagram in a fresh clay cup</l>
                        <l>And draw a crossed vajra on the lid.</l>
                        <l>Closing it with clay,</l>
                        <l>Temples and the like can be suppressed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-120"/>
                    <lg tid="133">
                        <l>“If you prefer not to have sections,</l>
                        <l>Make a wheel with twelve spokes.</l>
                        <l>In the center, place and affix</l>
                        <l>A <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign> and the name of the target.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-121"/>
                    <lg tid="134">
                        <l> “The remaining twelve are placed on the spokes. <ref cRef="F.163.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>When the drawing is complete, insert it in the heart center.</l>
                        <l>Summon, usher, and so forth, then burn.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-122"/>
                    <lg tid="135">
                        <l> “Perform the ritual for suppression of the unwanted; </l>
                        <l>From that time onward, there is auspiciousness.</l>
                        <l> Whenever the diagram is drawn,</l>
                        <l>There is no doubt that things will occur as desired.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-123"/>
                    <lg tid="136">
                        <l>“Just like dry grass being burnt up by flames,</l>
                        <l>The person will be unable to remain.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-124"/>
                    <trailer tid="246"> This was the fifth chapter on the ritual for drawing the diagram from <title xml:lang="en">The Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="273">Chapter 6</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="274">The Stages of Fire Offering</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-125"/>
                    <p tid="137">Then, once again, Vajrapāṇi asked the Blessed One, “Lord, since everything is the domain of the
                        profound, does one get liberated through such rituals as fire offerings, or not? Please clear away my
                        doubts!” </p>
                    <p tid="138">The Blessed One replied:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-126"/>
                    <lg tid="139">
                        <l>“Vajrapāṇi! Great compassion,</l>
                        <l>Removal through the power of faith,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-278" index="8">Tibetan:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab snyams.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>The maṇḍala endowed with substantial riches,</l>
                        <l>And the activity of the fire offering—these you should know.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-127"/>
                    <lg tid="140">
                        <l>“If your stream of being keeps samaya vows as your pledge,</l>
                        <l>You will be liberated through attributes.</l>
                        <l>Without a maṇḍala, fire offering, substances, and so forth,</l>
                        <l>Spiritual accomplishments will not be achieved.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-128"/>
                    <lg tid="141">
                        <l>“Therefore be diligent in the activity of fire offering.</l>
                        <l>Among the fire offerings of the four enlightened activities,</l>
                        <l>The stages of the wrathful one is as follows:</l>
                        <l>In the center of a maṇḍala of four cubits,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-129"/>
                    <lg tid="142">
                        <l>“There is a triangle of one cubit;</l>
                        <l>It should be dug to a depth of half a cubit.</l>
                        <l>Outside there are three levels;</l>
                        <l>Draw the features of a vajra in the middle.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-130"/>
                    <lg tid="143">
                        <l> “At the three levels, draw the three points of a vajra</l>
                        <l>Encircled by a chain.</l>
                        <l>In the intermediate spaces, draw iron hooks.</l>
                        <l>A piece of thorny wood</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-131"/>
                    <lg tid="144">
                        <l>“The size of a cubit is very auspicious.</l>
                        <l>Substances such as poison, blood, and black mustard seeds</l>
                        <l>Should be gradually known.</l>
                        <l>Oneself, through the yoga of the deity,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-132"/>
                    <lg tid="145">
                        <l>“Invites the wrathful wisdom,</l>
                        <l>Visualized in the form that tames the three worlds.</l>
                        <l>Perform the stages of worship.</l>
                        <l>For that, the mantra of the fire offering to be uttered is this:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-133"/>
                    <p tid="146">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara oṃ vajra­jvalānala hana sarva­duḥkha
                            sarva­vighna samma kuru­nīlāmbara­dhara vajra­pāṇi chegemo māraya hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="147">
                        <l> “Say this while burning the substances.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-134"/>
                    <lg tid="148">
                        <l>“From poison, blood, black mustard, and salt,</l>
                        <l>Create the form, accomplish it, and burn it. <ref cRef="F.164.a"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="149">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi <term type="ignore">yakṣa</term>
                            khādaya khādaya bandhaya bandhaya mohaya mohaya sha hum ānaya hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="150">
                        <l> “This was the mantra for scattering the form.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-135"/>
                    <p tid="151">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi sha hum gṛham ākarṣaya hūṃ jaḥ
                            jaḥ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="152">
                        <l>“This was the mantra for summoning beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-136"/>
                    <lg tid="153">
                        <l>“Having performed the fire offering in that manner,</l>
                        <l>Go to a dried-up river, fell a nāga tree,</l>
                        <l>And make a large fire with elephant dung.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-279" index="9">We
                                are unsure of this line: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">glang chen g.yang ltung me chen ’bar.
                                </foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Should illness and disease occur,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-137"/>
                    <lg tid="154">
                        <l>“Perform the activity of supreme pacification.</l>
                        <l>Dig a suitable spherical fire pit in three levels;</l>
                        <l>It should be one cubit wide</l>
                        <l>And half a cubit deep.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-138"/>
                    <lg tid="155">
                        <l>“Then perform the ritual of peaceful activity.</l>
                        <l>If done in this manner, there is no doubt that one obtains</l>
                        <l>Spiritual accomplishments with the marks of success.</l>
                        <l>Vajrapāṇi, Vajra Holder!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-139"/>
                    <lg tid="156">
                        <l> “With devotion, keep the meaning of the tantra,</l>
                        <l> And be diligent for the sake of living beings!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-140"/>
                    <lg tid="157">
                        <l>“O! This most secret great tantra</l>
                        <l>Grants great blessings from the start.</l>
                        <l> It was spoken by the teacher Vajradhara.</l>
                        <l>Be diligent in its practice.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-141"/>
                    <trailer tid="247"> This was the sixth chapter on the stages of fire offering from <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="275">Chapter 7</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="276">The Wheel of Expulsion</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-142"/>
                    <lg tid="158">
                        <l>Then the teacher, the Vajra Holder,</l>
                        <l>The Great Glorious One, stood up on his seat.</l>
                        <l>He gazed at Vajrapāṇi and said:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-143"/>
                    <lg tid="159">
                        <l>“One should know the ritual of activity.</l>
                        <l>With substances such as poison,</l>
                        <l> Produce the form that you wish for,</l>
                        <l>Then insert the diagram at the heart center.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-144"/>
                    <lg tid="160">
                        <l>“Visualize yourself as the deity of activity,</l>
                        <l>And place it in a box.</l>
                        <l>Tie it with five strings of various colors,</l>
                        <l>Then summon your target with the hook at the heart center.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-145"/>
                    <lg tid="161">
                        <l> “Next recite the thirteen letters of the diagram.</l>
                        <l>When the signs of shivering and trembling occur,</l>
                        <l>Throw it in the middle of a river.</l>
                        <l>If the signs should not occur,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-146"/>
                    <lg tid="162">
                        <l> “Mix the fluid of datura, </l>
                        <l>With blood and poison, and apply it.</l>
                        <l>Then burn it in the fire of a thorny tree.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="163">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi stambhaya mohaya bandhaya dāhanaya
                            hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-147"/>
                    <lg tid="164">
                        <l>“Fumigate it at the three times,</l>
                        <l>And utter many negative words.</l>
                        <l>Then throw it in the water, using this mantra:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="165">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-148"/>
                    <lg tid="166">
                        <l> “Roll it around in pigment and throw it away; <ref cRef="F.164.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Imagine that you throw it into a salty ocean.</l>
                        <l>Then, for the sake of irreversibility,</l>
                        <l>Recite this mantra continuously:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="167">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi hūṃ hūṃ stambhaya nan
                            phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-149"/>
                    <lg tid="168">
                        <l>“Recite this continuously.</l>
                        <l> Then the activity will certainly be accomplished.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-150"/>
                    <trailer tid="248"> This was the seventh chapter on the wheel of expulsion from <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="277">Chapter 8</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="278">Mantra</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-151"/>
                    <p tid="169">Then the Blessed One, the Vajra Holder, taught this chapter on mantra for the sake of living
                        beings:</p>
                    <p tid="170">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ nīlāmbara­dhara vajrapāṇi hūṃ hūṃ phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-152"/>
                    <lg tid="171">
                        <l>“The root mantra of the Blessed One accomplishes all activities;</l>
                        <l>This is the secret of the awakened mind of all buddhas.</l>
                        <l>It accomplishes all activity, even without practice;</l>
                        <l>With the vajra fists, you accomplish the binding of all mudrās.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-153"/>
                    <lg tid="172">
                        <l>“With vajra confidence, you accomplish all samaya vows!</l>
                        <l>With the vajra smile, you are affectionate toward all sentient beings.</l>
                        <l>By uttering the vajra <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>, you make everyone
                            mute.</l>
                        <l>Through the vajra lotus, you gain the spiritual accomplishment of traversing the sky.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-154"/>
                    <lg tid="173">
                        <l>“With the tail of the peacock, you tame all nāgas.</l>
                        <l>With the diagram, you kill all enemies.</l>
                        <l>If you wish to accomplish wealth, perform the water offering to Jambhala.</l>
                        <l>If you wish to repel obstacle makers, do so through absorption.</l>
                        <l>With the vajra iron hook, you summon all.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-155"/>
                    <lg tid="174">
                        <l>“Protect against epidemics with the kuśa grass pock.</l>
                        <l> If you wish to accomplish nāgas, use the shoots of hardwood trees and nectar.</l>
                        <l>If you wish to destroy an opposing army, do so with frankincense.</l>
                        <l>For all actions, recite a hundred thousand mantras.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-156"/>
                    <trailer tid="249"> This was the eighth chapter on mantra from <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Vajra in
                            the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="279">Chapter 9</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="280">Certainty and Purity</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-157"/>
                    <lg tid="175">
                        <l>“Then, moreover, the certainty of recitation</l>
                        <l>Will be taught now.</l>
                        <l>Whoever wishes to gain spiritual accomplishments</l>
                        <l>Should fully possess commitments and pledges,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-158"/>
                    <lg tid="176">
                        <l>“And visualize oneself as the deity of activity.</l>
                        <l>Then invite the wrathful wisdom.</l>
                        <l>Summon and the rest with <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jaḥ hūṃ vaṃ hoḥ.</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>In your heart, on a moon, is the mantra chain.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-159"/>
                    <lg tid="177">
                        <l>“Visualize it like a silver viper,</l>
                        <l>Swift, free, and clear—without vagueness. <ref cRef="F.165.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mentally perform a concentrated recitation,</l>
                        <l>Then make the fivefold offering.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-160"/>
                    <lg tid="178">
                        <l>“Through this fully concentrated recitation,</l>
                        <l>All desired spiritual accomplishments will surely be accomplished.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-161"/>
                    <lg tid="179">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ āḥ hūṃ.</foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="180">“That is the mantra for the blessings of enlightened body, speech, and mind.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-162"/>
                    <lg tid="181">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"> “Oṃ vajrapāṇi abhiṣiñca mām.</foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="182">
                        <l>“Such is the mantra for bestowing empowerment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-163"/>
                    <lg tid="183">
                        <l>
                            <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vajrapāṇi tiṣṭha hūṃ.</foreign>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="184">
                        <l>“That is the mantra for stabilizing enlightened mind.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-164"/>
                    <lg tid="185">
                        <l>“Through all the secrets of enlightened body and mind,</l>
                        <l>And enlightened speech in their entirety,</l>
                        <l>One will quickly meet with awakening.</l>
                        <l>Whenever someone is practicing diligently,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-165"/>
                    <lg tid="186">
                        <l>“The result will swiftly be attained within a single life.</l>
                        <l>The nondual nature is the vajra possessor;</l>
                        <l>It fully pervades the vajra sky.</l>
                        <l>It is inexpressible, nonconceptual, the meaning of thatness.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-166"/>
                    <lg tid="187">
                        <l>“Let go in this spontaneously accomplished state.</l>
                        <l>On the form of <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign> and <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">āḥ</foreign>,</l>
                        <l>Like a moon reflected in water,</l>
                        <l>Meditate continually, with an undistracted mind.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-167"/>
                    <lg tid="188">
                        <l>“Amazing! The Protector, the Blessed One,</l>
                        <l>Is the utterly supreme victor.</l>
                        <l>Amazing! This emanated body</l>
                        <l>Has no focus on sound.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-168"/>
                    <lg tid="189">
                        <l>“It is the domain of all joyful ones.</l>
                        <l>This natural luminosity is purity;</l>
                        <l>It abides as supreme awakening.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-169"/>
                    <trailer tid="250"> This was the ninth chapter on certainty and purity from <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of
                            the Vajra in the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="281">Chapter 10</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="282">Protection</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-170"/>
                    <lg tid="190">
                        <l>Then the teacher Vajradhara</l>
                        <l>Gazed at the protector of beings</l>
                        <l>And taught the ritual of protection:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-171"/>
                    <lg tid="191">
                        <l>“Vajrapāṇi, listen well!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="192">
                        <l>“Those beings who are seized by wicked ones</l>
                        <l>Should skillfully craft an image</l>
                        <l>Of an animal in pure copper</l>
                        <l>And fill its interior with silver and the like.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-172"/>
                    <lg tid="193">
                        <l>“Once filled, it should be well concealed</l>
                        <l>In a desirable place or on one’s own body.</l>
                        <l>This is the best protection.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-173"/>
                    <lg tid="194">
                        <l>“A reliquary of the bliss-gone ones together with its relics</l>
                        <l>Should be skillfully fashioned and consecrated.</l>
                        <l>If it is concealed wherever harm might occur,</l>
                        <l>There will be peace by pronouncing the power of truth.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-174"/>
                    <lg tid="195">
                        <l>“The buddhas, as numerous as the grains of sand in the Ganges,</l>
                        <l>Taught these incantation mantras</l>
                        <l>To many creatures, such as birds—</l>
                        <l>All pleasant and beautiful animals.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-175"/>
                    <lg tid="196">
                        <l>“With these mantras, one should consecrate</l>
                        <l>One hundred and eight blue cords and strings of silk. </l>
                        <l>Invoke the truth and perform a dedication; <ref cRef="F.165.b"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>When the oblation is given, there will be pacification.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-176"/>
                    <lg tid="197">
                        <l>“In a clean vessel, such as a cup,</l>
                        <l>Place such things as medicine and silk.</l>
                        <l>Make an offering of flowers, incense, and so forth.</l>
                        <l>If it is hidden in the ground,</l>
                        <l>All harmful influences will become pacified.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-177"/>
                    <lg tid="198">
                        <l>“Braid together three white cords</l>
                        <l>And make twenty-one knots.</l>
                        <l>Accomplish it and make the offering of accomplishment,</l>
                        <l>Then tie it around the neck of a victor.</l>
                        <l>It is certain to reverse all obstacles.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-178"/>
                    <lg tid="199">
                        <l>“If one smears the body, in equal measure,</l>
                        <l>With mustard seed, clarified butter, and brimstone,</l>
                        <l>One will be freed from the grasp of vicious beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-179"/>
                    <lg tid="200">
                        <l>“If one practices during the month of Kārttika,</l>
                        <l>On the <distinct>bagunada</distinct> flower,</l>
                        <l>And the <distinct>dahunada</distinct> fruit, </l>
                        <l>All vicious ones will have nowhere to remain.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-180"/>
                    <lg tid="201">
                        <l>“With the hairs of tiger, bear, and jackal,</l>
                        <l>One will be free from vicious ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-181"/>
                    <lg tid="202">
                        <l>“If, in a waterfall, a lake, and so forth,</l>
                        <l>The acts of protecting the body are perfectly performed,</l>
                        <l>It will be the supreme protection.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-182"/>
                    <lg tid="203">
                        <l>“You should accept the Vajra Holder!</l>
                        <l>Then, just as the full moon</l>
                        <l>Is freed from the grasp of the clouds,</l>
                        <l> So shall you be free.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-183"/>
                    <trailer tid="251"> This was the tenth chapter on protection from <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Vajra
                            in the Underworld</title>. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="283">Chapter 11</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="284">The Arrangement of Mantras</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-184"/>
                    <p tid="204">Vajrapāṇi then said these well-spoken words:</p>
                    <lg tid="205">
                        <l>“The ritual of arranging mantras,</l>
                        <l>How might that be?”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-185"/>
                    <lg tid="206">
                        <l>“Vajra Holder, please listen well.</l>
                        <l>Vajra Holder, listen well,</l>
                        <l>And I will teach you the arrangement of mantras.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-186"/>
                    <lg tid="207">
                        <l>“In a pleasing, triangular maṇḍala,</l>
                        <l>Draw a lotus with eight petals.</l>
                        <l>This accomplishes all desired aims.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-187"/>
                    <lg tid="208">
                        <l>“Within that, arrange the secret mantras.</l>
                        <l>In the center, place the lord of syllables.</l>
                        <l>In the fifth of the fourth,</l>
                        <l>Place the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">i</foreign>. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-188"/>
                    <lg tid="209">
                        <l>“In the third of the final,</l>
                        <l>Place the last of the fifth.</l>
                        <l>Then place the fourth of the fifth.</l>
                        <l>Next place the second in the last.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-189"/>
                    <lg tid="210">
                        <l>“Then place the fourth of the fourth,</l>
                        <l>And the second in the last.</l>
                        <l>Then in the third of the fifth,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-190"/>
                    <lg tid="211">
                        <l>“And the third of the second,</l>
                        <l>One should place a <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ra</foreign>.</l>
                        <l>Then, in the first of the fifth,</l>
                        <l>The syllable ah should be placed.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-191"/>
                    <lg tid="212">
                        <l>“Then, in the last of the third, <ref cRef="F.166.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Place the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">i</foreign>.</l>
                        <l>In the fourth of the seventh,</l>
                        <l>Place the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ū</foreign>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-192"/>
                    <lg tid="213">
                        <l>“By suppressing with emptiness, it becomes two.</l>
                        <l>In the second of the fifth,</l>
                        <l>Apply the first of the third.</l>
                        <l>The thirteen syllables are the incantation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-193"/>
                    <lg tid="214">
                        <l>“If they are recited diligently with love,</l>
                        <l>All desired spiritual accomplishments are certain.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-194"/>
                    <lg tid="215">
                        <l>Amazing, thus spoke the vajra possessor.</l>
                        <l>This is the king of mantras, the unsurpassable path,</l>
                        <l>That manifests the spiritual accomplishments of Vajrapāṇi. </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-195"/>
                    <trailer tid="252">This was the eleventh chapter on the arrangement of mantras from <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="285">Chapter 12</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="286"> Bestowing Empowerment on Students</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-196"/>
                    <lg tid="216">
                        <l>The teacher, Vajradhara,</l>
                        <l>Emanated light from his eyes.</l>
                        <l>Then, in order to ripen students,</l>
                        <l>He taught the ritual of conferring empowerment:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-197"/>
                    <lg tid="217">
                        <l>“The vajra master, the great ascetic,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-280" index="10">Tibetan:
                                    <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dka’ thub che.</foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Has obtained empowerment, replete with secrets.</l>
                        <l>He is disciplined, upright, and a great spiritual friend.</l>
                        <l>In the excellent state of little movement, he obtained the awakened mind.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-281" index="11">We are unsure of this line: <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">g.yo chung
                                    ngang bzang byang sems thob. </foreign>
                            </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Learned in the maṇḍala ritual,</l>
                        <l>He should bestow empowerment on the foremost student.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-198"/>
                    <lg tid="218">
                        <l>“For that, in a place such as a beautiful temple,</l>
                        <l>First train well in disciplined conduct,</l>
                        <l>Then perform the ritual of the ground.</l>
                        <l>Examine, purify, and prepare,</l>
                        <l>Then make offerings and requests.</l>
                        <l>Examine by means of signs in dreams.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-199"/>
                    <lg tid="219">
                        <l>“The fire offering should be performed</l>
                        <l>A total of 108 times with the peaceful ritual.</l>
                        <l>Make offerings to the bhūtas and instruct them;</l>
                        <l>They abide in the center of the maṇḍala.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-200"/>
                    <lg tid="220">
                        <l>“From <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>, visualize a great vajra.</l>
                        <l>From <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhrūṃ</foreign>, visualize the great celestial
                            palace.</l>
                        <l>The light from the two eyes, the sun and the moon,</l>
                        <l>Annihilates all obstructing forces without exception.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-201"/>
                    <lg tid="221">
                        <l>“With the dance movement of the great vajra,</l>
                        <l>Circumambulate the ground three times</l>
                        <l>And smear it with the five substances of a cow,</l>
                        <l>Then arrange the deities in a single group.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-202"/>
                    <lg tid="222">
                        <l>“Make offerings, praises, and requests.</l>
                        <l>Place the vase especially well,</l>
                        <l>Then ripen the student in the ritual.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-203"/>
                    <lg tid="223">
                        <l>“The ritual of threads and colors</l>
                        <l>Should be done just as the activity ritual.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-204"/>
                    <lg tid="224">
                        <l>“Then, with the blue blindfold,</l>
                        <l>Let the students enter.</l>
                        <l>On the vow holders, bestow the fivefold empowerment:</l>
                        <l>The empowerments of the vase, the vajra,</l>
                        <l>The bell, the crown, and the name. <ref cRef="F.166.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-205"/>
                    <lg tid="225">
                        <l>“The activity ritual is the same.</l>
                        <l>On the fourteenth and the thirteenth day,</l>
                        <l>Introduce the students to the activity.</l>
                        <l>The blessings should be transferred gradually,</l>
                        <l>While confidence should be produced immediately.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-206"/>
                    <lg tid="226">
                        <l>“This stainless tantra, the precious essence,</l>
                        <l>Is the root of all tantras.</l>
                        <l>It contains the sacred bestowal of empowerment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-207"/>
                    <lg tid="227">
                        <l>“Virtuous vow-holders who have been consecrated</l>
                        <l>Through the empowerment based upon the activities of ripening,</l>
                        <l>Which is taught in the supreme tantras,</l>
                        <l>Should please the sacred one with gifts.</l>
                        <l>This is the rite for perfecting liberation, for consecration,</l>
                        <l>And for the maturing of students.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-208"/>
                    <trailer tid="253">This was the twelfth chapter on bestowing empowerment on the students from <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>. </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="287">Chapter 13</head>
                    <head type="chapterTitle" tid="288">Establishing the Secret</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-209"/>
                    <p tid="228">Then the bodhisattva Vajrapāṇi requested the Blessed One, “Lord, for the sake of all sentient
                        beings, please explain the secret of enlightened mind.”</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-210"/>
                    <p tid="229">The Blessed One answered this request by saying:</p>
                    <lg tid="230">
                        <l>“Vajrapāṇi, terrifying one, </l>
                        <l>It is excellent that you consider the welfare of others so diligently.</l>
                        <l>In the degenerated age, whoever wishes</l>
                        <l>To tame those sentient beings that are difficult to tame,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-211"/>
                    <lg tid="231">
                        <l>“Should first give rise to the mind of awakening,</l>
                        <l>And completely perfect the two accumulations.</l>
                        <l>On a lotus base within a jeweled vessel,</l>
                        <l>Array the Lord of Secrets in the center,</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-212"/>
                    <lg tid="232">
                        <l>“Surrounded by the eight great nāgas on eight petals,</l>
                        <l>Each with the head of a snake.</l>
                        <l>When washed and pure,</l>
                        <l>Perform the practice of the deity of activity.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-213"/>
                    <lg tid="233">
                        <l>“First invite and make offerings,</l>
                        <l>Then recite while projecting and absorbing oneself and the deity.</l>
                        <l>Think that the eight nāgas are pacified.</l>
                        <l>Thus, from <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign> and the rope of <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>,</l>
                        <l>The one to be accomplished is turned into a mass of light, </l>
                        <l>And, in an instant, caught within the <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-214"/>
                    <p tid="234">
                        <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">“Oṃ vajrakrodha ahicaṇḍa phaṭ.</foreign>
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="235">
                        <l>“With ten thousand repetitions, one will certainly be freed from the grahas.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-215"/>
                    <lg tid="236">
                        <l>“Vajrapāṇi,</l>
                        <l>Your radiation and absorption of enlightened mind is secret.</l>
                        <l>Cover the body of the one to be accomplished in color,</l>
                        <l>And cut it with the radiation and absorption of the garland of the great <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">hūṃ</foreign>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-216"/>
                    <lg tid="237">
                        <l>“When examining the great substances,</l>
                        <l>One will surely be freed from grahas.</l>
                        <l>However, if this should not accomplish it,</l>
                        <l>Reverse the mantra chain and do the recitation.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-217"/>
                    <lg tid="238">
                        <l>“Having cut with the vajra chain, <ref cRef="F.167.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>It will be accomplished without any doubt.</l>
                        <l>The supreme ritual for repelling the obstructors below</l>
                        <l>Appears like a wish-fulfilling jewel.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-218"/>
                    <lg tid="239">
                        <l>“This great tantra is the ultimate secret,</l>
                        <l>Which, without doubt, is victorious among the three vehicles</l>
                        <l>And supreme among all protective intentions.”</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-219"/>
                    <p tid="240">As soon as the Blessed One had spoken, the retinues of the family, including Vajrapāṇi, along
                        with all the hosts of deities, rejoiced and praised what the Blessed Vajradhara had said.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-220"/>
                    <trailer tid="254"> This was the thirteenth chapter on establishing the secret from <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Glorious Tantra of the Vajra in the Underworld</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="289">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-221"/>
                    <p tid="241">The translation was completed by the Kashmiri scholar Celu and the Tibetan translator Phakpa
                        Sherab.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="290">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="291">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="292">Tibetan Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-222">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das phyag na rdo rje gos sngon po can gyi rgyud ces bya ba
                            (Bhagavan­nīlāmbaradhara­vajrapāṇi­tantra­nāma)</title>. Toh 498, Degé Kangyur vol. 87 (rgyud ’bum,
                        da), folios 158a.6–167a.3.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-223">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcom ldan ’das phyag na rdo rje gos sngon po can gyi rgyud ces bya ba.
                        </title>bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug
                        ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                        Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
                        House), 2006–9, vol. 87, 469–90. </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="293">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-224">Dalton, Jacob. “How Dhāraṇis were Proto-Tantric: Liturgies, Ritual Manuals,
                        and the Origins of the Tantras.” In Gray, David B. and Overbey, Ryan R., eds., <title xml:lang="en">Tantric Traditions on the Move</title>. Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-225">Davidson, Ronald M. <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Indian Esoteric Buddhism: A
                            Social History of the Tantric Movement</title>. New York: Columbia University Press, 2002.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-226">Isaacson, Harunaga. “Observations on the Development of the Ritual of
                        Initiation (abhiṣeka) in the Higher Buddhist Tantric Systems.” In <title xml:lang="en">Hindu and Buddhist
                            Initiations in India and Nepal</title>, edited by Astrid Zotter and Christof Zotter, 261–80.
                        Wiesbaden: Harrassowitz Verlag, 2010.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-227">Mayer, Robert. “The Importance of the Underworlds: Asuras’ Caves in
                        Buddhism, and Some Other Themes in Early Buddhist Tantras Reminiscent of the Later Padmasambhava Legends.”
                        In <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association for Tibetan Studies 3</title> (December
                        2007): 1–31.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-087-003-228">Williams, Paul. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Thought: A Complete
                            Introduction to the Indian Tradition</title>. London: Routledge, 2000.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-229">
                            <term>absorption </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ting nge ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིང་ངེ་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samādhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">A state of meditative concentration or <term type="ignore">absorption</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-230">
                            <term>bhūta </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> ’byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                            <term type="definition">A generic term for spirits or ghosts.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-231">
                            <term>burnt offering </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin sreg </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་སྲེག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Fire ritual.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-232">
                            <term>celestial chariot </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khang brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁང་བརྩེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The Sanskrit term <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vimāna</foreign> can refer to a
                                multi-storied mansion or palace, or even an estate, but is more often used in the sense of a
                                <term type="ignore">celestial chariot</term> of the gods, sometimes taking the form of a multi-storied palace; hence the
                                Tibetan translation, <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khang brtsegs</foreign>, literally “storied
                                house.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-233">
                            <term>commitment </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dam tshig </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དམ་ཚིག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">samaya</term>
                            <term type="definition">A tantric vow or <term type="ignore">commitment</term>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-234">
                            <term>diagram </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’khrul ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཁྲུལ་འཁོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">A <term type="ignore">diagram</term> drawn in tantric rituals.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-235">
                            <term>disciplined conduct </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bstul zhugs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྟུལ་ཞུགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vrata</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">saṃvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-236">
                            <term>five substances of a cow </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> ba yi rnam lnga </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བ་ཡི་རྣམ་ལྔ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pañcagavya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Milk, yogurt, clarified butter, cow urine, and cow dung.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-237">
                            <term>graha </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> gdon </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གདོན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">graha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of evil spirit known to exert a harmful influence on the human body and
                                mind. <term type="ignore">Grahas</term> are closely associated with the planets and other astronomical bodies.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-238">
                            <term>holder of the hare </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri bong ’dzin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་བོང་འཛིན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śaśadhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">An epithet of the moon.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-239">
                            <term>incantation</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A type of <term type="ignore">incantation</term> or spell used to accomplish a ritual goal. This can be
                                associated with either ordinary attainments or those whose goal is awakening.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-240">
                            <term>incantation mantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs sngags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས་སྔགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-241">
                            <term>nāga tree </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> klu shing </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ་ཤིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāgakesara</term>
                            <term type="definition">A species of euphorbia used in burnt offerings to get rid of nāga
                                influences.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-242">
                            <term>oblation </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtor ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཏོར་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bali</term>
                            <term type="definition">A ritual offering of food and drink.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-243">
                            <term>obstructors </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> bgegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བགེགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vighna</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-244">
                            <term>target</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsgrub bya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྒྲུབ་བྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">This is the object of ritual accomplishment, whatever is the focus and/or the
                                goal of ritual activity. Also translated “one to be accomplished.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-245">
                            <term>one to be accomplished</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsgrub bya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྒྲུབ་བྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhya</term>
                            <term type="definition">This is the object of ritual accomplishment, whatever is the focus and/or the
                                goal of ritual activity. Also translated “target.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-246">
                            <term>practice manual</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrub thabs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲུབ་ཐབས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-247">
                            <term>spiritual accomplishment</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngos grub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དངོས་གྲུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-248">
                            <term>yakṣa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-249">
                            <term>dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dhāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Used in several senses, elsewhere in this text translated as “incantation
                                mantra,” but here referring to entire canonical texts used mainly for ritual purposes, structured
                                around an incantation mantra in Sanskrit but also detailing its uses and the story of its
                                origin.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-250">
                            <term>Caryātantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyod pa’i rgyud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱོད་པའི་རྒྱུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">caryātantra</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Conduct tantras,” the second, middle category of the three outer tantras
                                according to the new translation (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsar ma</foreign>) traditions; in old
                                translation (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnying ma</foreign>) classifications the term Upa- or
                                Ubhaya-tantra is more often used.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-251">
                            <term>Anantaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mtha’ yas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཐའ་ཡས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anantaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ananta</term>
                            <term type="definition">Another name of Śesa, the serpent upon whom Viṣṇu rests during the interlude
                                between the destruction and recreation of the world.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-252">
                            <term>Bījakuṇḍalī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bi tsi kuN+Da li </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བི་ཙི་ཀུཎྜ་ལི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bījakuṇḍalī </term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-253">
                            <term>Constant Vajra Holder </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje kun tu ’dzin pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་ཀུན་ཏུ་འཛིན་པ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-254">
                            <term>Vajracaṇḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"> rdo rje gtum po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་གཏུམ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajracaṇḍa </term>
                            <term type="definition">Lit. "Fierce Vajra."</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-255">
                            <term>Guhyasthāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’brog gnas </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྲོག་གནས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guhyasthāna </term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-256">
                            <term>Jambhala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rmugs ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྨུགས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambhala </term>
                            <term type="definition">An alternate name for the yakṣa Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-257">
                            <term>Kubera</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ku be ra </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུ་བེ་ར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kubera </term>
                            <term type="definition">An alternate name for the yakṣa Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-258">
                            <term>Maṇibhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nor bzangs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནོར་བཟངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maṇibhadra </term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-259">
                            <term>Pāñcika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lngas rtsen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྔས་རྩེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pāñcika </term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-260">
                            <term>Phakpa Sherab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa shes rab </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཤེས་རབ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-261">
                            <term>Pūrṇabhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang ba bzang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་བ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇabhadra </term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-262">
                            <term>Terrible Vajra Conqueror </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje mi bzad ’joms </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་མི་བཟད་འཇོམས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-263">
                            <term>Celu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tse lu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཙེ་ལུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Celu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-264">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rnam thos bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྣམ་ཐོས་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-265">
                            <term>Vajra Joyfully Abiding Protector </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje dgyes gnas skyob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་དགྱེས་གནས་སྐྱོབ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-266">
                            <term>Vajra Regiment </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdor rje sde </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོར་རྗེ་སྡེ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-267">
                            <term>Vajra Tamer </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje rab tu ’dul byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་རབ་ཏུ་འདུལ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-268">
                            <term>Vajra Tamer of All Evil </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje gdug pa kun ’dul </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་གདུག་པ་ཀུན་འདུལ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-269">
                            <term>Vajra Victor of Basic Space </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rdo rje dbyings las rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྡོ་རྗེ་དབྱིངས་ལས་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">A bodhisattva in the Buddha Akṣobhya's retinue in this tantra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-270">
                            <term>Samprajñāna </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡང་དག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samprajñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">A yakṣa in this tantra. Although <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yang dag</foreign>
                                is normally translated as “Viśuddha,” we have rendered it here as “Samprajñāna” since this is the
                                Sanskrit rendering of this particular yakṣa’s name in the list of name mantras at 2.14.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-087-003-271">
                            <term>Alakāvatī </term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lcang lo can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྕང་ལོ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Alakāvatī </term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>