<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ye shes ta la la zhes bya ba’i
                    gzungs</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­nāma­dhāraṇī</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Tathāgata Jñānolka</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta la la zhes bya’i
                    gzungs ’gro ba thams cad yongs su sbyong ba</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­jñānolka­nāma­dhāraṇī­sarva­gatipariśodhanī</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Noble Tathāgata Jñānolka that Purifies All Rebirths</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">ཡེ་ཤེས་ཏ་ལ་ལ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་གཟུངས།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཏ་ལ་ལ་ཞེས་བྱའི་གཟུངས་འགྲོ་བ་ཐམས་ཅད་ཡོངས་སུ་སྦྱོང་བ།</title>


                <author role="translatorMain" ref="contributors.xml#team-9">Translated by The
                    Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/>under the patronage and supervision of
                    84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" ref="contributors.xml#person-274">Adam Krug</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 0.1.2 <date>2019</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="2.a">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global
                    non-profit initiative to translate all the Buddha’s words into modern languages,
                    and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC
                            BY-NC-ND (Attribution - Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright.
                            It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only with full
                            attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation.
                            For full details, see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-088-016"/>
                <date>2020-02-17</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh522" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 522</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 88 (rgyud ’bum, na), folios 59.a–60.b</biblScope><!-- bibl scope supplied in Docx -->
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="4">
                        <volume number="88" start-page="117" end-page="120"/>
                    </location>
                    <!--<biblScope>vol.88, ff.42r-43v(pp.83-86)</biblScope> bibl scope supplied in PLACEHOLDER 
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="4">
                        <volume number="88" start-page="83" end-page="86"/>
                    </location>-->
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21415" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12245" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
                <bibl key="toh848" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 848</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 100 (gzungs ’dus, e), folios 55.a–56.a</biblScope>
                    <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="3">
                        <volume number="101" start-page="109" end-page="111"/>
                    </location>
                    <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC20568" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                    <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12609" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated" date-time="2020-02-26T13:23:17.9Z" user="admin">26/02/2020 13:23:17</note>

                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.0" date-time="2019-10-10T08:04:49.554Z" user="andreas">v 0.1.0</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.d" date-time="2019-12-19T07:26:43.57Z" user="andreas">2.d</note>
                <note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.1" date-time="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" user="admin">Automated version
                    increment</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.e" date-time="2020-01-27T13:19:13.332Z" user="mike">2.e</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.b" date-time="2020-01-28T11:59:31.784Z" user="andreas">2.b</note>
                <note type="updated" update="translation-status" value="2.a" date-time="2020-01-29T06:04:47.549Z" user="mike">2.a</note>
            
<note type="updated" update="text-version" value="v 0.1.2" date-time="2020-02-26T13:23:14.499Z" user="andre">Mark-up completed with editor remarks</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="1">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-1"/>
                <p tid="2">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Tathāgata Jñānolka</title> opens
                    with a description of a group of four tathāgatas and four bodhisattvas seated in
                    the celestial palace of the Sun and Moon. Upon returning to their celestial
                    palace and seeing these tathāgatas and bodhisattvas, the deities of the Sun and
                    Moon both consider whether they might obtain a dhāraṇī that could allow them to
                    dispel the darkness and shine a light upon all beings. The tathāgatas,
                    perceiving the thoughts of the Sun and Moon, provide them with the first dhāraṇī
                    in the text. The bodhisattva Samanta­bhadra then provides a second dhāraṇī mantra
                    and instructs the deities of the Sun and Moon to use it to free beings who are
                    bound for rebirth in the lower realms—even those who have been born in the
                    darkest depths of the Avīci hell.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="3">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-2"/>
                <p tid="4">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the
                    supervision of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. The translation was produced by Adam Krug
                    and edited by Ryan Damron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="5">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-3"/>
                    <p tid="7">
                        <title xml:lang="en">The Dhāraṇī of the Noble Tathāgatha Jñānolka
                            that Purifies All Rebirths</title> centers on a pairing of four
                        tathāgatas and four bodhisattvas who offer dhāraṇīs to the deities of the
                        Sun and the Moon after perceiving their wish to shine a light upon beings
                        residing in the darkest depths of cyclic existence. The tathāgata Jñānolka
                        is identified in the Indic title to the work in the Kangyur, and the
                        Sanskrit names of his three accompanying tathāgatas have thankfully been
                        identified here based on an edition of the Khotanese manuscript of the
                            <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title> published along with a
                        brief study and German translation by Ernst Leumann in 1920.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-4" index="1"> Leumann (1920).</note> The set of
                        four tathāgatas and four bodhisattvas at the center of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title> cult appears in Leumann’s
                        Khotanese sources as follows: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-5"/>
                    <p tid="8">– The four tathāgatas: Jñānolka, Suvarṇa­prabhākūṭa­nirbhāsa, Satyavādin, and Bhīkṣmas­varagarjita­rājā.</p> 
                    <p tid="9">– The four bodhisattvas: Samanta­bhadra, Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta, Dhāraṇīś­vara­rāja, and Vajrapāṇi.</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-7"/>
                    <p tid="10">Leumann’s edition also preserves Khotanese Sanskrit versions of the
                        dhāraṇī mantras contained in the text that appear in this translation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-8"/>
                    <p tid="11">Mauro Maggi’s summary of sources for the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title> notes that the majority of known extant
                        versions of the text have survived in Khotanese witnesses and that the
                        earliest Chinese translations of the text derive from both a Khotanese
                        original and a Tibetan translation. According to Leumann, the Tibetan
                        translation of the text does not agree very closely with the Khotanese, and
                        the Khotanese versions vary.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-9" index="2"> Maggi (2008).</note>
                        While the variants between the Tibetan translation and Khotanese manuscripts
                        of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title> raise the
                        possibility that the version translated and preserved in the Degé edition of
                        the Kangyur derives from a separate source that has yet to be located, the
                        Sanskrit manuscript witnesses that are currently available all indicate
                        Khotan as the most likely location in which the cult of the four tathāgatas
                        and bodhisattvas in this text and the dhāraṇī mantras it preserves
                        flourished. Aside from its obvious applications for purifying the potential
                        consequences of lower rebirth for the living and its potential function as a
                        ritual liturgy for the bodhisattva’s practice of liberating beings, the
                        narrative frame of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title>
                        indicates that its dhāraṇī mantras could have functioned as part of a
                        funeral liturgy designed to liberate the recently deceased from lower
                        rebirth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title> appears in the
                            Denkarma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-11" index="3"> Yoshimura (1950), 154.</note> and
                            Phangthangma<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-12" index="4">
                                <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang thang ma</title>,
                                30.</note> royal Tibetan catalogues of translated works, which
                        indicates that the text was translated into Tibetan by at least the early
                        ninth century. The text was translated into Chinese twice, first in the late
                        seventh century by the translator Devaprajñā (T 1397)<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-13" index="5"> Lewis R. Lancaster, “K 476,” <title xml:lang="en">The Korean Buddhist Canon</title>, accessed
                                February 12, 2019,
                                http://www.acmuller.net/descriptive_catalogue/files/k0476.html.
                            </note> and then again in the tenth century by Dānapāla (T
                            1398).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-14" index="6"> Lewis R. Lancaster, “K 476,” <title xml:lang="en">The Korean Buddhist Canon</title>, accessed
                                February 12, 2019,
                                http://www.acmuller.net/descriptive_catalogue/files/k0476.html.</note>
                        This translation is based on the two versions of the text that are preserved
                        in the Degé Kangyur (Toh 522 and Toh 848<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-52" index="7">This text, Toh 848, and all those contained in this same volume (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ’dus, e</foreign>), are listed as being located in volume 100 of the Degé Kangyur by the Buddhist Digital Resource Center (BDRC). However, several other Kangyur databases—including the eKangyur that supplies the digital input version displayed by 84000 reading room—list this work as being located in volume 101. This discrepancy is partly due to the fact that the two volumes of the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs ‘dus</foreign> section are an added supplement not mentioned in the original catalogue, and also hinges on the fact that the compilers of the Tōhoku catalogue placed another text—which forms a whole, very large volume—the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalaprabhā­nāmakālacakra­tantraṭīkā</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dus 'khor 'grel bshad dri med 'od</title>, Toh 845), before the present volume, numbering it as vol. 100, although it is almost certainly intended to come right at the end of the Degé Kangyur texts as volume 102; indeed its final fifth chapter is often carried over and wrapped in the same volume as the Kangyur <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chags</foreign> (catalogue). Please note this discrepancy when using the eKangyur viewer in this translation.</note>) in consultation with the two versions of the text in the
                        Comparative Edition (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpe bsdur ma</title>) of the
                        Kangyur and the text as it is preserved in the Stok Palace Kangyur. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="13"> The Translation </head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="14">The Dhāraṇī of the Tathāgata Jñānolka that Purifies
                    All Rebirths</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-16"/>
                    <p tid="18">
                        <ref cRef="F.59.a" type="folio" key="toh522"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.55.a" type="folio" key="toh848"/> <ref cRef="F.59.b" type="folio" key="toh522"/> Homage to the Omniscient One.<lb/>Homage to all the buddhas and
                        bodhisattvas.<lb/>Homage to the blessed one the tathāgata
                        Jñānolka.<lb/>Homage to the tathāgata Suvarṇa­prabhākūṭa­nirbhāsa.<lb/>Homage
                        to the tathāgata Satyavādin.<lb/>Homage to the tathāgata
                        Bhīkṣmas­varagarjita­rājā.</p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-19"/>
                    <p tid="20">The four bodhisattvas—Samanta­bhadra, the youthful Mañjuśrī,
                        Dhāraṇīś­vara­rāja, and Vajrapāṇi—were dwelling in the abode of the Sun and
                        the Moon along with the tathāgatas. When the Sun and Moon reached the place
                        where the tathāgatas and bodhisattvas were seated, they saw the tathāgatas
                        upon lion thrones bedecked with jewels and the bodhisattvas seated within
                        palaces arrayed with banners bearing the rose apple insignia. The Sun and
                        Moon each thought, “How from these tathāgatas and bodhisattvas can we obtain
                        the dhāraṇī mantra called <distinct>the wise one who pervades the ten
                            directions,</distinct> which rises like the dawn to shine a light upon
                        all beings and dispel their thick darkness? With its power we could shine a
                        light upon all sentient beings.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-20"/>
                    <p tid="21">
                        <ref cRef="F.60.a" type="folio" key="toh522"/>
                        <ref cRef="F.55.b" type="folio" key="toh848"/> The tathāgatas and bodhisattvas perceived the
                        thoughts of the Sun and Moon and responded with the following dhāraṇī
                        mantra:</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-21"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="22">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="dharani">saryathīva cakṣurdada
                            cakṣuprabha dhulamētha kalatha ithithaṃsa sūrata sūrata suthāsa
                            itithaṃsa vēlu vēlu vēlāpaṇi cārumūrtani āraṇi kālāpaṇi kālāpaṇi
                            tturudhusi turuturudhusi dhāsuti dhāsuti dharadhara dhiridhiri
                            dhurudhuru dhūradhūra kālakāla sathāsa sathāsa gīla gīla gīlāpaya
                            gīlāpaya dhasu dhasu sūṃddhu sūmbhu ēthasu ēthasu ēthasāpaṇi yijuru rede
                            karakara kirikiri kurukuru kurmakurma karmāpaṇi karmāpaṇi karmāpaṇi
                            karmāpaṇi kēlukēlu kēlāpaṇi karkāri karkāri lāru vuddhe dhurude
                            mahādhurude karakara kirikiri piḍhusi piḍhusi dhasu dhasu hasu hasu
                            hasāpaṇi svāhā</mantra>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-22" index="8"> This is the Sanskrit for the
                                first dhāraṇī mantra as it appears in Leumann’s 1920 edition of the
                                Khotanese version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title>. See Leumann (1920), 158.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-23"/>
                    <p tid="23">Then the bodhisattva Samanta­bhadra addressed both the Sun and the
                        Moon, saying, “Sons of the lineage, eighty-four million buddhas have taught
                        this dhāraṇī mantra in order to help beings who are bound for lower rebirth.
                        Sons of the lineage, it is much easier to find a rare <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">udumbara</foreign> flower than it is for
                        these dhāraṇī mantra verses to appear in the world. Sons of the lineage,
                        obtaining these dhāraṇī mantra verses is much easier than reading and
                        retaining these verses in one’s mind. Sons of the lineage, it is far more
                        likely for a buddha to appear in the world than it is for these dhāraṇī
                        mantra verses to appear in the world. <ref cRef="F.56.a" type="folio" key="toh848"/> Sons of the lineage, if one
                        recites these dhāraṇī mantra verses three times a day and three times a
                        night for twenty-one days on behalf of those beings trapped for eons in
                        Avīci hell, namely, those who have committed the five inexpiable acts or who
                        have forsaken the holy Dharma, then the power of those verses shall open the
                        hundred doors of the great Avīci hell, and those beings shall attain
                        liberation. This is also the case, of course, for human beings in
                        Jambudvīpa. Whoever hears these dhāraṇī mantra verses shall truly know that
                        we, the four tathāgatas, the four bodhisattvas, and the Sun and Moon,
                        <ref cRef="F.60.b" type="folio" key="toh522"/> support them. The dhāraṇī mantra verses are: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-24"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="24">
                        <mantra xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="dharani">dhunaṭi mahādhuṇati surusuru
                            svāhā śuklaviśōdhani taratara svāhā || jyōtipradīpe turuturu svāhā ||
                            padmamālani sattyatarabudhe huruhuru svāhā satyabuddhe saty'ālōkani
                            kirikiri svāhā || dhāraṇibuddhi apratihatabuddhi curucuru svāhā ||
                            lakṣaṇârcite dhūmaparihāre khurukhuru dhāra mahādhāra dharadhara yaṃ
                            ttîye svāhā || avrrate sutape apratihatabuddhi dharadhara yam tîye svāhā ||</mantra>
                        <note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-53"> This
                                is the Sanskrit for the second dhāraṇī mantra as it appears in
                                Leumann’s 1920 edition of the Khotanese version of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānolka­dhāraṇī</title>.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-26"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>Homage to the blessed one, the tathāgata Jñānolka! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the tathāgata Suvarṇa­prabhākūṭa­nirbhāsa! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the tathāgata Satyavādin! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the tathāgata Bhīkṣmas­varagarjita­rājā! </l>
                        <l>Make these mantra verses effective! Svāhā!<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-54">The Sanskrit
                                    names for the four tathāgatas in this translation have been
                                    derived from the concluding verse to the preceding dhāraṇī, which reads:
                                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="quote">namo jñānolkasya
                                        tathāgatasya namo suvarṇaprabhākūṭanirbhāsasya tathāgatasya
                                        namo satyavādinē tathāgatasya namau
                                        bhikṣmasvaragarjitarājebhya tathātatēbhya siddhyaṃtu
                                        maṃtrapadā svāhā ||.</foreign> See Leumann (1920), 158.
                                </note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <trailer tid="26">This concludes “The Dhāraṇī of the Tathāgata Jñānolka that
                        Purifies All Rebirths.”</trailer>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="27">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="29">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="30">Source Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-28">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta
                            la la zhes bya ba’i gzungs ’gro ba thams cad yongs su sbyong ba
                            </title>
                        (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryajñānolkanāmadhāraṇīsarvagatipariśodhanī</title>). Toh
                        522, Degé Kangyur vol. 88 (rgyud ’bum, na), folios 59.a–60.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-30">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta
                            la la zhes bya ba’i gzungs ’gro ba thams cad yongs su sbyong ba
                    </title>(<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya­jñānolko­nāma­dhāraṇī­sarva­gatipariśodhanī</title>). Toh 848, Degé Kangyur vol. 100 (gzungs
                        ’dus, e), folios 55.a–56.a.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-31">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta
                            la la zhes bya ba’i gzungs ’gro ba thams cad yongs su sbyong ba</title>.
                        bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i
                        bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 88, pp. 189–94.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-32">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta
                            la la zhes bya ba’i gzungs ’gro ba thams cad yongs su sbyong ba</title>.
                        bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i
                        bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan
                        Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108
                        volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology
                        Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 97, pp. 168–73.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-33">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta
                        la la zhes bya ba’i gzungs </title>(Ārya­jñānolko­nāma­dhāraṇī­sarva­gatipariśodhanī). Stok Palace Kangyur, vol. 102 (rgyud
                        ’bum, da) folios 42a–44a.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="31">Reference Works</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-34">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dkar chag ’phang
                            thang ma: sgra sbyor bam po gnyis pa</title>. Beijing: mi rigs dpe skrun
                        khang, 2003.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-35">Edgerton, Franklin. <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary</title>. Delhi: Motilal
                        Banarsidass, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-36">Monier-Williams, Monier. <title xml:lang="en">A Sanskrit-English Dictionary: Etymologically and Philologically
                            Arranged with Special Reference to Cognate Indo-European
                            Languages</title>. Delhi: Motilal Banarsidass, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-37">Negi, J.S. <title xml:lang="en">Tibetan-Sanskrit Dictionary</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bod skad
                            dang legs sbyar gyi tshig mdzod chen mo</title>). Sarnath: Central
                        Institute of higher Tibetan Studies, 1993. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-38">Yoshimura, Shyuki. <title xml:lang="en">The
                            Denkar-Ma: An Oldest Catalogue of the Tibetan Buddhist Canons</title>.
                        Kyoto: Ryukoku University, 1950.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="32">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-39">Leumann, Ernst.
                            “Die Jñānolka­dhāraṇī.” In <title xml:lang="de">Buddhistische Literatur: Nordarish und Deutsch: I. Teil: Nebenstüke,
                            157–62.</title> Leipzig, 1920.</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-088-016-40">Maggi, Mauro. “Jñānolkadhāranī.” <title xml:lang="en">Encyclopedia Iranica</title>. Accessed February 2, 2018.
                        http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/jnanolkadharai.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">

                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-42">
                                <term>Ārya Jñānolka</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phags pa ye shes ta la la </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འཕགས་པ་ཡེ་ཤེས་ཏ་ལ་ལ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ārya Jñānolka</term>
                                <term type="definition">A tathāgata.</term>
                                <term type="alternative">Jñānolka</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-43">
                                <term>Bhīkṣmas­varagarjita­rājā</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs pa’i sgra sgrogs rgyal po </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་པའི་སྒྲ་སྒྲོགས་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhīkṣmas­varagarjita­rājā</term>
                                <term type="definition">A tathāgata associated with Ārya Jñānolka.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-44">
                                <term>Dhāraṇīś­vara­rāja</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs kyi dbang phyug rgyal po </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུངས་ཀྱི་དབང་ཕྱུག་རྒྱལ་པོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhāraṇīś­vara­rāja</term>
                                <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-45">
                                <term>Samanta­bhadra</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun tu bzang po </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཏུ་བཟང་པོ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Samanta­bhadraḥ</term>
                                <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-46">
                                <term>Satyavādin</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bden gsung </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">བདེན་གསུང་།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Satyavādin</term>
                                <term type="definition">A tathāgata associated with Ārya Jñānolka.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-47">
                                <term>Suvarṇa­prabhākūṭa­nirbhāsa</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od brtsegs snang ba </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་བརྩེགས་སྣང་བ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Suvarṇa­prabhākūṭa­nirbhāsa</term>
                                <term type="definition">A tathāgata associated with Ārya Jñānolka.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-48">
                                <term>Mañjuśrī, the youthful</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal gzhon nur gyur pa </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ་གཞོན་ནུར་གྱུར་པ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta </term>
                                <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                                <term type="alternative">Mañjuśrīkumārabhūta</term>
                                <term type="alternative">the youthful Mañjuśrī</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-50">
                                <term>Vajrapāṇi</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phyag na rdo rje </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྱག་ན་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajrapāṇi</term>
                                <term type="definition">A bodhisattva.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                            <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-088-016-51">
                                <term>Avīci hell</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnar med pa </term>
                                <term xml:lang="bo">མནར་མེད་པ།</term>
                                <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avīci</term>
                                <term type="definition">The lowest hell; the eighth of the eight hot hells.</term>
                            </gloss>
                        </item>

                    </list>
            </div>   
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>