<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa’i rgyud</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ་གཅིག་པུ་གྲུབ་པའི་རྒྱུད།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">The Tantra of Siddhaikavīra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­tantram</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ་གཅིག་པུ་གྲུབ་པ་ཞེས་བྱ་བའི་རྒྱུད་ཀྱི་རྒྱལ་པོ་ཆེན་པོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa zhes bya ba’i rgyud kyi rgyal po chen po</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Great Sovereign Tantra of Siddhaikavīra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­mahā­tantra­rājaḥ</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-9" role="translatorMain">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee <lb/>under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-76">Wiesiek Mical</author>
                <editor role="reviser" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.11 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone.</publisher>
                <availability>
                    <p type="tantricRestriction">
                        <emph rend="bold">Warning:</emph> Readers are reminded that according to Vajrayāna Buddhist tradition there are
                        restrictions and commitments concerning tantra. Practitioners who are not sure if they should read this
                        translation are advised to consult the authorities of their lineage. The responsibility for reading this text
                        or sharing it with others who may or may not fulfill the requirements lies in the hands of readers.</p>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-089-001"/>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh544" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 544</ref>, <biblScope> Degé Kangyur, vol. 89 (rgyud ’bum, pa), folios 1.b–13.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Géwai Lodrö</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Tsultrim Gyalwa</author>
                    <location count-pages="24">
                        <start volume="89" page="4"/>
                        <end volume="89" page="27"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21415"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12270" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 04/02/2019 at 20:14:51 by celso</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <!--              
                title style="contentsPage">Contents
            
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Summary
                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Acknowledgements
                    <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Introduction
                        
                        <title style="contentsTranslation">The Translation
                            <title style="contentsTextTitle">The Tantra of Siddhaikavīra
                                
                                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 1
                                    <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 2
                                        <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 3
                                            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Chapter 4
                                                
                                                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Notes
                                                    <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Bibliography
                                                        -->
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="411">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-1"/>
                <p tid="1">
                    <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra of Siddhaikavīra</title> is a tantra of ritual and magic. It is a relatively
                    short text extant in numerous Sanskrit manuscripts and in Tibetan translation. Although its precise date is
                    difficult to establish, it is arguably the first text to introduce into the Buddhist pantheon the deity
                    Siddhaikavīra—a white, two-armed form of Mañjuśrī. The tantra is primarily structured around fifty-five
                    mantras, which are collectively introduced by a statement promising all mundane and supramundane attainments,
                    including the ten bodhisattva levels, to a devotee who employs the Siddhaikavīra and, presumably, other
                    Mañjuśrī mantras. Such a devotee is said to become a wish-fulfilling gem, constantly engaged in benefitting
                    beings. Most of the mantras have their own section that includes a description of the rituals for which the
                    mantra is prescribed and a brief description of their effects. This being a tantra of the Kriyā class, the
                    overwhelming majority of its mantras are meant for use in rites of prosperity and wellbeing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="412">Acknowledgements</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-2"/>
                <p tid="2">This translation was produced by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the supervision of Chökyi
                    Nyima Rinpoche. Wiesiek Mical translated the text from the Sanskrit, and Andreas Doctor compared the
                    translation against the Tibetan translation contained in the Degé Kangyur and edited the text. </p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="413">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">Despite what its title might suggest, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­tantra</title>
                        (hereafter SEV) is not a tantra of Siddhaikavīra in the same way that, for example, the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hevajra­tantra</title> is a tantra of Hevajra. Siddhaikavīra is not the main
                        subject, and indeed, excluding the chapter colophons, his name is mentioned in the tantra only three
                        times—and, interestingly, never in a mantra. Nevertheless, Siddhaikavīra is awarded prominence in the text
                        in a short preamble that introduces the SEV and points out the soteriological nature of the mantra of
                        Siddhaikavīra-Arapacana, the forty-first mantra of the fifty-five in this text and the only one that
                        invokes him, setting this mantra somewhat apart from other mantras, most of which have magical and
                        practical applications. The ritual related to this particular mantra requires the visualization of
                        Siddhaikavīra, but even then he is invoked not by the name Siddhaikavīra but as Arapacana. Only one other
                        mantra, addressed to Arkamālinī (Mahāsarasvatī), involves the visualization of Siddhaikavīra. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-4"/>
                    <p tid="5"> The deity that can be distilled from the SEV is in essence Mañjuśrī; he is addressed in the
                        traditional homage at the beginning of the tantra under his name of Mañjughoṣa; it is he, under his name
                        Mañjuvajra, who delivers the SEV at the bodhisattva Vajradhara’s request; and Siddhaikavīra, likewise, is
                        none other than Mañjuśrī. In the paragraph following the forty-first mantra, Siddhaikavīra is equated with
                        both Arapacana and Mañjuvajra. Thus, the distribution and juxtaposition of these names throughout the text
                        implies that all these deities are one and the same: Mañjuśrī. One of the lesser-known forms of Mañjuśrī,
                        Siddhaikavīra is also the subject of four sādhanas in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sādhanamālā</title>
                        (Bhattacharyya 1968) where some of his descriptions correspond in detail to the visualizations given in
                        the SEV—he is a white figure with a blue lotus in his left hand and displaying a boon-granting gesture
                        with his right. In two of these sādhanas he is called Siddhaikavīramañjughoṣa, confirming that he is
                        identical to the deity mentioned in the homage at the beginning of the SEV, Mañjughoṣa. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-5"/>
                    <p tid="6"> Being a collection of mantras and their rituals, the SEV introduces the reader to the enchanted
                        world of magical powers that can affect the daily reality of people’s lives and, ultimately, deliver them
                        from the miseries of cyclic existence. Since, however, the SEV is a Kriyā tantra, it is the mantras of
                        magic that predominate in this text. These mantras testify to the richness and versatility of the Buddhist
                        pantheon in this formative period of the Buddhist tantra. The deities being invoked are given a range of
                        evocative names and epithets—the glossary of the names found in this tantra contains more than 100
                        entries. The appearance in this text of some deities, including Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa and Kurukullā,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-322" index="1">For more on these two deities, see Dharmachakra
                            (2016) and (2011), respectively.</note> could be the first anywhere in literary sources, making the
                        SEV a historically important text. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-6"/>
                    <p tid="7"> The date of the SEV is very uncertain. As a Kriyā tantra, it could date from as early as the
                        beginning of the Common Era. At the opposite end, its terminus ante quem is set by the date of the Tibetan
                        translation by the great paṇḍit Atīśa (980–1054). It might be not unreasonable to guess, however, that the
                        SEV dates to somewhere between the 7th and the 9th centuries. This tantra is extant in both Sanskrit and
                        in Tibetan. The Sanskrit text has been preserved in many manuscripts held in the National Archives in
                        Kathmandu as well as in several libraries around the world; it has also been edited and published twice,
                        by Janardan Pandey (1998) and then by Nobuo Otsuka (1995). The Tibetan canonical translation found in the
                        Kangyur (Toh 544) is attributed to Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna (Atīśa) and Géwai Lodrö. It is also included,
                        together with a commentary by Jamyang Khyentse Wangpo (1820–1892), in the 19th century collection of
                        practice materials, the <foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">Druptap Küntü</foreign> (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrub thabs kun btus</foreign>).<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-323" index="2">See
                            bibliography, Khyentse (1970).</note> That it was the subject of commentary as late as the 19th
                        century indicates that the SEV, despite being a Kriyā tantra, never lost its popularity over time. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="414">Summary of the Chapters</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">The SEV is divided into four chapters of decreasing length. Chapter 1, the longest, contains a
                        mixture of mantras with a variety of applications. They are grouped by their applications and include
                        mantras for controlling weather, warding off enemies, averting disasters, removing fear, pacifying
                        disputes, stopping fires, preventing epidemics, curing diseases, safely delivering a child, releasing one
                        from imprisonment, obtaining long life, and curing leprosy, as well as more general applications for
                        protecting humans and animals from all kinds of trouble, destroying evil, and fulfilling one’s wishes. The
                        deities invoked in this chapter range in their origin from flesh-eating demons, or piśācas, such as
                        Parṇaśabarī, to sambhogakāya deities such as Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">Chapter 2 contains two groups of mantras. The first group concerns divination and soothsaying. At
                        the beginning, the qualities of a person to whom the contents of this chapter can be revealed are
                        described and, pertinently, the value and sacredness of truth is stressed. As we read in the invocation to
                        Vimalacandra, one of the gods of divination (2.2-3): </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-9"/>
                    <q>
                        <lg tid="10">
                            <l>The world is sustained by truth;</l>
                            <l>It is preserved by truth;</l>
                            <l>Through truth, it abides in Dharma;</l>
                            <l>Truth is eternal as Brahman.</l>
                        </lg>
                        <lg tid="11">
                            <l>Truth is the Buddha, the Dharma and the Saṃgha;</l>
                            <l>It is the ocean of qualities.</l>
                            <l>By these words of truth</l>
                            <l>May you swiftly enter the mirror [of divination].<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-324" index="3">Pandey (1998), p 9.</note>
                            </l>
                        </lg>
                    </q>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-10"/>
                    <p tid="12">In the original Sanskrit we have a play on words, as the word used for “mirror,” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">darpaṇa</foreign>, can also be another name for the mountain of Kubera, itself
                        associated with divination. The rites and methods described aim at ascertaining facts that are normally
                        outside one’s sphere of perception, like possible good or bad outcomes of a particular undertaking, or
                        even the time of someone’s death. The requested knowledge can be revealed in a mirror, in one’s sleep, or
                        in some other way. The deities invoked in divination mantras range from piśācas, such as Karṇapiśācī, to
                        sambhogakāya deities such as Mañjuśrī. The name “Karṇapiśācī” suggests a piśācī who whispers into one’s
                        ear (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karṇa</foreign>), and as may be expected, her mantra requests her to
                        whisper her answers into one’s ear. Other divination deities can have equally suggestive names or
                        epithets, such as Siddhalocanā (Accomplished Vision), Satyavādinī (Speaker of Truth), or Svapnavilokinī
                        (One Who Can See Dreams). </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-11"/>
                    <p tid="13">The other group of mantras in this chapter is concerned with obtaining desired things, be it a
                        lover, wealth, or even a kingdom. First is the mantra of mighty Aditi, who, if propitiated in the
                        prescribed manner, can help one obtain a girl, riches, or power. Interestingly, we find a touch of realism
                        here, as the text tells us that one can obtain a kingdom only if one is of royal descent; otherwise one
                        will only obtain “great splendor.” The deities invoked in this section range from yakṣa spirits, such as
                        those in the retinues of Jambhala or Vasudharā, to the mighty Mahālakṣmī or the two deities just
                        mentioned. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">Chapter 3 is dedicated to the mantras of deities mainly invoked to increase powers of eloquence,
                        intelligence, memory, and learning. The first two mantras invoke two manifestations of Mañjuśrī,
                        Siddhaikavīra (even though, as discussed above, the mantra invokes him by the name Arapacana) and Vākya.
                        The rituals of the latter can also bestow longevity and other boons. The next few mantras are dedicated to
                        Mañjuśrī’s consort, Mahāsarasvatī; their benefits are the same as those mentioned above. Mahāsarasvatī,
                        here identified with Tārā, is visualized in the form of a young girl whose body has the nature of great
                        compassion and appears “in all the fresh beauty of budding youth.” She can grant all siddhis. The chapter
                        closes with the mantras invoking, again, various forms of Mañjuśrī. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">Chapter 4 contains only four mantras—all four used mainly for enthralling. The first two are
                        addressed to the mysterious deity Lavaṇāmbha (Salty Water), whom the SEV associates with Avalokiteśvara.
                        Invoked in the magic of love and seduction, his name could be a metaphor for the thirst that his rituals
                        produce—thirst that can only be quenched by union with the desired person. Next is the mantra of
                        Kurukullā, the goddess with an arrow and bow well known for her enthralling powers. The collection ends
                        with an obscure mantra whose grammar is ambiguous and open to different interpretations. The content of
                        the mantra also seems somewhat inconsistent with the ritual subsequently described. The mantra seems to be
                        addressed to a male deity who governs the movements of the planets and is responsible for timely rain and
                        for bringing prosperity and happiness, and yet the ritual in which it is employed is used to summon a
                        desired woman or man. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="415">Notes on the Translation</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-14"/>
                    <p tid="16"> As well as being divided into four chapters, the tantra can also be divided into fifty-five
                        sections, each containing one mantra. The content of each section fits a particular pattern. Typically, a
                        section starts with the mantra and is followed by a statement of the mantra’s application and effects,
                        with a description of one or more ritual procedures required to achieve a particular result. To reflect
                        this structure and for easy navigation and reference, we have numbered the mantras in our translation. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">There is no clear dividing line in the SEV between Buddhist and Hindu pantheons. Some deities,
                        such as Lakṣmī, would normally be regarded as Hindu, while others, such as Sarasvatī or Kubera, have been
                        shared to a great extent by both religions. Many are exclusively Buddhist. Because of the
                        non-denominational spirit in this world of magic, it can sometimes be difficult to determine whether a
                        deity is actually meant to be Buddhist or not, as for example in the case of Gaṇapati, whose form seems to
                        be the favorite for making ritual effigies in some rites, such as the rite for stopping an onslaught by a
                        hostile army. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-16"/>
                    <p tid="18">When translating the names of deities, particularly the names found in mantras, it is not easy to
                        decide whether a given appellation should be interpreted as a proper name or an epithet. When faced with
                        such ambiguities, our translation tends to leave the borderline cases untranslated, with the literal
                        meaning given in the glossary. In some mantras, the deity is addressed only by an epithet or epithets, and
                        we can do no more than guess who this could be. Only the context suggests Tārā, Sarasvatī, etc. In cases
                        where we find a group of names in grammatical apposition, our uncertainty regarding which names in the
                        group are proper names and which are merely epithets is sometimes further confounded by uncertainty about
                        whether a particular mantra addresses one or more deities. We were also faced with many difficulties due
                        to the specific mantra jargon itself, with its strong vernacular influence. Mantric syllables and words
                        that could not be identified have been printed in italics. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-17"/>
                    <p tid="19">As the ritual jargon of the SEV is often incompatible with modern English in terms of semantics
                        and usage, the reader will find that certain English words in our translation have been used in somewhat
                        unconventional ways. For example, the direct object of the verb “to incant,” in our translation, can be
                        not only the mantra but also the object over which the mantra is to be recited, such as a flower, a
                        substance, or a diseased body part. This latter usage was common in English until the mid-20th century,
                        and despite a precedent in modern English as well (the Harry Potter novels), to many readers it may still
                        seem “incorrect.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-18"/>
                    <p tid="20">Two editions of the Sanskrit text have been used for our translation: Otsuka 1995 and Pandey 1998,
                        as well as the Tibetan text (Toh 544) from the Degé edition of the Kangyur. Folio numbers given in square
                        brackets refer to the Degé Kangyur, whereas numbers in braces refer to the page numbers in Pandey’s
                        edition of the Sanskrit. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="416">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="417">The Great Sovereign Tantra of Siddhaikavīra</head>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="418">Chapter 1</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-19"/>
                    <p tid="21">
                        <ref cRef="F.1.b"/> {1} <!--modularPassage type=openingHomage-->
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, homage to Mañjughoṣa! <!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                    <lg tid="22">
                        <l>The teacher of living beings, Mañjuvajra,</l>
                        <l>Taught this tantra for the sake of the world—</l>
                        <l>The tantra of Siddhaikavīra, the heroic lord,</l>
                        <l>The best and foremost among speakers.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-20"/>
                    <lg tid="23">
                        <l>This very deity, in the form of the mantra,</l>
                        <l>Bounteously grants every accomplishment.</l>
                        <l>On him indeed should the follower of Mantra meditate.</l>
                        <l>He in whom Siddhaikavīra is realized will gain accomplishment.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-21"/>
                    <lg tid="24">
                        <l>A follower of Mantra who has a pure body,</l>
                        <l>Once the small accomplishment has been obtained,</l>
                        <l>Will make his body a field </l>
                        <l>In which the great accomplishment will arise </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-22"/>
                    <lg tid="25">
                        <l>And gradually to him will come</l>
                        <l>The attainment of bhūmis and so forth.</l>
                        <l>Like a wish-fulfilling gem, this follower of Mantra</l>
                        <l>Will always act for the benefit of beings.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-23"/>
                    <lg tid="26">
                        <l>With that in mind, overcome with compassion,</l>
                        <l>When asked by Vajradhara and others, <ref cRef="F.2.a"/>
                        </l>
                        <l>Mañjuvajra gave, for the sake of the world,</l>
                        <l>A mantra collection of the accomplished ones.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <label>First Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-24"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="292">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kālumelu kālumelu stambhaya śilāvarṣaṃ tuṣāra­varṣaṃ ca lucca
                                i lucca i svāhā</foreign>
                            |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="293">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, kālumelu kālumelu</foreign>, stop the hailstorm and snowfall,
                            stop, stop! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-325" index="4">Tib.: 
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kālumelu kālume
                                    stambhaya śilāvarṣaṃ tuṣāranya ca lucca i lucca i svāhā</foreign>
                                |</note>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-25"/>
                    <p tid="29">This king of mantras, when correctly recited, will stop a hailstorm. Merely to remember it, using
                        incanted ashes, can stop snow<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-326" index="5">Tib.: “a hailstorm
                            or a snowfall.”</note> falling, or make it fall wherever one wishes. In the same way, one can also
                        stop lightning, hurricanes, thunderbolt strikes, etc. {2}</p>
                    <label>Second Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-26"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="294">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ garuḍa haṃsa he he cala cala svāhā</foreign>
                         |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="295">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, garuḍa! Swan! Hey, hey! Move, move! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <p tid="32">The mere thought of this king of mantras will stop a hailstorm. By inscribing it on a kettle drum
                        with chalk and chanting over the drumstick, one can then use the sound of the drum to stop a hailstorm.
                        The same can be done with the sound of a conch, etc. </p>
                    <label>Third Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-27"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="296">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ he he tiṣṭha tiṣṭha bandha bandha dhāraya dhāraya nirundhaya
                            nirundhaya devadattam ūrṇāmaṇe svāhā </foreign>
                        |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="297">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, hey, hey! Remain, remain! Bind, bind! Hold, hold!
                        Restrain such-and-such, restrain! O Ūrṇāmaṇi, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-327" index="6">In the Tibetan the mantra
                            ends: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">nirundha nirundha chegemo* ūrṇāmaṇe
                                svāhā</foreign>.</note>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-28"/>
                    <p tid="35">One should write the name of the enemy, in combination with this mantra, on a palm leaf, and place
                        it in the burrow of a crab. That will bind the enemy’s mouth. It will also stop others’ evil designs,
                            etc.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-328" index="7">Tib. omits the three sentences starting
                            with “One should write…” and ending with “evil designs, etc.”</note> This king of mantras, when
                        recited 100,000 times according to the procedure of the preliminary practice,<!-- Moved to gloss <note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-329">“Preliminary practice” (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūrvasevā</foreign>) is a six-month period of formal practice to be performed before one can
                            start employing the mantra for specific purposes.</note>--> will bring success. By merely remembering
                        this mantra one will be able to stop lightning, wind, thunderbolt strikes, hail, snow, and so forth. One
                        will also stop torrential rain.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-330" index="8">In the Tibetan,
                            the sentence “One will also stop torrential rain” appears in the next paragraph. </note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-29"/>
                    <p tid="36">By using incanted ashes and mustard seeds, one will bind the snouts of mice, the stylets of
                        mosquitoes, etc. This will also stop attacks on a garden or field by birds, worms, locusts, and other
                        pests. One should inscribe this mantra on a rag that has been discarded in a charnel ground, together with
                        the name of a pregnant woman, enclose it in beeswax, place it in a charnel ground in a pot, seal it, and
                        bury it. That will stop the woman from losing her fetus. Digging it up again, rinsing it with milk,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-331" index="9">Tib.: “with water and milk.”</note> and floating
                        it on water will bring alleviation of discomfort. <ref cRef="F.2.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-30"/>
                    <p tid="37">One should write this mantra on birchbark or cloth<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-332" index="10">Tib.: “on birchbark, cloth, or leaves.”</note> with turmeric or yellow
                        orpiment. One should make an effigy<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-333" index="11">Tib.: “an
                            effigy in the form of Bhairava.”</note> using clay from an anthill, and place the mantra, enclosed in
                        beeswax, in the effigy’s heart. One should fill its mouth with ash and bury it.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-334" index="12">Skt.: “bury it right there.”</note> In case of a dispute, one
                        will be able to paralyze the mouth of one’s opponent. Also, in case of a lawsuit, one should incant the
                        tongue of the effigy seven times and pierce it with seven thorns.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-335" index="13">Tib.: “one should incant seven thorns and stick them in the tongue of the
                            effigy.”</note> That will bind the opponent’s mouth. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-31"/>
                    <p tid="38">One should write this mantra on a clay pot with chalk, fill the pot with ashes, seal it, and bury
                        it—that will paralyze the mouths of slanderers. With clay wiped off the hand of a potter, one should make
                        an effigy of a ram, and place in its heart this mantra inscribed on birchbark with turmeric or yellow
                        orpiment, tied up with a yellow string, and enclosed in beeswax.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-336" index="14">Except for the beeswax, the Tibetan omits the details of how the mantra
                            should be written and wrapped. </note> That will put an end to their anger and paralyze their
                            mouths.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-337" index="15">Tib.: “That will paralyze the mouths
                            of any aggressors.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-32"/>
                    <p tid="39">When this mantra is written with saffron<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-338" index="16">Tib. omits “written with saffron.”</note> and worn on one’s neck or arm, one will be able to stop the
                        enemy’s weapons in battle. This king of mantras, placed at the feet of an effigy of Gaṇapati made of clay
                        from an anthill and buried at a crossroads, {3} will stop all coming and going. It will interrupt all
                        daily activities. When this king of mantras, written on birchbark or cloth and enclosed in beeswax, is put
                        in the Gaṇapati’s abdomen and placed in a new jar filled with cool<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-339" index="17">Tib. omits “cool.”</note> water, it will stop all daily activities. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-33"/>
                    <p tid="40">While traveling, one will stop thieves and the like by tying a knot on the border of one’s upper
                        garment and recalling the mantra. In a forest, one will stop animals with horns,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-340" index="18">Tib.: “animals with horns, such as the gaur.”</note> or those
                        with fangs. By throwing a lump of clay, incanted with this mantra seven times, into water, one will bind
                        the teeth of water animals. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-34"/>
                    <p tid="41">One should write this mantra on a rag from a charnel ground, in combination with the names of the
                        commanders of an opposing army, in the center of a double vajra. Outside the double vajra, one should
                        write eight <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">laṁ</foreign> syllables, and around the outside of
                        these, one should draw a double<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-341" index="19">Tib. omits
                            “double.”</note> maṇḍala of Indra. The mantra should then be placed in the abdomen of a Gaṇapati made
                        of beeswax who is adorned with the double vajra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-342" index="20">Translation based on the Tibetan. The Sanskrit reads, “The mantra should then be adorned with the
                            double vajra and placed in the abdomen of a Gaṇapati made of beeswax.”</note> When it is buried next
                        to an opposing army, it will stop that army. <ref cRef="F.3.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="42">One should place this mantra, enclosed at both ends by a syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign> flanked by two <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭha</foreign>
                        syllables, adorned by eight <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">laṁ</foreign> syllables, covered with
                        a maṇḍala of Indra, and embellished with a double vajra, in the abdomen of the effigy of Gaṇapati made of
                        clay from an anthill. One should then place it in a cremation urn and bury this urn in a cemetery.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-343" index="21">Tib. adds “or burn it in a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa of chaff</foreign>.”</note> That will stop an opposing army. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-35"/>
                    <p tid="43">If a city is on fire, one should offer a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">chaff homa</foreign> and,
                        facing the fire, throw on seven double handfuls of water, having first incanted it with the mantra. One
                        will then be able to protect any house one wishes. </p>
                    <p tid="44">By tying ashes to one’s neck, one will put an end to vomiting. One should pronounce the mantra
                        while firmly pressing the tip of one’s little finger; that will stop hiccups. With incanted ash one can
                        cure blindness.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-344" index="22">Translation based on the Tibetan.
                            The Sanskrit reads, “one will arrest vision,” possibly meaning, “one will stabilize vision.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="45">When afflicted with blistering leprosy, one should draw a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">cirikā</foreign>
                        <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-345" index="23">A kind of weapon (Monier-Williams).</note> on a
                        piece of cloth.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-346" index="24">Skt. omits “on a piece of cloth.”
                        </note> Placed at any doorstep, it will prevent diseases such as blistering leprosy in that house. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-36"/>
                    <p tid="46">Outside a village one should offer a great bali of fish, meat, alcohol, sour gruel, etc. In the
                        center of the village, one should prepare a fire pit for the rite of pacifying, with five types of
                        sacrificial wood and five types of grain smeared with ghee, and perform a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> offering. This will stop all death-causing demons and accidents. A village,
                        etc., can be protected from being handed over to another owner by simply reciting the mantra. </p>
                    <p tid="47">By reciting the mantra continuously, one will become unassailable<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-347" index="25">Tib. reflects the reading <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">adṛśyo</foreign>
                            (“invisible”).</note> by gods, demi-gods, humans, and nāgas.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-348" index="26">Tib. omits “humans” and “nāgas,” but adds “mahoragas.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="48">This king of mantras emerged from the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">ūrṇā</foreign> hair
                        between the eyebrows of the venerable lord Buddha at the time of his awakening in order to conquer the
                        four māras. It is therefore called the <title xml:lang="en">jewel of the ūrṇā</title>. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-37"/>
                    <p tid="49">To drive away snakes one should scatter gravel that has been incanted, or write the mantra on the
                        wall of a house with incanted chalk. <ref cRef="F.3.b"/> Alternatively, one should engrave the mantra with
                        a chisel on a stone tablet and bury it. That will bind the teeth of wild animals and poisonous snakes in a
                        house, village, or town for {4} as long as one desires. One breaks the spell by digging it up. This mantra
                        accomplishes all endeavors even when it has not been fully mastered. </p>
                    <lg tid="50">
                        <l>To arrest the fangs of all creatures that bite,</l>
                        <l>One should incant gravel, etc., and scatter it.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-38"/>
                    <p tid="51">All mantras should be written, together with the name of the intended person, in the center of the
                        double vajra surrounded by a maṇḍala of Indra. </p>
                    <p tid="52">By hiding eight<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-349" index="27">Tib. omits
                            “eight.”</note> splinters from a funeral pyre, incanted seven times, above an entrance door, one will
                        interrupt the livelihood of all who live there. One can break the spell by taking the splinters out. </p>
                    <label>Fourth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-39"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="298">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ nihi nicule abhayaṃkari elu velu śila pa ḍa i jahaṃ pelu
                            āgāsapantharate ha attaṃdhari khili mo ḍi them bhi jakāre jā hi ṭhakāre hi ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ svāhā |
                        </foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="299">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ nihi</foreign>, O Niculā who grants fearlessness! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Elu velu śila pa ḍa i jahaṃ pelu āgāsapantharate ha attaṃdhari khili
                            mo ḍi them bhi jakāre jā hi ṭhakāre hi ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-40"/>
                    <p tid="55">This king of mantras accomplishes all the previously mentioned acts even if it is not fully
                        mastered. Moreover, it will accomplish all other tasks that may be desired by the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mantrin</foreign>.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-350" index="28">Tib.
                            omits “by the mantrin.”</note> Making a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> offering
                        of salt and black mustard, or a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">chaff homa</foreign> will certainly
                        put an opposing army to flight. </p>
                    <label>Fifth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-41"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="300">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ ambāsimbāka pyāsu jom mo phe ḍa i du pyāsu </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="301">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Ambāsimbāka, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">pyāsu jom mo phe ḍa i du pyāsu</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-42"/>
                    <p tid="58">This king of mantras will remove all fear in all those who constantly recite it, even before it is
                        fully mastered. By making a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tika</foreign> on one’s forehead<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-351" index="29">Tib. omits “by making a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tika</foreign> on one’s forehead.”</note> with vajra water incanted seven times, one
                        will confuse all of one’s adversaries and appease their anger. If one is imprisoned, constant recitation
                        of it will set one free. When one meets with misfortune, one will be without fear. </p>
                    <label>Sixth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-43"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="302">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">eṣotthito hulu hulu jvālājihve hulu hulu yatraivotthito hulu hulu
                            tatraiva pratigacchatu hulu hulu svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="303">
                        <seg type="mantra">It has arisen; destroy it, destroy! Jvālājihvā, destroy it, destroy! Wherever it
                        has arisen—destroy it, destroy—there you should go—destroy it, destroy! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> {5} </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-44"/>
                    <p tid="61">This king of mantras brings peace to all those afflicted by the scourge of quarrels and disputes,
                        even when recited just once.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-352" index="30">Tib. omits “just
                            once.”</note>
                        <ref cRef="F.4.a"/> Performing a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">chaff homa</foreign> will pacify
                        everything. By reciting this mantra over whatever flowers one may find and letting them float on water,
                        one will surely pacify all and gain victory. If a city is on fire, one should stand facing the blaze,
                        incant seven double-handfuls of water and throw them into the fire. Thus one will be able to protect any
                        house one wishes by keeping it safe from the flames. By offering a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">chaff homa</foreign> one will pacify epidemics among bipeds and quadrupeds.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-353" index="31">Tib. has instead, “one will pacify the teeth of bipeds and
                            quadrupeds,” which makes little sense, as the teeth of bipeds seldom constitute a cause of fear.
                        </note>
                    </p>
                    <label>Seventh Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-45"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="304">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ padme padmākṣi padmasubhage phura phura phura |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="305">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, O lotus-eyed Padmā! You with the beauty of a lotus!
                        Flicker, flicker, flicker!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-46"/>
                    <p tid="64">Having<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-354" index="32">The Sanskrit sentence begins with
                            “this king of mantras,” which does not fit the context.</note> incanted some ash with this mantra, one
                        should apply it to the eyes, making a dressing<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-355" index="33">Tib. omits “making a dressing.” </note> with it; by wiping the eyes, one will remove blindness. By
                        gazing at an angry person with an eye incanted seven times, one will appease him. To have everybody’s
                        adoration, one should rinse one’s face with water incanted seven times. By writing this mantra,
                        interspersed with the beneficiary’s name, on a wall with chalk, one will cure all eye diseases. </p>
                    <p tid="65">In a place where there are no people, one should one-pointedly incant one’s eyes seven times and
                        stand with a one-pointedly focused mind. In the case of a man,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-356" index="34">Tib. omits “in the case of a man.”</note> if the left eye throbs, it
                        foretells the successful accomplishment of a task according to his wishes. If the right eye throbs, it
                        announces something bad. </p>
                    <label>Eighth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-47"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="306">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ mocani mocaya mokṣaṇi mokṣaya jīvaṃvarade svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="307">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Mocanī, release! O Mokṣaṇī, set free! O
                        Jīvaṃvaradā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-48"/>
                    <p tid="68">When a pregnant woman’s birth canal is anointed with incanted sesame oil, she will give birth with
                        ease. </p>
                    <p tid="69">Facing a bound person, one should throw seven double-handfuls of incanted water toward him in the
                        three periods of the day. The bound person will then become free from his bondage. One should write this
                        mantra with saffron or bovine orpiment on birchbark, and tie it to the head of someone who is bound; it
                        will release him from bondage. </p>
                    <label>Ninth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-49"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="308">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ hari­markaṭa­nāma­sahasra­bāhur devadattaṃ bandhanād mocaya
                            svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="309">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, O thousand-armed one called Grey Monkey, please
                        release such-and-such from bondage! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> <ref cRef="F.4.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-50"/>
                    <p tid="72">Having incanted a piece of chalk, one should repeatedly write this mantra on the ground and rub it
                        out in the opposite direction. Then a bound person will be freed from bondage. Alternatively, one should
                        write the mantra and the person’s name on a slip of birchbark<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-357" index="35">Skt. omits “and the name”; Tib. omits “birchbark.” </note> and wear it on
                        one’s head. Then a bound person will be freed from bondage. </p>
                    <label>Tenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-51"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="310">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ tāraṇi tāraya mocani mocaya mokṣaṇi mokṣaya jīvaṃvarade
                            svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="311">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Tāraṇī, liberate! Mocanī, release! Mokṣaṇī, set
                        free! Jivaṃvaradā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> {6} </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-52"/>
                    <p tid="75">This king of mantras, correctly recited, will accomplish all actions. </p>
                    <p tid="76">One should anoint a pregnant woman’s birth canal with sesame oil incanted seven times. Then she
                        will give birth with ease. A pregnant woman will also give birth easily after drinking a handful of water
                        incanted seven times. By reciting the mantra continuously, one will free oneself and others from bondage.
                        Wearing a leaf with the mantra on one’s neck or arm will release one from bondage. </p>
                    <label>Eleventh Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-53"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="312">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ tāre tu tāre ture mokṣaya jīvaṃvarade svāhā</foreign>
                        </seg>
                         |                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="313">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Tārā, powerful Tārā, please liberate! O
                        Jivaṃvaradā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-54"/>
                    <p tid="79">This king of mantras accomplishes all previously mentioned actions. One should write this mantra,
                        interwoven with the beneficiary’s name, with saffron on a piece of birchbark, surround it with beeswax,
                        place it inside a new jar filled with scented water, and worship it in the three periods of the day with
                        offerings of fragrant flowers and so forth. The person whose name has been interwoven with the mantra will
                        be victorious in all quarrels and disputes. </p>
                    <label>Twelfth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-55"/>
                    <lg rend="mantra" tid="314">
                            <seg type="mantra">
                                <l>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">eraṇḍasya vane kāko gaṅgātīram upasthitaḥ</foreign> |</l>                 
                                <l>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">pibatu dūtaḥ pānīyaṃ viśalyā bhavatu gurviṇī</foreign> ||</l>
                            </seg>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-56"/>
                    <lg rend="mantra" tid="316">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <l>The crow in a thicket of palma christi </l>
                            <l>Roosting on the bank of Ganges— </l>
                            <l>The messenger—may he drink water! </l>
                            <l>May the pregnant woman be delivered of her child!</l>
                        </seg>
                    </lg>
                    <label>Thirteenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-57"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="317">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ amaraṇi jīvantīye svāhā </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="318">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Amaraṇī! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign> to Jīvantī!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-58"/>
                    <p tid="85">This king of mantras, duly recited, can accomplish all endeavors. After water incanted with it has
                        been drunk, blisters will not appear. </p>
                    <p tid="86">One should incant turmeric, yellow myrobalan, costus, etc., and rub it into a wound caused by a
                        venomous spider, a monkey, or skin eruptions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-358" index="36">Tib. omits “spider” but adds “snake.”</note> Then one will become well. <ref cRef="F.5.a"/> At the
                        onset of any type of illness, one will become well by tying a mantra knot. </p>
                    <p tid="87">A person who is about to die will, by reciting the mantra continuously, live one hundred years. By
                        offering a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> of [incanted] sesame and ghee, one will
                        pacify all ailments. By drinking an herbal remedy incanted with this mantra, one will become free from all
                        diseases. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-59"/>
                    <p tid="88">One should besmear an ailing body part with [incanted] butter, clarified one hundred times. Then
                        the part will become well. If one has a headache, one should incant sesame oil and rub it onto one’s head.
                        One will become well. </p>
                    <p tid="89">One should make a dressing of [incanted] water over a festering wound and it will heal. In the
                        case of enlargement of the spleen, one should split an eggplant with an [incanted] machete. This will make
                        the enlargement disappear. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-60"/>
                    <p tid="90">One should bring together a root of the five-leaved chaste tree, a root of the margosa tree, and a
                        peacock’s feather, and incant them one hundred and eight times and add incense.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-359" index="37">According to the Tibetan, it is the incense that should be
                            incanted 108 times.</note> This will cure fevers—a one-, two-, three-, or four-day fever, etc. It will
                        also chase away ghosts, spirits of the deceased, ghouls, gods, and demons. </p>
                    <p tid="91"> A woman whose child has died can bring that child back to life by bathing it from a jar incanted
                        with the mantra one hundred and eight times. {7} A woman who carries this mantra, written on birchbark, on
                        her waist or arm will have her fetus protected. </p>
                    <p tid="92"> When one recalls this mantra in battle, one will meet with victory. </p>
                    <p tid="93">By using the mantra for cleansing<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-360" index="38">Based
                            on the Tibetan (the Sanskrit is unclear).</note> one will remove all diseases.</p>
                    <label>Fourteenth Mantra </label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-61"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="319">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ pādacalane svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="320">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Pādacalanā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-62"/>
                    <p tid="96">This king of mantras, when fully mastered, will accomplish all endeavors after the prescribed
                        preliminary practice. When one is in danger of developing the blisters of leprosy, one should drink water
                        incanted with it and the leprosy will not appear. If this mantra is written on a leaf<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-361" index="39">Tib.: “on a leaf or parchment.”</note> and placed by the door,
                        the leprosy will not come. In all dangers, a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign>
                        oblation of sesame mixed with ghee will afford great protection. </p>
                    <p tid="97"> One should incant a crow’s wing, holding it in one’s hand. Throwing it onto the roof of any house
                        will then drive out its owner. <ref cRef="F.5.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <label>Fifteenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-63"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="321">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ piśācī parṇaśabari sarvopadrava­nāśani svāhā </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="322">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, demoness Parṇaśabarī! Remover of all misfortunes,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-64"/>
                    <p tid="100">This great mantra removes all misfortunes that afflict bipeds and quadrupeds and accomplishes all
                        endeavors, even when it has not been fully mastered. </p>
                    <p tid="101">A <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> offering, mantra recitation,
                            meditation,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-362" index="40">Tib. omits “meditation.”</note> a
                        mantra knot, a drink of incanted water, or cleansing with incanted water will remove all diseases. </p>
                    <p tid="102">One should write the mantra with turmeric on birchbark and wear it on one’s arm or neck. Thus one
                        will obtain success in business transactions.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-363" index="41">Tib.: “disputes.”</note> One will be cured even of the quartan fever and other recurring fevers. One
                        will be rid of the danger of rākṣasas, etc. One will be victorious in quarrels and disputes. One will
                        become invisible to tigers, alligators, mahoragas, thieves, etc. By reciting it non-stop, one will be
                        adored by everyone. </p>
                    <label>Sixteenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-65"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="323">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ adya tṛtīyā amukasya cakṣuḥ stambhaya ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ
                            svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="324">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, now you are the third. Stabilize the vision of
                        such-and-such a person! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ṭhaḥ ṭhaḥ</foreign>! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-66"/>
                    <p tid="105">On whichever lunar day one’s sight deteriorates, the name of that day should be written with
                        chalk on a wall or a tablet. It should be enclosed three times with three <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭhaḥ</foreign> syllables.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-364" index="42">The Devanāgarī letter <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ṭha</foreign> has the shape of a circle, and it can
                            therefore be drawn around objects or shapes.</note> The visual problem will be cured. </p>
                    <label>Seventeenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-67"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="325">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa hūṁ phaṭ </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="326">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign> Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">hūṁ
                            phaṭ</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-68"/>
                    <p tid="108">This king of mantras, pronounced once, burns all evil. It affords protection in every way. One
                        will remove the danger of<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-365" index="43">Tib.: “possession
                            by.”</note> spirits, etc., by pelting them with beans, etc.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-366" index="44">Tib.: “mustard seeds.”</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="109">Having written this mantra with chalk on a platter, one should hang it by the door. {8} This will
                        protect newborn babies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-69"/>
                    <p tid="110">One should make a beeswax effigy, four fingers long, and insert this mantra, written along with
                        the name of the person targeted, into its heart. If one pierces its mouth with a thorn the opponent’s
                        mouth will be nailed. If one pierces its feet, one will stop him moving. If one pierces its heart, it will
                        quell his anger. Whichever body parts one seizes and pierces with a splinter of human shinbone or an iron
                        nail, his equivalent body parts will decay. If one buries the effigy under an enemy’s door, one will drive
                        him out. <ref cRef="F.6.a"/> One can also drive an enemy out by throwing incanted ashes from a charnel
                        ground on the lintel of his door. </p>
                    <p tid="111">Incanting one’s sword will bring victory if one goes into battle. </p>
                    <p tid="112">To fulfil any need need, one should offer a bali, and that need will be fulfilled. Whatever the
                        follower of Mantrayāna desires, whether wholesome or unwholesome, he will accomplish it all merely by
                        reciting the mantra. </p>
                    <label>Eighteenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-70"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="327">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kāśe syanda kuśe syanda syanda tvaṃ śūnyaveśmani mama tvaṃ
                            tathā syanda yathā syandasi vajriṇaḥ svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="328">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, flow into the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kāśa</foreign> grass, flow into the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kuśa</foreign> grass, flow into an
                        empty house! Flow for me as you flow for the possessor of the vajra! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <p tid="115">For conjunctivitis, relief will come after wiping the eyes.</p>
                    <label>Nineteenth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-71"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="329">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ jambhe mohe hṛdaya­hṛdayāvartani hūṁ phaṭ svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="330">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Jambhā, Mohā! You who make one heart turn toward
                        another heart! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Hūṁ phaṭ</foreign>! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-72"/>
                    <p tid="118">By rinsing one’s face with water incanted seven times with this king of mantras early in the
                        morning before crows start to caw, one will be adored by everyone. </p>
                    <p tid="119">When the moon is in the asterism of Puṣya, one should take some lampblack with a garland of white
                        lotuses and cow’s ghee<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-367" index="45">This clause is unclear
                            both in the Sanskrit and the Tibetan.</note> and incant it 108 times. Anyone whose eyes have been
                        anointed with this substance will steal the hearts of all wanton<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-368" index="46">Tib. omits “wanton.”</note> women. </p>
                    <p tid="120">One should blend sandalwood with the root of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">adhaḥpuṣpikā</foreign> and make a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tika</foreign> with this
                        substance. When the mantra is incanted 108 times, a capable practitioner will be able to appease others’
                        anger, and will be victorious in disputes and quarrels. One who recites the mantra continuously according
                        to the ritual will be able to make a city tremble. </p>
                    <label>Twentieth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-73"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="331">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ stambhani stambhaya jambhani jambhaya mohani mohaya rakṣaṇi
                            rakṣaya māṁ varade siddha­locane svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="332">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Stambhanī, immobilize! Jambhanī, destroy! Mohanī,
                        delude! Rakṣaṇī, protect me! Varadā, Siddhalocanā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <p tid="123">This heart mantra of Locanā will remove all fear.</p>
                    <trailer tid="407">This was the first chapter in the <title xml:lang="en">Great Sovereign Tantra of
                            Siddhaikavīra</title>. {9}</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="419">Chapter 2</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-74"/>
                    <lg tid="124">
                        <l>One should explain this king of tantras </l>
                        <l>To a disciple who is an awakened Buddhist, </l>
                        <l>Who has many good qualities,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-369" index="47">Tib.: “who has
                                the potential for good qualities.”</note>
                        </l>
                        <l>Who is devoted to his teacher, and who is skilled.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-75"/>
                    <lg tid="125">
                        <l>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, homage to the god Vimalacandra! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <lg tid="126">
                        <l>The world is sustained by truth;</l>
                        <l>It is preserved by truth;</l>
                        <l>Through truth, it abides in Dharma;</l>
                        <l>Truth is eternal as Brahman.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-370" index="48">In the Tibetan,
                                this verse and the next are transcribed in Sanskrit, like a mantra.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-76"/>
                    <lg tid="127">
                        <l>Truth is the Buddha, the Dharma, and the Saṃgha;</l>
                        <l>It is the ocean of qualities.</l>
                        <l>By these words of truth</l>
                        <l>May you swiftly enter the mirror.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-371" index="49">We have a
                                play on words here, as <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">darpaṇa</foreign> can mean “mirror”
                                as well as be the name of the mountain of Kubera. Both of these meanings are required for the
                                context that follows. </note>
                            <ref cRef="F.6.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <p tid="128">As here follows:</p>
                    <label>Twenty-First Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-77"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="333">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ sara sara siri siri suru suru meru­mandara­pratīkāśa āviśa
                            āviśa kailāsa­kūṭa­putrāya namaḥ svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="334">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, run, run! Move, move! Go, go! Become like Mount
                        Meru, become! Homage to the Kailāsakūṭa­putra! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-78"/>
                    <lg tid="131">
                        <l>“Whatever task I can think of,</l>
                        <l>Please explain it to me in its entirety, according to the facts,</l>
                        <l> Regardless of whether it is for one’s own sake, or the sake of another,</l>
                        <l>Whether it is wholesome or unwholesome.”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-372" index="50">In
                                the Tibetan, this verse is transcribed, like a mantra.</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-79"/>
                    <p tid="132">Early in the morning, in a clean place, one should draw a maṇḍala, set up a jar, and make
                        generous offerings to the god Vimalacandra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-373" index="51">Skt.
                            omits “to the god Vimalacandra.”</note> One should incant the mirror and show it to a boy or girl who
                        is well washed,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-374" index="52">According to Jamyang Khyentse
                            Wangpo’s commentary, “well washed” means “washed with water from the jar.” </note> dressed in very
                        clean clothes, anointed with white sandalwood paste and wearing a necklace of sweet-smelling flowers, and
                        uncorrupted by “villagers’ dharma.”<!-- Removed because it was duplicated with gloss <note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-375" index="53">“Villagers’
                            dharma” is a euphemism for carnal knowledge.</note>--> Then the mirror will reveal without error what
                        should be done as regards the intended task. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-80"/>
                    <p tid="133">In the evening, one should wipe the top surface of the maṇḍala disc and make generous offerings
                        to the god, lord Vimalacandra.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-376" index="53">Tib.: “to the
                            Blessed One and the god Vimalacandra.”</note> Having made an offering 108 times, one should go to
                        sleep without speaking. The beneficial and harmful results of the task one has in mind will be revealed.
                        To those who recite the mantra continuously, the events taking place in the three worlds will be revealed. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Second Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-81"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="335">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ śravaṇa­piśācini muṇḍe svāhā </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="336">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Śravaṇa­piśācī, Muṇḍā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> {10}</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-82"/>
                    <p tid="136">If one stands under a belleric myrobalan tree or under a banyan tree and silently recites the
                        mantra 100,000 times, one will attain success. Muṇḍā, whispering in one’s ear,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-377" index="54">Tib. omits “Muṇḍā, whispering in one’s ear.”</note> will recount all that
                        is happening in the three worlds. Alternatively, bathed and dressed in clean clothes, one should recite it
                        10,000 times in a secluded place. Then one will attain success. </p>
                    <p tid="137">At night, one should incant costus root 108 times. Then, having anointed one’s face and feet with
                        it, one should go to sleep without speaking. It will then be revealed in one’s sleep what will be
                        beneficial and what will not. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Third Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-83"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="337">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ namaḥ saptānāṃ samyak­saṃbuddha­koṭīnām | tadyathā | oṁ cale
                            cule cunde mahāvidye satyavādini varade kathaya kathaya svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="338">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, homage to the seven <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">koṭis</foreign> of
                        perfectly awakened buddhas! Just as here follows, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, Calā, Culā,
                        Cundā, Mahāvidyā, Satyavādinī, Varadā, speak, speak! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-84"/>
                    <p tid="140">If one follows here the same procedure described for the previous mantra, Calā will reveal things
                        in a mirror, a conch, a candle, or a dish of water. One who recites the mantra silently, after washing his
                        face with water incanted 108 times, will perceive in his sleep what is beneficial and what is not. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Fourth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-85"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="339">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ mucili svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">mohani svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">dantili
                            svāhā</foreign>  |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="340">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, Mucilī, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svāhā</foreign>! Mohanī,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svāhā</foreign>! Dantilī, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-86"/>
                    <p tid="143">This mantra<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-378" index="55">Tib.: “secret
                            mantra.”</note> can be mastered by reciting it 10,000 times. <ref cRef="F.7.a"/> One should make
                        generous offerings to the blessed noble lord Avalokiteśvara, wash one’s face with water incanted 108
                        times, and recite the mantra, having set one’s mind on the task to be accomplished. If one goes to sleep
                        without speaking, one will behold the lord as one’s own body and learn what will be beneficial and what
                        will not. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Fifth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-87"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="341">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ prajvala hūṁ phaṭ  |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="342">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, Prajvala! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hūṁ, phaṭ</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-88"/>
                    <p tid="146">This mantra is the heart essence of Lord Lokanātha. One will attain success by reciting it one
                        million times. If one follows here the same ritual described for the previous mantra, it will be revealed
                        in one’s dreams what is beneficial and what is not. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Sixth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-89"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="343">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ namaḥ saptānāṃ buddhānām apratihata­śāsanānām</foreign> |
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">tadyathā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kumāra­rūpeṇa darśaya darśaya ātmano vibhūtiṃ samudbhāvaya svapnaṃ nivedaya yathābhūtaṃ hūṁ hūṁ
                            phaṭ phaṭ svāhā </foreign>|</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="344">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, homage to the seven buddhas whose teachings are inviolable! As
                        here follows: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, show yourself in the form of the Youthful One,
                        show! Manifest your power! Send me a dream to reveal the way things are! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hūṁ,
                            hūṁ</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Phaṭ, phaṭ</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> {11} </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-90"/>
                    <p tid="149">One should make offerings, according to one’s ability, in front of a painting or a statue of
                        venerable Mañjuśrī,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-379" index="56">Tib.: “venerable youthful
                            Mañjuśrī.”</note> or by a memorial that contains his body relics. If one recites the mantra seven
                        hundred times, one will oneself behold the lord in a dream and show him to others, too. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Seventh Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-91"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="345">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ karṇapiśāci karṇe me kathaya hūṁ phaṭ </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="346">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Karṇapiśācī, whisper into my ear! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Hūṁ phaṭ</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-92"/>
                    <p tid="152">Beneath a tree inhabited by piśācas, one should observe silence and sit absorbed in the samādhi
                        of conquering the three worlds. Then, one should incant meat, fish,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-380" index="57">The Tib. adds “human flesh.”</note> and black plum, and with them prepare
                        a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">bali</foreign>. One should recite the mantra in the three periods
                        of the day. On the first day Karṇapiśācī will give a sign. Later, she will come, and one will attain
                        success. From then on, whispering into one’s ear, she will recount all that is happening in the three
                        worlds. After twenty-one days, one will succeed even in killing Brahmā. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Eighth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-93"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="347">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra"> oṁ caturbhuja ṣaṇmukha vikṛtānana karṇapiśācīm ākarṣaya hūṁ
                            phaṭ |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="348">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, the four-armed and six-faced one! You with a
                        contorted face! Please summon Karṇapiśācī! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Hūṁ phaṭ</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <p tid="155">One should recite [this mantra] in a charnel ground in front of a painting of Yamāntaka. After
                        twenty-one days,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-381" index="58">Tib.: “one week.”</note>
                        Karṇapiśācī will be in one’s control. </p>
                    <label>Twenty-Ninth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-94"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="349">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ buddha curu curu mārge svāhā  |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="350">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Buddha! Curu, curu on the path! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-95"/>
                    <p tid="158">In a memorial containing his relics, or in front of the venerable Buddha, one should recite the
                        mantra 10,000 times as preliminary practice. Later, one should make offerings according to one’s ability.
                            <ref cRef="F.7.b"/> At bedtime, one should recite the mantra eight hundred times. One should go to
                        sleep with the following question in one’s mind: “What was my past existence, and what will my future
                        existence be?” In one’s sleep, one will perceive one’s past and future births, there is no doubt. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-96"/>
                    <p tid="159">If one is to die within six months, then in one’s dream one will not be able to see one’s own
                        head or those of others. Similarly, a boy or a girl whom one sees in an incanted mirror with his or her
                        head invisible will die within six months.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-382" index="59">The
                            translation is based on the Tibetan. The Sanskrit suggests that, rather than the head, one will not
                            see the neck.</note>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="160">One should make an unguent from malachite and the root of white <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">agastya</foreign> tree, incant it 108 times, and smear it on one’s eyes. One will
                        distinctly see without heads all those who are going to die within six months, whether humans or animals. </p>
                    <label>Thirtieth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-97"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="351">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ svapna­vilokini siddha­locane svapnaṃ me kathaya svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="352">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Svapnavilokinī! Siddhalocanā! Interpret my dream
                        for me! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> {12}</p>
                    <p tid="163">This king of mantras works with all the methods previously described.</p>
                    <label>Thirty-First Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-98"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="353">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ aditi devadattāṃ me dehi dadāpaya svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="354">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Aditi, give me such-and-such a girl! Please give!
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-99"/>
                    <p tid="166">If one recites this mantra surrounded by water, one will be given the girl one has in mind. </p>
                    <p tid="167">One should recite the mantra 100,000 times for each syllable. By offering a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">priyaṅgu</foreign> flowers or <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">palāśa</foreign> flowers one will obtain great splendor. </p>
                    <p tid="168"> If one recites this mantra at night while performing a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign>
                        using the wood of a milk tree, one will obtain any village for which one performs the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> and recitation. </p>
                    <p tid="169">By performing 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> rituals with lotuses or bilva
                        fruits, one born into a royal family will obtain the kingdom. Others will obtain great splendor. </p>
                    <p tid="170">When one offers 700,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> rituals with any type of
                        flowers, one will obtain inexhaustible wealth. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Second Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-100"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="355">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ jaye vijaye ajite aparājite svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="356">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Jayā, Vijayā, Ajitā, Aparājitā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="173">Reciting this king of the heart mantras of the four sisters 400,000 times, following the same
                        procedures as described previously, will accomplish all the rituals described previously. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Third Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-101"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="357">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ megholkāya svāhā </foreign>|</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="358">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Megholka!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="176">By offering a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> with flowers of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">palāśa</foreign> tree 100,000 times, using, as an option, firewood from
                        the same tree, one will obtain 100,000 pieces of gold. <ref cRef="F.8.a"/> One who wishes for a girl will
                        soon obtain the one he desires. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Fourth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-102"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="359">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kamalavikāsini kamale mahālakṣmi rājyaṃ me dehi varade
                            svāhā |</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="360">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Kamalavikāsinī, Kamalā, Mahālakṣmī, give me the
                        kingdom! You who grant boons, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-103"/>
                    <p tid="179">This mantra is the essence of Mahālakṣmī. When recited continuously, it will bring enormous
                        glory. By offering a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> of whatever flowers are
                        available, one will obtain great splendor and any girl one desires. By offering 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">homas</foreign> of bdellium pills the size of a kernel of a cotton
                        tree, smeared with the three sweet substances, or 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of lotuses, one will obtain a kingdom. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Fifth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-104"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="361">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ nandini varade kiṇi kiṇi khiṇi khiṇi śriyaṃ me dada vauṣaṭ
                        </foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="362">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Nandinī! You who grant boons! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Kiṇi, kiṇi! Khiṇi, khiṇi</foreign>! Give me splendor! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Vauṣaṭ</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <p tid="182">This king of mantras is the heart essence of Nandinī. It accomplishes all the previously
                        described activities.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-383" index="60">Tib.: “This king of Nandinī
                            mantras accomplishes all…”</note> {13} </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Sixth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-105"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="363">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ jambhe mohe svāhā</foreign>  |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="364">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Jambhā! Mohā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="185">This king of mantras brings the fulfillment of wishes when one makes offerings of oleander
                        flowers to the venerable Tārā and recites the mantra 100,000 times for each syllable. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Seventh Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-106"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="365">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasudhāriṇi svāhā</foreign>  | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ śrīvasu svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasuśriye
                            svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasumukhi svāhā | oṁ vasu­matiśriye
                            svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="366">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vasudharā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Śrīvasu, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vasuśrī, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vasumukhī, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vasumatiśrī, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-107"/>
                    <p tid="188">One should imagine oneself in the form of Jambhala, and visualize in one’s heart, in the center
                        of a moon disk, the goddess Vasudharā, who is of golden color, has two arms, and is adorned with all
                        adornments. In the four directions, starting with the east, she is surrounded by four goddesses. Her right
                        hand is in a boon-granting gesture, and in her left she is holding grain and a cluster of blossoms.
                        Visualizing her like this will bring fulfillment of one’s wishes. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-108"/>
                    <p tid="189">One should draw a four-sided maṇḍala with cow dung, two hands in diameter, and offer
                            sweet-smelling<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-384" index="61">Skt. omits
                            “sweet-smelling.”</note> flowers in the three periods of the day. When one has done 4,000 recitations,
                        one’s wishes will become fulfilled within six months. </p>
                    <p tid="190">By offering 400,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of whatever flowers
                        may be available, one will obtain great splendor. By reciting the mantra 100,000 times for each syllable,
                        one will ensure great splendor. After offering 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of bdellium pills, one’s wishes will come true. <ref cRef="F.8.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Eighth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-109"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="367">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasudhāriṇi amukīṃ kanyāṃ me dehi dadāpaya svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="368">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vasudharā, give such-and-such girl to me! Cause her
                        to be given to me! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-110"/>
                    <p tid="193">Observing one’s minor vows,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-385" index="62">Tib. omits
                            “observing one’s minor vows.”</note> one should bathe and, while in the water, recite this mantra
                        400,000 times. Then one will obtain the girl one desires. </p>
                    <p tid="194"> At night, one should do a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> offering 100,000
                        times with the wood of a milk tree, including [in the mantra] the name of a village. Then one will obtain
                        that village. </p>
                    <label>Thirty-Ninth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-111"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="369">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasudhāriṇi svāhā</foreign>  | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ candrakāntyai svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ dattāyai
                            svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vasudattāyai svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ āryāyai svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ subhadrāyai svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ guptāyai svāhā</foreign>
                         | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ devyai svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ sarasvatyai svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="370">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign> Vasudharā, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Candrakāntī! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>,
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Dattā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Vasudattā!
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Āryā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Subhadrā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Guptā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>
                        to Devī! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign> to Sarasvatī!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-112"/>
                    <p tid="197">One should draw Vasudharā on a gold, silver, or copper leaf in the center of an eight-petaled
                        lotus. On its petals, starting from the east, one should draw the great yakṣiṇīs, Candrakāntī, and so
                        forth. One should then enclose it in two leaves and place it in between ghee, honey, and sugar.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-386" index="63">According to the Tibetan, the ghee, honey, and
                            sugar are inside the two leaves. The Sanskrit, however, seems to reflect the standard way of placing
                            the yantra between the three sweet things.</note> By following the same procedures as previously
                        described, one will accomplish the tasks previously described. {14} </p>
                    <label>Fortieth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-113"/>
                    <lg tid="291">
                        <l>In the center:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="371">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ jambhala­jalendrāya svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="372">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Jambhala, the lord of the waters!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-114"/>
                    <lg tid="201">
                        <l>In the cardinal directions:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="373">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ maṇibhadrāya svāhā</foreign>  | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ pūrṇabhadrāya svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ dhanadāya
                            svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vaiśravaṇāya svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="374">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Maṇibhadra! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Pūrṇabhadra! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ,
                            svāhā</foreign> to Dhanada! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to
                        Vaiśravaṇa!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-115"/>
                    <lg tid="204">
                        <l>In the intermediate directions:</l>
                    </lg>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="375">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kelimāline svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vicitrakuṇḍaline svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ
                            sukhendrāya svāhā</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ carendrāya svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="376">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Kelimālin! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Vicitra­kuṇḍalin! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ,
                            svāhā</foreign> to Sukhendra! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to
                        Carendra!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-116"/>
                    <p tid="207">The lord is surrounded by the eight great kings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-387" index="64">Skt. omits “kings.”</note> of the yakṣas, and accompanied by the goddess
                        Vasudharā. He is of golden color, holding a mongoose and a citron, with a protruding belly, and adorned
                        with all the jewel ornaments. The yakṣa lords, for their part, are accompanied by the yakṣiṇīs mentioned.
                        The lord can even grant the rulership of the three worlds to those who meditate, make offerings during the
                        three periods of the day, and recite the mantras, or to those who offer eight hundred handfuls of water. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-117"/>
                    <p tid="208">One who recites this early in the morning, before crows start to caw, while standing in water,
                        will have an inexhaustible accumulation of wealth. </p>
                    <p tid="209">Alternatively, on a golden plate one should engrave Vasudharā surrounded by the yakṣiṇīs, and on
                        a second plate Lord Jambhala surrounded by the yakṣas. <ref cRef="F.9.a"/> One should join them together
                        and wear<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-388" index="65">Tib.: “serve.”</note> them. Then the
                        lord will grant the eight great siddhis, not to mention other siddhis. </p>
                    <trailer tid="408">This was the second chapter in the <title xml:lang="en">Great Sovereign Tantra of
                            Siddhaikavīra</title>. {15} </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="420"> Chapter 3</head>
                    <label>Forty-First Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-118"/>
                    <lg rend="mantra" tid="377">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <l>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vajratīkṣṇa duḥkhaccheda prajñā­jñāna­mūrtaye</foreign> |</l>
                            <l>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">jñānakāya vāgīśvara arapacanāya te namaḥ</foreign> ||</l>
                        </seg>
                    </lg>
                    <lg rend="mantra" tid="212">
                            <seg type="mantra">
                                <l>
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vajratīkṣṇa! You who cut through suffering!</l>
                                <l>The embodiment of wisdom and knowledge!</l>
                                <l>The body of knowledge, Vāgīśvara—</l>
                                <l>Homage to Arapacana!</l>
                            </seg>                    
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-119"/>
                    <p tid="213">One should visualize oneself in the form of Lord Mañjuvajra Siddhaikavīra, white like the light
                        of the autumn moon. In his left hand he is holding a blue lotus and his right hand is in the boon-granting
                        gesture. He is the pure sphere of phenomena, shining forth from his primordially unborn nature.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-389" index="66">In the Tibetan the last sentence is transcribed as
                            a Sanskrit mantra. In the Sanskrit, however, it is impossible to take it as such.</note> After
                        twenty-one days one will obtain the speech of Sarasvatī.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-390" index="67">The translation “the speech of Sarasvatī” is based on emended Sanskrit
                            reading (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sarasvatīṃ vāṇīm to sarasvatī­vāṇīm</foreign>).</note> Within six
                        months, one will accomplish Vāgīśvara. One will see Vāgīśvara right in front of oneself and remember
                        everything one has heard. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-120"/>
                    <p tid="214">If, early in the morning, over the period of one month, one drinks half a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tola</foreign> of sweet flag, incanted 108 times, with milk, oil, or ghee, one will
                        cure dullness,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-391" index="68">Tib. omits “dullness.”</note>
                        stammering, or dumbness; one’s voice will become like that of a love-intoxicated cuckoo; and one’s speech
                        will be distinct and sweet. After six months of practice, the treatises one has not heard will become
                        clearly known, and those that have been learned will not be forgotten. One will be able to retain whatever
                        one has learned. </p>
                    <label>Forty-Second Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-121"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="379">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ vākyedaṃ namaḥ</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="380">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vākya! Homage to you!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-122"/>
                    <p tid="217">This is the heart mantra of the venerable Vāgīśvara. One who is practicing this mantra while
                        absorbed in the samādhi described earlier can accomplish all the tasks that were previously mentioned. One
                        should gather 100,000 jasmine flower buds and descend into the waters of a great river flowing toward the
                        ocean to where the water reaches up to one’s neck. Reciting this mantra, one should throw the buds, one by
                        one, into the stream. Should any bud float against the stream, one should swallow it without touching it
                        with one’s teeth. Then one will be granted the ability to remember everything that has been learned. </p>
                    <p tid="218">Similarly, by offering 400,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of any type
                        of flower, one will become identical to Vāgīśvara. <ref cRef="F.9.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-123"/>
                    <p tid="219">Early in the morning, one should prepare a maṇḍala disc using one cat’s paw<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-392" index="69">“Cat’s paw” is a particular measure of weight. The Tibetan
                            suggests “four karṣas.”</note> of powdered pennywort and incant it 108 times. One should then make as
                        many offerings to Lord Vāgīśvara<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-393" index="70">Skt. omits
                            “Vāgīśvara.”</note> as one can, and drink the powder with ghee or fermented rice water. Within six
                        months one will be able to remember whatever one has learned; one will be eloquent and have a sweet voice.
                        This king of mantras will be mastered if one recites it 100,000 times for each syllable according to the
                        procedure of the preliminary practice. Later, during a lunar eclipse or a solar eclipse, one should hold a
                        sword wrought from fine iron in one’s hand, and recite the mantra while the moon is invisible, until it
                        reappears. One will then become a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">vidyādhara</foreign> of the
                        sword. In the same way one may use the mantra to empower a wheel, a scepter, a trident, an arrow, a
                        hammer, a noose, and so forth. After that, one should refine and empower the elixirs of long life. One
                        should prepare the substances for an eye ointment, a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">tika</foreign>
                        ointment, an ointment for the feet, a salve of enthrallment, etc., and empower them. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-124"/>
                    <p tid="220">One should fill up a dish with either milk or yogurt mixed with rice, together with ghee and
                        sugar. One should recite the mantra while covering it with one’s hand {16} and then eat it. Then one will
                        live for five hundred years. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-125"/>
                    <p tid="221">One should put some beans in one’s mouth and recite the mantra. If sprouts come forth,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-394" index="71">Tib.: “if they are swallowed.”</note> one will
                        become eloquent, learned, skilled in writing, and able to remember all that one has learned. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-126"/>
                    <p tid="222">If one offers 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of lotuses, the lord
                        will clearly appear before one. With 100,000 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of
                        bilva fruits, one will obtain the kingship of the triple universe. If one offers 400,000<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-395" index="72">Tib. omits “400,000.”</note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homas</foreign> of whatever kind of flowers may be available, one
                        will obtain mastery of speech. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-127"/>
                    <p tid="223"> With 400,000 <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> offerings of five types of
                        grain smeared with ghee, one will be able to summon a yakṣiṇī or a girl from the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pātāla</foreign>. In the same way, one should offer five types of wood. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-128"/>
                    <p tid="224">Practiced continuously, the mantra will even lead to the state of awakening in this very
                        lifetime. </p>
                    <label>Forty-Third Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-129"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="381">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ hrīḥ hūṁ</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="382">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ hrīḥ hūṁ.</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="227">This king of mantras will grant the same result.</p>
                    <label>Forty-Fourth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-130"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="383">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ hrīḥ mahāmāyāṅge mahā­sarasvatyai namaḥ</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="384">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, hrīḥ</foreign>, Mahāmāyāṅgā! Homage to Mahāsarasvatī!</seg> <ref cRef="F.10.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-131"/>
                    <p tid="230">This heart mantra of the venerable, noble Tārā accomplishes all actions. Reciting the mantra
                            “<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, all phenomena are pure by nature. I am pure by nature on
                        both the outside and inside,”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-396" index="73">Skt.: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ prakṛti­pari­śuddhāḥ sarva­dharmāḥ prakṛti­pari­śuddho ‘haṃ
                                sabāhyābhyantaram</foreign>  |</note> one should meditate that everything animate and inanimate,
                        as well as oneself, is pure by nature. One should visualize a white lotus seven hands in diameter, on top
                        of it a moon disk, and in the center of the moon disk the goddess in all her splendor, one hand holding a
                        lotus and the other displaying the boon-granting gesture. The nature of the Blessed Lady’s body is great
                        compassion. She is there solely to benefit others. She delights in granting practitioners the siddhis they
                        desire. She is white like the rays of the autumn moon, anointed with cream of white sandalwood, and
                        beautifully adorned with flowers.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-397" index="74">Skt. omits
                            “anointed with cream of white sandalwood, and beautifully adorned with flowers.”</note> She is dressed
                        in white garments; pearl necklaces, white and so forth,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-398" index="75">Tib. omits “white, and so forth.”</note> gleam on her chest, and many
                        jewels adorn her body. She illuminates the endless and limitless world sphere with thousands of flashing
                        light rays. She has the form of a twelve-year-old girl, her body in all the fresh beauty of budding youth.
                        One should visualize oneself thus in the form of Mahāsarasvatī, with Prajñā in front, Medhā to the right,
                        Mati behind, and Smṛti to the left—each goddess beautiful, with the same characteristics as just
                        described. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-132"/>
                    <p tid="231">Then, in the area of one’s navel, in the center of a moon disc, one should visualize a white
                        syllable <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign>. Now one should recite the mantra, visualizing its
                        complete garland as the nature of speech emerging from the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign> in an unbroken stream.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-399" index="76">Tib. omits “in an unbroken stream.”</note> The follower of Mantra, with
                        his mind wholly focused on this practice and his body disciplined, sitting silently in the center of a sun
                        disc the color of red lotus,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-400" index="77">Instead of “in the
                            center of a sun disc of the color of red lotus,” the Tibetan has “in the navel of the goddess.”</note>
                        will obtain the speech of Sarasvatī within one month. Within three months he will succeed even in the
                        slaying of Brahmā. Within six months, he will become equal to Sarasvatī. {17} </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-133"/>
                    <lg tid="232">
                        <l>One should drink well-prepared Sarasvatī’s<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-401" index="78">Instead of “well prepared Sarasvatī’s…” the Tibetan seems to be saying, “in order to accomplish
                                Sarasvatī.” The epithet sārasvata is again used to qualify ghee in the section of the forty-sixth
                                mantra below.</note> ghee</l>
                        <l>Incanted seven times</l>
                        <l>Together with goat’s milk, yellow myrobalan, the three hot substances,</l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pāṭhā, ugrā</foreign>, drum-stick plant, and salt. <ref cRef="F.10.b"/>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-134"/>
                    <lg tid="233">
                        <l>A wise person should cook one prastha of ghee</l>
                        <l>With four times the amount of milk<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-402" index="79">Tib.:
                                “goat’s milk.” </note>
                        </l>
                        <l>And one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pala</foreign> of each of the ingredients mentioned previously,</l>
                        <l>Slowly, on a low fire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-135"/>
                    <lg tid="234">
                        <l>If one consumes it for just one month</l>
                        <l>One will obtain an unsurpassable gift of language.</l>
                        <l>After a preliminary practice of six months,</l>
                        <l>One will attain the state of Vāgīśvara.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-136"/>
                    <lg tid="235">
                        <l>One will master language by licking</l>
                        <l>Sweet flag, licorice, spiked ginger lily, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siṃhī</foreign>, </l>
                        <l>
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pathyā, nāgara,</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">dīpaka,</foreign>
                        </l>
                        <l>Together with costus, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kaṇa</foreign>, and cumin.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-137"/>
                    <lg tid="236">
                        <l>Early in the morning, one should make offerings to the goddess</l>
                        <l>With fragrant flowers and so forth.</l>
                        <l>By eating the above ingredients, incanted seven times,</l>
                        <l>One will become able, within six months, to remember what one hears.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-138"/>
                    <lg tid="237">
                        <l>Within three months one will become a master of speech,</l>
                        <l>And within one month one becomes an intelligent person.</l>
                        <l>One will have a sweet voice </l>
                        <l>Like a cuckoo intoxicated with love.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-139"/>
                    <lg tid="238">
                        <l>Early in the morning one should incant seven times</l>
                        <l>Himalayan yellow myrobalan </l>
                        <l>And Himalayan sweet flag.</l>
                        <l>One should leave them standing for one month and then eat them.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-140"/>
                    <lg tid="239">
                        <l>Within a month one will become an intelligent person,</l>
                        <l>A master of language with a beautiful voice, and full of knowledge. </l>
                        <l>Within six months one will be able to remember </l>
                        <l>Everything that one has learned.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <label>Forty-Fifth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-141"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="385">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vāgvādini vācaṃ me niyaccha sarasvati mahāśvete
                            svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="386">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vāgvādinī, grant me the gift of speech! Sarasvatī!
                        Mahāśvetā! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p tid="242">This heart mantra of the Great White Goddess born from a lotus<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-403" index="80">The translation “born from a lotus” is based on the Tibetan and on the
                            emended Sanskrit reading (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">°āmbujāyāḥ to °āmbujajāyāḥ</foreign>).</note>
                        accomplishes all the tasks described previously.</p>
                    <label>Forty-Sixth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-142"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="387">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ arkamālini kiṇi kiṇi khiṇi khiṇi svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="388">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, Arkamālinī! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Kiṇi
                            kiṇi</foreign>! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Khiṇi khiṇi</foreign>! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-143"/>
                    <p tid="245">One should visualize oneself as the youthful lord Mañjuvajra Siddhaikavīra. He is free from the
                        afflictions, holds a book that embodies all statements,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-404" index="81">Skt. omits “that embodies all statements.”</note> and brandishes the
                        sword of wisdom in his right hand. In front of him, one should visualize the sunlight-garlanded
                        Mahāsarasvatī; behind him, Mahāśrī; to his right, Keśinī; and to his left, Upakeśinī. One should visualize
                        them as white like the autumn moon and adorned with every ornament.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-405" index="82">Tib. omits “adorned with every ornament.”</note> While resting in this
                        visualization one should first make offerings to the best of one’s ability {18} and then recite this
                        mantra 400,000 times following the procedures of the preliminary practice as already described. <ref cRef="F.11.a"/> Then, one should incant one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pala</foreign> of Sarasvatī’s
                        ghee or pennywort ghee. Next, one should visualize that Sarasvatī offers this substance to oneself with
                        her hand. Absorbed in samādhi, one should drink it. Here is the recipe for this ghee mixed with pennywort. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-144"/>
                    <lg tid="246">
                        <l>One should cook one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prastha</foreign> of ghee</l>
                        <l>With the juice of pennywort and milk.</l>
                        <l>One should add to it </l>
                        <l>The following herbs and powders<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-406" index="83">Tib. omits the
                                sentence “One should add… powders:</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-145"/>
                    <lg tid="247">
                        <l>Turmeric, jasmine, and turpeth,</l>
                        <l>Together with yellow myrobalan.</l>
                        <l>One should use one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pala</foreign> of each of these;</l>
                        <l>The remaining ingredients are, traditionally, one <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karṣa</foreign>.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-146"/>
                    <lg tid="248">
                        <l>Also, pepper and the fruits of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viḍaṅga</foreign>,</l>
                        <l>Together with salt and sugar— </l>
                        <l>One should blend all this together</l>
                        <l>And cook it slowly on a low fire.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-147"/>
                    <lg tid="249">
                        <l>Then, by merely eating it</l>
                        <l>One will attain an unequalled purity of speech.</l>
                        <l>By doing this for seven days,</l>
                        <l>One’s voice will equal the kiṃnaras.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-148"/>
                    <lg tid="250">
                        <l>By doing this over a period of one month,</l>
                        <l>One will become full of knowledge.</l>
                        <l>By doing this for three months,</l>
                        <l>One will excel in being able to remember whatever one hears.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-149"/>
                    <lg tid="251">
                        <l>Within six months one will become, in reality,</l>
                        <l>Equal to Vāgīśvara.</l>
                        <l>One will conquer the eighteen types of leprosy</l>
                        <l>And the seven types of tuberculosis.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <label>Forty-Seventh Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-150"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="389">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ ananta­jñāna­śriye mañjuśriye namaḥ</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="390">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, homage to Mañjuśrī who has the infinite splendor of
                        knowledge!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-151"/>
                    <p tid="254">One should visualize oneself in the form of Vāgīśvara, surrounded by the four goddesses as
                        described before, and recite the mantra according to the procedure previously set out. Then one will be
                        able to perform all the rites already mentioned. </p>
                    <label>Forty-Eighth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-152"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="391">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ arapacana dhīḥ svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="392">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Arapacana, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">dhīḥ</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-153"/>
                    <p tid="257">In an isolated place, one should draw a maṇḍala and make offerings to the blessed Vāgīśvara and
                        to one’s precious guru. Then, one should sit on a comfortable seat and arouse the mind set upon awakening.
                        Afterward, one should recite three times the mantra “<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Oṁ</foreign>, all
                        phenomena are pure by nature; I am pure by nature,”<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-407" index="84">Skt.: <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ svabhāva­śuddhāḥ sarvadharmāḥ
                                svabhāva­śuddho ’ham</foreign>  |</note> and, considering oneself and everything else to be
                        naturally pure, bring emptiness directly to mind. {19} One should then visualize oneself, instantaneously
                        arisen, upon a white lotus and a moon disk; one is white in color, holding a book and a sword. <ref cRef="F.11.b"/> On the right side of oneself as Vāgīśvara is Keśinī, and on one’s left, Upakeśinī.
                        Each of them is white and holds a red lotus. In front is Jālinīprabha,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-408" index="85">The Tibetan reflects the reading “Sūryaprabha,” which is another name for
                            Jālinīprabha.</note> of white color, astride<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-409" index="86">Tib. omits “astride.”</note> a sun disk and holding a blue lotus. Behind, one should visualize
                        Candraprabha, astride<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-410" index="87">Tib. omits
                            “astride.”</note> a moon disk and holding a blue lotus. Then, in one’s heart, one should visualize the
                        syllable <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">a</foreign>, radiating blazing streams of light, which is then
                        transformed into an eight-spoked wheel, extremely ornate as it is the nature of the complete range of
                        speech. One should vizualize the wheel clearly and consider that it is rapidly revolving. Practicing in
                        this way, one will come to know all the treatises clearly within six months as regards both their meaning
                        and composition, even if one has never heard them before. After one year, one will become equal to
                        Vāgīśvara. This was the method of <emph>the wheel of Arapacana</emph>. </p>
                    <label>Forty-Ninth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-154"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="393">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ vāgīśvara muḥ</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="394">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vāgīśvara, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">muḥ</foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-155"/>
                    <p tid="260">All the results mentioned previously will come to the person who recites this mantra. One should
                        visualize, in the center of a circle, the syllable <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">muḥ</foreign>
                        surrounded by a garland of flames. This is called the <emph>circle of wisdom procedure</emph>. </p>
                    <label>Fiftieth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-156"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="395">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ dharma­dhātu­vāgīśvara muḥ svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="396">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vāgīśvara of the sphere of phenomena, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">muḥ</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-157"/>
                    <p tid="263">In the same order as just described, one should imagine oneself as having the nature of the five
                        deities. Then, one should visualize a sixteen-spoked wheel with the syllable <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">muḥ</foreign> in its center. To those who visualize this or an eight-spoked wheel<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-411" index="88">Tib. omits “or an eight-spoked wheel.”</note> will
                        come the results previously mentioned. </p>
                    <label>Fifty-First Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-158"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="397">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ vajratīkṣṇa varada muḥ svāhā</foreign> |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="398">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Vajratīkṣṇa, the boon giver, <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">muḥ</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-159"/>
                    <p tid="266">One should visualize oneself as the syllable <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">muḥ</foreign>. Then, as it transforms, one instantaneously becomes Vāgīśvara, the sole hero, who, like a
                        blazing fire, illuminates the entire environment. In one’s heart one should visualize the syllable
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">oṁ</foreign>, which is then transformed into a sun disk that
                        illuminates all worlds, shining with a hundred thousand rays. By meditating thus, within six months the
                        practitioner will become equal to Vāgīśvara and will obtain all the results previously described. <ref cRef="F.12.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <trailer tid="409">This was the third chapter in the <title xml:lang="en">Great Sovereign Tantra of
                            Siddhaikavīra</title>. {20} </trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="chapter">
                    <head type="chapter" tid="421">Chapter 4</head>
                    <label>Fifty-Second Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-160"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="399">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ lavaṇāmbho ’si tīkṣṇo ’si udagro ’si bhayṃkara </foreign>|
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">amukasya daha gātrāṇi daha māṃsāni daha tvacam nakhāny api
                            daha asthīni asthibhyo majjakaṃ daha</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">lavaṇaṃ
                            chindati lavaṇaṃ bhindati lavaṇaṃ pacati</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">kṣoṇita­lavaṇe hriyamāṇe kuto nidrā kuto ratiḥ | yadi vasati yojanaśate nadīnāṃ ca śatāntare | nagare
                            lohaprākāre kṛṣṇa­sarpa­kṛtākule</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">tatraiva vaśam
                            ānīhi lavaṇa­bandha­puraskṛta</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ ciṭi ciṭi
                            vikloli amukaṃ sadhana­parivāram eva samānaya svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-161"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="400">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Lavaṇāmbha! You are fierce! You are vast! O
                        terrifying one! Burn the limbs of such-and-such! Burn his flesh! Burn his skin! Burn even his nails! Burn
                        his bones and the marrow in his bones! He cuts the salt, breaks the salt, and cooks the salt. When the
                        salt of the earth is being seized, how could one sleep, how could one find pleasure? If such-and-such
                        dwells a hundred leagues away, behind a hundred rivers, in a city surrounded by iron walls and protected
                        by cobras—at that very place, enthrall that person, having first bound the salt. <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, ciṭi, ciṭi</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Vikloli</foreign>! Please bring here such-and-such a person! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-162"/>
                    <p tid="269">As a preliminary practice, one should perform 10,000 recitations before commencing the sādhana
                        practice. Here, one should visualize oneself as the noble lord Avalokiteśvara, standing beneath a
                        blossoming aśoka tree. He is red in color and wears red garlands,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-412" index="89">Tib. omits “red garlands.”</note> red clothes, jewelry, and unguents. He
                        has a distinctively erotic appearance and in his four arms he holds a noose, a goad, a bow, and an arrow.
                        He is accompanied by two goddesses, Tārā and Bhṛkuṭī, who stand to his right and left respectively. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-163"/>
                    <p tid="270">Visualizing oneself like this, one should offer, in the three periods of the day, 108 <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> offerings<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-413" index="90">Translation based on the Tibetan. The Sanskrit suggests “figurines made of salt.”</note> of salt.
                        After seven days, one will succeed in enthralling a man or a woman. After twenty-one days, one will be
                        able to enthrall an eminent person. </p>
                    <p tid="271">One should make an effigy from beeswax mixed with salt in the shape of the target person, four
                        fingers in size. Then one should heat up that effigy at the three junctions of the day above the smokeless
                        embers of cutch tree wood while saying the mantra aloud. Whoever’s name is included in the mantra, that
                        person will become enthralled. One should give the target salt mixed with vajra water after incanting it
                        108 times. Then the target will become enthralled simply by drinking it. </p>
                    <label>Fifty-Third Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-164"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="401">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ lavaṇāmbho ’si tikṣṇo ’si udagro ’si hṛdayaṃgama amukasya
                            hṛdayaṃ pītaṃ nāsti loke cikitsakaḥ oṁ ciṭi ciṭi vikloli vikloli mahāvikloli mahāvikloli amukaṃ me
                            vaśam ānaya svāhā | </foreign>
                        </seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="402">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ</foreign>, Lavaṇāmbha! You are fierce! You are vast! You touch
                        the heart! The heart of such-and-such a person is drunk. There is no physician in the world for this.
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, ciṭi, ciṭi</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Vikloli, vikloli</foreign>! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Mahāvikloli,
                            mahāvikloli</foreign>! Please enthrall such-and-such a person for me! <foreign type="mantra" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-165"/>
                    <p tid="274">Having completed the procedure of the preliminary practice as before, one should drink three
                        handfuls of incanted water with salt in the three periods of the day. Whoever’s name one includes, that
                        person will become enthralled. </p>
                    <p tid="275">One should mix equal amounts of salt and black mustard seed and offer them in a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> offering. Whoever’s name is used in the offering, that
                        person will become enthralled. <ref cRef="F.12.b"/>
                    </p>
                    <label>Fifty-Fourth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-166"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="403">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">oṁ kurukulle svāhā</foreign>  |</seg>
                    </p>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="404">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Oṁ, svāhā</foreign> to Kurukullā!</seg> {21}</p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-167"/>
                    <p tid="278">This is the heart mantra of the venerable noble Tārā. Its invincible power in the activity of
                        enthralling the three worlds is known far and wide. </p>
                    <p tid="279">One should, while absorbed in the absorption mentioned previously, recite the mantra 100,000
                        times for each syllable. Later, the person to whom one gives flowers, incense, unguents, fragrant powders,
                        or betel will become enthralled. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-168"/>
                    <p tid="280">By censing oneself with a pleasant-smelling incense, one will be adored by everyone. If one
                        offers a <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">homa</foreign> of red flowers, the person whose name one
                        uses in the <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> will become enthralled. If one incants
                        food and drink, whoever it is given to will become enthralled. To enthrall an important person, one should
                        offer white mustard seeds in the fire. Later, on an auspicious lunar day, during an auspicious asterism,
                        etc., one should make offerings to her, the Blessed One. Then one should draw a circle with sixteen
                        divisions in the form of a lotus with petals. One should draw it on birchbark or cloth using saffron,
                        bovine orpiment, resin, etc. In the center of the circle, one should write both the name of the target and
                        that of the practitioner.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-414" index="91">Tib. only mentions the
                            name of the target.</note> On the petals, one should write the four syllables <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ku ru ku llā</foreign> in combination with the target’s name only.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-415" index="92">Skt. omits “only.”</note> On the outside, one should surround
                        this with a threefold circle of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">oṁ</foreign> syllables using a red cord and
                        insert the drawing into the heart of an effigy made of beeswax. Then, while heating up the effigy over the
                        embers of cutch tree wood at the three junctions of the day, one should draw the effigy’s feet toward
                        oneself. Whether one is enthralling a man or a woman, one should pierce the feet with a copper needle and
                        heat them. The target will become enthralled. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-169"/>
                    <p tid="281">One should visualize the wind maṇḍala arisen from the syllable <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yaṁ</foreign>. Above it, one should visualize the target with disheveled hair,
                        naked, and with a noose tied around his neck. One should pull him by the chest with a hook and draw him by
                        means of the mantra which has the force of the wind. As he is visualized prostrate at the practitioner’s
                        feet, all that one wants from him can be accomplished. With dedicated practice, one will be able to draw
                        even material objects<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-416" index="93">The Sanskrit word is
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">piṇḍa</foreign>, which means a lump of any solid material.
                            Tib. says “the sky.” </note> into one’s presence by mere concentration. <ref cRef="F.13.a"/>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-170"/>
                    <p tid="282">One should place the mantra in the center of a bowl of ghee, honey, and sugar-candy and, in the
                        three periods of the day, offer flowers and other things to it while reciting the mantra. Then one will
                        enthrall whomever one wishes. </p>
                    <p tid="283">One should make a lamp wick with fibers of white lotus and put lampblack into a dish of unbaked
                        clay along with clarified butter from a brown cow. By applying this lampblack, incanted 108 times, to
                        one’s eyes, one will be adored by everyone. </p>
                    <p tid="284">In the ancestors’ grove,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-417" index="94">Tib.: “in a
                            cemetery.”</note> one should collect lampblack from a wick made of white lotus fibers burning inside a
                        human skull with human fat. This should be done at night on the eighth or the fourteenth day of the waning
                        moon. By anointing one’s eyes with this lampblack, one will be adored by everyone. </p>
                    <label>Fifty-Fifth Mantra</label>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-171"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="405">
                        <seg type="mantra">
                            <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">amale vimale kuṅkume samayena baddho ‘si</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">bindūn bindūn icchayā devo varṣati vidyotayati garjati
                            garjati</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">vismaya­mahā­rāja samāyita vardhayita
                            hūṁ</foreign> | <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">devebhyo manuṣyebhyo gandarvebhyo
                            śikhi­graha­deva ānandasya grahaṇāyāgama­nāyākramaṇāya<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-418" index="95">
                                <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Grahaṇāyāgama­nāyākramaṇāya</foreign> is a conjectured reading. In the
                                manuscripts we have <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">grahaṇīyāgama­nāyākramaṇīya</foreign>.</note>
                            juhomīha svāhā</foreign> |</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-172"/>
                    <p rend="mantra" tid="406"> <seg type="mantra">In the pure and stainless saffron, you are bound by your pledge. The god rains
                        raindrops, raindrops, as he pleases. He sends lightning and thunder. O amazing great king! May he bring
                        prosperity and growth! <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">Hūṁ</foreign>! {22} O god of comets and
                        planets, I now offer an oblation to gods, humans, and gandharvas, for the seizing, the coming, and the
                        traversing of happiness,<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-419" index="96">Perhaps a metaphor is
                            intended here: it is the function of the god of comets and planets to control the seizing (i.e.,
                            eclipsing), coming, and traversing of heavenly bodies, but here he is meant to apply this function to
                            the “movements” of happiness. The grammar, however, is not very clear. </note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">svāhā</foreign>!</seg> </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-173"/>
                    <p tid="287">With this king of mantras one should perform the preliminary ritual. Then, in the center of a
                        house yard, one should smear cow dung and delineate the altar space.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-420" index="97"> Instead of “delineate an altar,” Tib. has “shape it into a
                            square.”</note> One should spread <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">darbha</foreign> grass there
                        and set it alight. Next, one should take 108 flowers of the giant milkweed shrub and, repeating the
                        mantra, offer the flowers one by one in the fire. Then one summons the woman or man one desires. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-174"/>
                    <p tid="288">An intelligent person, knowing what is described here, should treat it with respect.<note place="end" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-421" index="98"> Based on the Tibetan, which is glossed by
                            Jamyang Khyentse Wangpo: “An intelligent person who takes pleasure in benefitting others, knowing
                            merely from reading [this text] the mantras that are to be found in it, should practice them with
                            respect.” The Sanskrit could be interpreted as, “When they see things accomplished, skillful ones
                            should feel respect.” </note>
                    </p>
                    <trailer tid="410">This was the fourth chapter in the <title xml:lang="en">Great Sovereign Tantra of
                            Siddhaikavīra</title>.</trailer>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="422">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-175"/>
                    <p tid="289">Here ends the <title xml:lang="en">Great Sovereign Tantra of Siddhaikavīra</title>.</p>
                    
                        
                        <p tid="290">Translated by the great Indian preceptor Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna and the translator monk Géwai
                            Lodrö, and finalized by the monk Tsultrim Gyalwa. </p>
                    
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="423">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="424">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-176">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa zhes bya ba’i rgyud kyi rgyal po chen po</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaika­vīra­mahā­tantra­rāja</title>). Toh 544, Degé Kangyur vol. 89 (rgyud ’bum,
                        pa), folios 1b–13a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-177">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa zhes bya ba’i rgyud kyi rgyal po chen po. bka’
                            ’gyur</title> (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste
                        gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology
                        Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing
                        House), 2006-2009, vol. 89, pp 3-44. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-178">Bhattacharyya, Benoytosh, ed. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sādhanamālā</title>.
                        2nd edition. Gaekwad’s Oriental Series, nos. 26, 41. Baroda: Oriental Institute, 1968. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-179">Otsuka, Nobuo (Mikkyo Seiten Kyekyūkai), ed. “Siddhaikavīratantra.” In
                            <title xml:lang="Ja-Ltn">Taisho Daigaku Sogo-Bukkyo-Kenkyujo-Kiyo</title>, vol. 15, pp (1)–(18). Tokyo:
                        Taisho University Press, 1995. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-180">Pandey, Janardan, ed. <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaikavīra­mahā­tantram</title>. Rare Buddhist Texts Series, no. 20. Sarnath: Central Institute
                        for Higher Tibetan Studies, 1998. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-181">Khyentse, Jamyang — Wangpo (’jam dbyangs mkhyen brtse’i dbang po). “sna
                        tshogs pa’i las rab tu ’byung ba ’jam dpal dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa’i rgyud ’grel man ngag dang bcas pa.”
                        In <title xml:lang="en">Compendium of Methods for Accomplishment</title> (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrub
                            pa’i thabs kun las btus pa dngos grub rin po che’i ’dod ’jo</title>), vol. 7, folios 1.a–39.a (pp
                        1–77). Edited by Jamyang Khyentse Wangpo and Loter Wangpo (blo gter dbang po). Dehra Dun: G. Loday, N.
                        Gyaltsen and N. Lungtok, 1970. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-182">Dharmachakra Translation Committee (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Practice
                            Manual of Kurukullā</title> (Toh 437). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2011-2016. (<ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-081-006.html">read.84000.co</ref>).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-089-001-183">Dharmachakra Translation Committee (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Tantra
                            of Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa</title> (Toh 431). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2016. (<ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-080-015.html">read.84000.co</ref>).</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-184">
                            <term>bali</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gtor ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཏོར་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bali</term>
                            <term type="definition">Ritual oblation offered into the fire.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-185">
                            <term>bhūmi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūmi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Level of the realization of a bodhisattva. Typically there are ten <term type="ignore">bhūmis</term>,
                                sometimes thirteen.</term> 
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-186">
                            <term>wish-fulfilling gem</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid bzhin nor bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་བཞིན་ནོར་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cintāmaṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-187">
                            <term>sole hero</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ་གཅིག་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ekavīra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ekalavīra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ekallavīra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Male deity visualized with a consort, but without the maṇḍala deities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-188">
                            <term>mantra knot</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngags mdud </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྔགས་མདུད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gaṇḍaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Knot which has been incanted with the mantra while being tied.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-189">
                            <term>villagers’ dharma</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grong pa’i chos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲོང་པའི་ཆོས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">grāmyadharma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Euphemism for sexual intercourse.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-190">
                            <term>homa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sbyin sreg </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྦྱིན་སྲེག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Ritual oblation offered into the fire. Unlike <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bali</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> in a
                                tantric ritual is a repetitive act performed a prescribed number of times.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-191">
                            <term>karṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zho </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A unit of weight equal to 280 grains troy, or, sometimes, 176 grains
                                troy.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-192">
                            <term>human skull</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ka pa chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀ་པ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahākapala</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-193">
                            <term>human fat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">snum chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣུམ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahātaila</term>
                            <term type="definition">In this context, a ritual object used in rituals of enthrallment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-194">
                            <term>maṇḍala of Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbang chen gyi dkyil ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབང་ཆེན་གྱི་དཀྱིལ་འཁོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahendra­maṇḍala</term>
                            <term type="definition">A rainbow.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-195">
                            <term>follower of Mantra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྔགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mantrin</term>
                            <term type="definition">A practitioner of mantra; a follower of the Mantra Vehicle.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-196">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of semi-divine serpent-like beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-197">
                            <term>pala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pala</term>
                            <term type="definition">A unit of weight equal to four <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">karṣa</foreign>.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-198">
                            <term>pātāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pātāla</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the seven subterranean realms, the abode of nāgas.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-199">
                            <term>piśāca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piśāca</term>
                            <term type="definition">A class of spirits.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-200">
                            <term>prastha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bre </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">prastha</term>
                            <term type="definition">A unit of weight equal to thirty-two pala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-201">
                            <term>effigy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzugs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟུགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puttalaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">puttalikā</term>
                            <term type="definition">
                                <term type="ignore">Effigy</term> of the target used in magical rites.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-202">
                            <term>target</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bsgrub bya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བསྒྲུབ་བྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sādhyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Person or being who is the target of a particular sādhana, or ritual.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-203">
                            <term>pacifying</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zhi ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཞི་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śāntika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śānti</term>
                            <term type="definition">Peace; one of the four main types of enlightened activity.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-204">
                            <term>siddhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngos grub </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དངོས་གྲུབ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">siddhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">An accomplishment that is the goal of sādhana practice; a supernatural power
                                or ability.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-205">
                            <term>tika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tika </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཏིཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tilaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Dot painted between the eyebrows.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-206">
                            <term>three hot substances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tsha ba gsum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚ་བ་གསུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trikaṭu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trikaṭuka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Black pepper, long pepper, and dry ginger.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-207">
                            <term>chaff homa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phub ma’i sbyin sreg </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕུབ་མའི་སྦྱིན་སྲེག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">tuṣahoma</term>
                            <term type="definition">Type of <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">homa</foreign> where chaff fire
                                is used or chaff is offered. Sometimes mixed with clarified butter.</term>
                            <term type="alternative">homa of chaff</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-208">
                            <term>ūrṇā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mdzod spu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཛོད་སྤུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ūrṇā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">ūrṇākośa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Circular tuft of hair between the eyebrows.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-209">
                            <term>vidyādhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rig ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རིག་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vidyādhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Knowledge holder,” a being possessed of magical powers.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-210">
                            <term>double vajra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sna tshogs rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣ་ཚོགས་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">viśvavajra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Two crossed vajras.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-211">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Class of non-human beings.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-212">
                            <term>yakṣiṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣiṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Female yakṣa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-213">
                            <term>eight great siddhis</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dngos grub chen po brgyad </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དངོས་གྲུབ་ཆེན་པོ་བརྒྱད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">aṣṭamahāsiddhi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Eight “ordinary” accomplishments attained through practice: (1) eye medicine
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">añjana</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig sman</foreign>); (2) swift-footedness (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jaṅghākara</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rkang
                                    mgyogs</foreign>); (3) magic sword (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khaḍga</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ral gri</foreign>); (4) travel beneath the earth
                                    (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pātāla</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’og spyod</foreign>); (5) medicinal pills (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gulikā</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ril bu</foreign>);
                                (6) travel in the sky (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">khecara</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mkha’ spyod</foreign>); (7) invisibility (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">antardhāna</foreign>, <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi snang
                                    ba</foreign>); and (8) elixir (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rasāyana</foreign>,
                                    <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bcud len</foreign>). (From Jamyang Khyentse Wangpo’s
                                commentary).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-214">
                            <term>Aditi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aditi</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked to help win a girl.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-215">
                            <term>Ajitā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ajitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the “four sisters of victory.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-216">
                            <term>Amaraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Amaraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Immortal One,” epithet of Jīvantī in the mantra of long life.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-217">
                            <term>Ambāsimbāka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ambāsimbāka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to remove fear.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-218">
                            <term>Aparājitā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aparājitā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the “four sisters of victory.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-219">
                            <term>Arapacana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arapacana</term>
                            <term type="definition">Emanation of Mañjuśrī, invoked to obtain the gift of speech, memory, sharp
                                intellect, and learning.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-220">
                            <term>Arkamālinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Arkamālinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Having the nimbus of the sun,” epithet of Mahāsarasvatī, one of the four
                                retinue goddesses of Siddhaikavīra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-221">
                            <term>Āryā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Āryā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-222">
                            <term>Avalokiteśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">spyan ras gzigs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྤྱན་རས་གཟིགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Avalokiteśvara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-223">
                            <term>Lokanātha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jig rten mgon po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིག་རྟེན་མགོན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lokanātha</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Lord of the World,” an epithet of Avalokiteśvara.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-224">
                            <term>Bhṛkuṭī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">khro gnyer can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཁྲོ་གཉེར་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhṛkuṭī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Along with Tārā, a female deity visualized in the sādhana of
                                Lavaṇāmbha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-225">
                            <term>Calā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Calā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess of fortune invoked in divination and soothsaying.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-226">
                            <term>Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Caṇḍa­mahā­roṣaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to destroy evil and to grant protection.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-227">
                            <term>Candrakāntī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candrakāntī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-228">
                            <term>Candraprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">zla ba’i ’od </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཟླ་བའི་འོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Candraprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue deities of Arapacana.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-229">
                            <term>Carendra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Carendra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-230">
                            <term>Culā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Culā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Calā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-231">
                            <term>Cundā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cundā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Calā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-232">
                            <term>Dantilī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dantilī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess who reveals hidden facts in one’s sleep.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-233">
                            <term>Dattā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dattā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-234">
                            <term>Devī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Devī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-235">
                            <term>Dhanada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dhanada</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-236">
                            <term>Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Dīpaṃkara Śrījñāna</term>
                            <term type="definition">The famed Indian scholar who spent twelve years in Tibet from 1042–1054. Also
                                known as Atīśa.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-237">
                            <term>Gaṇapati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Gaṇapati</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Ganeśa; sometimes of other deities.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-238">
                            <term>Guptā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guptā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-239">
                            <term>Grey Monkey</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Harimarkaṭa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to release a prisoner from bondage.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-240">
                            <term>Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jālinīprabha</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue deities of Arapacana, also called Sūryaprabha.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-241">
                            <term>Jambhā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambhā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to make a person lovable; also to fulfill one’s wishes.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-242">
                            <term>Jambhala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambhala</term>
                            <term type="definition">God of riches.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-243">
                            <term>Jambhanī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jambhanī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Snapper.” This seems to be an epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-244">
                            <term>Jayā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jayā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the “four sisters of victory.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-245">
                            <term>Jīvaṃvaradā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jīvaṃvaradā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Giver of the Boon of Life,” epithet of a goddess (Tārā?) invoked to give an
                                easy delivery of a child.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-246">
                            <term>Jīvantī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jīvantī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Ever Alive,” goddess invoked in the mantra of long life.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-247">
                            <term>Jvālājihvā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jvālājihvā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Tongue of Flames,” goddess invoked to pacify disputes, quash fires, and stop
                                epidemics.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-248">
                            <term>Kailāsakūṭa­putra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kailāsakūṭa­putra</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Son of Mount Meru,” god invoked in divination and soothsaying
                                (Kubera?).</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-249">
                            <term>Kamalā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kamalā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the names of Lakṣmī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-250">
                            <term>Kamalavikāsinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kamalavikāsinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Possessor of lotus blossoms,” epithet of Lakṣmī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-251">
                            <term>Karṇapiśācī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za rna sgrogs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ་རྣ་སྒྲོགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Karṇapiśācī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Demoness of the Ear,” female spirit who reveals hidden facts or the future by
                                whispering them into one’s ear; very likely another name for Śravaṇa­piśācī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-252">
                            <term>Kelimālin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kelimālin</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-253">
                            <term>Keśinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">skra can ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྐྲ་ཅན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Keśinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Siddhaikavīra; also of Arapacana.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-254">
                            <term>Kubera</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kubera</term>
                            <term type="definition">God of wealth.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-255">
                            <term>Youthful One</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kumāra</term>
                            <term type="definition">In the SEV, deity invoked in a divination and soothsaying rite; often an
                                epithet of Mañjuśrī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-256">
                            <term>Kurukullā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kurukullā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked in the rites of enthrallment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-257">
                            <term>Lakṣmī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lakṣmī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess of fortune, here invoked to obtain power, splendor, a girl, or even a
                                kingdom.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-258">
                            <term>Lavaṇāmbha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Lavaṇāmbha</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Salty water,” epithet of Avalokiteśvara; invoked in the rites of
                                enthrallment.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-259">
                            <term>Locanā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sangs rgyas spyan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སངས་རྒྱས་སྤྱན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Locanā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked in divination and soothsaying.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-260">
                            <term>Mahālakṣmī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahālakṣmī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the names of Lakṣmī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-261">
                            <term>Mahāmāyāṅgā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyāṅgā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“One having the body of great illusion,” epithet of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-262">
                            <term>Mahāsarasvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngag gi dbang phyug ma chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངག་གི་དབང་ཕྱུག་མ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāsarasvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess of learning; in the SEV she is associated with Tārā; she is also one
                                the four retinue goddesses of Siddhaikavīra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-263">
                            <term>Mahāśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpal chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔལ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Siddhaikavīra.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-264">
                            <term>Mahāśvetā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāśvetā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Great White Goddess,” epithet of Sarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-265">
                            <term>Mahāvidyā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāvidyā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Great Knowledge,” epithet of Calā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-266">
                            <term>Maṇibhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Maṇibhadra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-267">
                            <term>Mañjughoṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjughoṣa</term>
                            <term type="definition">Emanation of Mañjuśrī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-268">
                            <term>Mañjuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuśrī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-269">
                            <term>Mañjuvajra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jam pa’i rdo rje </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇམ་པའི་རྡོ་རྗེ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mañjuvajra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Emanation of Mañjuśrī; the deity delivering the SEV.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-270">
                            <term>Mati</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">blo ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བློ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mati</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-271">
                            <term>Medhā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yid gzhungs ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡིད་གཞུངས་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Medhā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-272">
                            <term>Megholka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Megholka</term>
                            <term type="definition">God of lightning (Indra?) invoked to obtain riches or women.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-273">
                            <term>Mocanī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mocanī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Releaser,” epithet of a goddess (Tārā?) invoked to give an easy delivery of a
                                child.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-274">
                            <term>Mohā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mohā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to make a person lovable; also to fulfill one’s wishes.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-275">
                            <term>Mohanī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mohanī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Deluder.” This seems to be an epithet of Locanā. Goddess who reveals hidden
                                facts in one’s sleep.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-276">
                            <term>Mokṣaṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mokṣaṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Reliever,” epithet of a goddess (Tārā?) invoked to give an easy delivery of a
                                child.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-277">
                            <term>Mucilī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mucilī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess who reveals hidden facts in one’s sleep; possibly another name for the
                                nāga goddess Mucilindā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-278">
                            <term>Muṇḍā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Muṇḍā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Female spirit invoked in divination and soothsaying.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-279">
                            <term>Nandinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ byed ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བྱེད་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Nandinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked to obtain power, riches, and splendor.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-280">
                            <term>Niculā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Niculā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked to protect one from danger.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-281">
                            <term>Pādacalanā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pādacalanā</term>
                            <term type="definition">This appears to be a goddess invoked to protect one from leprosy.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-282">
                            <term>Padmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Padmā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess invoked to cure diseases of the eyes, etc.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-283">
                            <term>Parṇaśabarī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Parṇaśabarī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Female piśāca invoked to protect people and animals from all kinds of
                                troubles.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-284">
                            <term>Prajñā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shes rab ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤེས་རབ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajñā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-285">
                            <term>Prajvala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prajvala</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Blazing Light,” epithet of Avalokiteśvara when he is invoked in the rites of
                                divination.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-286">
                            <term>Pūrṇabhadra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇabhadra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-287">
                            <term>Rakṣaṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rakṣaṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Protector.” This seems to be an epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-288">
                            <term>Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dbyangs can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དབྱངས་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sarasvatī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess of learning; one of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of
                                Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-289">
                            <term>Satyavādinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Satyavādinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Speaker of Truth,” epithet of Calā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-290">
                            <term>Siddhaikavīra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dpa’ bo gcig pu grub pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དཔའ་བོ་གཅིག་པུ་གྲུབ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhaikavīra</term>
                            <term type="definition">Emanation of Mañjuśrī; the title deity of the SEV. He is visualized in the
                                rituals of the 41st and 46th mantras of the SEV.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-291">
                            <term>Siddhalocanā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Siddhalocanā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Endowed with Supernatural Vision,” epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-292">
                            <term>Smṛti</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dran pa ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲན་པ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Smṛti</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-293">
                            <term>Śravaṇa­piśācī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śravaṇa­piśācinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Demoness of the Ear,” epithet of Muṇḍā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-294">
                            <term>Śrīvasu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīvasu</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-295">
                            <term>Stambhanī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Stambhanī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Immobilizer.” This seems to be an epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-296">
                            <term>Subhadrā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Subhadrā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-297">
                            <term>Sukhendra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sukhendra</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-298">
                            <term>Svapnavilokinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svapnavilokinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“One Who Can See Dreams,” epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-299">
                            <term>Tārā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgrol ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲོལ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tārā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-300">
                            <term>Tāraṇī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Tāraṇī</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Savioress,” epithet of a goddess (Tārā?) invoked to give an easy delivery of
                                a child.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-301">
                            <term>Upakeśinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye ba’i skra can ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བའི་སྐྲ་ཅན་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upakeśinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Siddhaikavīra; also of Arapacana.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-302">
                            <term>Ūrṇāmaṇi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ūrṇāmaṇi</term>
                            <term type="definition">“One With the Jewel of Ūrṇā,” deity invoked to ward off enemies and natural
                                disasters.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-303">
                            <term>Vāgīśvara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsung gi dbang phyug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསུང་གི་དབང་ཕྱུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vāgīśvara</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Lord of Speech,” epithet of Mañjuśrī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-304">
                            <term>Vāgvādinī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vāgvādinī</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Sarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-305">
                            <term>Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-306">
                            <term>Vajradhara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajradhara</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the sambhogakāya deities; the bodhisattva requesting the teaching in
                                the SEV.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-307">
                            <term>Vajratīkṣṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vajratīkṣṇa</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Diamond-sharp,” epithet of Mañjuśrī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-308">
                            <term>Speech</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vāk</term>
                            <term type="definition">Speech personified; one of the names of Mahāsarasvatī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-309">
                            <term>Vākya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vākya</term>
                            <term type="definition">Epithet of Mañjuśrī used in his heart mantra, which grants intelligence,
                                longevity, and other boons.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-310">
                            <term>Varadā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Varadā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“Boon-giver,” this seems to be an epithet of Locanā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-311">
                            <term>Vasudattā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasudattā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣiṇīs who form the retinue of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-312">
                            <term>Vasudharā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasudharā</term>
                            <term type="definition">Goddess of riches, Earth personified; invoked for the fulfillment of wishes;
                                also to obtain a girl or a village.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-313">
                            <term>Vasumatiśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasumatiśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-314">
                            <term>Vasumukhī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasumukhī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-315">
                            <term>Vasuśrī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasuśrī</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the four retinue goddesses of Vasudharā.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-316">
                            <term>Vicitra­kuṇḍalin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vicitra­kuṇḍalin</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the eight great yakṣas who form the retinue of Jambhala.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-317">
                            <term>Vijayā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vijayā</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the “four sisters of victory.”</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-318">
                            <term>Vimalacandra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri ma med pa’i zla ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མ་མེད་པའི་ཟླ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalacandra</term>
                            <term type="definition">God invoked in divination and soothsaying, possibly associated with Kubera, or
                                an epithet of Kubera.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-319">
                            <term>Yamāntaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshin rje mthar byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤིན་རྗེ་མཐར་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Yamāntaka</term>
                            <term type="definition">Deity invoked to summon and subdue Karṇapiśācī.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-320">
                            <term>Géwai Lodrö</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dge ba’i blo gros </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགེ་བའི་བློ་གྲོས།</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three translators responsible for the canonical translation of the
                                SEV.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-321">
                            <term>Tsultrim Gyalwa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshul khrims rgyal ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚུལ་ཁྲིམས་རྒྱལ་བ།</term>
                            <term type="definition">One of the three translators responsible for the canonical translation of the
                                SEV.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-089-001-422">
                            <term>preliminary practice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sngon du bsnyen pa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྔོན་དུ་བསྙེན་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūrvasevā</term>
                            <term type="definition">“<term type="ignore">Preliminary practice</term>,” <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">pūrvasevā</foreign>, is a six-month period of formal practice to be performed before one can start employing the mantra for specific purposes.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>