<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="bo">གསང་སྔགས་ཆེན་པོ་རྗེས་སུ་འཛིན་པ།</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>
                <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānudhāraṇi</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="bo">གསང་སྔགས་ཆེན་པོ་རྗེས་སུ་འཛིན་པའི་མདོ།</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i mdo</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>
                <title type="longTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānudhāraṇi­sūtra</title>
                <title type="otherTitle" xml:lang="zh"/>
                <author sameAs="contributors.xml#team-9" role="translatorMain">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee<lb/> under the patronage and
                    supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha.</author>
                <author role="translatorEng" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-51">James Gentry</author>
                <consultant role="advisor" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-40">Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche</consultant>
                <editor role="reviser" sameAs="contributors.xml#person-50">Andreas Doctor</editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition>v 1.2 <date>2016</date>
                </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt status="1">
                <publisher>
                    <name>84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha</name> is a global non-profit initiative that aims to
                    translate all of the Buddha’s words into modern languages, and to make them available to everyone. </publisher>
                <availability>
                    <licence>
                        <graphic url="http://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-nd/2.0/88x31.png"/>
                        <p>This work is provided under the protection of a Creative Commons CC BY-NC-ND (Attribution -
                            Non-commercial - No-derivatives) 3.0 copyright. It may be copied or printed for fair use, but only
                            with full attribution, and not for commercial advantage or personal compensation. For full details,
                            see the Creative Commons license.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
                <idno xml:id="UT22084-090-007"/>
                <date>2016-05-30</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl key="toh563" type="text">
                    <ref>Toh 563</ref>
                    <biblScope>Degé Kangyur, vol. 90 (rgyud ’bum, pha), folios 150.b–156.a</biblScope>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śīlendrabodhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Jñānasiddhi</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Śākyaprabha</author>
                    <author role="translatorTib">Bandé Yeshé Dé</author>
                    <location count-pages="12">
                        <start volume="90" page="300"/>
                        <end volume="90" page="311"/>
                    </location>
                <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC21415"/>
                <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12295" work="W22084"/>
                </bibl>
            
            </sourceDesc>
            <notesStmt>
                <note type="lastUpdated">Last updated at 05/02/2019 at 16:52:36 by laura</note>
            </notesStmt>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!--title style="contentsPage">Contents
        
        <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Summary
            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Acknowledgements
                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Introduction
                    
                    <title style="contentsTranslation">THE TRANSLATION
                        <title style="contentsTextTitle">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret Mantra
                            
                            <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Bibliography
                                <title style="contentsAncillaryItem">Notes-->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary" tid="67">Summary</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-1"/>
                <p tid="1">
                    <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> is one of five texts that together constitute
                    the Pañcarakṣā scriptural collection, popular for centuries as an important facet of Mahāyāna-Vajrayāna
                    Buddhism’s traditional approach to personal and communal misfortunes of all kinds. It addresses a range of
                    human ailments, as well as misfortunes such as robbery, natural disaster, and criminal punishment, thought to
                    be brought on especially through the animosity of non-human spirit entities. The sūtra stipulates the
                    invocation of these spirit entities, which it separates into hierarchically ordered groups and thus renders
                    subordinate to the command of the Buddha and members of his saṅgha. The Buddha stipulates that just
                    “upholding” or intoning their names and the mantra formula for each will quell the violent interventions of
                    non-human entities and even hasten them to provide for the pragmatic needs of the saṅgha and its surrounding
                    communities. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment" tid="68">Acknowledgments</head>
                <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-2"/>
                <p tid="2">Translated by the Dharmachakra Translation Committee under the guidance of Chökyi Nyima Rinpoche. The
                    translation was produced by James Gentry, who also wrote the introduction. Andreas Doctor compared the
                    translation with the original Tibetan and edited the text.</p>
                <p tid="3">This translation has been completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words
                    of the Buddha. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction" tid="69">Introduction</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-3"/>
                    <p tid="4">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānu­dhāraṇi</title>,<note place="end" index="1" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-165">The Sanskrit
                            title in the Degé Kangyur is <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantranu­dhāraṇi­sūtra</title>, and the
                            same title (with variations in the diacritical marks) is found in the Lithang, Cone and Lhasa
                            Kangyurs. The Yonglé, Narthang, and Stok Palace Kangyurs, however, have <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantranu­dhāri­sūtra</title> (again, with variations in the exact spelling), and this latter
                            alternative was preferred by the compilers of the Tōhoku catalogue. However, the entry in Edgerton’s
                                <title xml:lang="en">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Dictionary</title> for <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānusāriṇī</title> suggests that this, instead, may be the original Sanskrit name of the
                            goddess concerned.</note> Toh 563) is the fifth scripture in a series of five; the other four texts
                        are <title xml:lang="en">Destroyer of the Great Trichiliocosm</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sāhasra­pramardanī</title>, Toh 558), <title xml:lang="en">The Great Peahen, Queen of
                            Incantations</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyūrī­vidyā­rājñī</title>, Toh 559), <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Amulet, Queen of Incantations</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­pratisāra­vidyā­rājñī</title>, Toh 561), and <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Great Cool
                            Grove</title>, (<title xml:lang="en">Mahā­śītavana</title>, Toh 562).<note place="end" index="2" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-166">For all four, see bibliography under Dharmachakra (2016) and
                            (forthcoming).</note> Together these five texts have been apotheosized in the Mahāyāna tradition as
                        five goddesses known collectively as the Pañcarakṣā, or the “Five Protectresses.” In the Tibetan tradition
                        this collection is known by the moniker <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzungs chen grwa
                            lnga</foreign>, the “Fivefold Great Dhāraṇī.” In the Degé Kangyur collection these texts constitute
                        60, 49, 43, 25, and 12 folios, respectively, making a total of 189 folios. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-4"/>
                    <p tid="5">Tibetan redactors of Kangyur collections have catalogued this set of five texts together within the
                        final Action (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">kriyā</foreign>) tantras section of the “tantra
                        collection” (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">rgyud ’bum</foreign>) division. Indeed, these
                        scriptures do contain elements—powerful incantations, an emphasis on external ritual hygiene and other
                        material details such as auspicious dates, and so forth—that resonate with standard Krīyayoga practice as
                        understood in Tibet. Yet missing from nearly all these texts is any extensive mention of the contemplative
                        visualization exercises, specialized ritual gestures (<foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">mudrā</foreign>), elaborate maṇḍala diagrams, and initiation ceremonies so typical of full-blown
                        Buddhist tantra. A close perusal of these five texts might then lead the reader to construe them as
                        standard Mahāyāna texts with a preponderance of elements—magical mantra formulas, ritual prescriptions,
                        pragmatic aims, and so forth—that only later coalesced and developed into a typically tantric practice
                        tradition with its own unique set of view, meditation, and conduct. To complicate things further, the core
                        of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrī</title>, for one, is rooted in Indian Buddhist traditions that
                        predate even the rise of <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Mahāyāna</foreign>.<note place="end" index="3" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-167">Sørensen (2006), p 90.</note> The <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāmāyūrī</title> also appears as a remedy for snakebites in the earlier <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinayavastu</title>.<note place="end" index="4" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-168">Pathak
                            (1989), p 32. The story comes at the very end of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajya­vastu</title>
                            (Toh 1 ch. 6); see Yao (forthcoming).</note> This accords with Gregory Schopen’s general observation,
                        based on inscriptional evidence, that “dhāraṇī texts were publically known much earlier and more widely
                        than texts we think of as ‘classically’ Mahāyāna”.<note place="end" index="5" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-169">Schopen (1989), p 157.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-5"/>
                    <p tid="6">Regardless of their bibliographical position in the Tibetan canon, the Five Protectresses have been
                        among the most popular texts used for pragmatic purposes throughout the Mahāyāna-Vajrayāna Buddhist world.
                        While it seems certain that these texts each developed independently and were only later combined into a
                        five-text corpus, their popularity is attested by their eventual spread to Nepal, Tibet, Central Asia,
                        China, Mongolia, Korea, Japan, and Indonesia (Hidas 2007: 189). In East Asia, the textual tradition
                        associated with the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">Mahāmāyūrī</foreign> in particular was
                        instrumental in integrating Buddhist and indigenous notions of divine kingship.<note place="end" index="6" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-170">Orzech (2002), p 58.</note> Moreover, the tradition of all five goddesses
                        and their texts still occupies a place of central importance today in the Vajrayāna Buddhism practiced by
                        the Newar population of the Kathmandu Valley in Nepal. Newar Buddhist communities of Kathmandu have even
                        translated the texts of the Five Protectresses into the modern vernacular, based on which they continue to
                        stage a number of annual rites for a broad range of pragmatic purposes.<note place="end" index="7" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-171"> Lewis (2000), pp 119–164.</note> Newars often propitiate the Five
                        Protectresses together by means of a five-section maṇḍala and other tantric elements that do not
                        necessarily feature in the scriptures themselves. This tradition reflects a specifically tantric ritual
                        treatment of the texts, which, judging by the presence of tantric <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">sādhana</foreign> practices associated with these five texts in the Tibetan Tengyur collections, had
                        already developed by the time the Tibetan translations were executed. This helps account for why Tibetan
                        redactors construed these five texts as belonging to the category of Krīyatantra, and not to the Dhāraṇī
                        or Sūtra sections. Indeed, the Tibetan translation of the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahāpratisarā</title>
                        reflects a recension of the Sanskrit text, which, Gergely Hidas suggests, “most likely served the better
                        integration of this text into the Vajrayāna, changing the historical locus of the <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="term">nidāna</foreign> to a mythical Vajrayānic setting.”<note place="end" index="8" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-172">Hidas (2007), p 188.</note>
                    </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-6"/>
                    <p tid="7">The designation Five Protectresses denotes the set of five texts, the incantations presented
                        therein, and the goddesses presiding over each. It is believed that all these texts, particularly their
                        incantations, provide special protection against a wide range of illnesses and misfortunes for those who
                        memorize, recollect, read, copy, teach, wear, or otherwise come into contact with them. Each text promises
                        protection against specific misfortunes, with considerable overlap witnessed between the texts. Despite
                        the pragmatic thrust of these scriptures, each text also contains numerous allusions to doctrinal notions.
                        The range of effects described therein sometimes, though rarely, extends beyond the pragmatic sphere to
                        include the purification of negative karma, deliverance from the lower realms, and even the attainment of
                        buddhahood. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-7"/>
                    <p tid="8">
                        <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title> was translated into Tibetan under Tibetan
                        imperial patronage sometime during the early ninth century by a translation team that included the
                        translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé (ca. late eighth to early ninth century) and the Indian scholars
                        Śīlendrabodhi, Jñānasiddhi, and Śākyaprabha. The sūtra promises protection against a range of threats,
                        from illnesses, natural disasters, and dangers while traveling, to warfare, corporal punishment, and
                        theft. This text frames all of these perils as originating from the animosity and ill will of human beings
                        and spirits. The principal focus is threats posed by the capricious spirit world of “non-humans” (<foreign type="term" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi ma yin</foreign>), who feed off the life force, vitality, flesh, and
                        blood of humans. The negative impact of these non-humans extends beyond the individual to include homes,
                        villages, towns, cities, regions, and entire countries. The text claims to be efficacious by means of
                        “drawing” or demarcating a “boundary” around those in need of protection, sealing them off from the source
                        of harm and thereby restoring health and internal cohesion. It is through “receiving, holding, reciting,
                        preaching, and mastering” this scripture that such a protective boundary is formed. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-8"/>
                    <p tid="9">The narrative of the sūtra begins with an interchange between the Buddha and the god Brahmā.
                        Brahmā, along with his divine retinue, visits the Blessed One at the Jetavana hermitage and requests that
                        he “guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being” to the entire trichiliocosm of a thousand
                        million worlds, just as the god himself does for the chiliocosm of a thousand worlds under his care. The
                        Buddha acquiesces to his request by remaining silent. He subsequently proceeds to teach the scripture’s
                        dhāraṇī formulas and to extol its many benefits. Much as in the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyūrī­vidyā­rājñī</title>, but with less elaboration, the Buddha prescribes the invocation by
                        name of the spirits responsible for personal and communal misfortunes. These litanies, which the Buddha
                        separates into groups based on the locations and activities of these beings, hierarchically arrange the
                        spirits so that they are all subordinate to the Buddha’s command and to the command of his saṅgha. The
                        Buddha states that just “upholding” or intoning these names along with the mantra formula that accompanies
                        each group will urge them to obey members of the saṅgha so that they desist from causing harm and instead
                        serve the pragmatic needs of the saṅgha and surrounding lay communities. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-9"/>
                    <p tid="10">Owing to the absence of a reliable Sanskrit edition that reflects the Tibetan translations, this
                        English translation is based on the Tibetan Degé edition, in consultation with the Pedurma (<foreign xml:lang="Bo-Ltn" type="term">dpe bsdur ma</foreign>) comparative edition. Thus, rather than
                        adjudicate on the many variant readings of the dhāraṇī formulas found in the different Tibetan versions of
                        this text, we have chosen to defer this issue for now and record only the Degé version until a Sanskrit
                        edition is produced that might shed further light on the matter. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation" tid="70">THE TRANSLATION</head>
                <head type="titleHon" tid="71">The Sūtra of</head>
                <head type="titleMain" tid="72">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-10"/>
                    <lg tid="11">
                        <l>
                            <ref cRef="F.150.b"/> Homage to the Three Jewels! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the Buddha! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the Dharma! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the Saṅgha! </l>
                        <l>Homage to the seven perfectly and completely awakened buddhas, along with their śrāvakas—those who have
                            perfectly gone, and those who have perfectly entered! </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-11"/>
                    <p tid="12">Following this homage:</p>
                    <lg tid="13">
                        <l>May these incantations be practiced for a purpose! </l>
                        <l>May these incantations be accomplished!</l>
                        <l>May their purpose—the goal for which they are practiced—</l>
                        <l>Be accomplished!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-12"/>
                    <p tid="14">Thus have I heard at one time. The Blessed One was dwelling in the Jetavana, Anāthapiṇḍada’s grove
                        in Śrāvastī. At that time, Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, with the gods of the Brahmā realm; Śakra,
                        lord of the gods, with the gods of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three; the four great kings, with the gods of
                        their realm; the twenty-eight great yakṣa generals; and Hārītī with her children and retinue of servants
                        went before the Blessed One, bowed their heads at his feet, and stood to one side. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-13"/>
                    <p tid="15">Standing there, Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, bowed toward the Blessed One with palms joined,
                        and said, “Venerable Blessed One, I rule as lord over the realms of the chiliocosm. <ref cRef="F.151.a"/>
                        Venerable Blessed One, when needed I guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the
                        realms in the chiliocosm. Venerable Bliss-Gone Dharma Sovereign, Blessed One, you rule as lord over the
                        realms of the great trichiliocosm. Blessed One, when you see fit you, too, guard, protect, look after, and
                        bring peace and well-being to the realms of the great trichiliocosm. So, Venerable Blessed One, I request
                        you to guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the realms of the trichiliocosm!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-14"/>
                    <p tid="16">The Blessed One acquiesced by remaining silent. Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, understood that
                        the Buddha had acquiesced by his silence, and at that moment he vanished. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-15"/>
                    <p tid="17">Subsequently, the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, last night I was approached by Brahmā,
                        master of the Sahā world, along with the gods of the Brahmā realm; Śakra, lord of the gods, with the gods
                        of the Heaven of the Thirty-Three; the four great kings, with the gods of the realm of the four great
                        kings; and the twenty-eight great yakṣa generals; and Hārītī with her children and retinue of servants
                        also came. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-16"/>
                    <p tid="18">“Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, said to me, ‘Venerable Blessed One, I rule as lord over the
                        realms of the chiliocosm. Venerable Blessed One, when needed, I guard, protect, look after, and bring
                        peace and well-being to the realms in the chiliocosm. <ref cRef="F.151.b"/> Venerable Bliss-Gone Dharma
                        Sovereign, Blessed One, you rule as lord over the realms of the great trichiliocosm. Blessed One, when you
                        see fit, you also guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the realms of the great
                        trichiliocosm. So, Venerable Blessed One, I request you to guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and
                        well-being to the realms of the trichiliocosm!’ </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-17"/>
                    <p tid="19">“Monks, I acquiesced by not responding to Brahmā, master of the Sahā world. Then Brahmā, master of
                        the Sahā world, knowing that I had acquiesced by remaining silent, disappeared at that moment. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-18"/>
                    <p tid="20">“Monks, this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret
                        Mantra</title>, was taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats of the past. It will
                        be taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And likewise, right now
                        in the present, I will also teach it as an aid for the awakening of buddhahood.” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-19"/>
                    <p tid="21">Then the Blessed One said to venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, you are to receive, hold, recite, preach,
                        and master this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>!
                        Ānanda, this queen of incantations, Upholding the Great Secret Mantra, will bring welfare, benefit,
                        happiness, and comfort to the four assemblies. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-20"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="63">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">tadyathā ubuddhe nibuddhe vibuddhe saṃbuddhe viśvaṣṭa­buddhe
                            īhabuddhe tattra­buddhe niyaṃgame chavila apula tapula <ref cRef="F.152.a"/> tāle māle maṅgagamaṅga
                            manana imam vidyā hudume huhume pūrvaprahare</foreign> | </ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-21"/>
                    <p tid="23">“Ānanda, this strong and powerful secret mantra, which has been practiced for a long time, was
                        taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats of the past. It will be taught by the
                        perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And such is also the case at present, as
                        I now teach it to aid in the awakening of buddhahood. With this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, I will protect and form a boundary around the
                        person named such-and-such. I will form a boundary one league to the east. I will form a boundary one
                        league in all the cardinal and intermediate directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-22"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="64">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">tadyathā samuca vimuca palamuca jagadhara madasṭhala nalakamaga
                            samuḥśvavāti vimukti yoga hinasagama aradamula vihaṃgami idiciri vitalākhayo makhayo lagabhi­dharaṇi
                            pratiprāyogi aḥcakrapati samasraḥvati ilāya milāya bahusaddhya anatama arthavati garavati tikhinitive
                            akanati sakanati samidima vasuvaṭe aṭe aṭe taṭṭa kharusmin kharusmin lahataṃ lahutaṃ sambhara sambhara
                            vatiranataṃ nirutaṃ ila taila saraphala bahuphala satamata daṃṣṭrimata</foreign> | </ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-23"/>
                    <p tid="25">“Ānanda, this strong and powerful secret mantra, which has been practiced for a long time, was
                        taught by the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats of the past. It will be taught by the
                        perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats in the future. And such is also the case at present,
                        for I too teach it. Brahmā, lord of the Sahā world, teaches it. Śakra, lord of the gods, also teaches it.
                        The four great kings also teach it. The twenty-eight great yakṣa generals also teach it. <ref cRef="F.152.b"/> And Hārītī, with her children and retinue of servants, also teaches it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-24"/>
                    <p tid="26">“Ānanda, any monk, nun, layman, or laywoman who receives this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, and understands, sees, or performs it,
                        precisely as it has been taught and mastered, will be guarded, protected, looked after, and brought peace
                        and well-being for as long as he or she shall live. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-25"/>
                    <p tid="27">“Ānanda, by the command of the perfectly and completely awakened thus-gone arhats of the past,
                        future, and present, this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret
                            Mantra</title>, shall guard, protect, look after, and bring peace and well-being to the person named
                        such-and-such. It will form a boundary. It will form a boundary one league to the east. Likewise, it will
                        form a boundary one league to the west. It will form a boundary one league to the south. It will form a
                        boundary one league to the north. It will form a boundary one league in all the cardinal and intermediate
                        directions. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-26"/>
                    <p tid="28">“Ānanda, there are four who dwell on and off the path of the four great kings.<note place="end" index="9" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-173">The commentary (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen mo
                                rjes su ’dzin ma’i mdo’i ’bum ’grel</title>, 263b–264a) reads: “The ‘path of the four great kings’
                            is the four great kings themselves…and those guarded by the four great kings. ‘Those not on the path”
                            refers to the sons of the great kings. These four entities garner petty lords and retinues, enacting
                            violence against beings. Who are they? They cause harm in the east, south, west, and north, such that
                            the 80,000 types of obstructers are also included within these four.”</note> Who are they? They are
                        Auspicious, Friend to All, Complete, and Glory of Joy. Whoever knows their names and families will not be
                        in danger of the great kings, nor will he be in danger of robbers, fire, water, humans, or non-humans. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-27"/>
                    <p tid="29">“Ānanda, Vajrapāṇi’s older brother called Swift Hand resides in the city known as Cakravālapur.
                        Whoever knows his name and family will be guarded, protected, looked after, pardoned, <ref cRef="F.153.a"/> and brought peace and well-being by him. On behalf of the person named such-and-such, I beseech and
                        supplicate Vajrapāṇi’s older brother Swift Hand! By the command of the blessed buddhas of the past,
                        future, and present, all yakṣas, rākṣasas, pretas, piśācas, kumbhāṇḍas, pūtanas, and kaṭapūtanas who seek
                        an occasion and look for an opportunity to harm the person named such-and-such will not find any such
                        opportunity, nor will they be able to quarrel with him! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-28"/>
                    <p tid="30">“Ānanda, there are fourteen great rākṣasīs. They protected the Bodhisattva while he was in his
                        mother’s womb. They also protected him during his birth, as a newborn, and while he was being reared. Who
                        are they? They are Powerful, Stainless, Tumult, Supple, Terrifying Lady, Voice of Jambū, Supreme Seizer,
                        Master, Renowned Female, Amazing Renown, Conflict Lover, Playful Lady, Earth Supporter, and Conflict
                        Engager. Whoever knows their names and families will be guarded, protected, looked after, and brought
                        peace and well-being by them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-29"/>
                    <p tid="31">“Ānanda, there are eight rākṣasīs who steal the vitality of men or women regardless of whether
                        they are asleep or not. Who are they? They are Horn, Unassailable, Instigator of Evil, Slanderous, Red
                        Female Servant, Greatest, Excellent Eyes, and Terrifying. Whoever knows their names and families will be
                        guarded, protected, looked after, and brought peace and well-being by them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-30"/>
                    <p tid="32">“Ānanda, there are seven rākṣasīs who travel as far as one hundred miles when they smell the scent
                        of blood. Who are they? They are Excellent Splendor, Layered Joy, Giver of Various Things, <ref cRef="F.153.b"/> Excellent White Female Servant, Desiring Engagement, Surrounding City, and Mountain
                        Protector. Whoever knows their names and families will be guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace
                        and well-being, and granted pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-31"/>
                    <p tid="33">“Ānanda, there is a rākṣasī called Mahākālī with one thousand sons who lives at the seashore and
                        travels 80,000 miles in a single night. Whoever knows her name and family will be guarded, protected,
                        looked after, brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon by her! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-32"/>
                    <p tid="34">“Ānanda, there are five rākṣasīs who, along with 7,700,000 yakṣas, guard and protect the humans in
                        the Jambu continent. Who are they? They are Always Insane, Further Insane, Bloated with Power, Bamboo
                        Stick, and Wealthy. Whoever knows their names and families will be guarded, protected, looked after,
                        brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon by them! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-33"/>
                    <p tid="35">“Therefore, on behalf of the person named such-and-such, I beseech and supplicate those five
                        rākṣasīs, along with the 7,700,000 yakṣas! By the command of the blessed buddhas of the past, future, and
                        present, may the person named such-and-such be guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace and
                        well-being, and granted pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-34"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="65">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">tadyathā vīmude vītide picarite pigarite karaṭi karavīra swāri
                            madhura­ghoṣe śatahanita bhaṣitaghe akke nakke vika ḍitā vikuṭite viraje vighaṣṭavāte</foreign> | </ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-35"/>
                    <p tid="37">“Ānanda, nowhere in the worlds of gods, demons, Brahmā, mendicants, priests, humans, kiṃnaras, and
                        mahoragas have I seen anyone—whether human, non-human, yakṣa, rākṣasa, asura, gandharva, nāga, garuḍa,
                        guhyaka, preta, piśāca, vetāla, kākhorda, kṛtya, pūtana, kaṭapūtana, unmāda, or apasmāra—<ref cRef="F.154.a"/> who, seeking an opportunity to hurt and looking for conflict, was ever able to harm a
                        person guarded, shielded, protected, looked after, brought peace and well-being, and granted pardon by
                        this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>—unless, that
                        is, the ripening of their karma precludes it. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-36"/>
                    <p tid="38">“Therefore, by the command of the blessed buddhas of the past, future, and present, I will use
                        this queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, to guard the
                        person named such-and-such from humans, non-humans, yakṣas, rākṣasas, piśācas, asuras, gandharvas, nāgas,
                        garuḍas, guhyakas, pretas, vetālas, kākhordas, kṛtyas, pūtanas, kaṭapūtanas, unmadas, and apasmāras. He
                        will be protected, shielded, brought peace and well-being, granted pardon, and purged of poison. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-37"/>
                    <p tid="39">“This queen of incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, will
                        intoxicate all those with hostile intentions, ill will, animosity, and rage, as well as all demons, <ref cRef="F.154.b"/> trail guards, fort guards, and customs guards. It will intoxicate them, cause
                        paralysis and stupefaction, and seize their hands, feet, minds, and tongues. Through this queen of
                        incantations, <title xml:lang="en">Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>, the person will escape on
                        each and every occasion. </p>
                    <lb/>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-38"/>
                    <lg tid="40">
                        <l>“Oh wonder! Brahmin! You transcended anguish,</l>
                        <l>Crossed over existence within the world,</l>
                        <l>And finally, after so long,</l>
                        <l>Saw the transcendence of all resentment and fear!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-39"/>
                    <lg tid="41">
                        <l>“Patience is the supreme austerity;</l>
                        <l>Patience is the supreme nirvāṇa—so proclaims the Buddha.</l>
                        <l>As for the ordained who harm others,</l>
                        <l>One who is violent toward others is not a proper renunciant.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-40"/>
                    <lg tid="42">
                        <l>“On the other hand, just as those with eyesight</l>
                        <l>Also have capabilities,</l>
                        <l>The wise, in this world of the living,</l>
                        <l>Avoid misdeeds.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-41"/>
                    <lg tid="43">
                        <l>“To all the buddhas</l>
                        <l>Of present, future, and past</l>
                        <l>I pay homage!</l>
                        <l>To all of them I go for refuge!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-42"/>
                    <lg tid="44">
                        <l>“Since in the world it is the bliss-gone arhats</l>
                        <l>To whom the moon goes for refuge,</l>
                        <l>Buddhas, with compassion for the world,</l>
                        <l>Free the moon from Rāhu!</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-43"/>
                    <lg tid="45">
                        <l>“ ‘Rāhu! The moon dispels darkness.</l>
                        <l>Illuminating the sky, </l>
                        <l>It shines with white </l>
                        <l>And pristine light. </l>
                        <l>Instead of seizing it in the sky,</l>
                        <l>Instantly release the lantern of creatures!’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-44"/>
                    <lg tid="46">
                        <l>“Then, suddenly,</l>
                        <l>Rāhu, with his body trembling and in a sweat</l>
                        <l>Like a sick person, </l>
                        <l>Abruptly released the moon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-45"/>
                    <lg tid="47">
                        <l>“ ‘Rāhu, why did you,</l>
                        <l>Trembling and in a sweat</l>
                        <l>Like a sick person, </l>
                        <l>Suddenly release the moon?’</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-46"/>
                    <lg tid="48">
                        <l>“ ‘If, upon uttering these verses of the Buddha,</l>
                        <l>The moon were not released,</l>
                        <l>My head would crack into seven pieces,</l>
                        <l>And even while alive, I would be unhappy.’<note place="end" index="10" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-174">The
                                commentary (<title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen mo rjes su ’dzin ma’i mdo’i ’bum
                                    ’grel</title>, 274a7) explains this in terms of the next life. It states: “Even after dying,
                                one will be reborn in the hell of Endless Torment.”</note>
                        </l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-47"/>
                    <lg tid="49">
                        <l>“Oh wonder! Amazing is the emergence of buddhas</l>
                        <l>Who see the truth!</l>
                        <l>If one recites these verses,</l>
                        <l>Rāhu will release the moon.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-48"/>
                    <p tid="50">“By such truth and true words, as follows: <ref cRef="F.155.a"/> one who is unforgettable to
                        beings appearing in the world is a ‘thus-gone one;’ that he speaks by speaking truly means he speaks by
                        speaking truly at the appropriate time. Furthermore, Ānanda, those verses were spoken by the Thus-Gone One
                        to assist in the observation of pure conduct. And what is more, Ānanda, the following words will secure
                        the purpose, as well as further assist and ease, whatever function those verses are set to perform: </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-49"/>
                    <ab type="mantra" tid="66">
                        <foreign xml:lang="Sa-Ltn" type="mantra">syād athedana svasti mati vilumati praharati kaśumadchi nanda
                            mati vihagrahe vidumati edakṛta ārtha sudṛśabuddhi bodhimati suhudume alakhūme alamite higaraśara
                            āśuha pragaśini</foreign> | </ab>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-50"/>
                    <p tid="52">“Ānanda, the ten roots of seeds and the ten root words of seeds have been spoken by the Thus-Gone
                        One. Ānanda, these words will be spoken by Thus-Gone Ones, and will be taught by them; so if people who
                        dwell in their teaching utter them, yakṣas and rākṣasas will perform activities for them like slaves. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-51"/>
                    <p tid="53">“By such truth and true words, as follows: true words at the irreversible level are called the
                        ‘words that are supreme in the world.’ Those who, of all renunciants, are ‘the most joyful renunciants,’
                        the perfectly and completely awakened, thus-gone arhats, who have neither fear nor terror, who, neither
                        cowering nor fleeing, lack fear, and who, having abandoned fear and its impetus, are called ‘free of
                        anything that causes one to cry out in hair-raising panic’—these are what is meant by ‘those who speak by
                        speaking truly, those who speak by speaking truly at the appropriate time.’ By their truth and those true
                        words, may the person named such-and-such have well-being! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-52"/>
                    <p tid="54">“By such truth and true words, as follows: of all those who observe ethical discipline, controlled
                        conduct, austerities, or pure conduct, those who are known as ‘supreme in the discipline that pleases the
                        noble ones’—by their truth and their true words, may the person named such-and-such have well-being! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-53"/>
                    <p tid="55">“Of the elders, Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya, like the eldest of a king’s sons, foremost among those
                        practicing pure conduct, <ref cRef="F.155.b"/> for a long time has passed since his ordination;
                        Mahākāśyapa, supreme among those with few desires who adhere to the qualities from training and have
                        contentment; Śāradvatīputra, supreme among those with great wisdom and eloquence; Mahā­maudgalyāyana,
                        supreme among those with great miraculous powers and great magical abilities; Aniruddha, supreme among
                        those with the divine eye; Ānanda, supreme among the learned; Upālī, supreme among holders of discipline;
                        Pūrṇa­maitrāyaṇī­putra, supreme among Dharma preachers; Rāhula, supreme among those with respect for the
                        trainings; Vasumallaputra, supreme among those who distribute bedding and cushions; Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja,
                        supreme among those who proclaim the lion’s roar; Kālodāyin, supreme among those who inspire householders;
                        and Sudarśana, supreme among those who are venerated by gods and men—by the truth and true words of these
                        elders, may the person named such-and-such be guarded, protected, looked after, brought peace and
                        well-being, and granted pardon. He shall be protected from kings, ministers, robbers, fire, water,
                        enemies, and adversaries, and when traveling, lost, asleep, drunk, or careless! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-54"/>
                    <p tid="56">“By such truth and true words, as follows: among all possible beings—those without feet, with two
                        feet, with four feet, or with many feet; those with form or without form; those with perception, without
                        perception, or neither with nor without perception—the Thus-Gone One is called ‘supreme.’ By his truth and
                        his true words, may the person person named such-and-such be guarded, protected, looked after, brought
                        peace and well-being, and granted pardon! </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-55"/>
                    <p tid="57">“By such truth and true words, as follows: in the entire range of conditioned and unconditioned
                        phenomena, freedom from attachment is called ‘supreme.’ By that truth and those true words, <ref cRef="F.156.a"/> may the person person named such-and-such be guarded, protected, embraced, brought
                        peace and well-being, and granted pardon. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-56"/>
                    <p tid="58">“By such truth and true words, as follows: of all kinds of assemblies, gatherings, multitudes, and
                        retinues, the saṅgha of the Thus-Gone One’s śrāvakas is called ‘supreme.’ By their truth and their true
                        words, may countries, regions, cities, towns, villages, houses, abodes, fields, and this sick patient be
                        guarded, protected, looked after, and brought peace and well-being. Boundaries will be formed around them.
                        All bhūtas will be turned back. Those who steal vitality will be turned back. </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-57"/>
                    <p tid="59">“By such truth and true words, as follows: in order that I—a blessed, perfectly and completely
                        awakened, thus-gone arhat—may end this person’s desire, anger, and ignorance, by the truth and true words
                        of the teaching, explanation, and enunciation of the 84,000 sections of teachings, may the 404 sicknesses
                        of the person named such-and-such come to an end! May they be eliminated! May they cease! May they cease
                        completely!” </p>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-58"/>
                    <p tid="60"><!--modularPassage type=concludingPraise-->When the Blessed One had spoken, the world, including
                        venerable Ānanda, Brahmā, master of the Sahā world, and all gods, humans, asuras, and gandharvas rejoiced
                        and praised what the Blessed One had said.<!--/modularPassage-->
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="colophon">
                    <head type="colophon" tid="73">Colophon</head>
                    <milestone unit="chunk" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-59"/>
                    <p tid="61"> This completes <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Upholding the Great Secret Mantra</title>.</p>
                    <p tid="62">This was translated and edited by the Indian scholars Śīlendrabodhi, Jñānasiddhi, and Śākyaprabha,
                        along with the translator-editor Bandé Yeshé Dé, who then revised it according to the new lexicon and
                        finalized it. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes" tid="74">Notes</head>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl" tid="75">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="76">Tibetan and Sanskrit Texts</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-60">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānu­dhāraṇi­sūtra</title>). Toh 563, Degé Kangyur vol. 90 (rgyud ’bum, pha), folios
                        150b–156a. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-61">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen po rjes su ’dzin pa’i mdo</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānu­dhāraṇi­sūtra</title>). bka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur],
                        krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation
                        Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun
                        khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–2009, vol. 90, pp. 457–476. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-62">
                        <title xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang sngags chen mo rjes su ’dzin ma’i mdo’i ’bum ’grel</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­mantrānu­dhāraṇī­sūtra­śata­sahasra­ṭīkā</title>). Toh 2692, Degé Tengyur vol.
                        72 (rgyud, du), folios 241b–282b. </bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section" tid="77">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-63">Dharmachakra Translation Committee (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">Destroyer of
                            the Great Trichiliocosm</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­sāhasra­pramardanī</title>, Toh 558).
                        84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha, 2016. (<ref target="http://read.84000.co/translation/UT22084-090-002.html">read.84000.co</ref>)</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-64">——— (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Great Peahen, Queen of
                            Incantations</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­māyūrī­vidyā­rājñī</title>, Toh 559). 84000:
                        Translating the Words of the Buddha, (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-65">——— (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Noble Great Amulet, Queen of
                            Incantations</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­prati­sāra­vidyā­rājñī</title>, Toh 561). 84000:
                        Translating the Words of the Buddha, (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-66">——— (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">The Sūtra of Great Cool Grove</title>,
                            (<title xml:lang="en">Mahā­śītavana</title>, Toh 562). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha,
                        (forthcoming).</bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-67">Hidas, Gergely (2012). <title xml:lang="en">Mahā­pratisarā-Mahā­vidyā­rājñī,
                            The Great Amulet, Great Queen of Spells: Introduction, Critical Editions and Annotated
                            Translation.</title> Sata-pitaka Series: Indo-Asian Literatures Vol. 636. New Delhi: International
                        Academy of Indian Culture and Aditya Prakashan, 2012. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-68">——— (2010). “<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­pratisarā­vidyā­vidhi</title>:
                        The Spell-Manual of the Great Amulet.” <title xml:lang="en">Acta Orientalia Academiae Scientiarum
                            Hung</title>, vol. 63(4) (2010): 473–484. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-69">——— (2007). “Remarks on the Use of the Dhāraṇīs and Mantras of the
                        Mahā­pratisarā-Mahā­vidyā­rājñī.” <title xml:lang="en">In Indian Languages and Texts Through the Ages:
                            Essays of Hungarian Indologists in Honour of Prof. Csaba Töttössy</title>. Edited by Csaba Dezsö, pp.
                        185–208. New Delhi: Manohar Publishers and Distributors, 2007. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-70">Lewis, Todd. <title xml:lang="en">Popular Buddhist Texts from Nepal:
                            Narratives and Rituals of Newar Buddhism</title>. Albany: SUNY Press, 2000. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-71">Orzech, Charles D. “Metaphor, Translation, and the Construction of Kingship
                        in the Scripture for Humane Kings and the Mahāmāyūrī Vidyārājñī Sūtra.” <title xml:lang="fr">Cahiers
                            d’Extreme-Asie</title>, vol. 13 (2002): 55–83. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-72">Pathak, Suniti K. “A Dharani-mantra in the Vinaya-vastu.” <title xml:lang="en">Bulletin of Tibetology</title>, vol. 25, no. 2 (1989). </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-73">Schopen, Gregory. “A Verse from the <title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhadra­cari­pranidhana</title> in a 10th Century Inscription found at Nalanda.” <title xml:lang="en">Journal of the International Association of Buddhist Studies</title>, 12(1) (1989): 149–57. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-74">Sørensen, Henrik H. “The Spell of the Great, Golden Peacock Queen: The
                        Origin, Practices, and Lore of an Early Esoteric Buddhist Tradition in China.” <title xml:lang="en">Pacific World Journal</title>, Fall (8) (2006): 89–123. </bibl>
                    <bibl xml:id="UT22084-090-007-75">Yao, Fumi (tr.). <title xml:lang="en">On Medicinal Materials</title> (<title xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhaiṣajyavastu</title>, Toh 1, ch. 6). 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha
                        (forthcoming).</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-76">
                            <term>apasmāra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brjed byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྗེད་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">apasmāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-77">
                            <term>asura</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lha ma yin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྷ་མ་ཡིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">asura</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-78">
                            <term>bhūta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byung po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱུང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">bhūta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-79">
                            <term>gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">gandharva</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-80">
                            <term>garuḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nam mkha’ lding </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནམ་མཁའ་ལྡིང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">garuḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-81">
                            <term>guhyaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gsang ba pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གསང་བ་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">guhyaka</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-82">
                            <term>kākhorda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byad stems </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱད་སྟེམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kākhorda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-83">
                            <term>kaṭapūtana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lus srul po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལུས་སྲུལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kaṭapūtana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-84">
                            <term>kiṃnara</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi’am ci </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིའམ་ཅི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kiṃnara</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-85">
                            <term>kṛtya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gshed byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཤེད་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kṛtya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-86">
                            <term>kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grul bum </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲུལ་བུམ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">kumbhāṇḍa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-87">
                            <term>league</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyang grags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱང་གྲགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">krośa</term>
                            <term type="definition">A measure of distance, one quarter of a <foreign type="term" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yojana</foreign>; supposedly the distance within which a cry can be heard.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-88">
                            <term>mahoraga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lto ’phye chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལྟོ་འཕྱེ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">mahoraga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-89">
                            <term>nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">klu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀླུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">nāga</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-90">
                            <term>piśāca</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha za </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ཟ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">piśāca</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-91">
                            <term>preta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">yi dags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཡི་དགས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">preta</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-92">
                            <term>pūtana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srul po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲུལ་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">pūtana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-93">
                            <term>rākṣasa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣasa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-94">
                            <term>rākṣasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">srin mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྲིན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">rākṣasī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-95">
                            <term>unmāda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">smyo byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྨྱོ་བྱེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">unmāda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-96">
                            <term>vetāla</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ro langs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རོ་ལངས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">vetāla</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-97">
                            <term>yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gnod sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གནོད་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">yakṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-98">
                            <term>Always Insane</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtag tu myos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྟག་ཏུ་མྱོས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-99">
                            <term>Amazing Renown</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rmad grags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྨད་གྲགས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-100">
                            <term>Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun dga’ bo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་དགའ་བོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ānanda</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-101">
                            <term>Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mgon med zas sbyin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མགོན་མེད་ཟས་སྦྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-102">
                            <term>Aniruddha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ma ’gags pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མ་འགགས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Aniruddha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-103">
                            <term>Auspicious</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bkra shis ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བཀྲ་ཤིས་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Svastika</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-104">
                            <term>Bamboo Stick</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od ma’i sbubs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་མའི་སྦུབས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-105">
                            <term>Bloated with Power</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs kyis rgyags </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ཀྱིས་རྒྱགས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-106">
                            <term>Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">tshangs pa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཚངས་པ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Brahmā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-107">
                            <term>Complete</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-108">
                            <term>Conflict Engager</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’thab ’jug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཐབ་འཇུག</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-109">
                            <term>Conflict Lover</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’thab dga’ </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཐབ་དགའ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kalahapriya?</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-110">
                            <term>Desiring Engagement</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jug ’dod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇུག་འདོད།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-111">
                            <term>Earth Supporter</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sa ’dzin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ས་འཛིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhūmidhāra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-112">
                            <term>Excellent Eyes</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mig bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མིག་བཟང་།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-113">
                            <term>Excellent Splendor</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gzi brjid mchog </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གཟི་བརྗིད་མཆོག</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-114">
                            <term>Excellent White Female Servant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bran mo dkar mo bzang </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲན་མོ་དཀར་མོ་བཟང་།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-115">
                            <term>Friend to All</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun bshes </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་བཤེས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Viśvāmitra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-116">
                            <term>Further Insane</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rjes su myos </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྗེས་སུ་མྱོས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-117">
                            <term>Giver of Various Things</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sna tshog sbyin sbong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྣ་ཚོག་སྦྱིན་སྦོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Citra?</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-118">
                            <term>Glory of Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ ba’i dpal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བའི་དཔལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śrīharṣa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-119">
                            <term>Greatest</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་ཆེན།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-120">
                            <term>Hārītī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’phrog ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཕྲོག་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Hārītī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-121">
                            <term>Horn</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rwa </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྭ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-122">
                            <term>Instigator of Evil</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ngan slob </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ངན་སློབ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-123">
                            <term>Kālodāyin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag po ’char ka </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནག་པོ་འཆར་ཀ</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kālodāyin</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-124">
                            <term>Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">kun shes kauN+Din+ya </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཀུན་ཤེས་ཀཽཎྜིནྱ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ājñāta­kauṇḍinya</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-125">
                            <term>Layered Joy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dga’ brtsegs </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དགའ་བརྩེགས།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-126">
                            <term>Mahākālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nag mo chen mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ནག་མོ་ཆེན་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākālī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-127">
                            <term>Mahākāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’od srung chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འོད་སྲུང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahākāśyapa</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-128">
                            <term>Mahā­maudgalyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">maud gal gyi bu chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཽད་གལ་གྱི་བུ་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Mahā­maudgalyāyana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-129">
                            <term>Master</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bla ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བླ་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Prabhu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Guru</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-130">
                            <term>Mountain Protector</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ri srung </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རི་སྲུང་།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-131">
                            <term>Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bha ra dwa dza bsod snyoms len </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྷ་ར་དྭ་ཛ་བསོད་སྙོམས་ལེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Piṇḍola Bhāradvāja</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-132">
                            <term>Playful Lady</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rtsed mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྩེད་མོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-133">
                            <term>Powerful</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stobs ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོབས་ལྡན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Balī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-134">
                            <term>Pūrṇa­maitrāyaṇī­putra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">byams ma’i bu gang po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྱམས་མའི་བུ་གང་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pūrṇa­maitrāyaṇī­putra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-135">
                            <term>Rāhu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhu</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-136">
                            <term>Rāhula</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra gcan zin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་གཅན་ཟིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Rāhula</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-137">
                            <term>Red Female Servant</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">bran mo dmar mo </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བྲན་མོ་དམར་མོ།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-138">
                            <term>Renowned Female</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grags ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲགས་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Kīrtī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-139">
                            <term>Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">brgya byin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">བརྒྱ་བྱིན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śakra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-140">
                            <term>Śākyaprabha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shAkya pra bha ba </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤཱཀྱ་པྲ་བྷ་བ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śākyaprabha</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-141">
                            <term>Śāradvatīputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sha ra dwa t’i bu </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤ་ར་དྭ་ཏའི་བུ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śāradvatīputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-142">
                            <term>Śīlendrabodhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">shrI len+dra bo dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཤྲཱི་ལེནྡྲ་བོ་དྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Śīlendrabodhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-143">
                            <term>Slanderous</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">phra ma can </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཕྲ་མ་ཅན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"/>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-144">
                            <term>Stainless</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dri med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">དྲི་མེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vimalā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-145">
                            <term>Sudarśana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">legs mthong </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལེགས་མཐོང་།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Sudarśana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-146">
                            <term>Supple</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rab mnyen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རབ་མཉེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Pramṛdū</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-147">
                            <term>Supreme Seizer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mchog len </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཆོག་ལེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Paramalabhā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-148">
                            <term>Surrounding City</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grong khyer ’khor yug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲོང་ཁྱེར་འཁོར་ཡུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Cakravālapur</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-149">
                            <term>Swift Hand</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">lag myur </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ལག་མྱུར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Laghupāṇi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-150">
                            <term>Terrifying</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs byed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་བྱེད།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-151">
                            <term>Terrifying Lady</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’jigs byed ma </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཇིགས་བྱེད་མ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Bhairavā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-152">
                            <term>Tumult</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">sgra chen </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྒྲ་ཆེན།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Ghoṣā</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-153">
                            <term>Unassailable</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">thub med </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཐུབ་མེད།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-154">
                            <term>Upālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">nye bar ’khor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཉེ་བར་འཁོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Upālī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-155">
                            <term>Vasumallaputra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">gyad bu nor </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྱད་བུ་ནོར།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Vasumallaputra</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-156">
                            <term>Voice of Jambū</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’dzam bu’i mgrin </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འཛམ་བུའི་མགྲིན།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-157">
                            <term>Wealthy</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">’byor ldan </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">འབྱོར་ལྡན།</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="person" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-158">
                            <term>Jñānasiddhi</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">dz+nyA na sid+dhi </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">ཛྙཱ་ན་སིདྡྷི།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Jñānasiddhi</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-159">
                            <term>great trichiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gsum gyi stong chen po </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གསུམ་གྱི་སྟོང་ཆེན་པོ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">trisāhasra­mahā­sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">The largest universe spoken of in Buddhist cosmology, consisting of one
                                billion smaller world systems.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-160">
                            <term>Sahā world</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mi mjed </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མི་མཇེད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sahā</term>
                            <term type="definition">A name for the “world” in which we live.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-161">
                            <term>Jetavana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">rgyal bu rgyal byed kyi tshal </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">རྒྱལ་བུ་རྒྱལ་བྱེད་ཀྱི་ཚལ།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">jetavana</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-162">
                            <term>Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">mnyan yod </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">མཉན་ཡོད།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">śrāvastī</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-163">
                            <term>chiliocosm</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">stong gi ’jig rten gyi khams </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">སྟོང་གི་འཇིག་རྟེན་གྱི་ཁམས།</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">sāhasra­loka­dhātu</term>
                            <term type="definition">A universe in Buddhist cosmology consisting of one thousand smaller world
                                systems.</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="place" xml:id="UT22084-090-007-164">
                            <term>Cakravālapur</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">grong khyer khor yug </term>
                            <term xml:lang="bo">གྲོང་ཁྱེར་ཁོར་ཡུག</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">cakravālapur</term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>